<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Bot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Exp. Bot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">exbotj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Experimental Botany</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-0957</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1460-2431</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6022596</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29912443</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ery147</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ery147</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Papers</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading"><subject>Plant&#x02014;Environment Interactions</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Genomic comparison of two independent seagrass lineages reveals habitat-driven convergent evolution</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HueyTyng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Golicz</surname><given-names>Agnieszka A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0003">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>Philipp E</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Severn-Ellis</surname><given-names>Anita A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>Chon-Kit Kenneth</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Batley</surname><given-names>Jacqueline</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kendrick</surname><given-names>Gary A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-7599-6760</contrib-id><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1"/><!--<email>dave.edwards@uwa.edu.au</email>--></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AF0001"><label>1</label>School of Agriculture and Food Sciences, University of Queensland, Brisbane, QLD, Australia</aff><aff id="AF0002"><label>2</label>School of Biological Sciences, University of Western Australia, WA, Australia</aff><aff id="AF0003"><label>3</label>Plant Molecular Biology and Biotechnology Laboratory, Faculty of Veterinary and Agricultural Sciences, University of Melbourne, Parkville, Melbourne, VIC, Australia</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1">Correspondence: <email>dave.edwards@uwa.edu.au</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>10</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2018-04-18"><day>18</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>18</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>69</volume><issue>15</issue><fpage>3689</fpage><lpage>3702</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>8</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Society for Experimental Biology.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="cc-by" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="ery147.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>In adapting to a marine environment, two independent seagrass lineages lost genes associated with ethylene and terpenoid biosynthesis and retained genes related to salinity adaptation, suggesting habitat-driven convergent evolution.</p></abstract><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>Seagrasses are marine angiosperms that live fully submerged in the sea. They evolved from land plant ancestors, with multiple species representing at least three independent return-to-the-sea events. This raises the question of whether these marine angiosperms followed the same adaptation pathway to allow them to live and reproduce under the hostile marine conditions. To compare the basis of marine adaptation between seagrass lineages, we generated genomic data for <italic>Halophila ovalis</italic> and compared this with recently published genomes for two members of Zosteraceae, as well as genomes of five non-marine plant species (Arabidopsis, <italic>Oryza sativa</italic>, <italic>Phoenix dactylifera</italic>, <italic>Musa acuminata</italic>, and <italic>Spirodela polyrhiza</italic>). <italic>Halophila</italic> and Zosteraceae represent two independent seagrass lineages separated by around 30 million years. Genes that were lost or conserved in both lineages were identified. All three species lost genes associated with ethylene and terpenoid biosynthesis, and retained genes related to salinity adaptation, such as those for osmoregulation. In contrast, the loss of the NADH dehydrogenase-like complex is unique to <italic>H. ovalis</italic>. Through comparison of two independent return-to-the-sea events, this study further describes marine adaptation characteristics common to seagrass families, identifies species-specific gene loss, and provides molecular evidence for convergent evolution in seagrass lineages.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Gene loss</kwd><kwd><italic>Halophila ovalis</italic></kwd><kwd>marine adaptation</kwd><kwd>NDH complex</kwd><kwd>osmoregulation</kwd><kwd>seagrass</kwd><kwd><italic>Zostera muelleri</italic></kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="14"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Seagrasses are a polyphyletic group of flowering plants that live fully submerged in the marine environment and form monospecific meadows resembling terrestrial grasses. The morphology of seagrasses varies among species, though common features include long, strap-shaped leaves and simple flowers. Seagrasses belong to a basal lineage that diverged around 140 million years ago (Mya), before the divergence of the Poaceae within the monocotyledon clade. Although similar in form, seagrass species represent at least three independent return-to-the-sea events (<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">Les <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>).</p><p>The convergent evolution of seagrasses is characterized by common physiological and morphological features that possibly represent a collection of marine adaptation traits. For example, seagrass leaves lack stomata, and gas exchange occurs through permeable cuticles, while seagrass roots and rhizomes have aerenchyma to enhance gas transport. Seagrasses have also adapted to variable quality and low levels of light, which attenuates quickly in seawater (<xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">Larkum <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0063" ref-type="bibr">Strydom <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>) and have effective osmoregulation to survive in the saline aqueous environment (<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Koch <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr">Touchette, 2007</xref>). Seagrasses are adapted to aquatic reproduction, where the transport and capture of pollen grains is carried out on or below the water surface.</p><p>Current seagrass taxonomy contains around 72 species forming three families, Zosteraceae, Hydrocharitaceae and Cymodoceaceae complex (<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">Les <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">Short <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">Nguyen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). Recent genome-wide comparative studies of two species in the Zosteraceae provided the first insight into genomic adaptation to the marine environment (<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">Golicz <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">Olsen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). Genes associated with the synthesis and signalling of volatile substances, including ethylene, methyljasmonate, and terpenoids, were lost in both <italic>Zostera muelleri</italic> and <italic>Z. marina</italic>. Genes associated with morphological adaptation, including those for stomatal cell differentiation, flower development and pollen formation, were also absent or greatly reduced in number. An increase in gene families associated with low light harvesting and cell wall modification was observed and postulated to contribute to survival in the light-attenuated and high salinity environment.</p><p>These gene losses, gene modifications, and gene family expansions in the two <italic>Zostera</italic> species may not reflect the independent adaptation of other seagrass lineages to the marine environment, and analysis of a second lineage is required to answer the question whether they share a common adaptation pathway to the ocean. <italic>Halophila ovalis</italic> is a seagrass species in the family Hydrocharitaceae, and is an ideal model for comparison with the <italic>Zostera</italic> species. The seagrass subclade in Hydrocharitaceae is embedded within branches of largely diverse aquatic angiosperms, including freshwater species (<xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">Larkum <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>), indicating the independent rise of marine adaption phenotypes.</p><p>As the likelihood of convergent evolution is predicted to decrease with phylogenetic distance (<xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">Ord and Summers, 2015</xref>), the divergence time difference between the seagrass subclade in Hydrocharitaceae (55 Mya; <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">Chen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>) and Zosteraceae (25 Mya; <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">Coyer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>) highlights the importance of this study. Moreover, since examples of parallel evolution, where similar phenotypes are generated from a similar genetic process of independent convergent evolution (<xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">Ord and Summers, 2015</xref>), are not abundant in plants (examples include carnivorous species (<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">Fukushima <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>), recurrence of C4 photosynthesis (reviewed in <xref rid="CIT0071" ref-type="bibr">Washburn <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>) and convergent mutations in loci during domestication (<xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">Paterson <italic>et al.</italic>, 1995</xref>)), and that habitat is the most common factor associated with reported examples of repeated evolution (<xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">Ord and Summers, 2015</xref>), independent seagrass lineages are excellent subjects for study.</p><p>In this work, a genomic comparison between seagrasses of Hydrocharitaceae and Zosteraceae was explored to determine whether the gene loss previously identified in <italic>Z. muelleri</italic> and <italic>Z. marina</italic> is also observed in <italic>H. ovalis</italic>. We also attempt to identify any seagrass-specific genes that are present in one or both lineages. <italic>Halophila ovalis</italic> genome sequencing data were compared with the annotated genomes of <italic>Z. marina</italic> and <italic>Z. muelleri</italic>, together with representative land plants. Our study demonstrates that lost genes associated with the synthesis and signalling of volatile substances, as well as stomatal development, are shared by both seagrass lineages. Genes that are uniquely conserved across the two lineages are enriched in pathways related to cell osmoregulation, and provide molecular evidence for independent marine colonization. Results also revealed the loss of the NADH dehydrogenase-like (NDH) protein complex in <italic>H. ovalis</italic>, a characteristic that is not shared by the other two seagrass species. This study provides a more complete description of marine adaptation, and suggest a parallel convergent evolution of two independent return-to-the-sea events in seagrasses separated by 30 million years.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s3"><title>Genome sequencing of <italic>H. ovalis</italic></title><p>One <italic>H. ovalis</italic> plant sample was collected at Swan River, Claremont, Perth, Western Australia (coordinates: 32&#x000b0; 0&#x02032; 3.98&#x02033; S, 115&#x000b0; 45&#x02032; 18.31&#x02033; E).</p><p>The growth tips of the seagrass thalli were carefully removed, rinsed in sterile water, and inspected for visible external contamination. Seven hundred milligrams of tissue was placed in 5 ml tubes, flash frozen in liquid nitrogen, and bead-pulverized using a 2010 Geno/Grinder (SPEX SamplePrep, USA). The Qiagen DNeasy Plant Mini Kit was used for the extraction of the DNA. The frozen powdered plant material was suspended in 3 ml of Buffer AP1 and 28 &#x000b5;l of RNAse A was added. After incubating at 65 &#x000b0;C, 910 &#x000b5;l of Buffer AP2 was added. The tubes were incubated on ice for 5 min and centrifuged thereafter to collect plant debris. Lysate (450 &#x000b5;l) was transferred to each of five to six QIAshredder tubes. The remainder of the DNA extraction steps were followed according to the kit protocol. The extracted DNA of each repetition was pooled after elution. DNA concentration was quantified using a Qubit 3.0 Fluorometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific) and visualized using a Labchip GX Touch 24 (PerkinElmer).</p><p>The extracted DNA was submitted to the Australian Genome Research Facility (AGRF) for library preparation and whole genome sequencing. The libraries for genome sequencing were prepared using the Illumina TruSeq Nano DNA HT Library Preparation Kit, according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. Genomic DNA was sequenced using an Illumina HiSeqX sequencer with 150 bp paired-end technology at the Garvan Institute of Medical Research.</p><p>A total of 510485779 paired-end reads were sequenced. Based on previous flow cytometry analysis of two other Hydrocharitaceae members, <italic>Najas minor</italic> (2C=7.28) and <italic>Eldodea Canadensis</italic> (2C=7.54) (<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Hidalgo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>), as well as genome size prediction (3628962593 bp, <italic>k</italic>=45) using the software Kmergenie (<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">Chikhi and Medvedev, 2014</xref>) the sequencing coverage was estimated as ~40&#x000d7;. The sequences were deposited in a public repository (NCBI BioProject Accession PRJNA396090). Clones and low quality reads were removed using Sickle (<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">Joshi and Fass, 2011</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Pipeline to identify lost and conserved genes</title><p>The identification of lost and conserved genes was achieved using the mapping of whole genome shotgun sequencing reads against reference genomes based on a previous approach (<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">Golicz <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). The reads were mapped to coding sequences (CDS) of reference species using dc-megaBLAST (<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Camacho <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>) with e-value 1e&#x02212;5. A custom python script, calculate_blast_coverage.py (downloadable at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/AppliedBioinformatics/H_ovalis_supplementary.git">https://github.com/AppliedBioinformatics/H_ovalis_supplementary.git</ext-link>), was used to calculate the horizontal coverage of each CDS. The average coverage of each CDS across multiple reference species was calculated. If the average coverage was &#x0003c;2%, which means that mapped reads covered less than 2% of the length of a CDS, the orthologue was considered lost. If the average coverage was &#x0003e;50%, the orthologue was conserved.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Orthologous gene cluster construction</title><p>A set of 16007 orthologous gene clusters (OGCs) conserved between seven model species with at least one gene originating from a monocot species, termed OGCsM (as defined in Table S1 in <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">Golicz <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>), was used to represent orthologues highly conserved in plants.</p><p>Gene clusters unique to Zosteraceae were identified using all-against-all comparison with BLASTP (<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Camacho <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>) using the following parameters: &#x02018;blastp -evalue 1e-5&#x02019;, followed by OrthoMCL (<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>) between <italic>Z. muelleri</italic>, <italic>Z. marina</italic>, one dicot (Arabidopsis), and three other monocots (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic>, <italic>Musa acuminata</italic>, and <italic>Spirodela polyrhiza</italic>) (species selection based on <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). This group of orthologous genes was termed OGCZ.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Lost and conserved <italic>H. ovalis</italic>, <italic>Z. muelleri</italic> and <italic>Z. marina</italic> genes in OGCsM</title><p>Primary transcript CDSs of five species (four land plants: Arabidopsis, <italic>Oryza sativa</italic>, <italic>Musa acuminata</italic>, and <italic>Phoenix dactylifera</italic>; one floating freshwater plant: <italic>Spirodela polyrhiza</italic>; versions as listed in <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">Golicz <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>) were used as references for mapping of reads from <italic>H. ovalis</italic>. Presence and absence results from a previous publication were used for <italic>Z. muelleri</italic> and <italic>Z. marina</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">Golicz <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). For each orthologue in OGCsM, lost or conserved status was assigned in each species.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Lost and conserved <italic>H. ovalis</italic> genes in OGCZ</title><p>Primary transcript CDSs of <italic>Z. muelleri</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.appliedbioinformatics.com.au/index.php/Seagrass_Zmu_Genome">http://www.appliedbioinformatics.com.au/index.php/Seagrass_Zmu_Genome</ext-link>; <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>) and <italic>Z. marina</italic> (Phytozome 10; <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">Olsen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>) were used as references for <italic>H. ovalis</italic> read mapping. For each orthologue in OGCZ, lost or conserved status was assigned in <italic>H. ovalis.</italic></p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Gene ontology enrichment and word cloud plotting</title><p>GO annotation and enrichment were performed using the topGO package (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">Alexa and Rahnenfuhrer, 2010</xref>) based on a previous approach (<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">Golicz <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). OGCsM was used as background, except for the GO enrichment of OGCZ genes where Arabidopsis whole proteome (TAIR10) was used.</p><p>A word cloud was generated and coloured to represent the enriched significance of GO terms using the wordcloud package (<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">Fellows, 2014</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Inferring gene function through the level of protein domain conservation</title><p>OGCZ proteins of <italic>Z. muelleri</italic>, <italic>Z. marina</italic> and Arabidopsis were compared with TIGRFAM, ProDom, Panther, PfamA and PrositePatterns using InterProScan (version 5.14, <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">Jones <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>) for motif and domain annotation. Domains of each protein were assigned with InterProScan IDs. The InterProScan IDs were compared between Arabidopsis and <italic>Zosteraceae</italic> genes for each OGCZ cluster.</p></sec><sec id="s10"><title>Assembly of <italic>H. ovalis</italic> protein and multiple sequence alignments with orthologues of other species</title><p>
<italic>Halophila ovalis</italic> reads aligned to CDS of 50S ribosomal protein L16 were extracted and assembled using Spades v3.10.1 (<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">Bankevich <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>) with the following commands: spades.py, only-assembler, 1 reads_1.fasta, 2 reads_2.fasta. Corresponding protein was aligned to the assembled contigs using Exonerate (<xref rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr">Slater and Birney, 2005</xref>) with the following parameters: exonerate, model protein2genome, E 1, bestn 1, score 100, softmaskquery no, softmasktarget yes, minintron 20, maxintron 20000, ryo &#x0201c;&#x0003e;HAL_%qi_%qd\n%tas&#x0201d;. The aligned target regions were translated to protein sequences using the translate tool in ExPASy (<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">Gasteiger <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>). Each <italic>H. ovalis</italic> protein sequence obtained was aligned with orthologues of selected species (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Table S1</xref> at <italic>JXB</italic> online) using MAFFT (<xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">Katoh <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>). A phylogenetic tree was plotted with PhyML (<xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">Guindon <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>) assuming the JTT model for amino acid substitution and gamma parameter for invariable sites (based on <xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">Huang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>) using the alignments excluding the outgroup (charophyte and chlorophyte). The multiple-sequence alignments were visualized and coloured using Jalview (<xref rid="CIT0072" ref-type="bibr">Waterhouse <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s11"><title>Results</title><sec id="s12"><title>Read alignment of <italic>H. ovalis</italic> to reference species CDS</title><p>A total of 112202319 <italic>H. ovalis</italic> reads (10.9%) were discarded in the process of clonal removal and quality-based filtering (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Table S2</xref>). Out of the remaining 908769239 <italic>H. ovalis</italic> reads, 2.7% (24495631) aligned to Arabidopsis CDS, 5.6% (50565060) aligned to <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> CDS, 1.3% (11617255) aligned to <italic>Musa acuminata</italic> CDS, 0.8% (7367361) aligned to <italic>Phoenix dactylifera</italic> CDS and 1.8% (16600802) aligned to <italic>Spirodela polyrhiza</italic> CDS. For the seagrass reference species, 1.8% (16727940) and 0.5% (5005993) of <italic>H. ovalis</italic> reads aligned to <italic>Z. muelleri</italic> and <italic>Z. marina</italic> CDSs, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="s13"><title>Conservation of core biological processes</title><p>A total of 4367 OGCsM genes, out of 16007, were conserved in <italic>H. ovalis</italic>. When compared with conserved genes previously described in <italic>Z. muelleri</italic> and <italic>Z. marina</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">Golicz <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">Olsen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>), 3335 (76.4%) genes were conserved in all three seagrass species, 377 genes were shared with either <italic>Z. muelleri</italic> or <italic>Z. marina</italic>, and 655 genes were only conserved in <italic>H. ovalis</italic>. A total of 508 genes were only conserved in the Zosteraceae species. A full list of genes conserved in <italic>H. ovalis</italic> and their presence in other seagrass species is presented in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Table S3</xref>. The GO terms enriched in these 4367 OGCsM genes conserved in <italic>H. ovalis</italic> involved core biological pathways such as photosynthesis, chlorophyll biosynthesis, and glycolytic processes, as well as response to stresses such as cadmium (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Significantly enriched biological process GO terms in the genes conserved in <italic>H. ovalis</italic> compared with five other plant species (Arabidopsis, <italic>Oryza sativa</italic>, <italic>Musa acuminata</italic>, <italic>Phoenix dactylifera</italic>, and <italic>Spirodela polyrhiza</italic>)</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO ID</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Term</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0046686</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Response to cadmium ion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;30</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006412</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Translation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;28</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0046496</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nicotinamide nucleotide metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;16</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006099</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tricarboxylic acid cycle</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;13</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0015991</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP hydrolysis-coupled proton transport</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;12</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:1901566</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Organonitrogen compound biosynthetic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;11</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0043039</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">tRNA aminoacylation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;10</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006090</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pyruvate metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;10</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:1901293</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nucleoside phosphate biosynthetic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;10</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0009156</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ribonucleoside monophosphate biosynthetic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;10</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0009225</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nucleotide-sugar metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;10</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0007264</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Small GTPase-mediated signal transduction</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;9</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0046034</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;9</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006108</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Malate metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;8</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006006</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glucose metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;8</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0034622</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cellular macromolecular complex assembly</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;8</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0071702</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Organic substance transport</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;8</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0018105</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peptidyl-serine phosphorylation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;8</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0009250</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glucan biosynthetic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;7</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0016192</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vesicle-mediated transport</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;7</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0010499</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proteasomal ubiquitin-independent protein catabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;7</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0043094</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cellular metabolic compound salvage</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.7 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;7</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0015994</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chlorophyll metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0034613</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cellular protein localization</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006536</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glutamate metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0005985</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sucrose metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0098656</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anion transmembrane transport</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0015672</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monovalent inorganic cation transport</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0009932</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell tip growth</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.9 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006081</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cellular aldehyde metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0018298</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein&#x02013;chromophore linkage</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0030163</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein catabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0048588</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Developmental cell growth</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006102</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isocitrate metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006607</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NLS-bearing protein import into nucleus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0015977</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carbon fixation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0015979</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Photosynthesis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006563</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-Serine metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006268</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA unwinding involved in DNA replication</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0007035</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vacuolar acidification</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0009768</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Photosynthesis, light harvesting in photosystem I</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0016197</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Endosomal transport</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0030048</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Actin filament-based movement</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00012</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0009651</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Response to salt stress</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00012</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006206</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pyrimidine nucleobase metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00013</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0030243</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cellulose metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00014</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0097164</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ammonium ion metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00015</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0010315</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Auxin efflux</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00015</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006551</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leucine metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00017</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006085</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acetyl-CoA biosynthetic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00018</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0045899</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive regulation of RNA polymerase II transcriptional preinitiation complex assembly</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00020</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0032012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regulation of ARF protein signal transduction</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00020</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0009735</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Response to cytokinin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00027</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006782</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protoporphyrinogen IX biosynthetic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00030</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0009846</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pollen germination</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00032</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:1901679</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nucleotide transmembrane transport</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00041</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0030042</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Actin filament depolymerization</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00048</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006558</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-Phenylalanine metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00050</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006544</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glycine metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00057</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0035999</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tetrahydrofolate interconversion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00096</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0009066</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aspartate family amino acid metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00103</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006222</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">UMP biosynthetic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00113</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0046500</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>S</italic>-Adenosylmethionine metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00125</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0015804</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutral amino acid transport</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00125</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006097</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glyoxylate cycle</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00125</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0030433</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Endoplasmic reticulum-associated ubiquitin- dependent protein degradation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00132</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0019627</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urea metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00169</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0015800</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acidic amino acid transport</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00169</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0000398</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mRNA splicing, via spliceosome</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00170</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0010540</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basipetal auxin transport</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00235</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0035435</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phosphate ion transmembrane transport</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00258</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006457</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein folding</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00262</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0051259</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein oligomerization</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00265</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006525</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arginine metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00265</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0016482</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cytoplasmic transport</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00284</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0016036</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cellular response to phosphate starvation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00288</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0043604</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amide biosynthetic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00295</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0019395</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fatty acid oxidation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00317</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006570</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tyrosine metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00326</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0052646</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alditol phosphate metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00326</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0010043</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Response to zinc ion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00346</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0055085</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transmembrane transport</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00377</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0000338</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein deneddylation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00436</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fructose 6-phosphate metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00436</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0043650</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dicarboxylic acid biosynthetic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00439</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0010501</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RNA secondary structure unwinding</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00439</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0009629</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Response to gravity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00447</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006103</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-Oxoglutarate metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00490</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0009833</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plant-type primary cell wall biogenesis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00490</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006610</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ribosomal protein import into nucleus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00490</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0010541</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acropetal auxin transport</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00540</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Galactose metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00540</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006511</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ubiquitin-dependent protein catabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00630</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0051275</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2;-Glucan catabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00735</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0009141</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nucleoside triphosphate metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00770</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0018208</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peptidyl-proline modification</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00803</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006486</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein glycosylation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00804</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0009624</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Response to nematode</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00847</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:1904659</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glucose transmembrane transport</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00872</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0046323</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glucose import</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00872</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006631</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fatty acid metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00878</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0044282</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Small molecule catabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00886</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s14"><title>Gene loss in <italic>H. ovalis</italic> and comparison of lost genes between the three seagrass species</title><p>A total of 1822 OGCsM genes were lost in <italic>H. ovalis</italic>, and these were compared with those previously reported as lost in both <italic>Z. muelleri</italic> and <italic>Z. marina</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">Golicz <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">Olsen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Table S4</xref>). A total of 1197 (65.6%) lost genes were shared between all three seagrass species, 187 were shared with either <italic>Z. muelleri</italic> or <italic>Z. marina</italic>, and 412 were only lost in <italic>H. ovalis</italic>. In comparison, 743 genes were only lost in the Zosteraceae lineage. Enriched GO terms for the 1822 OGCsM genes highlighted the loss of genes associated with ethylene synthesis and perception, and stomatal development (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The presence or absence of genes involved in stomatal development, ethylene synthesis and signalling, and terpenoid biosynthesis in <italic>H. ovalis</italic>, <italic>Z. marina</italic>, and <italic>Z. muelleri</italic> are listed in <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Significantly enriched biological process GO terms in the genes conserved in five other plant species (Arabidopsis, <italic>Oryza sativa</italic>, <italic>Musa acuminata</italic>, <italic>Phoenix dactylifera</italic> and <italic>Spirodela polyrhiza</italic>) but absent in <italic>H. ovalis</italic></p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Function</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO ID</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Term</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">Ethylene synthesis and signalling</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0009835</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fruit ripening</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;10</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0042218</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1-Aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylate biosynthetic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;10</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0009693</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethylene biosynthetic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;8</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0010105</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative regulation of ethylene-activated signalling pathway</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Stomata development</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0010375</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stomatal complex patterning</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00012</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:2000038</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regulation of stomatal complex development</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00608</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="22" colspan="1">Others</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0045168</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell&#x02013;cell signalling involved in cell fate commitment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006952</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Defence response</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0009626</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plant-type hypersensitive response</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0031640</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Killing of cells of other organism</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0010039</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Response to iron ion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00011</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0034644</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cellular response to UV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00014</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0071484</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cellular response to light intensity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00018</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0009773</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Photosynthetic electron transport in photosystem I</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00023</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0080027</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Response to herbivore</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00034</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0033473</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indoleacetic acid conjugate metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00034</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0009696</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Salicylic acid metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00059</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0033609</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oxalate metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00093</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0050832</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Defence response to fungus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00113</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0071423</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Malate transmembrane transport</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00209</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0042542</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Response to hydrogen peroxide</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00234</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:1900426</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive regulation of defence response to bacterium</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00239</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0010876</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lipid localization</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00313</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0018106</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peptidyl-histidine phosphorylation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00404</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0046688</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Response to copper ion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00558</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0010257</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NADH dehydrogenase complex assembly</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00608</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0009838</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abscission</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00704</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0071732</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cellular response to nitric oxide</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00791</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Presence and absence of genes involved in stomatal development, ethylene synthesis and signalling, and terpenoid biosynthesis in OGCsM, <italic>H. ovalis</italic>, <italic>Z. marina</italic>, and <italic>Z. muelleri</italic></p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene ID</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein name</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Function</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conserved in OGCsM</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Presence in <italic>H. ovalis</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Presence in <italic>Z. muelleri</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Presence in <italic>Z. marina</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">Stomata development</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT1G04110</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBT1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spacing and patterning</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT4G12970</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EPFL9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spacing and patterning</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT2G20875</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EPF1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spacing and patterning</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT1G80080</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TMM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spacing and patterning</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT1G34245</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EPF2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spacing and patterning</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT2G02820</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MYB88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Differentiation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT3G06120</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MUTE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Differentiation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT5G53210</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPCH</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Differentiation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT3G24140</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FAMA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Differentiation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT1G12860</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SCRM2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Differentiation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT1G14350</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FLP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Differentiation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">Ethylene synthesis and signalling</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT2G19590</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACO1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACC oxidase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT1G62380</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACO2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACC oxidase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT1G05010</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACO4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACC oxidase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT1G77330</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACO5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACC oxidase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT3G61510</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACS1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACC synthase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT1G01480</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACS2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACC synthase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT2G22810</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACS4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACC synthase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT5G65800</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACS5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACC synthase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT4G11280</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACS6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACC synthase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT4G26200</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACS7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACC synthase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT4G37770</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACS8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACC synthase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT3G49700</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACS9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACC synthase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT4G08040</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACS11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACC synthase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT2G40940</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ERS1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethylene receptor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT1G66340</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ETR1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethylene receptor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT3G23150</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ETR2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethylene receptor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT3G04580</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EIN4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethylene receptor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT5G03730</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTR1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Raf-like kinase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT5G03280</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EIN2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Signal transducer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT2G25490</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EBF1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EIN2 degradation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT5G25350</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EBF2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EIN2 degradation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">Terpenoid biosynthesis</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT3G25820</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPS-CIN</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Terpene synthase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT3G25830</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPS23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Terpene synthase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT4G16740</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPS03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Terpene synthase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT2G24210</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPS10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Terpene synthase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT3G25810</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPS24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Terpene synthase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fn-01"><p>Categories are: gene present (+), gene absent (&#x02212;), and information not available (NA).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s15"><title>
<italic>Halophila ovalis</italic> lost genes encoding NADH dehydrogenase-like complex assembly</title><p>The five most significantly enriched GO terms in the 412 genes that were only lost in <italic>H. ovalis</italic> were cellular response to light intensity (GO:0071484), cellular response to UV (GO:0034644), photosynthetic electron transport in photosystem I (GO:0009773), NADH dehydrogenase complex assembly (GO:0010257), and cellular response to salt stress (GO:0071472). A complete list of all significantly enriched terms is given in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Table S5</xref>. Closer examination revealed the loss of 23 (15 nuclear and 8 chloroplast) genes that encode the five subcomplexes in the NDH complex (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). In addition, 17 genes required for the supercomplex formation, including tethering of NDH to photosystem I, assembly of subunits, accessory proteins, and transcription factors, were absent in <italic>H. ovalis</italic>. Two proteins required for nitrate uptake and assimilation, nitrogen reductase 1 (NR1) and nitrate transporter (NRT3.1), were also lost in <italic>H. ovalis.</italic></p><table-wrap id="T4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p>Presence and absence of 40 nuclear and chloroplast-encoded genes involved in formation of the NDH complex</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene ID</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein name</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Function</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Presence in OGCsM</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Presence in <italic>H. ovalis</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Presence in <italic>Z. muelleri</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Presence in <italic>Z. marina</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">Nuclear encoded</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT1G70760</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NDHL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subunit A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT4G37925</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NDHM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subunit A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT5G58260</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NDHN</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subunit A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT1G74880</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NDHO</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subunit A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT4G23890</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NDHS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subunit ED</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT4G09350</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NDHT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subunit ED</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT5G21430</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NDHU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subunit ED</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT1G15980</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PNSB1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subunit B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT1G64770</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PNSB2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subunit B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT3G16250</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PNSB3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subunit B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT1G18730</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PNSB4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subunit B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT2G39470</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PNSL1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subunit B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT1G14150</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PNSL2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subunit L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT3G01440</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PNSL3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subunit L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT4G39710</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PNSL4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subunit L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT5G13120</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PNSL5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subunit L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT2G47910</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRR6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complex formation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT5G39210</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRR7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complex formation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT1G45474</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lhca5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complex formation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT1G19150</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lhca6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complex formation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT1G26230</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRR27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complex formation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT1G51100</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRR41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complex formation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT2G05620</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGR5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proton gradient regulation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT4G22890</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGRL1A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proton gradient regulation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT3G46790</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRR2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT2G01590</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRR3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT5G20935</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRR42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT2G01918</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PQL3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AT1G55370</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NDF5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">Chloroplast encoded</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>ATCG00890</italic>
<break/>
<italic>ATCG01250</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NDHB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subunit M</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>ATCG01010</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NDHF</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subunit M</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>ATCG00440</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NDHC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subunit M</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>ATCG01050</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NDHD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subunit M</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>ATCG01070</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NDHE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subunit M</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>ATCG01100</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NDHA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subunit M</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>ATCG01080</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NDHG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subunit M</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>ATCG01110</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NDHH</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subunit A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>ATCG00420</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NDHJ</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subunit A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>ATCG00430</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NDHK</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subunit A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>ATCG01090</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NDHI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subunit A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fn-02"><p>Categories are: gene present (+), gene absent (&#x02212;), and information not available (NA).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s16"><title>Co-evolution of genes for intracellular transport, cell wall, and ion transport-related genes in <italic>H. ovalis</italic> and <italic>Zostera</italic></title><p>We identified a set of 1748 genes that are unique to <italic>Z. muelleri</italic> and <italic>Z. marina</italic>, termed OGCZ (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Fig. S1</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Table S6</xref>), with 57 also found to be conserved in <italic>H. ovalis</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Table S7</xref>). Putative functions of these 57 genes were inferred by matching their protein domains to the corresponding best aligned Arabidopsis gene. Out of 57 OGCZ groups, 45 have identical domains (indicated as InterProScan IDs) to the corresponding Arabidopsis genes. A total of eight of them have fewer or different domains from Arabidopsis, and four of them have no domains assigned (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Table S7</xref>).</p><p>The majority of the 57 OGCZ genes conserved in <italic>H. ovalis</italic> are predicted to be involved in protein secretion and intracellular transport, with significantly enriched terms annotated with cellular component ontology, including organelles of the intracellular transport pathways, namely Golgi apparatus, trans-Golgi network, and endosome, and nearly half of the remaining terms intracellular transport-related (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). A total of 13 genes are predicted to function in protein secretion and intracellular transport, mainly as transport proteins or transport regulators. Nine genes are associated with cell wall construction, organization, and modification, while other predicted functions include ion or proton transport, lipid catabolism, transcription and translation-related, protein ubiquitination, and histone assembly (<xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 5.</label><caption><p>Fifty-seven orthologous groups of seagrass-specific genes shared in two Zosteraceae species (<italic>Z. muelleri</italic> and <italic>Z. marina</italic>) and <italic>Halophila</italic> categorized by predicted function</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Category of related function</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Name of best TAIR10 hit corresponding to <italic>Zostera</italic> orthologue</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ID of best TAIR10 hit corresponding to <italic>Zostera</italic> orthologue</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative gene function</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="10" colspan="1">Protein secretion and intracellular transport</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Endoplasmic reticulum retention defective 2B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT3G25040.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retention mechanism</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Endoplasmic reticulum-type calcium-transporting ATPase 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G10130.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Calcium and manganese ion transport</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RAB GTPase homologue A1F</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT5G60860.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTPase activity</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RAB GTPase homologue A2B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G07410.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTPase activity</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Secretory carrier 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G61250.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Integral membrane protein</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NOD26-like intrinsic protein 1;2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT4G18910.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aquaporin</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mitochondrial substrate carrier family protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT3G53940.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Substrate transport</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mitochondrial import inner membrane translocase subunit Tim17/Tim22/Tim23 family protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT5G63000.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein transport</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transducin/WD40 repeat-like superfamily protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT3G01340.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein transport</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein of unknown function</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G09330.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="9" colspan="1">Cell wall</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Expansin A16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT3G55500.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell wall loosening</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Expansin A1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G69530.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell wall loosening</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Galacturonosyltransferase-like 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT3G50760.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell wall organization</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Xyloglucan endotransglucosylase/hydrolase 5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT5G13870.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell wall organization</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glucan synthase-like 8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT2G36850.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Callose synthesis</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>S</italic>-Adenosyl-L-methionine-dependent methyltransferases superfamily protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT4G34050.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lignin biosynthesis</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peroxidase superfamily protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT5G05340.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lignin biosynthesis</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cotton Golgi-related 2 (pectin methyltransferase)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT3G49720.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell wall modification</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vascular related NAC-domain protein 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT2G18060.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Xylem secondary cell wall formation</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Ion flux and sequestering</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP synthase epsilon chain, mitochondrial</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G51650.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proton-transporting ATPase activity</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vacuolar proton ATPase A1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT2G28520.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proton-transporting ATPase activity</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Calmodulin 4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G66410.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Calcium ion binding</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">Lipid catabolism</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trigalactosyldiacylglycerol 5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G27695.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lipid transport</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GDSL-like lipase/acylhydrolase superfamily protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G29670.1<break/>AT5G45670.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lipid catabolic process</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peroxin 6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G03000.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peroxisomal matrix protein import</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alkaline phytoceramidase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT4G22330.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ceramide synthase involved in sphingolipid metabolism</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Transcription-related</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RNA polymerase subunit beta</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATCG00190.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constituent of RNA polymerase B</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-mRNA-splicing factor SPF27 homologue</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT3G18165.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mRNA splicing of resistance genes</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">Ribosome/ translation-related</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ribosomal protein L16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATCG00790.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Structural constituent of ribosome</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ribosomal protein S26e family protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT2G40510.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Structural constituent of ribosome</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ribosomal protein S8e family protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT5G59240.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Structural constituent of ribosome</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ribosomal protein S2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATCG00160.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Structural constituent of ribosome</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eukaryotic translation initiation factor 3A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT4G11420.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constituent of eukaryotic initiation factor 3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">Protein ubiquitination</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F-box protein PP2-A13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT3G61060.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein ubiquitination</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTB/POZ domain-containing protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G63850.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein ubiquitination</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ubiquitin-conjugating enzyme 28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G64230.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein ubiquitination</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ubiquitin-like protein 5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT5G42300.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ubiquitin-like modification</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Histone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Histone H2A.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT3G20670.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Histones/DNA binding/nucleosome assembly</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Histone H3.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT4G40030.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Histones/DNA binding/nucleosome assembly</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="15" colspan="1">Others</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Photosystem II light harvesting complex gene 2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT2G05100.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constituent of light harvesting complex II</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alternative oxidase 1A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT3G22370.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alternative oxidase activity</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tubulin folding cofactor D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT3G60740.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Microtubule stability</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asparagine synthetase 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT5G65010.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asparagine biosynthesis</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glutamate-1-semialdehyde 2,1-aminomutase 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT3G48730.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Porphyrin-containing compound metabolism</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Membrane-associated progesterone binding protein 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT3G48890.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Porphyrin binding</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thioredoxin superfamily protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT3G62950.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Electron carrier activity</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA polymerase epsilon catalytic subunit</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G08260.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA replication proofreading</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NAC domain containing protein 32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G77450.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transcription factor</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA-binding protein phosphatase 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT2G25620.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein phosphatase activity</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein kinase 1B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT2G28930.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serine/threonine kinase activity</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDP-glycosyltransferase superfamily protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT5G04480.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adenine nucleotide alpha hydrolases-like superfamily protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G11360.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein of unknown function (DUF300)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G11200.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein of unknown function (DUF803)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G34470.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fn-22"><p>Gene functions were predicted with corresponding Arabidopsis gene of highest sequence similarity.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig fig-type="figure" id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Significantly enriched cellular component GO terms in seagrass-specific genes. Terms in green are subcomponents or organelles of the intracellular transport pathways.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery14701"/></fig></sec><sec id="s17"><title>Molecular comparison of seagrass ribosomal proteins</title><p>Ribosomal 50S L16 orthologues from the two <italic>Zostera</italic> species, <italic>H. ovalis</italic>, and 12 species in the Alismatales order were aligned, together with predicted proteins from five model land plants (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Table S1</xref>). We identified nine amino acid positions that appear to be specific to the seagrasses <italic>H. ovalis</italic>, <italic>Z. muelleri</italic>, and <italic>Z. marina</italic> (white arrows in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>) and conserved among the other 17 angiosperms (12 belong to the Alismatales order, eight are freshwater plants), one charophyte and one chlorophyte.</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>Ribosomal protein L16 multiple sequence alignments between 19 species (AMA, <italic>Alocasia macrorhizzos</italic>; ATH, Arabidopsis; DSE, <italic>Dieffenbachia seguine</italic>; EAU, <italic>Epiprenum aureum</italic>; ECA, <italic>Elodia canadensis</italic>; LMI, <italic>Lemna minor</italic>; MAC, <italic>Musa acuminata</italic>; NFL, <italic>Najas flexilis</italic>; OSA, <italic>Oryza sativa</italic>; PDA, <italic>Phoenix dactylifera</italic>; PPE, <italic>Potamogeton perfoliatus</italic>; SLI, <italic>Sagittaria lichuanensis</italic>; SLY, <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>; SPO, <italic>Spirodela polyrhiza</italic>; SPU, <italic>Spirodela pundata</italic>; TTH, <italic>Tofieldia thibetica</italic>; WAU, <italic>Wolfia australiana</italic>) together with three seagrasses (HAL, <italic>H. ovalis</italic>; ZMA, <italic>Z. marina</italic>; ZMU, <italic>Z. muelleri</italic>). Species and corresponding IDs are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Table S1</xref>. Amino acids that were conserved within the non-seagrass group or among seagrasses are coloured according to physicochemical properties based on &#x02018;Zappo&#x02019; colour scheme. White arrows indicated seagrass-specific mutations.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery14702"/></fig><p>A phylogenetic tree for these 22 species based on this protein sequence, which describes the relationships between orthologues of these 22 species, separates the seagrass species (<italic>H. ovalis</italic>, <italic>Z. muelleri</italic>, and <italic>Z. marina</italic>) from the other species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). The separation of the two <italic>Zostera</italic> orthologues from <italic>H. ovalis</italic> is also well-supported. Sister genera of both <italic>Halophila</italic> and <italic>Zostera</italic> grouped together as members of core alismatids (red in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>) (Alismatidae <italic>sensu</italic>; <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">Les and Tippery, 2013</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>Phylogenetic tree showing distance between ribosome protein L16 sequences of 17 species (AMA, <italic>Alocasia macrorhizzos</italic>; ATH, Arabidopsis; DSE, <italic>Dieffenbachia seguine</italic>; EAU, <italic>Epiprenum aureum</italic>; ECA, <italic>Elodia canadensis</italic>; LMI, <italic>Lemna minor</italic>; MAC, <italic>Musa acuminata</italic>; NFL, <italic>Najas flexilis</italic>; OSA, <italic>Oryza sativa</italic>; PDA, <italic>Phoenix dactylifera</italic>; PPE, <italic>Potamogeton perfoliatus</italic>; SLI, <italic>Sagittaria lichuanensis</italic>; SLY, <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>; SPO, <italic>Spirodela polyrhiza</italic>; SPU, <italic>Spirodela pundata</italic>; TTH, <italic>Tofieldia thibetica</italic>; WAU, <italic>Wolfia australiana</italic>) together with three seagrasses (HAL, <italic>H. ovalis</italic>; ZMA, <italic>Z. marina</italic>; ZMU, <italic>Z. muelleri</italic>). The order and habitat of species were indicated in the second part of each ID: DL, dicot, land; ML, monocot, land; MLA, monocot, land, Alismatales; MMA, monocot, marine, Alismatales; MWA, monocot, freshwater, Alismatales. Complete details are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Table S1</xref>. IDs coloured in red are members of core Alismatids, blue are members of Araceae, and black are others. Branches are labelled with bootstrap values (%).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery14703"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s18"><title>Discussion</title><p>The concurrent absence of multiple genes in <italic>H. ovalis</italic>, <italic>Z. muelleri</italic>, and <italic>Z. marina</italic> suggests independently evolved convergent adaptation of seagrasses to the marine environment. Seagrass leaves lack stomata and the flowers have simplified structures when compared with terrestrial angiosperms (<xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">Kuo and Hartog, 2006</xref>). The loss of genes in stomata patterning and differentiation, and in sepal and petal development was previously described in <italic>Zostera</italic>, together with the loss of gaseous hormones and metabolites, such as ethylene, methyl jasmonate, and secondary volatile terpenes (<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">Golicz <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">Olsen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). Consistent with the low diffusion rate of gases underwater, the absence of ethylene production in seagrasses avoids accumulation in the tissues. In flood-adapted land plants, the ethylene signal is used to sense submergence and induces a response to flooding (<xref rid="CIT0070" ref-type="bibr">Voesenek <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). Ethylene biosynthesis and signalling also play an important role in plant response to salinity (<xref rid="CIT0081" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). There is conflicting evidence of ethylene as a positive or negative regulator during salinity stress in different species at different developmental stages (<xref rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr">Tao <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>), suggesting that some species adjust their sensitivity to environmental factors through regulation of the ethylene signalling pathway. As the loss of ethylene genes is observed in both <italic>H. ovalis</italic> and <italic>Zostera</italic>, it is likely that ethylene is selected against during seagrass adaptation to a submerged marine lifestyle.</p><p>The sharing of OGCZ genes in <italic>H. ovalis</italic> to form a seagrass-specific gene set identifies orthologous relationships that appear to be unique to seagrass adaptation, despite their evolutionary distance and multiple origins. It is important to note that these 57 OGCZ genes are not novel genes but genes that have diverged sufficiently to cluster separately from other plants in orthologue analysis. The functions of these genes were not annotated but inferred by homology using annotated Arabidopsis genes. The majority of these genes are predicted to be involved in intracellular transport and in cell wall organization and modification. In plant cells, secreted proteins are processed through the Golgi apparatus as cargo molecules and sorted by receptors in the trans-Golgi network to different destinations (<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">Brandizzi and Barlowe, 2013</xref>). Non-cellulosic cell wall matrix polysaccharides are among the wide range of vesicles synthesized and transported by the Golgi apparatus (<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">Driouich <italic>et al.</italic>, 1993</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">Lerouxel <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">Driouich <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Besides catalytic mechanisms of glycosyltransferases and nucleotide-sugar conversions for polysaccharide assembly, the Golgi is also responsible for methylation of the cell wall polysaccharides. There are significant differences between cell walls of seagrasses and land plants. Seagrass cell walls contain sulfated polysaccharides (<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">Aquino <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>) and seagrass pectin contains a rare class of apiose-substituted homogalacturonan (<xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">Ovodov <italic>et al.</italic>, 1971</xref>) with low levels of methyl esterification (<xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">Khotimchenko <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). These two modifications are thought to provide salt tolerance by increasing the polyanionic potential of cell walls (<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">Aquino <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">Olsen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). An expansion of pectin catabolic and methylesterase genes was observed in the genomes of <italic>Z. muelleri</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>) and <italic>Z. marina</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">Olsen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>), suggesting complex pectin modification in seagrasses. Interestingly, within the list of seagrass-specific genes conserved in <italic>H. ovalis</italic>, CGR2 (cotton Golgi-related 2), a methyltransferase, was shown to be involved in pectin methylesterification in Arabidopsis (<xref rid="CIT0073" ref-type="bibr">Weraduwage <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). Tubulin cofactor, which is responsible for the stability of microtubules (<xref rid="CIT0082" ref-type="bibr">Zhu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>), is also found to be conserved among seagrasses. A total of five genes that encode RAB GTPases, the key regulators of vesicle trafficking (<xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">Miserey-Lenkei <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0068" ref-type="bibr">Valente <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>), were also conserved across both seagrass lineages. In Arabidopsis, knockouts of some members of the RAB GTPases have demonstrated roles in salinity stress tolerance (<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Asaoka <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). It is likely that this conservation of cell wall-related genes, as well as proteins involved in intracellular transport, in both families of seagrasses is linked to modification of cell wall composition as one of the adaptations to osmotic stress.</p><p>Multiple salt-tolerance mechanisms have been hypothesized in seagrasses (reviewed in <xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr">Touchette, 2007</xref>), including cell wall rigidity, selective ion flux and vacuolar ion sequestering, and the synthesis of compatible solutes and amino acids (<xref rid="CIT0080" ref-type="bibr">Ye and Zhao, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">Carpaneto <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0067" ref-type="bibr">Touchette <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">Cambridge <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>). To avoid salt damage, plant cells adjust osmotic balance through influx and efflux of ions through the transmembrane transport proteins, assisted by H<sup>+</sup> pumps (<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">Hasegawa, 2013</xref>). Three genes, namely a component of a vacuolar proton pump, ATP synthase and calmodulin, were identified as conserved across the two seagrass lineages. Moreover, vacuolar proton ATPase A1 has been shown to be responsive to salt stress in sugar beet (<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">Kirsch <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>). This collection of genes may have a role in osmotic homeostasis of cells in the marine environment.</p><p>Lipid transport and catabolism is another important role of the intracellular transport system. The endoplasmic reticulum synthesizes and exports phospholipids, sterols, and storage lipids for various purposes, including formation of membrane structures (<xref rid="CIT0069" ref-type="bibr">van Meer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). A total of four genes involved in lipid transport and catabolism were conserved in all three seagrass species, including ceramidase, which is responsible for sphingolipid metabolism. Sphingolipids provide membrane structure and are involved in cellular signal transduction (<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Hannun and Obeid, 2008</xref>). The difference between lipids of seagrasses and land plants is not well understood, but expansion in genes related to sphingolipid metabolism was observed in <italic>Z. marina</italic> when compared with duckweed (<xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">Olsen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). Another alkaline ceramidase had been shown to regulate cell turgor pressure in Arabidopsis (<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">Chen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>), but more evidence is needed to determine whether seagrass-specific lipid metabolism plays a role in marine adaptation.</p><p>Two members of the core histone family are conserved in seagrasses. The domains in histone families, particularly H2A and H3, demonstrate expansion in numbers and variety, but with strong conservation of each variant across species (<xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">Kawashima <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). Ribosomal constituents were previously identified as modified in <italic>Z. muelleri</italic> when compared with land plants (<xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>) and positively selected in <italic>Z. marina</italic> and <italic>P. oceanica</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0077" ref-type="bibr">Wissler <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>), and our results demonstrate that these genes are also conserved in <italic>H. ovalis</italic>. The basis for the observed differences in ribosomal gene sequences is not known, but it is postulated to be related to salt tolerance. Translation, and consequently protein synthesis are known to be salt-sensitive in yeast and plants (<xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">Rausell <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>). For example, the expression of genes encoding the translation apparatus was lower when the transcriptome of Arabidopsis was compared with the halophyte salt cress (<xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr">Taji <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>). If seagrass ribosomes are adapted to relatively high salinity, this may have an application for improvement of salt tolerance in crop species.</p><p>Sequence variations were identified in chloroplast-encoded 50S ribosomal protein L16. Nine amino acid mutations were shared by the three seagrass species despite belonging to two separate clades (<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">Les <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">Li and Zhou, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">Les and Tippery, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">Petersen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">Ross <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). The possible convergence is highlighted by the absence of these mutations in representatives of sister genera for both clades. <italic>Potamogeton perfoliatus</italic> belongs to the tepaloid clade together with Zosteraceae, whereas <italic>Najas flexilis</italic>, <italic>Elodea canadensis</italic> and <italic>Sagittaria lichuanensis</italic> belong to the petaloid clade together with <italic>H. ovalis</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">Les <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">Li and Zhou, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">Les and Tippery, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">Petersen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">Ross <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). Protein sequences of L16 in these non-marine species have greater similarity with other monocots and dicots than with the seagrasses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>) suggesting selection and convergent evolution to the marine habitat in seagrasses. Since <italic>N. flexilis</italic> and <italic>P. perfoliatus</italic> shared submergence characteristics with seagrasses, the mutations may be linked to salinity tolerance, rather than an ability to survive underwater. These results complement the seagrass clustering of OGCZ through OrthoMCL analysis and provided further molecular evidence of convergent evolution of seagrasses.</p><p>Differences between <italic>H. ovalis</italic> and the two Zosteraceae species were identified in genes encoding NDH, a major protein complex residing in the thylakoid membrane of chloroplasts that participates in cyclic electron flow pathways as an oxidoreductase (reviewed in <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">Peltier <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). As the NDH complex is only present in the Streptophyta lineage, which includes charophyte algae and land plants, acquisition of novel NDH genes likely occurred during terrestrial transition, and NDH is hypothesized to be one of the innovations enabling land plant evolution (<xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">Mart&#x000ed;n <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">Ruhlman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). The absence of genes encoding NDH subunits and proteins required for complex formation in <italic>H. ovalis</italic> points to a total loss of the NDH complex in the <italic>H. ovalis</italic> thylakoid. Rare evidence of loss or pseudogenization of plastid NDH genes has been reported in independent lineages (<xref rid="CIT0078" ref-type="bibr">Wolfe <italic>et al.</italic>, 1992</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">Haberhausen and Zetsche, 1994</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">Funk <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">Braukmann <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">Logacheva <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>), including several genera in the Hydrocharitaceae family (<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">Iles <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">Peredo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0076" ref-type="bibr">Wilkin and Mayo, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">Ross <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). The observed loss of NDH genes in <italic>H. ovalis</italic> is the first report of their dispensability among Alismatales.</p><p>Several reasons for NDH dispensability have been suggested (<xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">Stefanovi&#x00107; and Olmstead, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">Iles <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">Peredo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0079" ref-type="bibr">Xu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). <xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">Ross <italic>et al.</italic> (2016)</xref> suggest that NDH loss enabled low N investment as an adaptation to nutrient deficiency in the submerged environment. This is plausible, as <italic>H. ovalis</italic> is adapted to grow in low nutrient sediments (<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">Carruthers <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>), and examples of nitrogen sources affecting NDH expression have been reported in green algae (<xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">Peltier and Schmidt, 1991</xref>). Interestingly, two proteins related to nitrate uptake, nitrogen reductase 1 (NR1) and nitrate transporter (NRT3.1) are also lost in <italic>H. ovalis</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Table S4</xref>). One limitation of seagrass nitrogen uptake studies is that the potential contribution of microbial communities is not accounted for, and may be compensating for the loss of NDH in <italic>H. ovalis</italic>, as demonstrated in myco-heterotrophic liverworts (<xref rid="CIT0075" ref-type="bibr">Wickett <italic>et al</italic>., 2008<italic>a</italic></xref>,<xref rid="CIT0074" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>). Cyanobacteria on leaves have been shown to contribute to nitrogen uptake in <italic>Posidonia</italic> (Jeremy Bougoure, personal communication). However, further targeted studies are required to determine whether the loss of the NDH complex in <italic>H. ovalis</italic> is related to nitrogen uptake.</p></sec><sec id="s19"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Together, the conservation of gene loss and the sharing of seagrass-specific orthologues in these two independent lineages, despite the phylogenetic distance, has shed light on the genetics of marine adaptation in angiosperms of land plant ancestry. These results also present another example of habitat-driven parallel evolution in the plant kingdom.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s20"><title>Supplementary data</title><p>Supplementary data are available at <italic>JXB</italic> online.</p><p>Fig. S1. Venn diagram showing the number of shared orthologous clusters among six species (Arabidopsis, <italic>M. acuminata</italic>, <italic>O. sativa</italic>, <italic>S. polyrhiza</italic>, and two Zosteraceae species).</p><p>Table S1. Species selected for multiple sequence alignment of orthologous proteins.</p><p>Table S2. Number of <italic>H. ovalis</italic> reads sequenced and remaining after filtering process.</p><p>Table S3. List of TAIR genes that were conserved in OGCsM and at least one species among <italic>H. ovalis</italic>, <italic>Z. muelleri</italic>, and <italic>Z. marina</italic>.</p><p>Table S4. List of TAIR genes that were conserved in OGCsM but absent in at least one species among <italic>H. ovalis</italic>, <italic>Z. muelleri</italic>, and <italic>Z. marina</italic>.</p><p>Table S5. Significantly enriched biological process GO terms in the genes that were lost in <italic>H. ovalis</italic>, but present in <italic>Z. muelleri</italic>, <italic>Z. marina</italic>, and five other plant species.</p><p>Table S6. List of orthologous groups that are conserved in <italic>Z. muelleri</italic> and <italic>Z. marina</italic> (OGCZ).</p><p>Table S7. List of OGCZ orthologous groups that are conserved in <italic>H. ovalis</italic> and the best corresponding TAIR ID hit; each protein ID is followed by InterProScan IDs of domains found or no domain found (NA).</p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sup1"><label>Supplementary Tables</label><media xlink:href="ery147_suppl_supplementary_tables_s1_s7.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sup2"><label>Supplementary Figure</label><media xlink:href="ery147_suppl_supplementary_figure_s1.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors would like to acknowledge funding support from the Australian Research Council (Projects LP160100030, LP140100537, LP130100925, LP110100200, and LP0989200). Support is also acknowledged from the Queensland Cyber Infrastructure Foundation (QCIF), the Pawsey Supercomputing Centre with funding from the Australian Government and the Government of Western Australia and resources from the National Computational Infrastructure (NCI), which is supported by the Australian Government.</p></ack><glossary><def-list><title>Abbreviations:</title><def-item><term id="term1">Mya</term><def><p>million years ago</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term2">NDH</term><def><p>NADH dehydrogenase-like</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term3">OGC</term><def><p>orthologous gene cluster</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term4">OGCsM</term><def><p>orthologous gene cluster with at least one gene originating from a monocot species</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term5">OGCZ</term><def><p>orthologous gene cluster unique to Zosteraceae</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term6">TAIR</term><def><p>The Arabidopsis Information Resource.</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rahnenfuhrer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<source>topGO: Enrichment analysis for Gene Ontology</source>. R package version 2.26.0. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioconductor.uib.no/2.7/bioc/html/topGO.html">http://bioconductor.uib.no/2.7/bioc/html/topGO.html</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aquino</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grativol</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mour&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Rising from the sea: correlations between sulfated polysaccharides and salinity in plants</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><volume>6</volume>, <fpage>e18862</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21552557</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aquino</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Landeira-Fernandez</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valente</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mour&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Occurrence of sulfated galactans in marine angiosperms: evolutionary implications</article-title>. <source>Glycobiology</source><volume>15</volume>, <fpage>11</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15317737</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Asaoka</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uemura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fujimoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> RABA1 GTPases are involved in transport between the trans-Golgi network and the plasma membrane, and are required for salinity stress tolerance</article-title>. <source>The Plant Journal</source><volume>73</volume>, <fpage>240</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>249</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22974509</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bankevich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nurk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Antipov</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>SPAdes: a new genome assembly algorithm and its applications to single-cell sequencing</article-title>. <source>Journal of Computational Biology</source><volume>19</volume>, <fpage>455</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>477</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22506599</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandizzi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barlowe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Organization of the ER-Golgi interface for membrane traffic control</article-title>. <source>Nature Reviews. Molecular Cell Biology</source><volume>14</volume>, <fpage>382</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>392</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23698585</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Braukmann</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuzmina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stefanovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Loss of all plastid <italic>ndh</italic> genes in Gnetales and conifers: extent and evolutionary significance for the seed plant phylogeny</article-title>. <source>Current Genetics</source><volume>55</volume>, <fpage>323</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>337</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19449185</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Camacho</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coulouris</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Avagyan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Papadopoulos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bealer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Madden</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>BLAST+: architecture and applications</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><volume>10</volume>, <fpage>421</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20003500</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cambridge</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zavala-Perez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cawthray</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mondon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kendrick</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Effects of high salinity from desalination brine on growth, photosynthesis, water relations and osmolyte concentrations of seagrass <italic>Posidonia australis</italic></article-title>. <source>Marine Pollution Bulletin</source><volume>115</volume>, <fpage>252</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>260</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27989371</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carpaneto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Naso</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paganetto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cornara</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pesce</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gambale</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Properties of ion channels in the protoplasts of the Mediterranean seagrass <italic>Posidonia oceanica</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell and Environment</source><volume>27</volume>, <fpage>279</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>292</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carruthers</surname><given-names>TJB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dennison</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kendrick</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Waycott</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cambridge</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Seagrasses of south-west Australia: a conceptual synthesis of the world&#x02019;s most diverse and extensive seagrass meadows</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology</source><volume>350</volume>, <fpage>21</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>45</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gituru</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>QF</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Generic phylogeny, historical biogeography and character evolution of the cosmopolitan aquatic plant family Hydrocharitaceae</article-title>. <source>BMC Evolutionary Biology</source><volume>12</volume>, <fpage>30</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22404786</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>DQ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>The Arabidopsis alkaline ceramidase TOD1 is a key turgor pressure regulator in plant cells</article-title>. <source>Nature Communications</source><volume>6</volume>, <fpage>6030</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chikhi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Medvedev</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Informed and automated <italic>k</italic>-mer size selection for genome assembly</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>30</volume>, <fpage>31</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>37</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23732276</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coyer</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoarau</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tronholm</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Veldsink</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Phylogeny and temporal divergence of the seagrass family Zosteraceae using one nuclear and three chloroplast loci</article-title>. <source>Systematics and Biodiversity</source><volume>11</volume>, <fpage>271</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>284</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Driouich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Faye</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Staehelin</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1993</year>
<article-title>The plant Golgi apparatus: a factory for complex polysaccharides and glycoproteins</article-title>. <source>Trends in Biochemical Sciences</source><volume>18</volume>, <fpage>210</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>214</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8346556</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Driouich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Follet-Gueye</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kousar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chevalier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vicr&#x000e9;-Gibouin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lerouxel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Golgi-mediated synthesis and secretion of matrix polysaccharides of the primary cell wall of higher plants</article-title>. <source>Frontiers in Plant Science</source><volume>3</volume>, <fpage>79</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22639665</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fellows</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year> wordcloud: Word Clouds. R package version 2.5. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=wordcloud">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=wordcloud</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fukushima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alvarez-Ponce</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Genome of the pitcher plant <italic>Cephalotus</italic> reveals genetic changes associated with carnivory</article-title>. <source>Nature Ecology &#x00026; Evolution</source><volume>1</volume>, <fpage>59</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28812732</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Funk</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krupinska</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>UG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Complete DNA sequences of the plastid genomes of two parasitic flowering plant species, <italic>Cuscuta reflexa</italic> and <italic>Cuscuta gronovii</italic></article-title>. <source>BMC Plant Biology</source><volume>7</volume>, <fpage>45</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17714582</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gasteiger</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gattiker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoogland</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ivanyi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Appel</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bairoch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>ExPASy: The proteomics server for in-depth protein knowledge and analysis</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><volume>31</volume>, <fpage>3784</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3788</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12824418</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Golicz</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schliep</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Larkum</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dolferus</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Batley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sablok</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ralph</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Genome-wide survey of the seagrass <italic>Zostera muelleri</italic> suggests modification of the ethylene signalling network</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><volume>66</volume>, <fpage>1489</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1498</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25563969</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guindon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delsuc</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dufayard</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gascuel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Estimating maximum likelihood phylogenies with PhyML</article-title>. <source>Methods in Molecular Biology</source><volume>537</volume>, <fpage>113</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>137</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19378142</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haberhausen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zetsche</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1994</year>
<article-title>Functional loss of all ndh genes in an otherwise relatively unaltered plastid genome of the holoparasitic flowering plant <italic>Cuscuta reflexa</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Molecular Biology</source><volume>24</volume>, <fpage>217</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>222</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8111019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hannun</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Obeid</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Principles of bioactive lipid signalling: lessons from sphingolipids</article-title>. <source>Nature Reviews. Molecular Cell Biology</source><volume>9</volume>, <fpage>139</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>150</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18216770</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Sodium (Na<sup>+</sup>) homeostasis and salt tolerance of plants</article-title>. <source>Environmental and Experimental Botany</source><volume>92</volume>, <fpage>19</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hidalgo</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Garnatje</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mumbr&#x000fa;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vigo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vall&#x000e8;s</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Genome size in aquatic and wetland plants: fitting with the large genome constraint hypothesis with a few relevant exceptions</article-title>. <source>Plant Systematics and Evolution</source><volume>301</volume>, <fpage>1927</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1936</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O&#x02019;Donnell</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barboline</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barkman</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Convergent evolution of caffeine in plants by co-option of exapted ancestral enzymes</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source><volume>113</volume>, <fpage>10613</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10618</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iles</surname><given-names>WJD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>A well-supported phylogenetic framework for the monocot order Alismatales reveals multiple losses of the plastid NADH dehydrogenase complex and a strong long-branch effect</article-title>. <source>Early Events in Monocot Evolution</source><volume>83</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Binns</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>InterProScan 5: genome-scale protein function classification</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>30</volume>, <fpage>1236</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1240</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24451626</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fass</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<source>Sickle: A sliding-window, adaptive, quality-based trimming tool for FastQ files (Version 1.33)</source>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/najoshi/sickle">https://github.com/najoshi/sickle</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Katoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Misawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miyata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>MAFFT: a novel method for rapid multiple sequence alignment based on fast Fourier transform</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><volume>30</volume>, <fpage>3059</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3066</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12136088</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawashima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lorkovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nishihama</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ishizaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Axelsson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yelagandula</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kohchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Diversification of histone H2A variants during plant evolution</article-title>. <source>Trends in Plant Science</source><volume>20</volume>, <fpage>419</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>425</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25983206</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0034"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khotimchenko</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khozhaenko</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kovalev</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khotimchenko</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Cerium binding activity of pectins isolated from the seagrasses <italic>Zostera marina</italic> and <italic>Phyllospadix iwatensis</italic></article-title>. <source>Marine Drugs</source><volume>10</volume>, <fpage>834</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>848</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22690146</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirsch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>An</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Viereck</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>L&#x000f6;w</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rausch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>Salt stress induces an increased expression of V-type H<sup>+</sup>-ATPase in mature sugar beet leaves</article-title>. <source>Plant Molecular Biology</source><volume>32</volume>, <fpage>543</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>547</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8980504</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0036"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schopmeyer</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kyhn-Hansen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Madden</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Tropical seagrass species tolerance to hypersalinity stress</article-title>. <source>Aquatic Botany</source><volume>86</volume>, <fpage>14</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0037"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>den Hartog</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Seagrass morphology, anatomy, and ultrastructure</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Larkum</surname><given-names>AWD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Orth</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group>, eds. <source>Seagrasses: Biology, Ecology and Conservation</source>. <publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>, <fpage>51</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>87</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0038"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Larkum</surname><given-names>AWD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Orth</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<source>Seagrasses: biology, ecology and conservation</source>. <publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0039"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Golicz</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>The genome of a southern hemisphere seagrass species (<italic>Zostera muelleri</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>172</volume>, <fpage>272</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>283</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27373688</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0040"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lerouxel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cavalier</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liepman</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keegstra</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Biosynthesis of plant cell wall polysaccharides&#x02014;a complex process</article-title>. <source>Current Opinion in Plant Biology</source><volume>9</volume>, <fpage>621</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>630</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17011813</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0041"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Les</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cleland</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Waycott</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Phylogenetic studies in Alismatidae, II: evolution of marine angiosperms (seagrasses) and hydrophily</article-title>. <source>Systematic Botany</source><volume>22</volume>, <fpage>443</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>463</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0042"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Les</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tippery</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>In time and with water ... the systematics of alismatid monocotyledons</article-title>. <source>Early Events in Monocot Evolution</source><volume>83</volume>, <fpage>118</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>164</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0043"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stoeckert</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>OrthoMCL: identification of ortholog groups for eukaryotic genomes</article-title>. <source>Genome Research</source><volume>13</volume>, <fpage>2178</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2189</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12952885</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0044"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>ZK</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Phylogenetic studies of the core Alismatales inferred from morphology and <italic>rbc</italic>L sequences</article-title>. <source>Progress in Natural Science</source><volume>19</volume>, <fpage>931</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>945</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0045"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Logacheva</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schelkunov</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Penin</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Sequencing and analysis of plastid genome in mycoheterotrophic orchid <italic>Neottia nidus-avis</italic></article-title>. <source>Genome Biology and Evolution</source><volume>3</volume>, <fpage>1296</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1303</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21971517</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0046"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mart&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Funk</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Serrot</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Poltnigg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sabater</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Functional characterization of the thylakoid Ndh complex phosphorylation by site-directed mutations in the <italic>ndhF</italic> gene</article-title>. <source>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta</source><volume>1787</volume>, <fpage>920</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>928</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19272354</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0047"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miserey-Lenkei</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chalancon</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bardin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Formstecher</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goud</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Echard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Rab and actomyosin-dependent fission of transport vesicles at the Golgi complex</article-title>. <source>Nature Cell Biology</source><volume>12</volume>, <fpage>645</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>654</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20562865</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0048"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>XV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hofler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Glasenapp</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thangaradjou</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Papenbrock</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>New insights into DNA barcoding of seagrasses</article-title>. <source>Systematics and Biodiversity</source><volume>13</volume>, <fpage>496</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>508</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0049"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rouz&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Verhelst</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>The genome of the seagrass <italic>Zostera marina</italic> reveals angiosperm adaptation to the sea</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>530</volume>, <fpage>331</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>335</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26814964</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0050"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ord</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Summers</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Repeated evolution and the impact of evolutionary history on adaptation</article-title>. <source>BMC Evolutionary Biology</source><volume>15</volume>, <fpage>137</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26156849</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0051"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ovodov</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ovodova</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bondaren</surname><given-names>OD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krasikov</surname><given-names>IN</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1971</year>
<article-title>The pectic substances of <italic>zosteraceae</italic>: Part IV. Pectinase digestion of zosterine</article-title>. <source>Carbohydrate Research</source><volume>18</volume>, <fpage>311</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>318</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0052"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paterson</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>YR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schertz</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Doebley</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pinson</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stansel</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Irvine</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1995</year>
<article-title>Convergent domestication of cereal crops by independent mutations at corresponding genetic loci</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>269</volume>, <fpage>1714</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1718</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17821643</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0053"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peltier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aro</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shikanai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>NDH-1 and NDH-2 plastoquinone reductases in oxygenic photosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Plant Biology</source><volume>67</volume>, <fpage>55</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>80</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0054"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peltier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1991</year>
<article-title>Chlororespiration: an adaptation to nitrogen deficiency in <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic></article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source><volume>88</volume>, <fpage>4791</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4795</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0055"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peredo</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>UM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Les</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>The plastid genome of <italic>Najas flexilis</italic>: adaptation to submersed environments is accompanied by the complete loss of the NDH complex in an aquatic angiosperm</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><volume>8</volume>, <fpage>e68591</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23861923</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0056"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seberg</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cuenca</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thadeo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Phylogeny of the Alismatales (Monocotyledons) and the relationship of <italic>Acorus</italic> (Acorales?)</article-title>. <source>Cladistics</source><volume>32</volume>, <fpage>141</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>159</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0057"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rausell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kanhonou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yenush</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Serrano</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ros</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>The translation initiation factor eIF1A is an important determinant in the tolerance to NaCl stress in yeast and plants</article-title>. <source>The Plant Journal</source><volume>34</volume>, <fpage>257</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>267</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12713533</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0058"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soto Gomez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Plastid phylogenomics and molecular evolution of Alismatales</article-title>. <source>Cladistics</source><volume>32</volume>, <fpage>160</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>178</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0059"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruhlman</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>NDH expression marks major transitions in plant evolution and reveals coordinate intracellular gene loss</article-title>. <source>BMC Plant Biology</source><volume>15</volume>, <fpage>100</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25886915</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0060"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Short</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Polidoro</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Livingstone</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Extinction risk assessment of the world&#x02019;s seagrass species</article-title>. <source>Biological Conservation</source><volume>144</volume>, <fpage>1961</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1971</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0061"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Slater</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Birney</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Automated generation of heuristics for biological sequence comparison</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><volume>6</volume>, <fpage>31</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15713233</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0062"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stefanovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olmstead</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Down the slippery slope: plastid genome evolution in Convolvulaceae</article-title>. <source>Journal of Molecular Evolution</source><volume>61</volume>, <fpage>292</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>305</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15999247</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0063"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Strydom</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kendrick</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Statton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lavery</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Seagrass <italic>Halophila ovalis</italic> is affected by light quality across different life history stages</article-title>. <source>Marine Ecology Progress Series</source><volume>572</volume>, <fpage>103</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>116</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0064"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taji</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Satou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sakurai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ishiyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Narusaka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Narusaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Comparative genomics in salt tolerance between <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>-related halophyte salt cress using Arabidopsis microarray</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>135</volume>, <fpage>1697</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1709</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15247402</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0065"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>The role of ethylene in plants under salinity stress</article-title>. <source>Frontiers in Plant Science</source><volume>6</volume>, <fpage>1059</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26640476</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0066"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Touchette</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Seagrass-salinity interactions: physiological mechanisms used by submersed marine angiosperms for a life at sea</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology</source><volume>350</volume>, <fpage>194</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>215</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0067"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Touchette</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marcus</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Bulk elastic moduli and solute potentials in leaves of freshwater, coastal and marine hydrophytes. Are marine plants more rigid</article-title>?<source>AoB Plants</source><volume>6</volume>, <fpage>plu014</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24876296</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0068"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Valente</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Polishchuk</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Matteis</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Rab6 and myosin II at the cutting edge of membrane fission</article-title>. <source>Nature Cell Biology</source><volume>12</volume>, <fpage>635</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>638</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20596045</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0069"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Meer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Voelker</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feigenson</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Membrane lipids: where they are and how they behave</article-title>. <source>Nature Reviews. Molecular Cell Biology</source><volume>9</volume>, <fpage>112</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>124</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18216768</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0070"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Voesenek</surname><given-names>LACJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pierik</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sasidharan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Plant life without ethylene</article-title>. <source>Trends in Plant Science</source><volume>20</volume>, <fpage>783</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>786</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26547812</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0071"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Washburn</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bird</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Conant</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pires</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Convergent evolution and the origin of complex phenotypes in the age of systems biology</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Plant Sciences</source><volume>177</volume>, <fpage>305</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>318</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0072"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Waterhouse</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Procter</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clamp</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Jalview version 2&#x02014;a multiple sequence alignment editor and analysis workbench</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>25</volume>, <fpage>1189</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1191</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19151095</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0073"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weraduwage</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Renna</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>C Anozie</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>D Sharkey</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brandizzi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Pectin methylesterification impacts the relationship between photosynthesis and plant growth</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>171</volume>, <fpage>833</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>848</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27208234</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0074"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wickett</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goffinet</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year><italic>a</italic>
<article-title>Distribution and evolution of pseudogenes, gene losses, and a gene rearrangement in the plastid genome of the nonphotosynthetic liverwort, <italic>Aneura mirabilis</italic> (Metzgeriales, Jungermanniopsida)</article-title>. <source>Journal of Molecular Evolution</source><volume>67</volume>, <fpage>111</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>122</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18594897</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0075"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wickett</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roper</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuehl</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Plock</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DePamphilis</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boore</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goffinet</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year><italic>b</italic>
<article-title>Functional gene losses occur with minimal size reduction in the plastid genome of the parasitic liverwort <italic>Aneura mirabilis</italic></article-title>. <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source><volume>25</volume>, <fpage>393</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>401</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18056074</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0076"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mayo</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<source>Early Events in Monocot Evolution</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0077"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wissler</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Codo&#x000f1;er</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reusch</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Procaccini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bornberg-Bauer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Back to the sea twice: identifying candidate plant genes for molecular evolution to marine life</article-title>. <source>BMC Evolutionary Biology</source><volume>11</volume>, <fpage>8</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21226908</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0078"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morden</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1992</year>
<article-title>Function and evolution of a minimal plastid genome from a nonphotosynthetic parasitic plant</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source><volume>89</volume>, <fpage>10648</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10652</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0079"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Law</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murcha</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Whelan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carrie</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>The dual targeting ability of type II NAD(P)H dehydrogenases arose early in land plant evolution</article-title>. <source>BMC Plant Biology</source><volume>13</volume>, <fpage>100</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23841539</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0080"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Osmotically active compounds and their localization in the marine halophyte eelgrass</article-title>. <source>Biologia Plantarum</source><volume>46</volume>, <fpage>137</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>140</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0081"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harberd</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>The regulatory roles of ethylene and reactive oxygen species (ROS) in plant salt stress responses</article-title>. <source>Plant Molecular Biology</source><volume>91</volume>, <fpage>651</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>659</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27233644</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0082"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ganguly</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baskin</surname><given-names>TI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McClosky</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meunier</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dixit</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>The fragile Fiber1 kinesin contributes to cortical microtubule-mediated trafficking of cell wall components</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>167</volume>, <fpage>780</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>792</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25646318</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>