<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Hortic Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Hortic Res</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Horticulture Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2662-6810</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2052-7276</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8166937</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">551</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41438-021-00551-w</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A high-quality genome assembly of <italic>Morinda officinalis</italic>, a famous native southern herb in the Lingnan region of southern China</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Jihua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Shiqiang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>Yu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Shike</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Yan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Minyang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Zhan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Yong</given-names></name><address><email>xiaoyaong1980@catas.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3138-3422</contrib-id><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Muqing</given-names></name><address><email>mqzhang@ufl.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Shaohai</given-names></name><address><email>yangshaohai@gdaas.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.135769.f</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0561 6611</institution-id><institution>Guangdong Provincial Key Laboratory of Crops Genetics &#x00026; Improvement, Crops Research Institute, </institution><institution>Guangdong Academy of Agricultural Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>510640 Guangzhou, China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>DongFuhang High-tech Agricultural Planting and Management Co., Ltd, 526000 Zhaoqing, China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.509155.d</institution-id><institution>Coconut Research Institute, Chinese Academy of Tropical Agricultural Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>571339 Wenchang, China </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.256609.e</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2254 5798</institution-id><institution>State Key Lab for Conservation and Utilization of Subtropical Agric-Biological Resources, </institution><institution>Guangxi University, </institution></institution-wrap>530005 Nanning, China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>1</day><month>6</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>1</day><month>6</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>135</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>23</day><month>2</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>3</month><year>2021</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2021</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1"><italic>Morinda officinalis</italic> is a well-known medicinal and edible plant that is widely cultivated in the Lingnan region of southern China. Its dried roots (called <italic>bajitian</italic> in traditional Chinese medicine) are broadly used to treat various diseases, such as impotence and rheumatism. Here, we report a high-quality chromosome-scale genome assembly of <italic>M. officinalis</italic> using Nanopore single-molecule sequencing and Hi-C technology. The assembled genome size was 484.85&#x02009;Mb with a scaffold N50 of 40.97&#x02009;Mb, and 90.77% of the assembled sequences were anchored on eleven pseudochromosomes. The genome includes 27,698 protein-coding genes, and most of the assemblies are repetitive sequences. Genome evolution analysis revealed that <italic>M. officinalis</italic> underwent core eudicot &#x003b3; genome triplication events but no recent whole-genome duplication (WGD). Likewise, comparative genomic analysis showed no large-scale structural variation after species divergence between <italic>M. officinalis</italic> and <italic>Coffea canephora</italic>. Moreover, gene family analysis indicated that gene families associated with plant&#x02013;pathogen interactions and sugar metabolism were significantly expanded in <italic>M. officinalis</italic>. Furthermore, we identified many candidate genes involved in the biosynthesis of major active components such as anthraquinones, iridoids and polysaccharides. In addition, we also found that the DHQS, GGPPS, TPS-Clin, TPS04, sacA, and UGDH gene families&#x02014;which include the critical genes for active component biosynthesis&#x02014;were expanded in <italic>M. officinalis</italic>. This study provides a valuable resource for understanding <italic>M. officinalis</italic> genome evolution and active component biosynthesis. This work will facilitate genetic improvement and molecular breeding of this commercially important plant.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Genome evolution</kwd><kwd>Medical genomics</kwd><kwd>Genome duplication</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2021</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2"><italic>Morinda officinalis</italic> How, belonging to the genus <italic>Morinda</italic> of the family Rubiaceae, is a perennial vine naturally distributed in southern China and northern Vietnam (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. <italic>M. officinalis</italic>, a commonly used traditional Chinese medicinal plant, was first reported in Shen Nong Ben Cao Jing and accepted in the Chinese Pharmacopoeia in 1963. The roots of <italic>M. officinalis</italic>, named <italic>bajitian</italic> in traditional Chinese medicine, are one of the four famous southern herbs from the Lingnan region of southern China. The roots of <italic>M. officinalis</italic> are widely used for the treatment of various diseases, such as impotence, infertility, abnormal menstruation, rheumatism, and arthralgia (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b, c</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. In China and northeast Asia, <italic>M. officinalis</italic> is also usually used as a tonic for nourishing the kidneys and enhancing immune functioning in the body<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Morphological characteristics of <italic>M. officinalis</italic>.</title><p><bold>a</bold> The <italic>M. officinalis</italic> plant. <bold>b</bold> The roots of <italic>M. officinalis</italic> with the woody core removed (named <italic>bajitian</italic> in traditional Chinese medicine). <bold>c</bold> The roots of <italic>M. officinalis</italic> at different growth stages</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41438_2021_551_Fig1_HTML" id="d32e431"/></fig></p><p id="Par3">Phytochemical studies have shown that <italic>M. officinalis</italic> contains anthraquinones, iridoids, flavonoids, polysaccharides, volatile oils, and other important compounds<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Anthraquinones are one of the main active components and mainly contain physcion, rubiadin-1-methylether, anthragallol-2-methylether, etc., which have various biological activities such as antibacterial, anticancer, anticoagulant, and antiviral activities<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. Monotropein, a kind of iridoid compound, has potent antiinflammatory and analgesic effects and is the main component of <italic>M. officinalis</italic> for dispelling wind and eliminating dampness<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. The polysaccharides in <italic>M. officinalis</italic> mainly consist of glucose and fructose, which have antifatigue, antidepressant, and antiosteoporosis roles<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. Various pharmacological and clinical studies have linked <italic>M. officinalis</italic> with aphrodisiac and immunomodulatory effects and antiosteoporosis, antidepression and antiinflammatory properties<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">In China, Guangdong Province is the main planting area for <italic>M. officinalis</italic>, accounting for approximately 90% of its output. In this province, Gaoyao District and Deqing County (Zhaoqing City) are authentic <italic>M. officinalis</italic>-producing areas<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. In recent years, wild resources of <italic>M. officinalis</italic> have been significantly threatened in China to a level risking extinction due to a sharp increase in <italic>M. officinalis</italic> market demand, especially in Guangdong Province<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. Therefore, artificially cultivated <italic>M. officinalis</italic> has become the primary source of related medicinal materials in China. <italic>M. officinalis</italic> has a long cultivation period of approximately five years; moreover, its sexual reproduction cycle is complex. Long-term asexual reproduction of <italic>M. officinalis</italic> has led to germplasm depletion that seriously affects its quality and yield. Thus, diseases of <italic>M. officinalis</italic> are becoming a severe issue, especially stem rot caused by <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic>, which is devastating<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. Thus, the breeding of promising new varieties is urgently needed.</p><p id="Par5">The genomic information of <italic>M. officinalis</italic> can lay the foundation for improving the quality of these medicinal materials, accelerating molecular breeding, protecting wild resources, and aiding the discovery and utilization of functional genes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. Whole-genome sequencing has been performed for many medicinal plants, such as <italic>Scutellaria baicalensis</italic>, <italic>Isatis indigotica</italic>, weeping forsythia, and <italic>Macleaya cordata</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. However, the genome sequence of <italic>M. officinalis</italic> has not yet been reported, which restricts the development of functional genomics and molecular breeding of this plant. In this study, we generated a high-quality genome for <italic>M. officinalis</italic> by nanopore sequencing and Hi-C technology to elucidate its genomic characteristics. Transcriptome sequencing was also carried out to identify the candidate genes related to active compound biosynthesis. The reference genome information obtained in this research will be a valuable resource for promoting genetic improvement and understanding the biosynthesis of active ingredients of this medicinal plant.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Genome assembly and quality validation</title><p id="Par6">To evaluate the genome size and heterozygosity of <italic>M. officinalis</italic>, a total of 61.4&#x02009;Gb short reads from the MGISEQ-2000 sequencing platform were subjected to K-mer analysis (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). The 17-mer frequency curve showed a bimodal distribution, with the highest peak occurring at a depth of 54 (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1a</xref>). Based on the total number of K-mers, the genome size and heterozygosity of <italic>M. officinalis</italic> were estimated to be 485.4&#x02009;Mb and 1.32%, respectively (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1b</xref>). These results indicated that the genome of <italic>M. officinalis</italic> was small but highly heterozygous.</p><p id="Par7"><italic>De novo</italic> assembly of the 62.92&#x02009;Gb of single-molecule long reads from the Oxford Nanopore PromethION sequencing platform was performed with NextDenovo software (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). After removing redundant and contaminated sequences (nontarget classes, mitochondria, and chloroplasts), the final postcorrection genome size was 484.85&#x02009;Mb, with a contig N50 of 4.21&#x02009;Mb (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The genome size was similar to that estimated by the genome survey. Employing Hi-C technology, 398.8 million clean reads from the Illumina NovaSeq 6000 sequencing platform were used for chromosome construction to further refine the <italic>M. officinalis</italic> genome assembly. Moreover, using the agglomerative hierarchical clustering method in LACHESIS software, a total of 99.94% of the assembly was anchored to 11 pseudochromosomes; the size ranged from 33.06&#x02009;Mb to 47.00&#x02009;Mb with a contig N50 of 3.61&#x02009;Mb and scaffold N50 of 40.97&#x02009;Mb (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). Finally, the contig sequences were connected in the determined order and direction by adding 100&#x02009;N to obtain the final chromosome-level genome sequence with a chromosome mount rate of 90.77% (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> and Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). A Hi-C interaction heatmap showed that the clustering, ordering, and orientation of the contigs was valid, providing the first high-quality chromosome-scale genome assembly for <italic>M. officinalis</italic> (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Summary of <italic>M. officinalis</italic> genome assembly and annotation</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Items</th><th>Number</th><th>Size (bp)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="3">Genome assembly</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Total contigs&#x02003;</td><td>209</td><td>484,851,740</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Contig N50</td><td>32</td><td>4,213,846</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Contig N90</td><td>118</td><td>1,061,677</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Total scaffolds</td><td>64</td><td>484,869,040</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Scaffold N50</td><td>6</td><td>40,972,926</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Scaffold N90</td><td>11</td><td>33,060,658</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Pseudochromosomes</td><td>11</td><td>440,084,418</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Genome annotation</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Repetitive sequences</td><td>58.04%</td><td>281,412,890</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Noncoding RNAs</td><td>2298</td><td>342,651</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Protein-coding genes</td><td>27,102</td><td>101,967,209</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Characterization of the <italic>M. officinalis</italic> genome.</title><p>The circle from outside to inside represents chromosomes (<bold>a</bold>), gene density (<bold>b</bold>), tandem repeat density (<bold>c</bold>), LTR-Copia density (<bold>d</bold>), LTR-Gypsy density (<bold>e</bold>), transposon element density (<bold>f</bold>), and gene collinearity connected by curved lines (<bold>g</bold>). All distributions are drawn in a window size of 1&#x02009;Mb</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41438_2021_551_Fig2_HTML" id="d32e785"/></fig></p><p id="Par8">A variety of methods have been employed to evaluate the assembly quality of genomes. Here, the assembly completeness was evaluated using Benchmarking Universal Single-Copy Orthologs (BUSCOs). The BUSCO analysis identified 97.02% of the complete BUSCOs in the assembly (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). To assess assembly consistency, the short reads were mapped to the genome using bwa software. In total, ~99.26% of the clean data were mapped to the genome assembly (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>). The mapping ratio of the RNA-seq reads from different tissues was in the range of ~93.94&#x02013;96.08% (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>). We further evaluated potential contamination in the genome by using GC depth analysis. The GC depth scatter plot showed that the GC content was distributed at 30&#x02013;40%, and the sequencing depth was concentrated at 110&#x02013;150&#x000d7;, indicating high quality without contamination in the data (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). All these results indicated high completeness and consistency of the <italic>M. officinalis</italic> genome assembly.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Genome annotation</title><p id="Par9">Homology-based annotation and a <italic>de novo</italic> approach were applied to identify transposable elements (TEs) and tandem repeats in the <italic>M. officinalis</italic> genome. In total, we identified 281.41&#x02009;Mb of nonredundant repetitive sequences, accounting for 58.04% of the assembled genome (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref>). Of these predicted repeats, TEs comprised the largest proportion (54.18%), including 42.92% Class I repeats and 11.26% Class II repeats. Long terminal repeat (LTR) retrotransposons accounted for 35.79% of the genome (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref>). Based on the assembled genome, a total of 209 rRNAs, 207 snRNAs, 78 miRNAs, and 644 tRNAs were predicted (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S7</xref>).</p><p id="Par10">A total of 27,102 nonredundant protein-coding genes were predicted by using a combination of <italic>de novo</italic>, homolog-based, and transcriptome-based predictions (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). The average gene length and coding sequence size were 3762.35 and 1169.11&#x02009;bp, respectively, with an average of five exons per gene (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Then, we performed functional annotation of predicted genes by comparison with different databases. Overall, 24,769 (91.39%) genes were functionally annotated in at least one of the public databases, and 6153 (22.70%) genes could be annotated in all databases (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4a</xref>). A total of 24,637 (90.90%) genes showed homologous genes in the NR database, while 20,712 (76.42%) genes were similar to proteins in the SwissProt database. Among the blastx top hits, species of the genus <italic>Coffea</italic> (Rubiaceae family) showed the highest proportion (82.77%) of homologous genes, including <italic>Coffea arabica</italic> (49.54%), <italic>Coffea eugenioides</italic> (20.44%), and <italic>C. canephora</italic> (12.79%) (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4b</xref>). In addition, 14,998 (55.34%) genes were assigned to at least one GO term and classified into 41 GO functional subcategories (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4c</xref>). To further understand the metabolic pathways of <italic>M. officinalis</italic>, 9737 (35.93%) genes were annotated in the KEGG pathway database (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4d</xref>). Pathways associated with &#x0201c;biosynthesis of other secondary metabolites&#x0201d; (466 genes) and &#x0201c;metabolism of terpenoids and polyketides&#x0201d; (216 genes) can be used to explore the biosynthesis pathways of active ingredients in <italic>M. officinalis</italic>.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Statistics of predicted protein-coding genes in the <italic>M. officinalis</italic> genome</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Gene set</th><th>Number</th><th>Average gene length (bp)</th><th>Average CDS length (bp)</th><th>Average exon number per gene</th><th>Average exon length (bp)</th><th>Average intron length (bp)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>De novo</td><td>27,698</td><td>3217.87</td><td>1134.10</td><td>5.10</td><td>222.27</td><td>507.94</td></tr><tr><td>Homology</td><td>18,549</td><td>3740.08</td><td>1314.22</td><td>5.44</td><td>241.60</td><td>546.40</td></tr><tr><td>RNA-seq</td><td>14,338</td><td>4787.57</td><td>1402.49</td><td>5.96</td><td>235.14</td><td>681.86</td></tr><tr><td>Final set</td><td>27,102</td><td>3762.35</td><td>1169.11</td><td>5.00</td><td>233.60</td><td>647.53</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par11">We conducted BUSCO analysis to verify the predicted genes. The results showed that approximately 96.80% of the complete BUSCOs could be identified in the annotated results, indicating the high reliability of the predicted results (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S8</xref>). The number of predicted genes and structural characteristics of the <italic>M. officinalis</italic> genome were consistent with those of related species, which indicated that the annotation results were acceptable (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S9</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Gene families and phylogenetic relationships</title><p id="Par12">OrthoMCL software was used to identify the gene families of <italic>M. officinalis</italic> and nine other species, among which <italic>C. canephora</italic> is the most closely related species to <italic>M</italic>. <italic>officinalis</italic> and also belongs to the Rubiaceae family. A total of 22,750 (83.94%) genes were categorized into 14,124 gene families, 849 of which were unique to <italic>M. officinalis</italic> (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S10</xref>). In each species, 1576 genes were identified as single-copy orthologs. A total of 7230 genes in <italic>M. officinalis</italic> did not cluster with the genes of other species, indicating that these genes were <italic>M. officinalis</italic> specific (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5a, b</xref>). Furthermore, we performed KEGG enrichment analysis to explore the metabolic pathways involved in these species-specific genes. Interestingly, we found that the pathways related to the synthesis of secondary metabolites were significantly enriched (<italic>q</italic> value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), including &#x0201c;indole alkaloid biosynthesis&#x0201d; (36 genes), &#x0201c;phenylpropanoid biosynthesis&#x0201d; (103 genes), and &#x0201c;stilbenoid, diarylheptanoid, and gingerol biosynthesis&#x0201d; (29 genes) (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S11</xref>). Moreover, we also identified 149 genes involved in &#x0201c;plant&#x02013;pathogen interaction&#x0201d;. These data will help to reveal the molecular mechanisms underlying the interactions between <italic>M. officinalis</italic> and pathogens.</p><p id="Par13">We used MAFFT software to perform multiple sequence alignments on the identified single-copy orthologous genes. The phylogenetic tree was constructed using the PROTGAMMAAUTO model of RAXML software, in which <italic>V. vinifera</italic> and <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> were outgroup species. As shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a</xref>, <italic>M. officinalis</italic> was most closely related to <italic>C. canephora</italic>, and the divergence time of the two was 49.27 (31.55&#x02013;65.27) million years ago (Mya). Comparative genomic analysis showed that 732 expanded and 308 contracted gene families were discovered in <italic>M. officinalis</italic> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b</xref>). Compared with the closely related species of <italic>C. canephora</italic> (383 expansion/370 contraction), <italic>M. officinalis</italic> showed more gene family expansion than contraction. KEGG enrichment analysis of the expanded genes suggested that they were mainly enriched in &#x0201c;ABC transporters&#x0201d; (30 genes), &#x0201c;starch and sucrose metabolism&#x0201d; (78 genes), &#x0201c;phenylpropanoid biosynthesis&#x0201d; (97 genes), &#x0201c;isoquinoline alkaloid biosynthesis&#x0201d; (19 genes) and so on, indicating that some of these might be related to the biosynthesis of active compounds (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S12</xref>). The contracted gene families were involved in &#x0201c;ether lipid metabolism&#x0201d; (8 genes), &#x0201c;endocytosis&#x0201d; (20 genes), &#x0201c;sesquiterpenoid and triterpenoid biosynthesis&#x0201d; (5 genes), &#x0201c;spliceosome&#x0201d; (18 genes), &#x0201c;protein processing in endoplasmic reticulum&#x0201d; (18 genes) and &#x0201c;plant&#x02013;pathogen interaction&#x0201d; (25 genes), indicating that some of these families may be related to environmental adaptation (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S13</xref>). Notably, we found that a series of genes related to secondary metabolism and environmental adaptation exhibited significant expansion (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S14</xref>). These results provide valuable resources for understanding the biosynthesis of active ingredients and the interaction between <italic>M. officinalis</italic> and its growth environment.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>The genome evolution of <italic>M. officinalis</italic>.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Phylogenetic tree and divergence time estimation. The value on each node represents the divergence time of each species. The red dots depict the fossil record used to correct the divergence time. <bold>b</bold> Gene family expansion (green) and contraction (red). <bold>c</bold> Ks distribution among <italic>M. officinalis</italic> and three other species. Lines show Ks distribution within (continuous) and between genomes (dashed). <bold>d</bold> Collinear relationship of <italic>M. officinalis</italic>, <italic>C. canephora</italic> and <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic>. The gray line connects matched gene pairs</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41438_2021_551_Fig3_HTML" id="d32e1130"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Positive selection, WGD, and collinearity</title><p id="Par14">The <italic>Ka/Ks</italic> ratios of the single-copy genes were used to evaluate the positive selection of genes in <italic>M. officinalis</italic>. A total of 101 candidate genes were strictly positively selected (<italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S15</xref>). GO enrichment analysis showed that these genes were enriched in &#x0201c;DNA repair&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;ATP-dependent helicase activity&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;chromosome&#x0201d;, and &#x0201c;DNA topological change&#x0201d;, indicating that these positively selected genes may improve DNA damage resistance in adverse environments. To estimate the potential WGD events of <italic>M. officinalis</italic>, synonymous nucleotide substitutions (Ks) were characterized in <italic>M. officinalis, C. canephora, Catharanthus roseus,</italic> and <italic>V. vinifera</italic>. Based on the Ks distribution between <italic>M. officinalis</italic> and the other three genomes, <italic>M. officinalis</italic>&#x02013;<italic>C. canephora</italic> (0.608) divergence time was slower than that of <italic>M. officinalis&#x02013;C. roseus</italic> (0.867) and <italic>M. officinalis&#x02013;V. vinifera</italic> (1.238), which was consistent with the phylogenetic tree (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3c</xref>). The distribution of Ks showed one peak at ~2.1 to 2.3 in the genomes of <italic>M. officinalis</italic>, <italic>C. canephora,</italic> and <italic>V. vinifera</italic>. The results showed that they shared an ancient WGD event (the core eudicot &#x003b3; triplication event) before their divergence and no recent independent WGD event (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3c</xref>). The comparative genome structure between <italic>M. officinalis</italic> and <italic>C. canephora</italic> showed high collinearity, indicating that there was no large-scale structural variation after the divergence between <italic>M. officinalis</italic> and <italic>C. canephora</italic> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d</xref> and Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref>). For most collinear regions, one chromosome of <italic>M. officinalis</italic> corresponded to one chromosome of <italic>C. canephora</italic>; for example, MoChr2, MoChr5, MoChr6, MoChr7, MoChr8, MoChr9, and MoChr10 of <italic>M. officinalis</italic> corresponded to CcChr2, CcChr3, CcChr10, CcChr7, CcChr8, CcChr5, CcChr11 and CcChr4 of <italic>C. canephora</italic>, respectively. MoChr1 corresponded to CcChr1, CcChr2 and CcChr6; MoChr3 corresponded to CcChr2, CcChr6 and CcChr9; MoChr4 corresponded to CcChr1, CcChr3, and CcChr6 (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref>). These observations indicated that MoChr1, MoChr3, and MoChr4 might have formed by fragmentation and recombination of ancestral chromosomes. We further conducted intergenomic collinearity between <italic>M. officinalis</italic> and <italic>V. vinifera</italic>. The <italic>M. officinalis</italic> genome generally showed a one-to-one syntenic relationship with <italic>V. vinifera</italic>, which was consistent with the result that the <italic>M. officinalis</italic> genome did not undergo a recent WGD event (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d</xref>). Interestingly, the collinear regions of MoChr5 mainly corresponded to VvChr5, and MoChr6 corresponded to VvChr 18, while other chromosomes, especially MoChr1, MoChr2, and MoChr3, did not exhibit any significant corresponding relationships between <italic>M. officinalis</italic> and <italic>V. vinifera</italic> (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Characteristic analysis of genes showing organ-specific expression</title><p id="Par15">Based on gene expression levels, we identified 451, 254, 109, 165, and 219 genes expressed explicitly in stalks, leaves, one-year-old roots (AR), three-year-old roots (TR), and six-year-old roots (SR), respectively, and 17,578 genes were expressed in all tissues (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>). To elucidate the similarities and differences of gene expression patterns in different tissues, we also performed a k-means cluster analysis. A total of 16,771 differentially expressed genes (DEGs) were divided into 10 clusters (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b</xref>). We, therefore, focused our attention on the clusters that contained genes with tissue-specific expression. We found that the leaf-biased genes (cluster 1) were highly correlated with fundamental pathways, such as &#x0201c;photosynthesis&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;biosynthesis of secondary metabolites&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;photosynthesis-antenna proteins&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;carbon fixation in photosynthetic organisms&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;porphyrin and chlorophyll metabolism&#x0201d; (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S16</xref>). In contrast, stalk-biased genes (cluster 9) were significantly associated with defense responses, such as &#x0201c;MAPK signaling pathway-plant&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;plant&#x02013;pathogen interaction&#x0201d; (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4c</xref> and Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S16</xref>). Additionally, we also identified that genes in clusters 2, 4, and 8 were highly expressed at different developmental stages of roots, and some genes were continuously enhanced with root development (clusters 3 and 7). The functions of these genes were mainly enriched in &#x0201c;phenylpropanoid biosynthesis&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;amino sugar and nucleotide sugar metabolism&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;ABC transporters&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;MAPK signaling pathway-plant&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;plant&#x02013;pathogen interaction&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;peroxisome&#x0201d;, indicating that they may be related to the synthesis, transport, and storage of active ingredients and defense responses (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S16</xref>). These results provide a basis for further analysis to reveal the gene expression regulatory network and regulate bioactive metabolite derivative production in <italic>M. officinalis</italic>.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>Gene expression patterns in different tissues.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Venn diagram showing the expressed genes in roots, stalks, and leaves (FPKM&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.1). The overlapping regions represent genes expressed in at least two tissues, while the nonoverlapping regions represent tissue-specific genes. <bold>b</bold> Hierarchical clustering showing the expression patterns of DEGs. The <italic>x</italic> axis represents different tissues, and the <italic>y</italic> axis represents the standardized gene expression level based on the log<sub>2</sub> (FPKM&#x02009;+&#x02009;1) values. AR, one-year-old roots; TR, three-year-old roots; SR, six-year-old roots. <bold>c</bold> Part of the MAPK signaling pathway. Various color blocks represent the normalized gene expression levels of the DEGs in different tissues</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41438_2021_551_Fig4_HTML" id="d32e1307"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Identification of genes related to the anthraquinone biosynthesis pathway</title><p id="Par16">Anthraquinones in Rubiaceae plants are mainly synthesized through the shikimate/<italic>o</italic>-succinylbenzoic acid pathway, which mainly involves the shikimate pathway, TCA cycle, mevalonate (MVA) pathway, and methylerythritol phosphate (MEP) pathway (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref>). 1,4-Dihydroxy-2-naphthoate (DHNA) is formed by isochorismate and &#x003b1;-ketoglutarate under the catalysis of a series of enzymes. Therefore, DHNA combines with dimethylallyl pyrophosphate (DMAPP), derived from the MVA and MEP pathways, to form the core structure of anthraquinone. We identified 11 crucial gene families in the shikimate pathway (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S17</xref>). In addition, compared with <italic>C. canephora</italic>, the key gene DHQS in the shikimate pathway was expanded to enhance the ability to produce 3-dehydroquinate (DHQ). On the other hand, the chlP gene number was also expanded, which may contribute to terpenoid-quinone biosynthesis. We also identified 14 important gene families in the MVA and MEP pathways (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref> and Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S17</xref>). Almost every node in the MEP pathway had only one gene copy, while the crucial genes ACAT, HMGR and PMK in the MVA pathway had two or three gene copies. Gene expression analysis showed that most MEP pathway genes had high expression in leaves, while genes in the MVA pathway were expressed in various tissues.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><title>Expression analysis of genes involved in major active compound biosynthesis.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Anthraquinone and terpenoid biosynthesis pathways. <bold>b</bold> Polysaccharide biosynthesis pathway. <bold>c</bold> Part of the starch and sucrose metabolism pathway. Various color blocks represent the normalized gene expression levels of all genes encoding in different tissues. Heat maps of these genes were plotted using the pheatmap package. Red dots represent gene family expansion in <italic>M. officinalis</italic></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41438_2021_551_Fig5_HTML" id="d32e1352"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Functional gene evolution contributed to the formation of terpenoids</title><p id="Par17">Terpenoid biosynthesis starts from the terpenoid backbone biosynthesis pathway. Isopentenyl pyrophosphate (IPP) and DMAPP are common precursors for terpenoid biosynthesis in plants and are mainly formed by the MVA and MEP pathways. Geranylgeranyl diphosphate (GGPP) is the direct precursor substrate of diterpene biosynthesis, which GGPPS catalyzes. In the <italic>M. officinalis</italic> genome, we found that GGPPS has ten gene copies, and tandem duplication was found on Chr6 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> and Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S17</xref>). Gene expression analysis showed that GGPPS might have potential functional divergence; for example, <italic>evm.model.LG06.1002</italic> was relatively highly expressed in AR, but <italic>evm.model.LG06.1003</italic> showed no expression in any tissues (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S17</xref>).<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><title>Chromosomal locations of expanded gene families in the M. officinalis genome.</title><p>Gene families related to anthraquinone and terpenoid biosynthesis pathways (chlP, CYP82G1, DHQS, GGPPS, TPS04 and TPS-Cin) and sugar metabolism (sacA, bglB, AMY, BGL, GN5/6, UGDH, SPS, TPS and TREH)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41438_2021_551_Fig6_HTML" id="d32e1387"/></fig></p><p id="Par18">Terpene synthase (TPS) is vital for terpenoid synthesis and uses geranyl diphosphate (GPP), GGPP, and farnesyl diphosphate (FPP) as direct precursors to synthesize monoterpenes, diterpenes, sesquiterpenes, and triterpenes. TPS proteins were identified by using the Pfam domain models PF03936 and PF01397 with an <italic>E</italic>-value cutoff of 1e&#x02212;5. We identified 41 TPS family genes in the <italic>M. officinalis</italic> genome. Based on the phylogenetic tree generated by aligning the TPS proteins of <italic>M. officinalis</italic>, <italic>C. canephora,</italic> and <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, we divided the <italic>M. officinalis</italic> TPS genes into seven groups (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S7a</xref> and Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S18</xref>). The TPS-a (14 genes) and TPS-b (14 genes) groups contained more genes, while the TPS-g group comprised only two genes. We also found that the TPS-a group had tandem duplication on Chr2 (10 genes), and the TPS-b group had tandem duplication on Chr2 (6 genes) and Chr6 (6 genes) (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S18</xref>). Thus, tandem duplication is responsible for TPS-Cin and TPS04 gene family expansion in <italic>M. officinalis</italic> after its split from <italic>C. canephora</italic> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). In addition, we noticed that the expression patterns of most genes in the same group were similar. Nevertheless, TPS-a was mainly expressed in AR, and TPS-b showed high expression in stalks, which may be related to the tissue-specific localization of substance synthesis (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S7b</xref> and Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S18</xref>).</p><p id="Par19">Iridoids are the major terpenoids in <italic>M. officinalis</italic> and are monoterpene analogs. In the iridoid biosynthesis pathway, one GES (TPS-g subfamily), fifteen G10Hs, six 10HGOs, three ISs, four 7-DLSs and twelve 7-DLGTs were identified (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref> and Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S17</xref>). Based on the chromosome location, we found that these functional genes (G10H, 10HGO, IS, 7-DLS, and 7-DLGT) may have undergone tandem duplication in the <italic>M. officinalis</italic> genome. Interestingly, this duplication also existed in <italic>C. canephora</italic>, which suggested that the duplication of these gene families may have occurred before the speciation of <italic>M. officinalis</italic> and <italic>C. canephora</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Significant expansion of genes related to sugar metabolism</title><p id="Par20">As shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5b</xref>, we deduced the synthesis pathway of polysaccharides in <italic>M. officinalis</italic> based on the enzymes involved in carbon metabolism in the pathways &#x0201c;starch and sucrose metabolism&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;amino and nucleotide sugar metabolism&#x0201d;. In <italic>M. officinalis</italic>, nine genes encoding sacA, four genes encoding malZ, six genes encoding scrK, and 12 genes encoding HK were identified, most of which were highly expressed in leaves and stalks (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5b</xref> and Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S19</xref>). We also identified 44 genes encoding nucleotide-diphospho-sugar interconversion enzymes, most of which showed diverse expression patterns in different tissues, indicating the complexity of the regulation of polysaccharide biosynthesis (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5b</xref> and Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S19</xref>). The sacA gene catalyzes the formation of D-fructose and Glc-6P as precursors. Two tandem repeat blocks were found on Chr1 and Chr3 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). UGDH is responsible for the biosynthesis of UDP-GlcA, which might be the restrictive precursor of other nucleotide-diphospho-sugars, such as UDP-Gal, UDP-d-Xyl and UDP-l-Ara. We found that the UGDH gene in <italic>M. officinalis</italic> was expanded compared to that in <italic>C. canephora</italic>, which might have contributed to the formation of UDP-GlcA (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> and Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S20</xref>).</p><p id="Par21">We also paid particular attention to other expanded gene families related to the starch and sucrose metabolism pathways (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5c</xref>). Based on their function, these extended genes catalyze the formation of glucose from other sugars, which is one of the important substrates for glycolysis and polysaccharide synthesis. A significant tandem duplication event of BGL genes was identified in <italic>M. officinalis</italic> on Chr1, Chr2, Chr4, contig9, and contig 17 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). For the bglB genes, similar tandem repeats were found on Chr3, Chr9, and Chr11 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> and Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S20</xref>). The AMY genes can decompose starch into maltose and then form glucose under the catalysis of malQ and malZ. Tandem duplication of AMY genes was also found on Chr6 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> and Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S20</xref>). These results suggested that tandem duplication is responsible for the expansion of these genes after the separation between <italic>M. officinalis</italic> and <italic>C. canephora</italic>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par22"><italic>M. officinalis</italic> is one of the top four most famous southern herbs in China. Nevertheless, in the past, research on <italic>M. officinalis</italic> has mainly focused on its pharmacology. Because of the impediments associated with the sexual reproduction of this species and the exhaustion of its wild resources, germplasm resources are very limited<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. Additionally, the lack of genomic information seriously hinders genetic research on <italic>M. officinalis</italic>. Therefore, obtaining genomic information on <italic>M. officinalis</italic> will enable potential genetic improvements and the development of molecular breeding resources. However, a genome survey showed that its genome was highly heterozygous (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). High repetition rates and high heterozygosity are challenges for high-quality genome assembly<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. To overcome this issue, we combined third-generation sequencing and Hi-C technology to assemble the <italic>M. officinalis</italic> genome. Here, we present a high-quality chromosome-scale genome sequence for <italic>M. officinalis</italic>, with a scaffold N50 of 40.97&#x02009;Mb, which is higher than that of other medicinal plants, such as <italic>S. baicalensis</italic> (408.14&#x02009;Mb, N50 33.2&#x02009;Mb)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. A total of 97.02% complete BUSCO core genes were detected in our assembly, which suggested that the quality of this reference genome is comparable to that of the published highly heterozygous <italic>T. wilfordii</italic> genome (95.10%)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. In brief, the assembly of <italic>M. officinalis</italic> is relatively accurate and complete, which will provide a valuable genome resource for understanding the evolution, active ingredient biosynthesis, and genetic improvement of this species.</p><p id="Par23">The genus <italic>Morinda</italic> (Rubiaceae), which includes 102 species, is distributed in tropical, subtropical, and temperate regions of the world<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. However, there are few reports on genome research of the species in this genus. We found that 82.77% of annotated genes were matched to the proteins of the genus <italic>Coffea</italic> (Rubiaceae). This indicates the lack of reference genome sequences and limited public data on the genus <italic>Morinda</italic>. As one of the members of this genus, the genome information of <italic>M. officinalis</italic> can fill this gap and promote evolutionary research. Ks analysis found that <italic>M. officinalis</italic> shared only an ancient WGD event with <italic>C. canephora</italic> and <italic>V. vinifera</italic>, and no recent WGD event occurred (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3c</xref>). The <italic>M. officinalis</italic> chromosomal regions showed a one-to-one correspondence with <italic>V. vinifera</italic>; similar results were also found between <italic>C. canephora</italic> and <italic>V. vinifera</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. WGD events can cause plant genome size variation, chromosomal rearrangement, gene family expansion and species evolution<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. We found a high collinearity relationship between <italic>M. officinalis</italic> and <italic>C. canephora</italic> chromosomes, which may be because they have not undergone recent WGD events or large-scale chromosomal variation after species divergence (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref>).</p><p id="Par24"><italic>M. officinalis</italic> diseases are one of the critical factors that affect yield and quality. Stem rot is a common destructive disease of <italic>M. officinalis</italic>, often occurring at the stem base<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. We identified 59 expanded and 25 contracted genes associated with plant&#x02013;pathogen interactions in the <italic>M. officinalis</italic> genome (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S14</xref> and Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S8</xref>). These extended genes are located on all chromosomes of <italic>M. officinalis</italic>, and the KCS gene (K15397) and CML gene (K13448) have undergone tandem duplication on Chr5 and Chr6, respectively (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S8</xref>). This may be a unique adaptative mechanism evolved by <italic>M. officinalis</italic> in response to changes in various pathogens during natural selection. Based on the gene expression patterns, we found increased expression of 2,741 DEGs in the stalks, and functional enrichment showed that these genes were significantly associated with defense responses, such as &#x0201c;MAPK signaling pathway-plant&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;plant&#x02013;pathogen interaction&#x0201d; (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b</xref> and Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S16</xref>). These genes (e.g., FLS2, MPK3/6, and WRKY22) are involved in signal perception, cascade amplification, transmission, and regulation of downstream functional gene expression, which plays a crucial role in plant disease resistance by regulating multiple defenses<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. Therefore, our results provide insights into the molecular mechanism of the interaction between <italic>M. officinalis</italic> and pathogens.</p><p id="Par25">As medicinal and edible plants, <italic>M. officinalis</italic> contains medicinally active compounds, mainly including anthraquinones, iridoids, and polysaccharides<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. Although genes involved in anthraquinone, iridoid, and polysaccharide biosynthesis have been identified in other medicinal plants, such as <italic>Ophiorrhiza pumila</italic>, <italic>Senna tora</italic>, <italic>Gardenia jasminoides</italic>, and <italic>Artemisia sphaerocephala</italic>, the biosynthesis pathways in <italic>M. officinalis</italic> are still unclear<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. Previous studies have shown that there are two metabolic pathways in plant anthraquinone biosynthesis. The shikimate/o-succinylbenzoic acid pathway mainly exists in Rubiaceae plants, while the polyketide pathway mainly exists in fungi and other plants, such as Leguminosae, Rhamnaceae, and Polygonaceae<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. Terpenoids are the main active ingredients of many medicinal plants, such as <italic>Andrographis paniculata</italic>, <italic>Gynostemma pentaphyllum</italic> and <italic>Gardenia jasminoides</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>. The synthesis of terpenoids starts from the common precursors IPP and DMAPP, and then TPS converts the corresponding substrates to form structurally diverse monoterpenes, diterpenes, sesquiterpenes, etc.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. Polysaccharides are important bioactive components with various activities. Previous studies have shown that the polysaccharides in <italic>M. officinalis</italic> are mainly composed of glucose and fructose<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. In this work, we identified candidate genes related to the biosynthesis of these active components in <italic>M. officinalis</italic> and analyzed their expression patterns in different tissues (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a, b</xref>). We also found that some essential genes involved in the synthesis of these active ingredients, such as DHQS, GGPPS, TPS-Clin, TPS04, sacA, and UGDH, expanded in <italic>M. officinalis</italic> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). The expansion of key genes in metabolic pathways is beneficial to the synthesis and accumulation of active components and is a common event in medicinal plants during the evolutionary process<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. Notably, we found that the expression patterns of some expanded genes with the same function were diverse, indicating a potential functional divergence of these gene families.</p><p id="Par26">The roots of <italic>M. officinalis</italic> serve as an effective agent in traditional Chinese medicine, and there are two main stages in plant growth and development in this species: the growth of aboveground tissues and the growth of roots. Therefore, the vines need to be manually cut to promote the expansion of the roots after three years of cultivation, but this process may affect photosynthesis. Glucose is an important substrate for glycolysis and the TCA cycle, which provides energy for biological activities and intermediates for other metabolic processes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. Interestingly, we found that gene families involved in converting other sugars to glucose, such as BGL, AMY, and TREH, expanded significantly (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). We speculate that these evolutionary genes in <italic>M. officinalis</italic> may need to compensate for glucose deficiency. Although we have identified related candidate genes, their functions and evolutionary mechanisms should be explored in future work.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par27">In this work, we first report the high-quality chromosome-scale reference genome of <italic>M. officinalis</italic>. Genome evolution showed that <italic>M. officinalis</italic> shared an ancient WGD event with <italic>C. canephora</italic> and <italic>V. vinifera</italic>. We further used high-quality genome information to identify candidate genes for terpenoid, anthraquinone, and polysaccharide biosynthesis. We found that the functional genes related to pathogen resistance and active component biosynthesis were expanded in the <italic>M. officinalis</italic> genome. Overall, this high-quality reference genome provides insights into genome evolution and active component biosynthesis in <italic>M. officinalis</italic>. Our research also lays the foundation for further studies for genetic improvement and breeding, not only in <italic>M. officinalis</italic> but also in other <italic>Morinda</italic> species.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec14"><title>Plant materials and sequencing</title><p id="Par28">Root, leaf, and stem samples of &#x0201c;Gaoji 3&#x0201d;, a cultivated variety of <italic>M. officinalis</italic>, were collected from the Gaoyao District (Zhaoqing city, 28&#x000b0;28&#x02032;&#x02013;28&#x000b0;66&#x02032; N, 85&#x000b0;13&#x02032;&#x02013;85&#x000b0;28&#x02032; E) in Guangdong Province, China. Because of its unique geography and environment, the Gaoyao District of Zhaoqing City is considered the authentic production area of <italic>M. officinalis</italic>. &#x0201c;Gaoji 3&#x0201d;, with many excellent cultivation characteristics, including high yield, high quality, and disease resistance, is the main variety of <italic>M. officinalis</italic> grown in Gaoyao District.</p><p id="Par29">High-quality genomic DNA was extracted using a QIAGEN<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> Genomic Kit (QIAGEN, Germany). The integrity of the DNA was checked by 0.75% agarose gel electrophoresis. The purity and concentration of the DNA were analyzed by using a NanoDrop 2000 spectrophotometer (ThermoFisher Scientific, USA) and Qubit Fluorometer (ThermoFisher Scientific, USA). A paired-end library was constructed and sequenced using the MGISEQ-2000 (BGI, Shenzhen, China) and Illumina NovaSeq 6000 platforms (Illumina, San Diego, USA) to generate short sequencing reads. We constructed DNA libraries for long-read single-molecule sequencing and sequenced them on the Nanopore PromethION platform. Total RNA was extracted from the roots, stems, and leaves using an RNAprep Pure Plant Kit (TIANGEN Biotech, China). The RNA libraries were prepared using a TruSeq RNA Library Kit (Illumina, CA, USA) and then sequenced on the Illumina NovaSeq 6000 platform.</p><p id="Par30">The quality of the short sequencing reads was estimated using the FastQC tool, and the adapter sequences, contamination, PCR duplicates, and low-quality reads (reads with more than 30 low-quality bases or 5% unknown bases) were removed using fastp<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. For the Nanopore data, long raw reads were converted into fastq format after base calling by using the Guppy tool<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>. Reads with a mean_qscore_template value greater than seven were retained<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. NextDenovo (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/Nextomics/NextDenovo">https://github.com/Nextomics/NextDenovo</ext-link>), with the parameters read_cutoff = 1&#x02009;kb and seed-cutoff = 37&#x02009;kb, was employed to ensure further correction and assembly. These clean data were used for further assembly and subsequent analysis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Genome survey</title><p id="Par31">To estimate the <italic>M. officinalis</italic> genome characteristics, we used a K-mer-based method to estimate the genome size and heterozygosity. Approximately 61.4&#x02009;Gb (~127&#x000d7;) clean short reads were generated and used for 17 K-mer analyses (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). The frequency distribution of 17 K-mers was counted by Jellyfish software<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. Then, the K-mer depth distribution curve was calculated to estimate the genome size. To further estimate the heterozygosity rate, the genome of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> was used to simulate the corresponding depth of short-read data, and K-mer curve fitting was carried out under different gradient heterozygosity rates. The heterozygosity rate was estimated according to K-mer curve fitting.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Genome and chromosome assembly</title><p id="Par32">After quality control, a total of 62.92&#x02009;Gb (~130&#x000d7;) corrected Nanopore long reads were generated with an average length of 22.39 Kb and N50 of 30.16 Kb. These qualified long reads were assembled by using NextGraph with default parameters to obtain the preliminary assembled genome sequence. The Nanopore long reads were mapped to the preliminary assembled genome using minimap2 with the parameters &#x0201c;-x map-ont&#x0201d; and subjected to three rounds of polishing using Nextpolish with default parameters<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>. Furthermore, to improve accuracy, the clean paired-end reads were mapped to the genome sequence using bwa to polish the assembled contigs with Pilon (iterative correction of four times)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>. Finally, Redundant software was employed to resolve redundancy in the assembly with the parameters &#x0201c;&#x02013;identity 0.8&#x02013;overlap 0.8&#x0201d; to obtain the final nonredundant genome<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par33">To further anchor the contigs to chromosomes, we used fresh young leaves to construct a Hi-C library using a NEBNext Ultra II DNA Library Prep Kit. Approximately 55.8&#x02009;Gb of clean data were generated for Hi-C analyses by the Illumina NovaSeq 6000 platform. These clean reads were mapped to the <italic>M. officinalis</italic> genome using Bowtie2 software (v2.3.2) with the parameters &#x0201c;&#x02013;very-sensitive -L 30&#x0201d; to obtain the uniquely mapped paired-end reads<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>. After filtering out the invalid interaction pairs, including dangling end paired-end reads, self-circle paired-end reads, and dumped paired-end reads, valid paired-end reads were identified and separated by using HiC-Pro (v2.7.8)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>. We then used LACHESIS software to cluster and reorder the contigs into pseudochromosomes with the following parameters: cluster min re sites = 100, cluster max link density = 2.5, cluster noninformative ratio = 1.4, order min n res in trunk = 60, and order min n res in shreds = 60<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup>. Finally, the order and direction of the contigs on the pseudochromosomes were evaluated and adjusted by examining their interactions in the Hi-C heatmap.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Evaluation of the assembled genome</title><p id="Par34">We used multiple methods to assess the accuracy and completeness of the assembled genome. First, the paired-end reads were mapped to the genome to evaluate its completeness using bwa with the default parameters. RNA-seq data from different tissues (leaf, stalk, and root) were also aligned to the reference genome to obtain the mapping rate using HISAT2 with the default settings<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>. Second, GC depth scatter plots were used to evaluate any contamination in the sequencing data. Finally, the accuracy and completeness of the genome assembly were evaluated by using BUSCOs to identify the single-copy genes in the assembled genome with the Embryophyta_odb10 database<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Repeat element identification</title><p id="Par35">The repetitive sequences in the genome can be divided into two main categories: tandem repeats and transposable elements. We used two software programs, GMATA and Tandem Repeats Finder, to search for tandem repeats in the whole genome with default parameters<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup>. Homology alignment and de novo searches were combined to identify transposable elements. RepeatModeler was used for de novo searching for repetitive sequences, which were then classified with Teclass<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup>. We identified the repeats through a homology-based repeat search using Repbase<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup>. We also used MITE-hunter to discover the small transposon called MITE<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup>. LTR_finder and LTR_harvest software were employed to identify the LTRs, and LTR_retriever was used to integrate these results to obtain an LTR retrotransposon library of <italic>M. officinalis</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Noncoding RNA prediction</title><p id="Par36">The tRNA genes were predicted using tRNAscan-SE, and other noncoding RNAs, including rRNA, snRNA, and miRNA, were predicted by comparison with the Rfam database using Infernal software with the default parameters<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref></sup>. At the same time, we also used RNAmmer software to construct models to predict rRNA and its various subunits<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Gene prediction and functional annotation</title><p id="Par37">Transcriptome-based, homology-based, and ab initio prediction methods were combined to predict gene models in the <italic>M. officinalis</italic> genome. To improve gene prediction, RNA libraries were prepared from mixed fresh leaf, stem, and root tissues, and finally 33.43&#x02009;Gb clean data were generated. For homology-based annotation, the protein sequences of <italic>C. canephora</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>, <italic>C. Arabica</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref></sup>, <italic>C. roseus</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref></sup>, and <italic>A. thaliana</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref></sup> were downloaded and aligned against the <italic>M. officinalis</italic> genome using GeMoMa<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref></sup>. For transcriptome-based prediction, the non-redundant transcripts were aligned to the reference genome to obtain gene structures using PASA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref></sup>. Then, TransDecoder was used to search the longest open reading frames according to the PASA results<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref></sup>. We chose 3000 genes with the highest alignment scores (identity &#x0003e;95%) as the training sets for the AUGUSTUS model to generate a generalized hidden Markov probability model for ab initio gene prediction<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref></sup>. Finally, we integrated the gene models from the three approaches with EvidenceModeler, and TransposonPSI was used to remove genes containing transposable elements to generate the final consensus gene models<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par38">Functional annotation of the protein-coding genes was carried out by using Blastp with a cutoff E-value of 1e&#x02212;5 with different public databases. The functions of the genes were predicted and classified using the KOG, NR, and UniProtKB/SwissProt databases. The GO database classified and annotated genes according to three categories: biological processes, cellular components, and molecular functions. We used InterProScan software to identify protein domains by matching them against Pfam database entries to obtain GO terms<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref></sup>. Pathway annotation was performed with the KEGG database with an <italic>E</italic>-value &#x02264; 1e&#x02212;5.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Gene families and phylogenetic analysis</title><p id="Par39">We collected the protein sequences of <italic>M. officinalis</italic> and nine other species, including <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, <italic>Capsicum chinense</italic>, <italic>C. roseus</italic>, <italic>C. canephora</italic>, <italic>Erythranthe guttata</italic>, <italic>Olea europaea</italic>, <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>, <italic>Striga asiatica,</italic> and <italic>V. vinifera</italic>, for evolutionary analysis. An all-to-all BLASTP analysis of the protein sequences of all species was performed with an <italic>E</italic>-value &#x02264; 1e&#x02212;5. Subsequently, orthologous genes, paralogous genes, and single-copy homologous genes were identified using OrthoMCL software with the default parameters<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par40">Phylogenetic construction was performed based on the single-copy orthologous genes from the ten species. We used MAFFT software to align the protein sequences and extracted the conserved sites from the alignments using Gblocks<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref></sup>. We used <italic>V. vinifera</italic> and <italic>A. thaliana</italic> as an outgroup and performed 1000 bootstrap replicates to construct a phylogenetic tree by RaxML<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref></sup>. The divergence time of each species was estimated based on the Bayesian relaxed molecular clock approach using MCMCTREE of the PAML package<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref></sup>. According to the results of the gene families and phylogenetic tree, &#x003bb; values were estimated with CAFE software to predict the expansion or contraction of gene families of different species in each evolutionary branch based on a stochastic birth and death process model<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref></sup>. Gene families with a <italic>p</italic>-value smaller than 0.05 were considered significantly expanded or contracted.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Positive selection genes and WGD analysis</title><p id="Par41">Based on the results of single-copy genes, Codeml software was used to calculate the selection pressure to identify the positively selected genes of <italic>M. officinalis</italic> (<italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.05)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref></sup>. We performed multiple sequence alignment to extract the conserved paralogs of the protein sequences of <italic>M. officinalis</italic> by using BLASTP (<italic>E</italic>-value &#x02264; 1e&#x02212;5). MCScan was used to identify collinearity blocks, and Ks values were calculated by PAML to predict WGD events<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Transcriptome profiling analysis</title><p id="Par42">A total of 108.94&#x02009;Gb clean reads were produced from the leaves, stalks, and roots at different developmental stages of <italic>M. officinalis</italic>. These reads were aligned to the reference genome by using HISAT2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>. The fragments per kilobase of transcript per million fragments mapped (FPKM) were calculated to estimate the expression level of genes. EdgeR was used to analyze the significantly DEGs with an FDR&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.05 and an absolute log<sub>2</sub> (fold change) &#x02265;1 as the threshold<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref></sup>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><sec id="Sec24"><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41438_2021_551_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary data</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p>These authors contributed equally: Jihua Wang, Shiqiang Xu</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41438-021-00551-w.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This project was supported by a study on the cultivation of the six new varieties of Lingnan Traditional Chinese Medicine (2020B020221001), Scientific Innovation Strategy Construction of the High-level Academy of Agriculture Science (R2019PY-JX003), and Southern Medicinal Plants Modern Agricultural Industrial Park of Gaoyao (2018).</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>S.Y. and M.Z. designed and supervised the project. S.C., Y.M., Y.G., Z.L., and M.S. prepared the samples. Y.X., S.X., and J.W. analyzed the data. J.W. and S.X. wrote the manuscript, and S.Y. and M.Z. revised the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The sequencing data, including the MGI genome data (SRA accession: SAMN14599083) and Hi-C data (SRA accession: SAMN14599083), are available in the NCBI Sequence Read Archive (SRA) database under BioProject accession number PRJNA625354.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par43">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lim, T. K. <italic>Edible Medicinal and Non-Medicinal Plants</italic> Vol. 5 (Springer, 2013).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic>Morinda officinalis</italic> how&#x02014;a comprehensive review of traditional uses, phytochemistry and pharmacology</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>213</volume><fpage>230</fpage><lpage>255</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2017.10.028</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29126988?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29126988</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>ZQ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of bajijiasu isolated from <italic>Morinda officinalis</italic> FC how on sexual function in male mice and its antioxidant protection of human sperm</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>164</volume><fpage>283</fpage><lpage>292</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2015.02.016</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25686781?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25686781</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Anthraquinone compounds from <italic>Morinda officinalis</italic> inhibit osteoclastic bone resorption in vitro</article-title><source>Chem. Biol. Interact.</source><year>2011</year><volume>194</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cbi.2011.08.013</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21945525?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21945525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Simultaneous analysis of iridoid glycosides and anthraquinones in <italic>Morinda officinalis</italic> using UPLC-QqQ-MS/MS and UPLC-Q/TOF-MSE</article-title><source>Molecules</source><year>2018</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1070</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules23051070</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical components isolated from the roots of <italic>Morinda officinalis</italic></article-title><source>Chem. Nat. Compd.</source><year>2015</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>548</fpage><lpage>549</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10600-015-1338-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anthraquinones as pharmacological tools and drugs</article-title><source>Med. Res. Rev.</source><year>2016</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>705</fpage><lpage>748</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/med.21391</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27111664?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27111664</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>PHAKHODEE</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution of naturally occurring anthraquinones, iridoids and flavonoids from <italic>Morinda</italic> genus: chemistry and biological activity</article-title><source>Walailak J. Sci. Technol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>188</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antinociceptive anti-inflammatory effect of monotropein isolated from the root of <italic>Morinda officinalis</italic></article-title><source>Biol. Pharm. Bull.</source><year>2005</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1915</fpage><lpage>1918</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1248/bpb.28.1915</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16204945?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16204945</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structural characterization and anti-fatigue activity of polysaccharides from the roots of <italic>Morinda officinalis</italic></article-title><source>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>261</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2008.12.010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19150459?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19150459</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Extraction of polysaccharides from <italic>Morinda officinalis</italic> by response surface methodology and effect of the polysaccharides on bone-related genes</article-title><source>Carbohydr. Polym.</source><year>2011</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.carbpol.2011.01.016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>ZP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of the oligosaccharides extracted from <italic>Morinda officinalis</italic>, a Chinese traditional herbal medicine, on the corticosterone induced apoptosis in PC12 cells</article-title><source>Life Sci.</source><year>2003</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>933</fpage><lpage>942</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0024-3205(02)02331-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12493574?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12493574</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification and characterization of a polysaccharide from the roots of <italic>Morinda officinalis</italic>, as an inducer of bone formation by up-regulation of target gene expression</article-title><source>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</source><year>2019</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>446</fpage><lpage>456</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2019.04.084</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30991070?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30991070</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Research of <italic>Morinda officinalis</italic> how&#x02019;s oligosaccharide extraction and antidepressant effects</article-title><source>Bulgar. Chem. Commun.</source><year>2017</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>162</fpage><lpage>167</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Investigation on germplasm resources of <italic>Morinda officinalis</italic> how</article-title><source>Mod. Chin. Med</source><year>2016</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>482</fpage><lpage>487</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resource survey of medicinal plant of <italic>Morinda officinalis</italic> how in Guangdong and Fujian Provinces</article-title><source>J. Guangzhou Univ. Trad. Chin. Med.</source><year>2009</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>485</fpage><lpage>487</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Research progress of <italic>Morinda officinalis</italic> disease</article-title><source>J. Agric. Sci.</source><year>2018</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1312</fpage><lpage>1317</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional genome of medicinal plants</article-title><source>Mol. Pharmacogn.</source><year>2019</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-981-32-9034-1_7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The reference genome sequence of <italic>Scutellaria baicalensis</italic> provides insights into the evolution of wogonin biosynthesis</article-title><source>Mol. Plant</source><year>2019</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>935</fpage><lpage>950</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molp.2019.04.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30999079?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30999079</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A chromosome-scale genome assembly of <italic>Isatis indigotica</italic>, an important medicinal plant used in traditional Chinese medicine</article-title><source>Hortic. Res.</source><year>2020</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41438-020-0240-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31908804</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name><surname>Cushman</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome sequencing and population genomics modeling provide insights into the local adaptation of weeping forsythia</article-title><source>Hortic. Res.</source><year>2020</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41438-019-0222-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31908804?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31908804</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The genome of medicinal plant <italic>Macleaya cordata</italic> provides new insights into benzylisoquinoline alkaloids metabolism</article-title><source>Mol. Plant</source><year>2017</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>975</fpage><lpage>989</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molp.2017.05.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28552780</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A high-quality reference genome of wild <italic>Cannabis sativa</italic></article-title><source>Hortic. Res.</source><year>2020</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41438-019-0222-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31908804</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome of <italic>Tripterygium wilfordii</italic> and identification of cytochrome P450 involved in triptolide biosynthesis</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31911652</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Denoeud</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The coffee genome provides insight into the convergent evolution of caffeine biosynthesis</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2014</year><volume>345</volume><fpage>1181</fpage><lpage>1184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1255274</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25190796?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25190796</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christianson</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Roots of biosynthetic diversity</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2007</year><volume>316</volume><fpage>60</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1141630</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17412944?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17412944</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El Baidouri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Panaud</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative genomic paleontology across plant kingdom reveals the dynamics of TE-driven genome evolution</article-title><source>Genome Biol. Evol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>954</fpage><lpage>965</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gbe/evt025</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23426643?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23426643</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional regulation of the immune receptor FLS2 controls the ontogeny of plant innate immunity</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2018</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>2779</fpage><lpage>2794</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.18.00297</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30337428?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30337428</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Phosphorylation of an ERF transcription factor by <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> MPK3/MPK6 regulates plant defense gene induction and fungal resistance</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2013</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1126</fpage><lpage>1142</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.112.109074</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23524660?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23524660</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saand</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>XZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cyclic nucleotide gated channel gene family in tomato: genome-wide identification and functional analyses in disease resistance</article-title><source>Front. Plant Sci.</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>303</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2015.00303</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25999969?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25999969</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Coupling deep transcriptome analysis with untargeted metabolic profiling in <italic>Ophiorrhiza pumila</italic> to further the understanding of the biosynthesis of the anti-cancer alkaloid camptothecin and anthraquinones</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>686</fpage><lpage>696</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pct040</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23503598?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23503598</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-enabled discovery of anthraquinone biosynthesis in <italic>Senna tora</italic></article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31911652</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptome analysis and targeted metabolic profiling for pathway elucidation and identification of a geraniol synthase involved in iridoid biosynthesis from <italic>Gardenia jasminoides</italic></article-title><source>Ind. Crops Prod.</source><year>2019</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2019.02.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptome analysis reveals the molecular mechanisms of mucilage biosynthesis during <italic>Artemisia sphaerocephala</italic> seed development</article-title><source>Ind. Crops Prod.</source><year>2020</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>111991</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2019.111991</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Van der Heijden</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Verpoorte</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biosynthesis of anthraquinones in cell cultures of the Rubiaceae</article-title><source>Plant Cell Tissue Organ Cult.</source><year>2001</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>220</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1012758922713</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Research progress on synthesis of anthraquinones based on shikimic acid/o-succinylbenzoic acid pathway</article-title><source>Chin. Trad. Herb. Drugs</source><year>2020</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>1939</fpage><lpage>1950</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The genome of the medicinal plant <italic>Andrographis paniculata</italic> provides insight into the biosynthesis of the bioactive diterpenoid neoandrographolide</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2019</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>841</fpage><lpage>857</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.14162</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30444296?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30444296</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptome-wide analysis of the AP2/ERF transcription factor gene family involved in the regulation of gypenoside biosynthesis in Gynostemma pentaphyllum</article-title><source>Plant Physiol. Biochem.</source><year>2020</year><volume>154</volume><fpage>238</fpage><lpage>247</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plaphy.2020.05.040</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32563852?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32563852</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Two new iridoid glycosides from the fruit of Gardenia jasminoides</article-title><source>Nat. Prod. Res.</source><year>2020</year><volume>2015</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chromosome-scale genome assembly provides insights into the evolution and flavor synthesis of passion fruit (<italic>Passiflora edulis</italic> Sims)</article-title><source>Hortic. Res.</source><year>2021</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41438-020-00455-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33384412</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative genome analysis of <italic>Scutellaria baicalensis</italic> and <italic>Scutellaria barbata</italic> reveals the evolution of active flavonoid biosynthesis</article-title><source>Genomics Proteomics Bioinformatics</source><year>2020</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>230</fpage><lpage>240</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gpb.2020.06.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 33157301?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33157301</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fernie</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrari</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sweetlove</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Respiratory metabolism: glycolysis, the TCA cycle and mitochondrial electron transport</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. plant Biol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>254</fpage><lpage>261</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2004.03.007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15134745?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15134745</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NGS QC toolkit: a toolkit for quality control of next generation sequencing data</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e30619</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0030619</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22312429?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22312429</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>fastp: an ultra-fast all-in-one FASTQ preprocessor</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2018</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>i884</fpage><lpage>i890</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bty560</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 6129281?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30423086</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wick</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Judd</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Performance of neural network basecalling tools for Oxford Nanopore sequencing</article-title><source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>129</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-019-1727-y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31234903?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31234903</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Senol Cali</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghose</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Alkan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mutlu</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nanopore sequencing technology and tools for genome assembly: computational analysis of the current state, bottlenecks and future directions</article-title><source>Brief Bioinformatics</source><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1542</fpage><lpage>1559</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bib/bby017</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29617724?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29617724</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mar&#x000e7;ais</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kingsford</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A fast, lock-free approach for efficient parallel counting of occurrences of k-mers</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2011</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>764</fpage><lpage>770</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 3051319?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21217122</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Minimap and miniasm: fast mapping and de novo assembly for noisy long sequences</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2016</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>2103</fpage><lpage>2110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btw152</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27153593?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27153593</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NextPolish: a fast and efficient genome polishing tool for long read assembly</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2020</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>2253</fpage><lpage>2255</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btz891</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31778144?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31778144</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Li, H. Aligning sequence reads, clone sequences and assembly contigs with BWA-MEM. Preprint at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1303.3997">https://arxiv.org/abs/1303.3997</ext-link> (2013).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pilon: an integrated tool for comprehensive microbial variant detection and genome assembly improvement</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e112963</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0112963</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25409509?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25409509</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pryszcz</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabald&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Redundans: an assembly pipeline for highly heterozygous genomes</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2016</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>e113</fpage><lpage>e113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkw294</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27131372?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27131372</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Langmead</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fast gapped-read alignment with Bowtie 2</article-title><source>Nat. Methods</source><year>2012</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1923</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22388286?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22388286</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Servant</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>HiC-Pro: an optimized and flexible pipeline for Hi-C data processing</article-title><source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>259</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-015-0831-x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26619908?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26619908</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chromosome-scale scaffolding of de novo genome assemblies based on chromatin interactions</article-title><source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>1119</fpage><lpage>1125</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.2727</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24185095?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24185095</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Paggi</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Graph-based genome alignment and genotyping with HISAT2 and HISAT-genotype</article-title><source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source><year>2019</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>907</fpage><lpage>915</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41587-019-0201-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31375807?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31375807</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sim&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Waterhouse</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ioannidis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kriventseva</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name><surname>Zdobnov</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BUSCO: assessing genome assembly and annotation completeness with single-copy orthologs</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2015</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>3210</fpage><lpage>3212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv351</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26059717?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26059717</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GMATA: an integrated software package for genome-scale SSR mining, marker development and viewing</article-title><source>Front. Plant Sci.</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1350</fpage><?supplied-pmid 27679641?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27679641</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tandem repeats finder: a program to analyze DNA sequences</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>1999</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>573</fpage><lpage>580</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/27.2.573</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9862982?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9862982</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bedell</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Korf</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Gish</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MaskerAid: a performance enhancement to RepeatMasker</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2000</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1040</fpage><lpage>1041</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/16.11.1040</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11159316?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11159316</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abrus&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Grundmann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>DeMester</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Makalowski</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TEclass&#x02014;a tool for automated classification of unknown eukaryotic transposable elements</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2009</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1329</fpage><lpage>1330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp084</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19349283?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19349283</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jurka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Repbase update, a database of eukaryotic repetitive elements</article-title><source>Cytogenet. Genome Res.</source><year>2005</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>462</fpage><lpage>467</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000084979</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16093699?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16093699</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wessler</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MITE-Hunter: a program for discovering miniature inverted-repeat transposable elements from genomic sequences</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2010</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>e199</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkq862</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20880995?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20880995</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>LTR-FINDER: an efficient tool for the prediction of full-length LTR retrotransposons</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2007</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>W265</fpage><lpage>W268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm286</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17485477?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17485477</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ellinghaus</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurtz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Willhoeft</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>LTRharvest, an efficient and flexible software for de novo detection of LTR retrotransposons</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2008</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>18</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-9-18</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18194517?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18194517</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>LTR_retriever: a highly accurate and sensitive program for identification of long terminal repeat retrotransposons</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>176</volume><fpage>1410</fpage><lpage>1422</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.17.01310</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29233850?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29233850</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>tRNAscan-SE On-line: integrating search and context for analysis of transfer RNA genes</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2016</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>W54</fpage><lpage>W57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkw413</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27174935?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27174935</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rfam: updates to the RNA families database</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2009</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>D136</fpage><lpage>D140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkn766</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18953034?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18953034</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nawrocki</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolbe</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Infernal 1.0: inference of RNA alignments</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2009</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1335</fpage><lpage>1337</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp157</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19307242?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19307242</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lagesen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>RNAmmer: consistent and rapid annotation of ribosomal RNA genes</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2007</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>3100</fpage><lpage>3108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm160</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17452365?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17452365</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Nardi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Differential responses of <italic>Coffea arabica</italic> L. leaves and roots to chemically induced systemic acquired resistance</article-title><source>Genome</source><year>2006</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>1594</fpage><lpage>1605</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/g06-125</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17426774?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17426774</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Franke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gene discovery in Gelsemium highlights conserved gene clusters in monoterpene indole alkaloid biosynthesis</article-title><source>ChemBioChem</source><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>87</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cbic.201800592</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30300974?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30300974</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaul</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Analysis of the genome sequence of the flowering plant <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2000</year><volume>408</volume><fpage>796</fpage><lpage>815</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35048692</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11130711</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keilwagen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Using intron position conservation for homology-based gene prediction</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2016</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>e89</fpage><lpage>e89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkw092</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26893356?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26893356</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Improving the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> genome annotation using maximal transcript alignment assemblies</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>5654</fpage><lpage>5666</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkg770</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14500829?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14500829</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>De novo transcript sequence reconstruction from RNA-seq using the Trinity platform for reference generation and analysis</article-title><source>Nat. Protoc.</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1494</fpage><lpage>1512</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2013.084</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23845962?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23845962</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stanke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Diekhans</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Baertsch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Haussler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Using native and syntenically mapped cDNA alignments to improve de novo gene finding</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2008</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>637</fpage><lpage>644</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btn013</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18218656?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18218656</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR78"><label>78.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Automated eukaryotic gene structure annotation using EVidenceModeler and the Program to Assemble Spliced Alignments</article-title><source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>R7</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2008-9-1-r7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18190707?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18190707</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR79"><label>79.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Urasaki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Draft genome sequence of bitter gourd (<italic>Momordica charantia</italic>), a vegetable and medicinal plant in tropical and subtropical regions</article-title><source>DNA Res.</source><year>2017</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><?supplied-pmid 28028039?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28028039</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR80"><label>80.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>InterPro: the integrative protein signature database</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2009</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>D211</fpage><lpage>D215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkn785</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18940856?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18940856</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR81"><label>81.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoeckert</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>OrthoMCL: identification of ortholog groups for eukaryotic genomes</article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><year>2003</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>2178</fpage><lpage>2189</lpage><?supplied-pmid 403725?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12952885</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR82"><label>82.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Standley</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MAFFT multiple sequence alignment software version 7: improvements in performance and usability</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>772</fpage><lpage>780</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/mst010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23329690?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23329690</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR83"><label>83.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castresana</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selection of conserved blocks from multiple alignments for their use in phylogenetic analysis</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source><year>2000</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>540</fpage><lpage>552</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.molbev.a026334</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10742046?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10742046</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR84"><label>84.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stamatakis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RAxML-VI-HPC: maximum likelihood-based phylogenetic analyses with thousands of taxa and mixed models</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2006</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>2688</fpage><lpage>2690</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btl446</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16928733</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR85"><label>85.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PAML: a program package for phylogenetic analysis by maximum likelihood</article-title><source>Comput. Appl. Biosci.</source><year>1997</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>555</fpage><lpage>556</lpage><?supplied-pmid 9367129?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9367129</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR86"><label>86.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Bie</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Cristianini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Demuth</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CAFE: a computational tool for the study of gene family evolution</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2006</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1269</fpage><lpage>1271</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btl097</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16543274</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR87"><label>87.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>EasyCodeML: a visual tool for analysis of selection using CodeML</article-title><source>Ecol. Evol.</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>3891</fpage><lpage>3898</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ece3.5015</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31015974?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31015974</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR88"><label>88.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MCScanX: a toolkit for detection and evolutionary analysis of gene synteny and collinearity</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2012</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>e49</fpage><lpage>e49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkr1293</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22217600?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22217600</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR89"><label>89.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>edgeR: a Bioconductor package for differential expression analysis of digital gene expression data</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2010</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp616</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19910308</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>