<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Pharmacognosy Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Pharmacognosy Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PR</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Pharmacognosy Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0976-4836</issn><issn pub-type="epub">0974-8490</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications &#x00026; Media Pvt Ltd</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3996750</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PR-6-138</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0974-8490.129033</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Presence of monoterpene synthase in four Labiatae species and Solid-Phase Microextraction- Gas chromatography-Mass Spectroscopy analysis of their aroma profiles</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Saeidnia</surname><given-names>Soodabeh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gohari</surname><given-names>Ahmad Reza</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Haddadi</surname><given-names>Azita</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Amin</surname><given-names>Gholamreza</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nikan</surname><given-names>Marjan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hadjiakhoondi</surname><given-names>Abbass</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><italic>Medicinal Plants Research Center, Faculty of Pharmacy, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran</italic></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><italic>Division of Pharmacy, College of Pharmacy and Nutrition, University of Saskatchewan, Saskatoon, Canada</italic></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><italic>Department of Pharmacognosy, Faculty of Pharmacy, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran</italic></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Dr. Soodabeh Saeidnia, Medicinal Plants Research Center, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, P. O. Box 14155-6451, Tehran, Iran. E-mail: <email xlink:href="saeidnia_s@sina.tums.ac.ir">saeidnia_s@sina.tums.ac.ir</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Apr-Jun</season><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>138</fpage><lpage>142</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>7</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>17</day><month>8</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>3</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; Pharmacognosy Research </copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="st1"><title>Background:</title><p>The family Lamiaceae (Labiatae) has included some medicinal plants. some monoterpene synthases, including linalool and limonene synthases, have been cloned and functionally characterized from several plants of Labiatae family.</p></sec><sec id="st2"><title>Materials and Methods:</title><p>In this study, presence of linalool and limonene synthases, in four species of Labiatae family including <italic>Nepeta cataria</italic>, <italic>Lavandula angustifolia</italic>, <italic>Hyssopus officinalis</italic> and <italic>Salvia sclarea</italic> has been determined by molecular biological techniques together with the Head space SPME &#x02013; GC-MS analysis of the aroma profile of these species.</p></sec><sec id="st3"><title>Results:</title><p>Indicated that none of the plant species produced distinguishable bands with primer pairs related to <italic>d</italic>-limonene synthase. Distinguishable bands around 1800 bp in cDNA samples of <italic>L. angustifolia</italic>, <italic>H. officinalis</italic> and <italic>S. sclarea</italic> were observed regarding to the presence of linalool synthase. Head space SPME-GC-MS analysis of the aroma profiles of the above-mentioned plants showed that linalool (31.0%), linalyl acetate (18.2%), were found as the major compounds of <italic>L. angustifolia</italic>, while geraniol (5.5%), nerol (34.0%) and &#x003b1;- citral (52.0%) were identified as the main compounds of the <italic>N. cataria</italic>. The major components of <italic>H. officinalis</italic> and <italic>S. sclarea</italic> oils were determined as <italic>cis</italic>-pinocamphone (57.3%), and linalool (19.0%), linalyl acetate (51.5%), respectively.</p></sec><sec id="st4"><title>Conclusion:</title><p><italic>H. officinalis</italic> was rich of cyclic monoterpenes, <italic>L. angustifolia</italic>, <italic>N. cataria</italic> and <italic>S. sclarea</italic> showed considerable amount of linear monoterpenes. The aroma profile of the above-mentioned plants contained low concentration of sesquiterpenes except <italic>N. cataria</italic>, which indicated no sesquiterpene. The profiles of the main components of these plants are in agreement with molecular assays.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Essential oil</kwd><kwd>headspace solid phase microextraction</kwd><kwd>labiatae</kwd><kwd>monoterpene synthase</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>The family Labiateae (Lamiaceae) has 180 genera and about 3500 species. The aerial parts of these plants contain flavonoids, triterpenoids, and monoterpenes, particularly in the flowers and leaves.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref><xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] Essential oils of these plants consist of various monoterpenes and sesquiterpenes, as well as their derivatives, such as alcohols, aldehydes, esters, and acetates.[<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref><xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref><xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] Terpenoids are formed from the condensation of dimethylallyl pyrophosphate (DMAPP) and isopentyl pyrophosphate (IPP), to give geranyl diphosphate (GPP), farnesyl diphosphate (FPP), or geranyl geranyl diphosphate (GGPP).[<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref><xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref><xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] Terpene synthases in plant kingdom may fall into two categories. First class (e.g., limonene synthase) involves in ionization of allylic diphosphate to initiate the reaction, but second class (e.g., copalyl diphosphate synthase (CPS)) acts in double-bond protonation of substrate.[<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]</p><p>Among the terpene synthases, cyclases enzymes, such as limonene synthase (LMS), have been focused and studied in diverse plant species. LMS contains approximately 600 amino acids and is responsible for catalyzing the formation of limonene.[<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] Limonene is a simple cyclic monoterpene, with a chiral center and two enantiomers (<italic>d</italic> and <italic>l</italic>). Although various <italic>d</italic>- and <italic>l</italic>-limonene synthase genes have been identified, there are a few reports about the relationship between gene transcription and biosynthesis during plant growth.[<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] Linalool synthase (LIS), involves in biosynthesis of linalool as an acyclic monoterpene alcohol, is not simply classified on the basis of its amino acid sequence, because N-terminal part reveals higher sequence similarity to CPS but C-terminal exhibits higher similarity to LMS.[<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref><xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] Intron positions in LMS-type terpene cyclase genes are very similar to each other.[<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</p><p>So far, some monoterpene synthases, including linalool and limonene synthases, have been cloned and functionally characterized from several plants of Labiatae family.[<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref><xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] In the present study, we aimed to determine the presence of two monoterpene synthases, linalool and limonene synthases, in four species of Labiatae family including <italic>Nepeta cataria</italic>, <italic>Lavandula angustifolia</italic>, <italic>Hyssopus officinalis</italic> and <italic>Salvia sclarea</italic> together with the Head space Solid-phase Microextraction - Gas chromatography - Mass spectroscopy analysis of the aroma profile of these species.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec1-2"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Experimental</title><p>Chemical reagents and solvents were purchased from Merck Co. (Germany). Agarose and 1kb DNA size marker were prepared from Invitrogen Co. (UK). RNeasy Plant Mini Kit was prepared from Qiagen (USA). Polymerase chain reactions were performed on a Primus 25 (Peqlab, Germany) thermal cycler. Primers were produced in Cinnagene (Iran).</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Plant material</title><p>All the plants mentioned here were grown in the Herboratum of Faculty of Pharmacy, Tehran University of Medical Sciences and identified by Dr. Gholamreza Amin (Department of Pharmacognosy) as <italic>Nepeta cataria</italic>, <italic>Lavandula angustifolia</italic>, <italic>Hyssopus officinalis</italic> and <italic>Salvia sclarea</italic>. Young leaves of each species were harvested (during June, 2010) from a plant grown outside in a mini-garden under natural conditions.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title>Primer designation</title><p>Protein sequences of linalool and limonene synthases from <italic>Mentha spicata</italic> (Gen-Bank Accession No. AAC37366), <italic>Mentha citrate</italic> (AAL99381), <italic>Perilla frutescens</italic> (AAL38029), <italic>A. thaliana</italic> (AAO85533) and <italic>Lavandula angustifolia</italic> (ABB73045, ABB73044) were aligned with free ClustalW software and revealed several conserved regions. Based on the DNA and peptide sequences the different primers have been designed and synthesized [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Primers designed according to different terpene synthases gene sequences</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PR-6-138-g001"/></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec2-4"><title>cDNA Preparation and PCR</title><p>About 200 mg of each plant's leaves were frozen in liquid nitrogen and ground into a fine powder. Total RNA was extracted using &#x0201c;RNeasy Plant Mini Kit&#x0201d; and reverse transcribed with oligo (dT) primer [ad: 5&#x02019;-GCT GTC AAC GAT ACG CTA CGT AAC GGC ATG ACA GTG TTT TTT TTT TTT TTT TTT-3&#x02019;] designed to have an adaptor sequence at the 5&#x02019;-end to obtain the cDNA. The obtained cDNAs were employed as the templates in various PCRs with Taq and/or KOD Dash DNA polymerases. The temperature program was started at 94&#x000b0;C (3 min), followed by 40 cycles: 94&#x000b0;C for 30 s, 46&#x000b0;C for 30 s (different annealing temperatures were used for each pair of primers) and 72&#x000b0;C for 1 min, then 72&#x000b0;C for 2 min. Elongating times were different (30-60 s) based on the expected length of the amplified fragment. The PCR was performed by DNA polymerase (0.2 &#x003bc;L), each degenerate forward and reverse primers (0.3 &#x003bc;L, 20 pmol), dNTP (0.1mM, 2 &#x003bc;L), DNA template (1 &#x003bc;L) and appropriate amounts of recommended buffer, DMSO and water. The partial size of monoterpene synthase sequences was estimated by gel electrophoresis. PCR products were run on a 1% (w/v) agarose gel along with a 1 kb DNA size marker, stained by ethidium bromide (0.5 &#x003bc;g/ml) and visualized in a gel documentation system.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-5"><title>SPME- GC-MS analysis</title><p>Head space Solid-phase Microextraction (SPME) coupled to gas chromatography and mass spectrometry has been applied for analyzing the essential oil directly evaporated from young leaves of four species. GC-MS was performed on a cross-linked 5% methyl phenyl siloxane (HP-5, 30 m &#x000d7; 0.25-mm i.d., 0.25-&#x003bc;m film thickness), carrier gas, He; split ratio, 1:15; quadruple mass spectrometer Hewlett-Packard 6890) operating at 70 eV ionization energy. In order to obtain the retention index for each compound, normal alkanes (C8-C25) were injected at the same temperature and condition. The components were identified by comparison of their retention indices (RI, DB-5) and mass fragmentation with those reported in the literature.[<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] Percentage of each component was calculated on the basis of the peak area.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec1-3"><title>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</title><p>In this investigation, PCR method was employed with different primers designed regarding to the conserved amino acid sequence in various Labiatae plant terpene synthases, in order to reveal the presence of limonene and linalool synthases in four Labiatae species: <italic>N. cataria</italic>, <italic>L. angustifolia</italic>, <italic>H. officinalis</italic> and <italic>S. sclarea</italic>. As it is indicated in [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>], none of the plant species produced distinguishable bands with primer pairs: amm-A, amm-B and ann-B&#x02019; which were related to <italic>d</italic>-limonene synthase [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>]. Limonene is biologically formed from geranyl pyrophosphate (GPP) through linalyl pyrophosphate (LPP). Limonene synthases is thought to promote the cyclization of GPP into limonene and have been previously cloned from <italic>Perilla</italic>, <italic>Mentha</italic> and <italic>Abies</italic> and occurred <italic>l</italic>-enantiomer, while <italic>d</italic>-limonene synthase was cloned from <italic>Schizonepeta tenuifolia</italic> for the first time.[<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] The degenerate forward primers TerpDeg1, TerpDeg2 and TerpDeg3 were designed on the basis of the conserved sequences F (RK)(LI) LRQ (HE) G, E (GD) E (DHS)(TI) L and DD (VI)(YF) D (VI)(YF) G. PCRs using these primers with reverse primer TerpDeg4 resulted in presence of the mentioned sequences in three Labiatae species employed in this study [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>]. The results were supported by further PCRs using LaLIMS (forward) and GR3&#x02019; (reversed) primers, which revealed that limonene synthase should be expressed in all species except <italic>N. cataria</italic>. On the other hand, volatile oils of <italic>L. angustifolia</italic>, <italic>H. officinalis</italic> and <italic>S. sclarea</italic> contained limonene and its derivatives [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The results obtained from gel electrophoresis of various PCR products (cDNA of <italic>N. cataria</italic>, <italic>L. angustifolia</italic>, <italic>H. officinalis</italic> and <italic>S. sclarea</italic>) with different primer pairs</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PR-6-138-g002"/></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Aroma profile composition of <italic>L. angustifolia</italic>, <italic>N. cataria</italic>
<italic>H. officinalis S. sclarea</italic> young leaves obtained by HS/SPME</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PR-6-138-g003"/></table-wrap><p>Interestingly, PCRs with LaLINS (forward) and GR3&#x02019;Nested (reversed) primers resulted in distinguishable bands around 1800 bp in three cDNA samples, which could be related to linalool synthase, well known as a &#x0201c;dead end product&#x0201d; in the general monoterpene biosynthetic pathway.[<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] Because linalool is found in the essential oils [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>] of three species (<italic>L. angustifolia</italic>, <italic>H. officinalis</italic> and <italic>S. sclarea</italic>), linalool synthase should be expressed simultaneously in these plants whose main constituents harbor linalool structure.</p><p>Among the selected Labiatae plants, <italic>N. cataria</italic> did not show neither limonene nor linalool synthases. The essential oil of this plant was also enriched of geraniol derivatives supporting positive bands with ddmot3 and amm primers.</p><p>The results of the head space SPME-GC-MS analysis of the aroma profiles of the above-mentioned plants have been summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref> and showed that linalool (31.0%), linalyl acetate (18.2%), lavandulyl acetate (10.7%) and alpha-terpineol (6.3%) were found as the major compounds of <italic>L. angustifolia</italic>, while &#x003b2;- citronellol (8.0%), geraniol (5.5%), nerol (34.0%) and &#x003b1;- citral (52.0%) were identified as the main compounds of the <italic>N. cataria</italic> [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>]. The major components of <italic>H. officinalis</italic> and <italic>S. sclarea</italic> oils were determined as <italic>cis</italic>-pinocamphone (57.3%), &#x003b2;-pinene (7.0%), terpinen-4-ol (7.0%), and linalool (19.0%), linalyl acetate (51.5%), &#x003b1;-pinene (4.0%), respectively.</p><p>The profiles of the main components of these plants are in agreement with those reported in the literature.[<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref><xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref><xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref><xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] Although <italic>H. officinalis</italic> was rich of cyclic monoterpenes, <italic>L. angustifolia</italic>, <italic>N. cataria</italic> and <italic>S. sclarea</italic> showed considerable amount of linear monoterpenes. The aroma profile of the above mentioned plants contained low concentration of sesquiterpenes except <italic>N. cataria</italic>, which indicated no sesquiterpene.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec1-4"><title>CONCLUSIONS</title><p>Plants of Lamiaceae family are well-known for application in traditional medicine and phytotherapy.[<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] In this study, presence of linalool and limonene synthases, in four species of Labiatae family including <italic>N. cataria</italic>, <italic>L. angustifolia</italic>, <italic>H. officinalis</italic> and <italic>S. sclarea</italic> has been determined by molecular biological techniques together with the Head space SPME - GC-MS analysis of the aroma profile of these species. Taking together, <italic>H. officinalis</italic> was rich of cyclic monoterpenes, <italic>L. angustifolia</italic>, <italic>N. cataria</italic> and <italic>S. sclarea</italic> showed considerable amount of linear monoterpenes. The aroma profile of the above mentioned plants contained low concentration of sesquiterpenes except <italic>N. cataria</italic>, which indicated no sesquiterpene. The profiles of the main components of these plants are in agreement with molecular assays.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENT</title><p>This research has been supported by Tehran University of Medical Sciences and health Services grant No. 15246.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="supported-by"><p><bold>Source of Support:</bold> Nil</p></fn><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Conflict of Interest:</bold> None declared.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abu-Dahab</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Afifi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasabri</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Majdalawi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Naffa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of the antiproliferative activity of crude ethanol extracts of nine <italic>salvia</italic> species grown in Jordan against breast cancer cell line models</article-title><source>Pharmacogn Mag</source><year>2012</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24082637</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasmal</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazumder</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The anti hyperglycemic effect of aerial parts of <italic>Salvia splendens</italic> (scarlet sage) in streptozotocin-induced diabetic-rat</article-title><source>Pharmacogn Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>190</fpage><lpage>4</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shuge</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiaoying</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Dongqing</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Essential oil composition of the <italic>Dracocephalum moldavica</italic> L from Xinjiang in China</article-title><source>Pharmacogn Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>172</fpage><lpage>4</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gohari</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hadjiakhoondi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadat-Ebrahimi</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Saeidnia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shafiee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Composition of volatile oils of <italic>Satureja spicigera</italic> and <italic>Satureja macrantha</italic> from Iran</article-title><source>Flavour Fragr J</source><year>2006</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>510</fpage><lpage>2</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saeidnia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gohari</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hadjiakhoondi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shafiee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bioactive compounds of the volatile oil of <italic>Dracocephalum kotschyi</italic></article-title><source>Z Naturforsch C</source><year>2007</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>793</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18274279</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fakhari</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Salehi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Heydari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebrahimi</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Haddad</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hydrodistillation-headspace solvent microextraction, a new method for analysis of the essential oil components of <italic>Lavandula angustifolia</italic> Mill</article-title><source>J Chromatogr A</source><year>2005</year><volume>1098</volume><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16314156</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gershenzon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Croteau</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Terpenoid biosynthesis: the basic pathway and formation of monoterpenes, sesquiterpenes, and diterpenes</article-title><source>Lipid metabolism in plants</source><year>1993</year><publisher-loc>Florida</publisher-loc><publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name><fpage>340</fpage><lpage>88</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamane</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Murofushi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamiya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular cloning and characterization of a cDNA encoding the gibberellin biosynthetic enzyme ent-kaurene synthase B from pumpkin (<italic>Cucurbita maxima</italic> L.)</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>1996</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8771778</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Artemisinin biosynthesis and its regulatory enzymes: Progress and perspective</article-title><source>Pharmacogn Rev</source><year>2011</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22279377</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cseke</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudareva</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Pichersky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure and evolution of linalool synthase</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>1998</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1491</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12572612</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Endo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Omura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and characterization of a new d-limonene synthase gene with a different expression pattern in <italic>Citrus unshiu</italic> Marc</article-title><source>Scientia Horticulturae</source><year>2005</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>507</fpage><lpage>12</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pichersky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewinsohn</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Croteau</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Purification and characterization of S-linalool synthase, an enzyme involved in the production of floral scent in <italic>Clarkia breweri</italic></article-title><source>Arch Biochem Biophys</source><year>1995</year><volume>316</volume><fpage>803</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7864636</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bohlmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Steele</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Croteau</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Monoterpene synthases from grand fir (<italic>Abies grandis</italic>)</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1997</year><volume>272</volume><fpage>21784</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9268308</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Back</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Chappell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cloning and bacterial expression of a sesquiterpene cyclase from <italic>Hyoscyamus muticus</italic> and its molecular comparison to related terpene cyclases</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1995</year><volume>270</volume><fpage>7375</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7706281</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colby</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Katahira</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McGarvey</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Croteau</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>4S-limonene synthase from the oil glands of spearmint (<italic>Mentha spicata</italic>). cDNA isolation, characterization, and bacterial expression of the catalytically active monoterpene cyclase</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1993</year><volume>268</volume><fpage>23016</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8226816</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maruyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiuchi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Honda</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular cloning, functional expression and characterization of d-limonene synthase from <italic>Schizonepeta tenuifolia</italic></article-title><source>Biol Pharm Bull</source><year>2001</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11305598</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Meadows</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microarray Technology in Practice</article-title><year>2009</year><publisher-loc>USA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hosoi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yagura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Honda</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>cDNA isolation and functional expression of myrcene synthase from <italic>Perilla frutescens</italic></article-title><source>Biol Pharm Bull</source><year>2004</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1979</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15577217</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Landmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fink</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Festner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dregus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwab</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cloning and functional characterization of three terpene synthases from lavender (<italic>Lavandula angustifolia</italic>)</article-title><source>Arch Biochem Biophys</source><year>2007</year><volume>465</volume><fpage>417</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17662687</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of essential oil components by gas chromatography/Quadruple Mass Spectroscopy</article-title><year>2001</year><publisher-loc>Carol Stream llinois</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Allured</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masumoto</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Korin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Geraniol and linalool synthases from wild species of <italic>perilla</italic></article-title><source>Phytochemistry</source><year>2010</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>1068</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20447664</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saeidnia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gohari</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hadjiakhoondi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trypanocidal activity of oil of the young leaves of <italic>Nepeta cataria</italic> L. obtained by solvent extraction</article-title><source>J Med Plants</source><year>2008</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yousefzadi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonboli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Karimi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebrahimi</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Asghari</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeinali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activity of some <italic>Salvia</italic> species essential oils from Iran</article-title><source>Z Naturforsch C</source><year>2007</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>514</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17913065</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kazazi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rezaei</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of various parameters on the selective extraction of main components from <italic>Hyssop</italic> using supercritical fluid extraction (SFE)</article-title><source>Food Sci Technol Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>645</fpage><lpage>52</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shekarchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hajimehdipoor</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Saeidnia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gohari</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamedani</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative study of rosmarinic acid content in some plants of Labiatae family</article-title><source>Pharmacogn Mag</source><year>2012</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22438661</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>