<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7552398</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">73130</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-73130-z</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><italic>Agasicles hygrophila</italic> attack increases nerolidol synthase gene expression in <italic>Alternanthera philoxeroides</italic>, facilitating host finding</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Yuanxin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Yanhong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Xingchun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>Dong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Jun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Ling-Ling</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Ruiyan</given-names></name><address><email>maruiyan2019@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412545.3</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1798 1300</institution-id><institution>College of Plant Protection, </institution><institution>Shanxi Agricultural University, </institution></institution-wrap>Taigu, 030801 Shanxi People&#x02019;s Republic of China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412545.3</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1798 1300</institution-id><institution>College of Life Sciences, </institution><institution>Shanxi Agricultural University, </institution></institution-wrap>Taigu, 030801 Shanxi People&#x02019;s Republic of China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>CSIRO Agriculture and Food, Centre for Environment and Life Sciences, Wembley, WA 6014 Australia </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>12</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>16994</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>3</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Herbivorous insects use plant volatile compounds to find their host plants for feeding and egg deposition. The monophagous beetle <italic>Agasicles hygrophila</italic> uses a volatile (E)-4,8-dimethyl-1,3,7-nonanetriene (DMNT) to recognize its host plant <italic>Alternanthera philoxeroides</italic>. <italic>Alternanthera philoxeroides</italic> releases DMNT in response to <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> attack and nerolidol synthase (NES) is a key enzyme in DMNT biosynthesis; however, the effect of <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> on <italic>NES</italic> expression remains unclear. In this study, the <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> transcriptome was sequenced and six putative <italic>NES</italic> genes belonging to the terpene synthase-g family were characterized. The expression of these <italic>NES</italic> genes was assayed at different times following <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> contact, feeding or mechanical wounding. Results showed that <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> contact and feeding induced <italic>NES</italic> expression more rapidly and more intensely than mechanical wounding alone. This may account for a large release of DMNT following <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> feeding in a previous study and subsequently facilitate <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> to find host plants. Our research provides a powerful genetic platform for studying invasive plants and lays the foundation for further elucidating the molecular mechanisms of the interaction between <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> and its specialist <italic>A. hygrophila</italic>.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Herbivory</kwd><kwd>Wounding</kwd><kwd>Entomology</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Applied Basic Research Program of Shanxi Province</institution></funding-source><award-id>201901D211354</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Shanxi Province Graduate Education Innovation Project</institution></funding-source><award-id>2019BY072</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Yuanxin</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution></funding-source><award-id>31570436</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Ruiyan</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Alligator weed, <italic>Alternanthera philoxeroides</italic> (Mart.) Griseb. (Caryophyllales: Amaranthaceae), is an invasive weed that has spread across 30 countries, including the USA, New Zealand, and China<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. It not only causes serious economic losses by hindering river transportation and crop production, but also has a detrimental impact on native wildlife, causing many ecological problems in the invaded areas<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. The most successful method of effectively controlling <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> is the use of the alligator weed flea beetle <italic>Agasicles hygrophila</italic> (Selman and Vogt) (Coleoptera: Chrysomelidae), which is stably monophagous and has a high food requirement<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. In China, the safety of using <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> near local crops was evaluated, revealing that the specific diet of this beetle did not change even many years after its introduction<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. This stable and specific feeding relationship means that <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> and its host plant <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> can be an useful model to study the interaction between plants and their host-specific herbivorous insects; however, few reports have been published on this particular relationship.</p><p id="Par3">Research into the specific interaction between <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> and <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> has largely focused on surface phenomena, such as the biological performance, life history, and host selection of <italic>A. hygrophila</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Recently, this plant&#x02013;insect specificity was further elucidated in a report that host specificity is related to the response of <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> to specialized volatiles released by the plant, which can be detected at a distance<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. This laboratory-based study found that under undamaged conditions the main volatile of <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic>, homoterpene (<italic>E</italic>)-4,8-dimethyl-1,3,7-nonanetriene (DMNT), was present in larger quantities in this species than in other plants tested. <italic>Agasicles hygrophila</italic> prefers the volatile emitted from plants fed by conspecific insects for 24&#x000a0;h than those from healthy plants, because insect injured plants released more DMNT. DMNT is a significant attractant of <italic>A. hygrophila</italic>, allowing <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> to discriminate host from non-host plants. DMNT is therefore considered to be an important volatile cue for <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> to orient, locate, and feed on <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic>.</p><p id="Par4">DMNT is an important plant terpenoid volatile compound, emitted by the flowers of night-scented plants and plant leaves damaged by herbivores<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>, and is thought to attract pollinators or take part in indirect defense to reduce feeding damage and enhance plant fitness<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. Undamaged individuals of most plant species do not release DMNT, or only release a small amount, however, healthy <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> plants also emit DMNT<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>, which is a derivative of nerolidol. The terpene synthase enzyme nerolidol synthase (NES) was previously reported in lima beans (<italic>Phaseolus lunatus</italic> L.), maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic> L.), and cucumber (<italic>Cucumis sativus</italic> L.), and was shown to catalyze the biosynthesis of the DMNT precursor nerolidol from farnesyl pyrophosphate (FPP)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. After generating nerolidol, the P450 enzyme takes part in the further cleavage reaction to produce homoterpene DMNT<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. During this process, terpene synthases determine the type and the quantity of terpenoids produced<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. Here, nerolidol synthase belongs to the terpene synthase g (TPS-g) subfamily, of which proteins use FPP, geranyl pyrophosphate (GPP) or geranylgeranyl pyrophosphate (GGPP) as substrates to catalyze the production of acyclic monoterpenes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">The expression of terpene synthase genes is involved in the interactions between plants and biotic environmental factors. For example, the linalool produced by transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> expressing <italic>FaNES1</italic> from cultivated strawberry (<italic>Fragaria</italic>&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;<italic>ananassa</italic> Duch.) has a repellent effect on the green peach aphid (<italic>Myzus persicae</italic> (Sulzer)), while the volatiles produced by these plants ((3, S)-(<italic>E</italic>)-nerolidol and DMNT) attract predatory mites such as <italic>Phytoseiulus persimilis</italic> Athias-Henriot<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. Likewise, transgenic chrysanthemum (<italic>Chrysanthemum morifolium</italic> Ramat.) expressing <italic>FaNES1</italic> releases linalool and DMNT, rapidly attracting western flower thrips (<italic>Frankliniella occidentalis</italic> (Pergande))<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Transgenic rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.) expressing a DMNT biosynthesis gene <italic>Pltps4</italic> from <italic>P. lunatus</italic> enhanced the attraction of <italic>Cotesia chilonis</italic> (Matsumura), a parasitoid of trunk borers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. However, there is no report on the expression of <italic>NES</italic> genes in <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> and the associated effect on <italic>A. hygrophila</italic>.</p><p id="Par6">To elucidate the specific interaction between <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> and <italic>A. hygrophila</italic>, we explored the role of the <italic>A. philoxeroides NES</italic> genes in this relationship. When we began this study, we lacked available <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> gene data; therefore, we performed transcriptome sequencing on mixed <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> tissues and screened the putative <italic>NES</italic> genes. In a previous study, <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> adults were placed on <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> for 24&#x000a0;h to obtain herbivore-damaged plants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. However, in general, the biosynthesis of organic volatiles from damaged plants often takes several minutes to several hours, with the release of terpenoids being typically slower than that of the green leaf volatiles (GLVs)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. It is possible that this long period of wounding could mask changes in the expression levels of the <italic>NES</italic> genes in these plants. Therefore, in the present study, we examined the behavior of <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> adults on the leaves in the first two hours. We then compared the expression of <italic>NES</italic> genes in leaves subjected to contact, feeding by <italic>A. hygrophila</italic>, and mechanical wounding, revealing that <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> contact upregulates <italic>NES</italic> genes in <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> before feeding, and <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> feeding significantly increases <italic>NES</italic> gene expression. Chemicals secreted by <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> likely induce the release of large amounts of DMNT from bitten <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Plant and insect</title><p id="Par7"><italic>Alternanthera philoxeroides</italic> was collected from a naturalized population in Yuhuan County, Zhejiang, China, then grown in the glasshouse of Shanxi Agricultural University, Taigu, Shanxi, China. Shoots from a single individual were separately cultured in pots at a constant temperature of 25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, with 14&#x000a0;h light and 10&#x000a0;h dark.</p><p id="Par8"><italic>Agasicles hygrophila</italic> was obtained from South China Agricultural University, Guangzhou, China, fed with fresh <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> leaves, and maintained in an insectary at Shanxi Agricultural University for several generations under controlled conditions (25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, 80&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5% relative humidity, and with a 14-h light: 10-h dark photoperiod).</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Transcriptome sequencing, assembly, and annotation</title><p id="Par9"><italic>Alternanthera philoxeroides</italic> individuals with similar growth were selected for sampling. The fourth and fifth pairs of leaves, the third and fourth internodes from the top, flowers, and roots were harvested and frozen in liquid nitrogen for further processing. Total RNA was isolated from each of the four tissues (leaves, stems, flowers, and roots) using TRIzol (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA) and RNA from each tissue was mixed in equal amounts. The RNA was then submitted to Biomarker Technologies (Beijing, China) for transcriptome sequencing on a HiSeq 2500 system (Illumina, San Diego, CA, USA). The sequencing adaptors, primer sequences, and low-quality data (reads that were&#x0003c;&#x02009;50&#x000a0;bp and contained more N-bases) were removed from the original data, after which the clean reads were assembled using Trinity (Broad Institute, Cambridge, MA, USA)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup> to obtain transcripts and unigenes. The unigenes were annotated by using them as a template for BLASTX-searches of multiple public repositories of known proteins, including RefSeq non-redundant proteins (NR), UniProtKB/Swiss-Prot<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>, Gene Ontology (GO; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://geneontology.org/">https://geneontology.org/</ext-link>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>, Clusters of Orthologous Genes (COG; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/COG/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/COG/</ext-link>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>, EuKaryotic Orthologous Groups (KOG), Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.kegg.jp/kegg/kegg1.html">https://www.kegg.jp/kegg/kegg1.html</ext-link>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>, Pfam (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pfam.xfam.org/">https://pfam.xfam.org/</ext-link>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>, and other databases. The results were parsed to calculate the total number of positive identities per query&#x02013;subject pair and further filtered using an E-value&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;1e&#x02212;05. The KEGG Orthology results of the unigenes were predicted using KOBAS 2.0 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://kobas.cbi.pku.edu.cn">https://kobas.cbi.pku.edu.cn</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Identification of terpene synthase genes</title><p id="Par10">The identified nerolidol synthase FaNES1 was used to align to the unigene data from the <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> transcriptome. The Unigenes in the results annotated as &#x0201c;terpene synthase&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;TPS&#x0201d; were then selected and aligned with the NCBI NR database using an online BLAST search (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi">https://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi</ext-link>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. The open reading frames (ORFs) were searched with ORFfinder (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/orffinder/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/orffinder/</ext-link>) and translated into amino acid sequences. DNAMan 7.0 (Lynnon Biosoft, San Ramon, CA, USA) was used to analyze the sequence identity of the <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> TPS protein sequences. After removing incomplete sequences shorter than 500&#x000a0;bp and those shorter than 150 aa of translated protein sequences, we used the Maximum Likelihood method and JTT&#x02009;+&#x02009;G&#x02009;+&#x02009;I model to construct a phylogenetic tree of the TPS protein sequences in <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> together with other plant species (Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>) by MEGA6.0 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.megasoftware.net/">https://www.megasoftware.net/</ext-link>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. The phylogenetic tree was verified using 1000 bootstrap replicates and was drawn by iTOL 5.6.1 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://itol.embl.de/">https://itol.embl.de/</ext-link>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Investigation of the short-term feeding behavior in <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> adults</title><p id="Par11">Newly emerged adults of <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> were placed in two glass bottles separately by their genders. The genders of adults were distinguished by individual size and abdominal morphological characteristics. Specifically, the female adult was larger than the male. The female adult has a ventral flat, and two abdominal segments at the end of its abdomen exposed outside the elytra. The abdomen of the male adult is covered with the elytra, and an oblong cavity that contains retractable external genitalia is in the 5th abdominal sternite. Ten newly emerged healthy <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> adults (five males and five females) were taken out from the bottles and starved for 12&#x000a0;h, then placed in a cylindrical box 5&#x000a0;cm in diameter and 4&#x000a0;cm in height. At the beginning of the light period, fresh leaves with stem were placed into the containers. The feeding duration of each beetle was observed and recorded for 2&#x000a0;h, and the area consumed by each adult was evaluated after 1 and 2&#x000a0;h using scanning pixel method. Specifically, we scanned a piece of square paper 10&#x000a0;cm in side length, the same leaf before and after insects feeding with a scanner for grayscale scanning. To calculate the gray part pixels, Photoshop CS6 was used. According to the paper size and the number of pixels, the area size of the insect feeding part was calculated as following: Consumed area&#x02009;=&#x02009;(pixel of leaf&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;pixel of leaf after consumed)&#x000b7;centimeter/pixel ratio. Centimeter/pixel ratio was calculated by Photoshop CS6.0 using a scanned picture contains a square paper 10&#x000a0;cm in side length. Each experiment was repeated three times.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Analyses of <italic>NES</italic> expression</title><sec id="Sec20"><title>Plant treatments</title><p id="Par12">Plants with similar levels of growth were selected and cultured in cylindrical glass tubes (3.5&#x000a0;cm diameter, 30&#x000a0;cm height) containing 50&#x000a0;ml water until the roots were grown. One of the fourth pair of leaves was covered with a gauze cage (3&#x000a0;cm diameter, 6&#x000a0;cm height). Six newly emerged <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> adults (three males and three females) were starved for 12&#x000a0;h before they were placed in the cage. Starting from the time adults touched the leaves, a 5-min insect contact treatment was recorded as long as no feeding or excretion occurred. After 1&#x000a0;h of feeding, <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> was removed, and the leaves were collected at 0, 15, 30, 60, 180, 360, and 720&#x000a0;min after insect feeding. For each time point, different individual plants were used. Mechanical wounding was used to distinguish the effect caused by <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> secretion or mechanical damage by <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> feeding. The area and duration of mechanical wounding affect the plants&#x02019; volatile release<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. Therefore, a 6-mm aperture puncher was used to mechanically injure the plant leaf margin for about 5&#x000a0;min until the area was similar to the insect feeding area, and the leaves were collected respectively from different individual plant at 0, 15, 30, 60, 180, 360, and 720&#x000a0;min after the mechanical wounding. At each point, a control was also performed. The leaves were frozen with liquid nitrogen for subsequent RNA extraction. Each treatment has five biological replicates, and each contained three leaves from different plant.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Sequence search and primer design</title><p id="Par13">The sequences of the housekeeping and <italic>NES</italic> genes were identified in the transcriptome data based on their similarity with the sequences of these genes in other species stored in the NR protein database. The actin gene <italic>ACT</italic>, the &#x003b1;-tubulin gene <italic>TUA</italic>, the &#x003b2;-tubulin gene <italic>TUB</italic>, and the gene encoding ubiquitin-binding enzyme, <italic>UBC</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>, were selected as the reference genes. Real-time quantitative PCR (qPCR) primers (Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>) were designed using Primer3 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://primer3.ut.ee/">https://primer3.ut.ee/</ext-link>) and synthesized by Sangon Biotech (Shanghai, China). To check the specificity of all primers, total RNA was reverse transcribed using the PrimeScript RT reagent kit with gDNA eraser (Takara Bio, Kusatsu, Japan). PCR was performed on the cDNA, and the PCR products were analyzed on a 1% agarose gel.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>qPCR and data analysis</title><p id="Par14">The total RNAs of the collected materials were extracted using the TRIzol method outlined above. The RNAs were quantified using a BioPhotometer Plus (Eppendorf, Hamburg, Germany), and their quality was verified using electrophoresis on an agarose gel. A 1-&#x003bc;g aliquot of total RNA was reverse transcribed at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 15&#x000a0;min with an oligo-dT primer using the PrimeScript RT reagent kit with gDNA eraser (Takara Bio, Kusatsu, Japan). The gDNA eraser was used to remove genomic DNA. Two independent reactions were performed for each RNA sample.</p><p id="Par15">The qPCR was performed using an Applied Biosystems 7500 Fast Real-Time Detection system (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA) with the SYBR Green Realtime PCR Master Mix (Toyobo, Osaka, Japan). Each reaction was carried out according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol in a 20-&#x000b5;l volume, which contained 2&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l tenfold diluted reverse-transcribed cDNA as a template and 500&#x000a0;nM of each primer. In all qPCR experiments, the transcript levels of three independent biological replicates were measured, with three technical replicates performed for each sample. A no-template control was included in each run for each gene. The qPCR reaction was performed using the following conditions: 95&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 2&#x000a0;min, followed by 40 cycles of 95&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 15&#x000a0;s, 55&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 15&#x000a0;s, and 72&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x000a0;s. Finally, a melting curve was generated by increasing the temperature from 65&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C to 95&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C to determine the specificity of the reactions.</p><p id="Par16">The stability of the four candidate reference genes <italic>UBC</italic>, <italic>ACT</italic>, <italic>TUA</italic>, and <italic>TUB</italic> were evaluated in the control group, <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> contact group, <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> feeding group, and mechanical wounding group using the reference screening software geNorm<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>, NormFinder<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>, and BestKeeper<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. The most stable reference gene, <italic>UBC</italic>, was selected as the reference for the qPCR experiment.</p><p id="Par17">The normalized expression values of the genes of interest were calculated using the 2<sup>&#x02013;&#x02206;&#x02206;<italic>C</italic>t</sup> method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. For calculating the basal gene expression in the control group, <italic>ApTPS19</italic> was used as the control gene and the basal expression of <italic>ApTPS19</italic> was normalized equal to 1. Other <italic>NES</italic> gene basal expression levels in the <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> control group leaves were calculated and compared as the folds of <italic>ApTPS19</italic> basal expression. The transcript levels of the <italic>NES</italic> genes in the control leaves and each of those subjected to contact, feeding by <italic>A. hygrophila</italic>, and mechanical wounding were transformed with logarithmic transformation to ensure normal distribution and compared using independent two-sample Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-tests performed in IBM SPSS Statistics 22.0 (International Business Machines Corporation, Amonk, New York, USA). One-way ANOVA was used to analyze the basal expression of each <italic>NES</italic> gene. Two-way ANOVA was used to analyze the expression of each <italic>NES</italic> gene in each treatment group, with treatment methods and post-treatment time as the influential factors. Two-way ANOVAs were also used to analyze the expression of the <italic>NES</italic> genes in the four treatment groups at the same time point. Multiple comparisons were performed using Tukey&#x02019;s post-hoc test. Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test was used to compare the expression levels of <italic>NES</italic> genes between two different treatments, after the homogeneity test.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec9"><title>RNA sequencing, assembly, and annotation</title><p id="Par18">To identify the terpene synthase genes involved in DMNT biosynthesis in <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic>, we performed transcriptome sequencing on the major tissues of this plant. A total of 9.91&#x000a0;Gb nucleotides and 40,984,113 raw reads were obtained from the <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> sequencing, and the percentage of Q30 bases reached 91.14%. The original data were deposited in the NCBI SRA library under the accession number SRR10537333. In total, 95.97% of the clean reads were assembled into 4,904,951 contigs, 182,318 transcripts, and 83,179 unigenes (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Summary of the RNA-seq data and the de novo assembly of the <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> unigenes.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Sequencing</th><th align="left"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Raw reads</td><td align="left">40,984,113</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Clean reads</td><td align="left">39,332,453</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Q30</td><td align="left">91.14%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">N</td><td align="left">0.01%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">N50</td><td align="left">1103</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Unigene number</td><td align="left">83,179</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Unigene length (nt)</td><td align="left">67,987,255</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mean length (nt)</td><td align="left">817.36</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Unigenes annotations based on homology with the NR protein database</td><td align="left">63,076</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Unigenes annotations based on homology with the KEGG database</td><td align="left">23,984</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Unigenes annotations based on homology with the COG database</td><td align="left">20,587</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Unigenes annotations based on homology with the GO database</td><td align="left">42,386</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par19">Homologs of the unigenes were identified by BLASTX; each publicly available protein database was searched using the transcriptome data, which resulted in the successful annotation of 63,536 (76.4%) of the unigenes. Among them, 63,076 genes were annotated based on their homology with sequences in the NR protein database, which accounted for 99.28% of the total number of annotations (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). 32.74% of <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> annotated sequences were aligned to beet (<italic>Beta vulgaris</italic> subsp. <italic>vulgaris</italic> L.) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Species with high levels of similarity in the NR database and GO classification statistics of <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> annotated unigenes. (<bold>A</bold>) Species with relatively high levels of similarity to the <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> unigenes in the NR protein database; (<bold>B</bold>) GO classification statistics of <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> annotated unigenes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_73130_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par20">We classified the predicted genes of <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> using the GO, COG, KOG, KEGG, and other protein databases. A total of 42,386 unigenes were divided into three major categories and 52 functional groups (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>B); 23,984 unigenes were mapped to 277 KEGG pathways, including the glycolytic, gluconeogenesis, and pentose phosphate pathways, among which the numbers of unigenes associated with the carbon cycle (ko01200), amino acid synthesis (ko01230), and ribosome (ko03010) pathways were 1172, 1057, and 1016, respectively (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>; Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>, <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Identification and analysis of the terpene synthase genes and <italic>NES</italic> genes in <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic></title><p id="Par21">In the <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> transcriptome data, a total of 34 terpene synthase genes were identified (Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). Their encoded protein sequences were compared with those of other species. The sequences of terpene synthase genes in <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> had the highest similarity to those of <italic>B. vulgaris</italic>.</p><p id="Par22">The phylogenetic tree showed that the 12 terpene synthase proteins were divided into five subfamilies: TPS-a, TPS-b, TPS-c, TPS-e, and TPS-g (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The TPS-a, TPS-b, and TPS-g subfamilies contained the terpene synthases specific to angiosperm species, which were isolated from the other TPS subfamilies. These angiosperm-specific proteins were class-III terpene synthases, which was in accordance with the species classification of <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic>. ApTPS7, ApTPS9, ApTPS17, ApTPS18, ApTPS21, and ApTPS22 were classified into the TPS-a subfamily; ApTPS5 and ApTPS6 were classified into the TPS-b subfamily; and ApTPS16 and ApTPS19 were classified into TPS-g family. The TPS-e subfamily largely comprised kaurene synthase, which had a function similar to the annotated function of ApTPS23. The TPS-c subfamily mainly contained the monofunctional diterpene synthase, copalyl diphosphate synthase (CPS). ApTPS25, which was annotated as CPS, was also grouped into the TPS-c subfamily.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Phylogenetic tree of <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> terpene synthase (TPSs) together with previously characterized plant TPSs.The tree was created in MEGA6 using the Maximum Likelihood method with JTT&#x02009;+&#x02009;G&#x02009;+&#x02009;I model, verified by bootstrap method, and drawn using iTOL (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://itol.embl.de/">https://itol.embl.de/</ext-link>). The outermost circle layer indicates the species name and associated clade of each protein. Proteins labeled in blue font are terpene synthase proteins obtained from the <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> transcriptome. The proteins and accession numbers used in the figure are shown in Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>. The number on the branches indicate the supporting bootstrap value of proteins on the branches (between 40 and 100%). The closer the bootstrap value is to 1, the higher confident the branch is. The proteins on the same branch mean they are the most related proteins, which may share high homology and have similar function.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_73130_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par23">In total, six <italic>NES</italic> genes were obtained: <italic>ApTPS10</italic>, <italic>ApTPS12</italic>, <italic>ApTPS14</italic>, <italic>ApTPS15</italic>, <italic>ApTPS16</italic>, and <italic>ApTPS19</italic> (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). <italic>ApTPS19</italic> was the longest of these genes (2161&#x000a0;bp), and was predicted to have an ORF of 1791&#x000a0;bp and to encode a protein of 596 aa in length. Four NES proteins were removed due to their shorter sequences, leaving ApTPS16 and ApTPS19, both of which were classified into the TPS-g subfamily. These proteins were annotated as NES, and shared about a 40% similarity with the other TPS enzymes in <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic>.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Nerolidol synthase genes in the <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> transcriptome.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Genes</th><th align="left">Length (bp)</th><th align="left">Identity (%)</th><th align="left">e-value</th><th align="left">Annotated function</th><th align="left">Gene accession</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>ApTPS10</italic></td><td char="." align="char">656</td><td char="." align="char">43</td><td align="left">3e<sup>&#x02212;10</sup></td><td align="left">(3S)-linalool/(E)-nerolidol /(E,E)-geranyl linalool synthase [<italic>Vitis vinifera</italic>]</td><td align="left">NP_001267990.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>ApTPS12</italic></td><td char="." align="char">415</td><td char="." align="char">42</td><td align="left">3e<sup>&#x02013;28</sup></td><td align="left">nerolidol synthase [<italic>Tripterygium wilfordii</italic>]</td><td align="left">AQA26342.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>ApTPS14</italic></td><td char="." align="char">336</td><td char="." align="char">50</td><td align="left">7e<sup>&#x02013;15</sup></td><td align="left">(3S,6E)-nerolidol synthase 1 [<italic>Beta vulgaris</italic> subsp. <italic>vulgaris</italic>]</td><td align="left">XP_010686920.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>ApTPS15</italic></td><td char="." align="char">830</td><td char="." align="char">61</td><td align="left">3e<sup>&#x02013;81</sup></td><td align="left">terpene synthase 3 [<italic>Populus trichocarpa</italic>]</td><td align="left">AEI52903.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>ApTPS16</italic></td><td char="." align="char">1495</td><td char="." align="char">46</td><td align="left">1e<sup>&#x02013;123</sup></td><td align="left">(3S)-linalool/(E)-nerolidol /(E,E)-geranyl linalool synthase [<italic>Vitis vinifera</italic>]</td><td align="left">ADR74213.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>ApTPS19</italic></td><td char="." align="char">2161</td><td char="." align="char">45</td><td align="left">3e<sup>&#x02013;147</sup></td><td align="left">(3S)-linalool/(E)-nerolidol /(E,E)-geranyl linalool synthase [<italic>Vitis vinifera</italic>]</td><td align="left">ADR74213.1</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Short-term feeding behavior of <italic>A. hygrophila</italic></title><p id="Par24">In the present study, we examined the behavior of <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> adults on the leaves of <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> within the first two hours. These actions include contacting, eating and resting. The time between the male and female adults touching the leaves and the initiation of feeding was 5.9&#x000a0;min and 6.2&#x000a0;min, respectively, after a 12-h starvation. The duration of a single feed was 19.6&#x000a0;min for males and 26.5&#x000a0;min for females. No statistical differences were observed between the feeding behaviors of male and female adults (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The interval between the first and second feeding periods varied from 1 to 90&#x000a0;min, during which the adults usually remained inactive. We, therefore, selected a 5-min period after placing the adults into the cage for use as the contact treatment in future experiments.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Early feeding behaviors of <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> adults.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Gender</th><th align="left">Time between touch and feeding (min)</th><th align="left">Duration of single feeding behavior (min)</th><th align="left">Leaf area consumed by a single adult within 1&#x000a0;h (mm<sup>2</sup>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Female</td><td char="." align="char">6.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.27</td><td char="." align="char">26.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.63</td><td char="." align="char">618.91&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;59.67*</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Male</td><td char="." align="char">5.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.35</td><td char="." align="char">19.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.17</td><td char="." align="char">433.01&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;28.44</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The data in the table are presented as means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE. Asterisks (*) indicate a statistical difference between male and female adults, determined using a Student's <italic>t</italic> test (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par25">In addition, the leaf areas consumed by one adult in 1&#x000a0;h and the areas consumed by different numbers of adults in 1&#x000a0;h were also evaluated (Tables <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>). The feeding of male and female adults resulted in different leaf areas consumed; therefore, the use of six adults (three males and three females) was chosen as the insect feeding group for the subsequent 1-h feeding experiment. The leaf area consumed was about 20% of the entire leaf using this treatment method, which provided a basis for the mechanical wounding treatment of the <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> leaves.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Selection of reference genes in leaves under <italic>A. hydrophila</italic> contact, feeding, or mechanical wounding</title><p id="Par26">To ensure the accuracy of the quantitative analysis of <italic>NES</italic> expression under the different treatment conditions, the expression stabilities of the commonly used reference genes <italic>ACT</italic>, <italic>TUA</italic>, <italic>TUB</italic>, and <italic>UBC</italic> were screened. The results showed that the <italic>C</italic>t values of the four candidate reference genes were 19&#x02013;26 (Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>), with the lowest <italic>C</italic>t values observed for <italic>UBC</italic> (19&#x02013;22) and the highest <italic>C</italic>t values observed for <italic>TUB</italic> (23&#x02013;26). The expression levels of each candidate reference gene were different when they were analyzed using GeNorm, NormFinder, and BestKeeper.</p><p id="Par27">The GeNorm and NormFinder software analysis revealed that the M values of the four reference genes were all less than 1.5, and therefore these genes were considered to be relatively stable when expressed. Among them, <italic>UBC</italic> had the smallest M value and the best expression stability, whereas <italic>TUA</italic> had the largest M value and a relatively poorer stability. The BestKeeper software analysis revealed that the SD values of the <italic>C</italic>t values for the four reference genes were &#x0003c;&#x02009;1, indicating relatively stable gene expressions. Among them, <italic>UBC</italic> had the smallest SD value and the best expression stability, whereas <italic>TUA</italic> had the largest SD value and the worst stability (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Based on these results, the expression stabilities of the four candidate reference genes were ranked as follows: <italic>UBC</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;<italic>TUB</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;<italic>ACT</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;<italic>TUA</italic>. We therefore used <italic>UBC</italic> as the reference gene to investigate the expression of the <italic>NES</italic> genes in the leaves of <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> under the different damage treatments.<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Stable values of data analyses performed using GeNorm, NormFinder, and BestKeeper.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="2">GeNorm</th><th align="left" colspan="2">NormFinder</th><th align="left" colspan="3">BestKeeper</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Gene name</th><th align="left">M</th><th align="left">Gene name</th><th align="left">M</th><th align="left">Gene name</th><th align="left">SD</th><th align="left">CV</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>UBC</italic></td><td align="left">0.776</td><td align="left"><italic>UBC</italic></td><td align="left">0.319</td><td align="left"><italic>UBC</italic></td><td align="left">0.53</td><td align="left">2.60</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>TUB</italic></td><td align="left">0.797</td><td align="left"><italic>TUB</italic></td><td align="left">0.319</td><td align="left"><italic>TUB</italic></td><td align="left">0.59</td><td align="left">2.38</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>ACT</italic></td><td align="left">0.843</td><td align="left"><italic>ACT</italic></td><td align="left">0.431</td><td align="left"><italic>ACT</italic></td><td align="left">0.85</td><td align="left">3.92</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>TUA</italic></td><td align="left">0.968</td><td align="left"><italic>TUA</italic></td><td align="left">0.573</td><td align="left"><italic>TUA</italic></td><td align="left">0.86</td><td align="left">3.67</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>M dictates the stability index: the larger the M value, the worse the expression stability of the gene. SD is standard deviation of the Ct value. CV is coefficient of variation of the <italic>C</italic>t value. If SD&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;1, the gene was considered to be relatively stable; therefore, the smaller the standard deviation and coefficient of variation, the more stable the gene expression.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Basal expression of various <italic>NES</italic> genes in healthy leaves</title><p id="Par28">We investigated the basal expression level of the <italic>NES</italic> genes in the healthy leaves because of the large amount of DMNT from healthy <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> plants<italic>.</italic> The results revealed statistical differences in the basal expression of the six <italic>NES</italic> genes in the leaves of the control plants (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). Among them, <italic>ApTPS19</italic> had the lowest basal expression, while <italic>ApTPS15</italic> had the highest basal expression, which was 2058.9 times higher than that of <italic>ApTPS19</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Relative transcription levels of the six nerolidol synthase genes in the plant of <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> under undamaged control conditions. <italic>UBC</italic> was used as the reference gene to calculate the gene transcript level. The relative expression level of each <italic>NES</italic> is shown in fold relative to that of <italic>ApTPS19</italic> which had the lowest transcription level that was taken as &#x0201c;1&#x0201d;. The values are means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD of three biological replications. Different letters indicate statistical differences between the genes, revealed using a one-way ANOVA and a Tukey&#x02019;s post-hoc test (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_73130_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Induction of <italic>NES</italic> genes in <italic>A. philoxeroides </italic>prior to feeding by <italic>A. hygrophila</italic></title><p id="Par29">The early feeding behavior of <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> adults was investigated, revealing that the time between the flea beetles touching the leaves and the initiation of feeding was typically longer than 5&#x000a0;min. The changes in <italic>NES</italic> gene expression were evaluated in the leaves touched by <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> for 5&#x000a0;min. The expression levels of <italic>ApTPS10</italic>, <italic>ApTPS12</italic>, <italic>ApTPS16</italic>, and <italic>ApTPS19</italic> increased significantly in <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> leaves touched by <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), with the expression of <italic>ApTPS16</italic> being 6.27 times higher than that of the control group. By contrast, <italic>ApTPS15</italic> expression decreased significantly in the leaves touched by <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), whereas <italic>ApTPS14</italic> expression was not statistically different between the control and <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> contact group (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Nerolidol synthase gene expression levels in the control group and the <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> contact group of <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> plants. <italic>UBC</italic> was selected as the reference gene. The values are means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD (normalized that the expression level in the control group equal to 1) of three biological replications. Asterisks indicate statistical differences between the treatments (*<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05; **<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01; Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_73130_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title><italic>A. hygrophila</italic> feeding strongly induces <italic>NES</italic> gene expression in <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic></title><p id="Par30">The changes in the <italic>NES</italic> gene expression upon <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> feeding were also analyzed in a time series. All of the six <italic>NES</italic> genes in the leaves were significantly up-regulated immediately after 1&#x000a0;h insect-damaged (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Nerolidol synthase gene expression levels in the control group, <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> feeding group, mechanical wounding group of <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> plants. In the <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> feeding group, the <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> leaves were sampled at the indicated time points following a 1-h feeding experiment. In the mechanical wounding group, the <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> leaves were sampled at the indicated time points following their mechanical damage. The values are means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD (normalized that the expression level in the control group equal to 1) of three biological replications. Different letters indicate statistical differences between different time treatments in control group, as determined using a one-way ANOVA and a Tukey&#x02019;s post-hoc test (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). Different letters with single quotation mark indicated statistical differences between different time treatments after insect feeding, as determined using a one-way ANOVA and a Tukey&#x02019;s post-hoc test (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). Different letters with double quotation marks indicate statistical differences between different time treatments after mechanical wounding, as determined using a one-way ANOVA and a Tukey&#x02019;s post-hoc test (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). Asterisks indicate statistical differences between every two treatments in the same time treatment (*<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05; **<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01; Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_73130_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p><p id="Par31"><italic>ApTPS14</italic> expression showed the greatest up-regulation, reaching a level 42.7 times higher than that of the control plants (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). The expression of <italic>ApTPS19</italic> showed the smallest up-regulation by insect feeding, reaching a level only 7.3 times higher than that of the control plants (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). The four other <italic>NES</italic> genes showed several-fold up-regulation of their expression following <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> feeding, and were significantly different from the control plants (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). Fifteen minutes after feeding ended, the expression of the six <italic>NES</italic> genes remained statistically higher than in the control plants (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), but as time progressed their expression levels gradually decreased, returning to their normal levels within 15 to 30&#x000a0;min. <italic>ApTPS12</italic>, <italic>ApTPS14</italic>, <italic>ApTPS15</italic>, and <italic>ApTPS16</italic> also showed a small peak in expression 1&#x000a0;h after feeding ended (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Mechanical wounding induces delayed and low levels of <italic>NES</italic> gene expression</title><p id="Par32">Upon mechanical wounding, all of six <italic>NES</italic> gene expression showed no statistical difference from that in the leaves of the control group (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>).</p><p id="Par33">After the mechanical wounding, the expression levels of the differentially expressed <italic>NES</italic> genes first increased to a peak at around 30&#x02013;60&#x000a0;min, then gradually decreased to a level similar to that of the control plants after 1&#x02013;3&#x000a0;h. After 30&#x000a0;min, <italic>ApTPS10</italic>, <italic>ApTPS12</italic>, <italic>ApTPS15</italic>, and <italic>ApTPS16</italic> were significantly differentially expressed in the leaves subjected to mechanical wounding in comparison with the control plants (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). After 1&#x000a0;h, <italic>ApTPS14</italic> expression remained significantly different in the two groups (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). However, at several time points, <italic>ApTPS19</italic> expression was similar between the two groups (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par34">Here, we showed that the presence of <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> affects <italic>NES</italic> gene expression in <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> even before feeding and short-term feeding (1&#x000a0;h), and by <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> strongly and rapidly induces the up-regulation of the <italic>NES</italic> genes. This up-regulation of <italic>NES</italic> expression was likely the main reason why chewed leaves released more DMNT, in turn attracting more <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> to feed on these plants.</p><p id="Par35">Initially, second-generation transcriptome sequencing was performed on the roots, stems, leaves, and flowers of <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> to provide genetic and protein data that were lacking for this species. Compared with the previously reported transcriptomes of <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> roots<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup> and <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> individuals growing in ponds and uplands<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>, our sequencing provided novel genetic data for the flowers, which are an important organ for the release of volatile compounds<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. Also, the annotation of the <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> genes and proteins was improved. Along with the full-length transcriptome sequencing of <italic>A. hygrophila</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>, we provided valuable data for the comprehensive study of the molecular mechanisms underlying the specificity between <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> and <italic>A. hygrophila</italic>. Few studies have reported sequencing data for other species in the <italic>Alternanthera</italic> genus; the genetic and protein data obtained from sequencing other related species in this family are limited to several edible and medicinal crops, such as <italic>Amaranthus caudatus</italic> L.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>, <italic>Amaranthus hypochondriacus</italic> L.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>, and <italic>Achyranthes bidentata</italic> Blume<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. The transcriptome data of <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> has therefore enriched the genetic data available for the Amaranthaceae, especially the <italic>Alternanthera</italic> genus. It also enriched the genetic data available for invasive plants, providing powerful genetic support for exploring their invasive properties, and their interactions with herbivorous insects.</p><p id="Par36">In total, 34 <italic>TPS</italic> genes were predicted in the <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> transcriptome (Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). In plants with published genomes, the number of <italic>TPS</italic> genes ranges from 19 to 152<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>; for example, there are 40 <italic>TPS</italic> genes in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, of which 32 have known or predicted functions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. Based on the materials and methods used for this transcriptome sequencing, we speculate that the <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> genome may contain more <italic>TPS</italic> genes, which should be further explored using genome sequencing. The discovery of these <italic>TPS</italic> genes will enhance our understanding of the <italic>TPS</italic> genes in the Amaranthaceae as a whole.</p><p id="Par37">Feeding by the specialist insect <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> affects <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic>, causing the release of DMNT<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. The <italic>NES</italic> genes, which belong to TPS-g subfamily, are related to DMNT biosynthesis. Six <italic>NES</italic> genes were screened in this transcriptome. Following the contact or feeding <italic>by A. hygrophila</italic>, the expression pattern of <italic>A. philoxeroides NES</italic> genes was further studied. The <italic>NES</italic> genes were up-regulated before feeding by <italic>A. hygrophila</italic>. In the 5&#x000a0;min before feeding, when adults merely touched the leaves of <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic>, the initial contact caused significant up-regulation of most of the <italic>NES</italic> genes. After injury, plants usually activated a transcription cascade, leading to the expression of genes involved in the release of volatile organic compounds; however, it generally takes a few hours to a day (24&#x000a0;h) for the compounds to be released<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>. Compared with the <italic>Lilium</italic> &#x02018;Siberia&#x02019; terpene synthase gene <italic>LoTPS1</italic>, which is activated in response to wounding, <italic>NES</italic> genes in <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> responded to damage much faster<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par38">The rapid up-regulation of these genes following contact with <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> may have two explanations. In the first case, when the beetle touches the leaf surface, it might cause slight mechanical damage to the leaf, which in turn up-regulates <italic>NES</italic> expression. The tarsus of an insect typically has claws, which can cause fine scratches on leaf blades and break their trichomes as the insect crawls along the leaf surface. This has been confirmed in tobacco (<italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic> L.), soybean (<italic>Glycine max</italic> (L.) Merr.)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>, and tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> L.)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup>. Also, the minor mechanical damage causes the release of plant terpenoid volatiles, which has been documented in a touch study of potato (<italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic> L.)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>. However, the expression level of <italic>NES</italic> in the <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> contact group was significantly higher than that in the mechanical wounding group. The other possibility is the chemical substances secreted by insects may generate a chemical &#x0201c;footprint&#x0201d; on the leaf and up-regulate the expression of the <italic>NES</italic> genes. In other species, insect chemical footprints have been shown to mediate the transmission of the insect&#x02019;s intraspecific and interspecific information. For example, some pollinators has been showed to transmit flower information to the same species by chemical &#x0201c;footprint&#x0201d;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>, some parasitoids have located host insects by recognition of the chemical traces that host insects deposited after crawling<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup>. It is not yet clear whether these secretions can trigger plant responses<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup>, a hypothesis that will need to be tested in future studies.</p><p id="Par39">When <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> was in contact with the plant for prolonged periods of time, the beetles began to feed. Short-term feeding (1&#x000a0;h) by <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> caused rapid and intense up-regulation of <italic>NES</italic> genes, which is consistent with the previous study showing release of large amounts of DMNT after feeding by <italic>A. hygrophila</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. Plants responded quickly to insects&#x02019; damage, including the rapid biosynthesis of monoterpenes and sesquiterpenes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup>. For example, the feeding behavior of insect herbivores such as <italic>Spodoptera littoralis</italic> (Boisduval)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup>, <italic>Lymantria dispar</italic> L.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup>, and <italic>Hylobius abietis</italic> (L.)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref></sup> also induced the expression of plant terpene synthase genes and the release of terpene volatiles. For insects with chewing mouthparts, such as <italic>A. hygrophila</italic>, the feeding behavior not only causes mechanical wounding to the leaves but also deposes oral secretions, such as saliva, in the leaf incisions. Both of these can induce plant volatile production through special transcriptional pathways<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup>. In this study, we used a puncher simulating similar feeding areas to rule out the effect of mechanical wounding on gene expression changes. However, <italic>NES</italic> expression in the <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> feeding group was still significantly greater than that in the mechanical wounding group. In our previously work, we measured the DMNT released from <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> following mechanical wounding and feeding by <italic>A. hygrophila</italic>. The DMNT released due to insect feeding was 240 units ng&#x000b7;h<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x000b7;10&#x000a0;g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x000b7;FW<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; by contrast, the DMNT release by mechanical wounding was only 13 units ng&#x000b7;h<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x000b7;10&#x000a0;g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x000b7;FW<sup>&#x02212;17</sup>. The magnitudes of <italic>NES</italic> expression caused by insect feeding and mechanical wounding in this study reflected the magnitudes of DMNT in response to these two treatments, respectively<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. In Li<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>, the DMNT was collected over a 12&#x000a0;h period which covered the time frame used in this study. If there would be any DMNT released by mechanical wounding, it would be very minimal compared to the large quantity of DMNT caused by insect feeding. This suggests that the chemicals secreted by <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> might trigger the up-regulation of <italic>NES</italic>, which leads to the release of a large amount of DMNT after <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> feeding<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par40">In damaged <italic>A. philoxeroide</italic>s leaves, high expression of <italic>NES</italic> genes causes a large amount of DMNT to be released, which attracts more specialist <italic>A. hygrophila</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. The release of plant volatiles has a significant attraction to insects (herbivore and their parasitoids) and may provide signals for conspecifics to find host plants or increase aggregation. For example, the root-feeding larvae of a specialized insect <italic>Bikasha collaris</italic> (Baly) can induce its host plant <italic>Triadica sebifera</italic> (L.) Small to produce volatiles, attracting aboveground conspecific adults<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref></sup>. Also, <italic>Spodoptera littoralis</italic> caterpillars could be attracted by volatiles emitted by maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic>) damaged by conspecific larvae, and thereby find a less suitable but easily detectable host plant<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref></sup>. We speculated that the specialist <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> might use the chemicals it secretes to affect the release of volatiles from the host plants and facilitate population development by making it easier for conspecifics to locate their host plants <italic>A. phyloxeroides</italic>. These questions will need to be explored in future research.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par41">In this study, we identified six <italic>NES</italic> genes from the <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> transcriptome. When the leaves were contact by <italic>A. hygrophila</italic>, <italic>NES</italic> gene expression increased rapidly, and was strongly up-regulated after <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> feeding. Our results suggested that the rapid and strong increase of <italic>NES</italic> transcript levels promotes the large-scale release of DMNT. The released DMNT helps conspecific species of <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> locate host plants. Our results also suggested that chemicals secreted by <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> could be responsible for the rapid and strong increase of <italic>NES</italic> transcript levels. Our results represent an initial explanation of the molecular mechanisms underlying the interaction between <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> and its natural enemy <italic>A. hygrophila</italic> and provide a molecular basis for understanding the relationships between obligate herbivorous insects and their host plants.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><sec id="Sec19"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2020_73130_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary information 1.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="41598_2020_73130_MOESM2_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p>Supplementary information 2.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="41598_2020_73130_MOESM3_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p>Supplementary information 3.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="41598_2020_73130_MOESM4_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p>Supplementary information 4.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p>is available for this paper at 10.1038/s41598-020-73130-z.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No.31570436), Applied Basic Research Program of Shanxi Province (No. 201901D211354), and Shanxi Province Graduate Education Innovation Project (No. 2019BY072). We are very grateful to Professor Thomas James Ridsdill-Smith (University of Western Australia, Perth) for his suggestion to consider the effects of insect-touch. We thank Biomarker Technologies for help in sequencing and analyzing the transcriptome data.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>Y.W. designed the experiments, performed the experiments, analyzed the data, prepared figures and/or tables, authored or reviewed drafts of the paper, and approved the final draft. Y.L. analyzed the data, authored or reviewed drafts of the paper, and approved the final draft. X.W., D.J. and J.H. designed the experiments, authored or reviewed drafts of the paper, and approved the final draft. L.L.G. directed the design of the experiments, helped the outline of this manuscript and co-write the draft of this paper, and approved the final draft. R.M. is the principal investigator of this grant, directed and supervised this research work, co-authored and reviewed the drafts of the paper, and approved the final draft.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par42">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Julien</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Skarratt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Maywald</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potential geographical distribution of Alligator Weed and its biological control by <italic>Agasicles hygrophila</italic></article-title><source>J.Aquat. Plant Manag.</source><year>1995</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>60</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Coulson, J. R. <italic>Biological Control of Alligatorweed, 1959&#x02013;s1972: A Review and Evaluation</italic>. (Department of Agriculture, Agricultural Research Service, 1977).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Vogt, G. B., Quimby, P. C. &#x00026; Kay, S. H. <italic>Effects of Weather on the Biological Control of Alligator Weed in the Lower Mississippi Valley Region, 1973&#x02013;83</italic>. (Technical bulletin/United States Department of Agriculture, USA, 1992).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Van Driesche, R., Blossey, B., Hoddle, M., Lyon, S. &#x00026; Reardon, R. <italic>Biological Control of iInvasive Plants in the Eastern United States</italic>. (Forest Health Technology Enterprise Team, USDA Forest Service, 2002).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Non-target plant testing of the flea beetle <italic>Agasicles hygrophila</italic>, a biological control agent for <italic>Alternanthera philoxeroides</italic> (alligatorweed) in China</article-title><source>J.Aquat. Plant Manag.</source><year>2015</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>88</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09583157.2012.708019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The fitness of <italic>Agasicles hygrophila</italic> on several non-target plant species</article-title><source>Acta Phytophyl. Sin.</source><year>2013</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>350</fpage><lpage>354</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Manipulating two olfactory cues causes a biological control beetle to shift to non-target plant species</article-title><source>J. Ecol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>1534</fpage><lpage>1546</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1365-2745.12778</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boland</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Donath</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000e4;bler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Are acyclic C11 and C16 homoterpenes plant volatiles indicating herbivory?</article-title><source>Naturwissenschaften</source><year>1992</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>368</fpage><lpage>371</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01140183</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trapping, investigation and reconstitution of fower scents. <italic>Perfumes: Art</italic></article-title><source>Sci.Technol.</source><year>1994</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-94-011-3826-0_7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turlings</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tumlinson</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exploitation of herbivore-induced plant odors by host-seeking parasitic wasps</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1990</year><volume>250</volume><fpage>1251</fpage><lpage>1253</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.250.4985.1251</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17829213?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17829213</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dicke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabelis</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Takabayashi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Posthumus</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant strategies of manipulating predatorprey interactions through allelochemicals: Prospects for application in pest control</article-title><source>J. Chem. Ecol.</source><year>1990</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>3091</fpage><lpage>3118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00979614</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24263298?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24263298</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boland</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Hopke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Donath</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>N&#x000fc;ske</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bublitz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Jasmonic acid and coronatin induce odor production in plants</article-title><source>Angew. Chem. Int. Ed.</source><year>1995</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>1600</fpage><lpage>1602</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/anie.199516001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bouwmeester</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Verstappen</surname><given-names>FWA</given-names></name><name><surname>Posthumus</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dicke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spider mite-induced (3S)-(E)-nerolidol synthase activity in cucumber and lima bean. The first dedicated step in acyclic C11-homoterpene biosynthesis</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>1999</year><volume>121</volume><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.121.1.173</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10482672?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10482672</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hopke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Donath</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Blechert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Boland</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Herbivore-induced volatiles: the emission of acyclic homoterpenes from leaves of <italic>Phaseolus lunatus</italic> and <italic>Zea mays</italic> can be triggered by a beta-glucosidase and jasmonic acid</article-title><source>FEBS Lett.</source><year>1994</year><volume>352</volume><fpage>146</fpage><lpage>150</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0014-5793(94)00948-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7925964?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7925964</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tholl</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sohrabi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Huh</surname><given-names>J-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The biochemistry of homoterpenes&#x02013;common constituents of floral and herbivore-induced plant volatile bouquets</article-title><source>Phytochemistry</source><year>2011</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>1635</fpage><lpage>1646</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2011.01.019</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21334702?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21334702</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Tholl</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohlmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pichersky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The family of terpene synthases in plants: A mid-size family of genes for specialized metabolism that is highly diversified throughout the kingdom</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2011</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>212</fpage><lpage>229</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2011.04520.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21443633?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21443633</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aharoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Terpenoid metabolism in wild-type and transgenic Arabidopsis plants</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2003</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>2866</fpage><lpage>2884</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.016253</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14630967?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14630967</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kappers</surname><given-names>IF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic engineering of terpenoid metabolism attracts bodyguards to Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2005</year><volume>309</volume><fpage>2070</fpage><lpage>2072</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1116232</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16179482?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16179482</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoopen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Thoen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiegers</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Jongsma</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chrysanthemum expressing a linalool synthase gene 'smells good', but 'tastes bad' to western flower thrips</article-title><source>Plant Biotechnol. J.</source><year>2013</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>875</fpage><lpage>882</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pbi.12080</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23745691?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23745691</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Expression of lima bean terpene synthases in rice enhances recruitment of a beneficial enemy of a major rice pest</article-title><source>Plant Cell Environ.</source><year>2018</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>120</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pce.12959</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28370092?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28370092</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loughrin</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Manukian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Heath</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Turlings</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tumlinson</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diurnal cycle of emission of induced volatile terpenoids by herbivore-injured cotton plant</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1994</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>11836</fpage><lpage>11840</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.91.25.11836</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11607499?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11607499</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mith&#x000f6;fer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wanner</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Boland</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of feeding Spodoptera littoralis on lima bean leaves. II. Continuous mechanical wounding resembling insect feeding is sufficient to elicit herbivory-related volatile emission</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>137</volume><fpage>1160</fpage><lpage>1168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.104.054460</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15728342?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15728342</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turlings</surname><given-names>TCJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Erb</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tritrophic interactions mediated by herbivore-induced plant volatiles: mechanisms, ecological relevance, and application potential</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Entomol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>433</fpage><lpage>452</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-ento-020117-043507</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29324043?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29324043</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grabherr</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Full-length transcriptome assembly from RNA-Seq data without a reference genome</article-title><source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>644</fpage><lpage>652</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.1883</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 3571712?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21572440</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Apweiler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>UniProt: The Universal Protein knowledgebase</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>D115</fpage><lpage>D119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkh131</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14681372?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14681372</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashburner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gene Ontology: Tool for the unification of biology</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><year>2000</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/75556</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10802651?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10802651</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tatusov</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Galperin</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Natale</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Koonin</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The COG database: A tool for genome-scale analysis of protein functions and evolution</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2000</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/28.1.33</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10592175?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10592175</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kanehisa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawashima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Okuno</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hattori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The KEGG resource for deciphering the genome</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>D277</fpage><lpage>D280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkh063</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14681412?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14681412</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finn</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pfam: The protein families database</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2013</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>D222</fpage><lpage>D230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkt1223</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24288371?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24288371</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gapped BLAST and PSI-BLAST: A new generation of protein database search programs</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>1997</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>3389</fpage><lpage>3402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/25.17.3389</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9254694?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9254694</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Filipski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MEGA6: Molecular evolutionary genetics analysis version 6.0</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>2725</fpage><lpage>2729</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/mst197</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24132122?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24132122</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Letunic</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bork</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interactive tree of life (iTOL) v3: An online tool for the display and annotation of phylogenetic and other trees</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2016</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>W242</fpage><lpage>W245</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkw290</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27095192?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27095192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene expression reaction norms unravel the molecular and cellular processes underpinning the plastic phenotypes of <italic>Alternanthera Philoxeroides</italic> in contrasting hydrological conditions</article-title><source>Front. Plant Sci.</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>991</fpage><lpage>991</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2015.00991</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26617628?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26617628</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vandesompele</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Accurate normalization of real-time quantitative RT-PCR data by geometric averaging of multiple internal control genes</article-title><source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2002</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2002-3-7-research0034</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12184808?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12184808</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x000d8;rntoft</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Normalization of real-time quantitative reverse transcription-PCR data: A model-based variance estimation approach to identify genes suited for normalization, applied to bladder and colon cancer data sets</article-title><source>Cancer Res.</source><year>2004</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>5245</fpage><lpage>5250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-04-0496</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15289330?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15289330</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pfaffl</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Tichopad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Prgomet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Neuvians</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determination of stable housekeeping genes, differentially regulated target genes and sample integrity: BestKeeper&#x02013;Excel-based tool using pair-wise correlations</article-title><source>Biotechnol. Lett.</source><year>2004</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>509</fpage><lpage>515</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/b:bile.0000019559.84305.47</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15127793?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15127793</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2(-Delta Delta C(T)) Method</article-title><source>Methods</source><year>2001</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>402</fpage><lpage>408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/meth.2001.1262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846609</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>novo characterization of the alligator weed (<italic>Alternanthera philoxeroides</italic>) transcriptome illuminates gene expression under potassium deprivation</article-title><source>J. Genet.</source><year>2015</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12041-015-0493-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25846881?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25846881</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dudareva</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Negre</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagegowda</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Orlova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant volatiles: Recent advances and future perspectives</article-title><source>Crit. Rev. Plant Sci.</source><year>2006</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>417</fpage><lpage>440</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07352680600899973</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sohrabi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>In planta variation of volatile biosynthesis: An alternative biosynthetic route to the formation of the pathogen-induced volatile homoterpene DMNT via triterpene degradation in Arabidopsis roots</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2015</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>874</fpage><lpage>890</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.114.132209</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25724638?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25724638</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>SMRT sequencing of full-length transcriptome of flea beetle <italic>Agasicles hygrophila</italic> (Selman and Vogt)</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2018</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>2197</fpage><lpage>2197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-20181-y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29396453?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29396453</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stetter</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of phylogenetic relationships and genome size evolution of the Amaranthus genus using GBS indicates the ancestors of an ancient crop</article-title><source>Mol. Phylogenet. Evol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>80</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ympev.2016.12.029</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28057554?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28057554</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>D&#x000e9;lano-Frier</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptomic analysis of grain amaranth (Amaranthus hypochondriacus) using 454 pyrosequencing: Comparison with <italic>A. tuberculatus</italic>, expression profiling in stems and in response to biotic and abiotic stress</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2011</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>363</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-12-363</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21752295?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21752295</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sunil</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The draft genome and transcriptome of <italic>Amaranthus hypochondriacus</italic>: A C4 dicot producing high-lysine edible pseudo-cereal</article-title><source>DNA Res.</source><year>2014</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>585</fpage><lpage>602</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/dnares/dsu021</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25071079?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25071079</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sunil</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hariharan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Dixit</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Choudhary</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential genomic arrangements in Caryophyllales through deep transcriptome sequencing of <italic>A. hypochondriacus</italic></article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2017</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>e0180528</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0180528</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28786999?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28786999</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The root transcriptome of <italic>Achyranthes bidentata</italic> and the identification of the genes involved in the replanting benefit</article-title><source>Plant Cell Rep.</source><year>2018</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>611</fpage><lpage>625</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00299-018-2255-z</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29344683?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29344683</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aubourg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lecharny</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohlmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomic analysis of the terpenoid synthase (AtTPS) gene family of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>Mol. Genet. Genomics</source><year>2002</year><volume>267</volume><fpage>730</fpage><lpage>745</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00438-002-0709-y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12207221?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12207221</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ke</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional characterization and expression analysis of two terpene synthases involved in floral scent formation in Lilium 'Siberia'</article-title><source>Planta</source><year>2019</year><volume>249</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00425-018-3006-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30218384?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30218384</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erb</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Reymond</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular interactions between plants and insect herbivores</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Plant Biol.</source><year>2019</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>527</fpage><lpage>557</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-arplant-050718-095910</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30786233?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30786233</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X-Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The terpene synthase gene family in <italic>Gossypium hirsutum</italic> harbors a linalool synthase GhTPS12 implicated in direct defence responses against herbivores</article-title><source>Plant Cell Environ.</source><year>2018</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>261</fpage><lpage>274</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pce.13088</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29044662?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29044662</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rauwane</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Odeny</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Rey</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rees</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The early transcriptome response of cassava (<italic>Manihot esculenta</italic> Crantz) to mealybug (<italic>Phenacoccus manihoti</italic>) feeding</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2018</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>e0202541</fpage><lpage>e0202541</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0202541</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30133510?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30133510</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamiru</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A maize landrace that emits defense volatiles in response to herbivore eggs possesses a strongly inducible terpene synthase gene</article-title><source>Ecol. Evol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>2835</fpage><lpage>2845</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ece3.2893</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28428873?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28428873</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bown</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>MacGregor</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insect footsteps on leaves stimulate the accumulation of 4-aminobutyrate and can be visualized through increased chlorophyll fluorescence and superoxide production</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2002</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>1430</fpage><lpage>1434</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.006114</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12177456?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12177456</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>MacGregor</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Nijsse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bown</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Footsteps from insect larvae damage leaf surfaces and initiate rapid responses</article-title><source>Eur. J. Plant Pathol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>441</fpage><lpage>447</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/B:EJPP.0000021072.89968.de</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peiffer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tooker</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Luthe</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Felton</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plants on early alert: Glandular trichomes as sensors for insect herbivores</article-title><source>New Phytol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>184</volume><fpage>644</fpage><lpage>656</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2009.03002.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19703113?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19703113</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Markovic</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Nikolic</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Glinwood</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Seisenbaeva</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ninkovic</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant responses to brief touching: A mechanism for early neighbour detection?</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>e0165742</fpage><lpage>e0165742</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0165742</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27828995?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27828995</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eltz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tracing pollinator footprints on natural flowers</article-title><source>J. Chem. Ecol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>907</fpage><lpage>915</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10886-006-9055-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16739012?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16739012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Witjes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Witsch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Eltz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reconstructing the pollinator community and predicting seed set from hydrocarbon footprints on flowers</article-title><source>Oecologia</source><year>2011</year><volume>166</volume><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>174</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00442-010-1824-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21069386?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21069386</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rost&#x000e1;s</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>W&#x000f6;lfling</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Caterpillar footprints as host location kairomones for <italic>Cotesia marginiventris</italic>: persistence and chemical nature</article-title><source>J. Chem. Ecol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10886-009-9590-z</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19153795?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19153795</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hilker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Meiners</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How do plants "notice" attack by herbivorous arthropods?</article-title><source>Biol. Rev. Camb. Philos. Soc.</source><year>2010</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-185X.2009.00100.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19961475?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19961475</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holopainen</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple functions of inducible plant volatiles</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci.</source><year>2004</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>529</fpage><lpage>533</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2004.09.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15501177?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15501177</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Degenhardt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gershenzon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Demonstration and characterization of (E)-nerolidol synthase from maize: A herbivore-inducible terpene synthase participating in (3E)-4,8-dimethyl-1,3,7-nonatriene biosynthesis</article-title><source>Planta</source><year>2000</year><volume>210</volume><fpage>815</fpage><lpage>822</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004250050684</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10805454?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10805454</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Irmisch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gershenzon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000f6;llner</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Terpene synthases and their contribution to herbivore-induced volatile emission in western balsam poplar (<italic>Populus trichocarpa</italic>)</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>270</fpage><lpage>270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-014-0270-y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25303804?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25303804</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kovalchuk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Activation of defence pathways in Scots pine bark after feeding by pine weevil (<italic>Hylobius abietis</italic>)</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2015</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>352</fpage><lpage>352</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-015-1546-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25943104?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25943104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Felton</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Tumlinson</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant-insect dialogs: Complex interactions at the plant-insect interface</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Plant Biol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>457</fpage><lpage>463</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2008.07.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18657469?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18657469</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sun, X.&#x000a0;<italic>et al.</italic>&#x000a0;Root feeding larvae increase their performance by inducing leaf volatiles that attract aboveground conspecific adults.&#x000a0;<italic>J.Ecol.</italic>&#x000a0;<bold>107</bold>, 2713&#x02013;2723. 10.1111/1365-2745.13196 (2019).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>von M&#x000e9;rey</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Veyrat</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x02019;ssAlessandro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Turlings</surname><given-names>TCJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Herbivore-induced maize leaf volatiles affect attraction and feeding behavior of <italic>Spodoptera littoralis</italic> caterpillars</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>209</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2013.00209</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23825475?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23825475</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>