<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Genome Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Genome Biol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Genome Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1474-7596</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1474-760X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7419205</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2088</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-020-02088-y</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The chromosome-level wintersweet (<italic>Chimonanthus praecox</italic>) genome provides insights into floral scent biosynthesis and flowering in winter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>Junzhong</given-names></name><address><email>shangjz@webmail.hzau.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Jingpu</given-names></name><address><email>tianjingpu@webmail.hzau.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Huihui</given-names></name><address><email>chenghuihui2009@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Qiaomu</given-names></name><address><email>343099704@qq.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Lai</given-names></name><address><email>970809702@qq.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jamal</surname><given-names>Abbas</given-names></name><address><email>Abbasjamal1@yahoo.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Zhongping</given-names></name><address><email>1099808298@qq.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>Lin</given-names></name><address><email>xianglin@mail.hzau.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Saski</surname><given-names>Christopher A.</given-names></name><address><email>SASKI@clemson.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1495-9154</contrib-id><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Shuangxia</given-names></name><address><email>jsx@mail.hzau.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Kaige</given-names></name><address><email>zhaokaige@mail.hzau.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Xiuqun</given-names></name><address><email>liu_xiuqun@sina.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Longqing</given-names></name><address><email>clqhzau@126.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.35155.37</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1790 4137</institution-id><institution>Key Laboratory of Horticultural Plant Biology, Ministry of Education, </institution><institution>Huazhong Agricultural University, </institution></institution-wrap>Wuhan, Hubei 430070 People&#x02019;s Republic of China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.410753.4</institution-id><institution>Novogene Bioinformatics Institute, </institution></institution-wrap>Beijing, 100083 People&#x02019;s Republic of China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.35155.37</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1790 4137</institution-id><institution>National Key Laboratory of Crop Genetic Improvement, </institution><institution>Huazhong Agricultural University, </institution></institution-wrap>Wuhan, Hubei 430070 People&#x02019;s Republic of China </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.443240.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1760 4679</institution-id><institution>Xinjiang Production and Construction Corps Key Laboratory of Protection and Utilization of Biological Resources in Tarim Basin, </institution><institution>Tarim University, </institution></institution-wrap>Alaer, Xinjiang, 843300 China </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.26090.3d</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0665 0280</institution-id><institution>Department of Plant, </institution><institution>Clemson University, </institution></institution-wrap>Clemson, SC 29631 USA </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412720.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1761 2943</institution-id><institution>Southwest Engineering Technology and Research Center of Landscape Architecture, State Forestry Administration, </institution><institution>Southwest Forestry University, </institution></institution-wrap>Kunming, Yunnan 650224 People&#x02019;s Republic of China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>10</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>21</volume><elocation-id>200</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Wintersweet (<italic>Chimonanthus praecox</italic>), an important ornamental plant, has evolved unique fragrant aroma and winter-flowering properties, which are critical for its successful sexual reproduction. However, the molecular mechanisms underlying these traits are largely unknown in this species. In addition, wintersweet is also a typical representative species of the magnoliids, where the phylogenetic position of which relative to eudicots and monocots has not been conclusively resolved.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par2">Here, we present a chromosome-level wintersweet genome assembly with a total size of 695.36&#x02009;Mb and a draft genome assembly of <italic>Calycanthus chinensis</italic>. Phylogenetic analyses of 17 representative angiosperm genomes suggest that Magnoliids and eudicots are sister to monocots. Whole-genome duplication signatures reveal two major duplication events in the evolutionary history of the wintersweet genome, with an ancient one shared by Laurales, and a more recent one shared by the Calycantaceae. Whole-genome duplication and tandem duplication events have significant impacts on copy numbers of genes related to terpene and benzenoid/phenylpropanoid (the main floral scent volatiles) biosynthesis, which may contribute to the characteristic aroma formation. An integrative analysis combining cytology with genomic and transcriptomic data reveals biological characteristics of wintersweet, such as floral transition in spring, floral organ specification, low temperature-mediated floral bud break, early blooming in winter, and strong cold tolerance.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par3">These findings provide insights into the evolutionary history of wintersweet and the relationships among the Magnoliids, monocots, and eudicots; the molecular basis underlying floral scent biosynthesis; and winter flowering, and highlight the utility of multi-omics data in deciphering important ornamental traits in wintersweet.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Wintersweet (<italic>Chimonanthus praecox</italic>)</kwd><kwd>Hi-C</kwd><kwd>Genome</kwd><kwd>Floral scent</kwd><kwd>Flowering</kwd><kwd>Cold tolerance</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par4">Calycantaceae is a small, evolutionarily ancient family composed of ten species assigned to three genera: <italic>Calycanthus</italic> L, <italic>Chimonanthus</italic>, and <italic>Idiospermum Black</italic> that display differences in flower color, flowering time, and geographical distribution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. <italic>Chimonanthus praecox</italic> (Chinese name &#x0201c;La Mei,&#x0201d; commonly known as wintersweet, 2<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;22), is a perennial deciduous shrub that belongs to the Calycantaceae family [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. It originates in China and has been cultivated for over a thousand years. Because of its distinctive fragrant aroma and unique flowering time in winter, wintersweet is also widely cultivated as an ornamental plant in Japan, Europe, and America, with high ornamental and economic value. Additionally, wintersweet is also utilized for its medicinal chemistries, primarily for the treatment of coughs, rheumatism, and measles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p><p id="Par5">Wintersweet flowers possess an intense fragrance that is endowed by a combination of volatile terpenoids (monoterpenes and sesquiterpenes) and benzenoids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>] which are emitted from nectaries distributed on the adaxial of inner petals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. These essential oils derived from its flower are widely used as components in perfume, cosmetics, and various flavor industries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Apart from broad industrial applications, the floral scent also functions in attracting and guiding pollinators to ensure its reproductive success, in addition to protecting the vulnerable reproductive organs from florivores and pathogens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Despite the high ornamental and ecological value of floral scent in wintersweet, the molecular mechanisms underlying the biosynthesis and regulation of the floral volatiles are not well understood. Furthermore, genetic resources are limited for wintersweet, which impedes progress on understanding floral scent biosynthesis and metabolism in wintersweet [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].</p><p id="Par6">Flowering is a critical developmental milestone in the plant life cycle influenced by endogenous cues and diverse environmental factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Different trees display diverse seasonal patterns in flowering. Wintersweet has evolved to synchronize flowering with seasonal climate changes (especially temperature fluctuations). Flower initiation occurs in spring, but flowers bloom during winter (typically late December or early January). During summer and autumn, flower buds grow extremely slow completing floral organ specification, differentiation, and maturation. Like most long-lived trees, wintersweet undergoes growth cessation and dormancy establishment prior to the advent of winter. Different from most flowering trees, wintersweet floral buds break and flowers bloom in midwinter (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a). This unusual flowering season requires flowers to have strong cold hardiness. Furthermore, wintersweet flowers possess an entirely petaloid perianth without differentiation of sepals and petals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Together, these interesting features offer a unique system for elucidating flowering-time regulation, flower development, floral bud dormancy, and break.
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Wintersweet flower morphology, genome features, and synteny information. <bold>a</bold> Wintersweet flower blooming in winter. <bold>b</bold> Overview of the wintersweet draft genome assembly. The outer layer of colored blocks represents the 11 pseudomolecules, with tick marks every 5&#x02009;Mb in size (i). Tracks displayed are as follows: (ii&#x02013;v) the density of genes, long interspersed nuclear elements, long terminal repeat retrotransposons and DNA elements; (vi) guanine-cytosine (GC) content; (vii) relationship between syntenic blocks, as indicated by lines. All the colored bands were featured in 1-Mb intervals across the chromosomes</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13059_2020_2088_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par7">Calycanthaceae belongs to Laurales and, together with Magnoliales, Canellales, and Piperales, constitutes the magnoliids (Magnoliidae). The magnoliids are the third major clades of Mesangiospermae with approximately 9000 species, many of which are early diverging lineages and possess an important phylogenetic position for better understanding the evolutionary history of extant flowering plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Decades of work have been dedicated to resolving the evolutionary relationships among Magnoliids, monocots, and eudicots; however, the phylogenetic position of Magnoliids relative to monocots and eudicots still remains to be debated. For instance, nuclear genomes of four magnoliids (that is, <italic>Cinnamomum kanehirae</italic>, <italic>Liriodendron chinense</italic>, <italic>Persea americana</italic>, and <italic>Piper nigrum</italic>) have been subsequently published [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]; however, phylogenetic analyses of these four genomes resulted in two incongruent placements of Magnoliids relative to monocots and eudicots&#x02014;that is, either monocots as sister group to a clade consisting of magnoliids and eudicots, or magnoliids as the sister to monocots-eudicots clade [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Furthermore, the genome evolution within Magnoliidae is also a widely studied topic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], but still not fully resolved.</p><p id="Par8">In this study, a chromosome-level genome assembly of wintersweet was obtained using a combination data produced from three advanced technologies. Comparative analyses of the wintersweet genome with those of the other four magnoliids and 12 angiosperms have enabled the resolution of the phylogenetic position of magnoliids and yielded new insights into the genome evolution of magnoliids. Through gene mining, cytology, transcriptome, and metabolic data generated from diverse floral developmental stages, we present new insights into the molecular basis of floral scent biosynthesis and flowering in winter.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Genome sequencing, assembly, and annotation</title><p id="Par9">The DNA for genome sequencing of wintersweet was obtained from an accession planted in the campus of Huazhong Agricultural University. DNA was extracted and sequenced by combining three different sequencing methods that include Illumina HiSeq, 10X Genomics, and PacBio SMRT sequencing. A total of 76.96&#x000a0;Gb of PacBio long reads were achieved (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1), approximately 98.83-fold high-quality sequence coverage of the 778.71&#x02009;Mb genome (size estimated by k-mer frequency analysis) (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S1a and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S2). Flow cytometry determined an estimated haploid genome size of 805.88&#x02009;Mb (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S1b), which was consistent with the k-mer method. After interactive error correction, the PacBio reads were assembled into primary contigs using FALCON [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. The primary generated contigs were then polished with Quiver, yielding 1623 contigs with an N50 length of 2.19&#x02009;Mb (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The sequence error correction of the final contigs were performed using 36.48&#x000a0;Gb (46.85X) Illumina short reads by pilon [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. The consensus sequences were further scaffolded by integrating with 156.26&#x000a0;Gb (200.67X) 10X Genomics linked reads (Additional file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1). The final assembly consists of 1259 scaffolds totalling 695.31&#x02009;Mb with a scaffold N50 size of 4.49&#x02009;Mb, covering 89.2% of the genome size estimated by genome survey (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S3). In order to improve the assembly, we used 93&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;Hi-C data to assist the assembly correction and anchored 1027 of 1259 scaffolds into 763 super-scaffolds (Additional&#x000a0;file 1: Table S4 and S5). All the super-scaffolds were accurately clustered and ordered into 11 pseudochromosomes (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S2), covering 99.42% of the original 695.31&#x02009;Mb assembly, with a super-scaffold N50 of 65.35&#x02009;M and a maximum scaffold length of 85.71&#x02009;Mb (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S5). The number of groups corresponded well with the experimentally determined number of chromosomes in somatic cells (2<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;22) (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S3). In addition, 185.93&#x000a0;Gb Illumina sequence data was also generated and used to assemble the <italic>Calycanthus chinensis</italic> (a close relative of wintersweet belonging to the same family) genome (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1). The size of the assembled <italic>C. chinensis</italic> draft genome was 767.4&#x02009;Mb, representing ~&#x02009;92.78% of estimated genome size (Additional&#x000a0;file 1: Table S2), with 291,991 contigs (N50&#x02009;=&#x02009;38.7&#x000a0;kb) and 241,923 scaffolds (N50&#x02009;=&#x02009;20.34&#x02009;Mb) respectively (Additional&#x000a0;file 1: Table S3).
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Major indicators of the wintersweet genome</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Assembly feature</th><th>Statistic</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Estimated genome size (by k-mer analysis) (Mb)</td><td>778.71</td></tr><tr><td>Contig N50 (Mb)</td><td>2.19</td></tr><tr><td>Scaffold N50 (Mb)</td><td>65.35</td></tr><tr><td>Longest scaffold (Mb)</td><td>85.71</td></tr><tr><td>Assembled genome size (Mb)</td><td>695.36</td></tr><tr><td>Assembly % of genome</td><td>99.42</td></tr><tr><td>Repeat region % of assembly</td><td>47.53</td></tr><tr><td>Predicted gene models</td><td>23,591</td></tr><tr><td>Average coding sequence length (bp)</td><td>1250</td></tr><tr><td>Average exons per gene</td><td>5.69</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par10">To assess the genome assembly quality, we performed BUSCO and CEGMA analysis and found that 95% and 92.74% complete eukaryotic conserved genes were identified in wintersweet genome respectively (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S6), suggesting a high degree of completeness of the final assembly. In addition, the high-quality short reads generated from Illumina were mapped to the assembled genome, which exhibits excellent alignments with a mapping rate of 99.95%. Taken together, the above results indicate a high degree of contiguity and completeness of the wintersweet genome.</p><p id="Par11">Based on de novo and homology-based predictions and transcriptome data, a total of 23,591 protein-coding genes were predicted with an average length of 9017&#x02009;bp and an average CDS length of 1250&#x02009;bp, which were comparable to that in <italic>Amborella</italic> and <italic>Lotus</italic> (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S7). The spatial distribution of these protein-coding genes along the chromosome was uneven with higher densities located at the ends of the chromosomal arms (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b). A total of 21,940 (93.1%) predicted protein-coding possessed functional annotation (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S8). A total of 2749 non-coding RNAs (ncRNAs) including 245 ribosomal RNAs (rRNAs), 567 transfer RNAs (tRNAs), 909 microRNA, and 1028 small nuclear RNAs (snRNAs) (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S9) were also identified.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Comparative evolutionary analyses of wintersweet and other typical flowering plant species</title><p id="Par12">The expansion or contraction of gene families has a profound role in driving phenotypic diversity and adaptive evolution in flowering plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. In comparison with gene families in its relative species <italic>C. chinensis</italic>, wintersweet exhibited significant enrichment and reduction of 12 and 45 gene families respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a). KEGG functional enrichment analysis of the expanded gene families demonstrates that they were mainly assigned in &#x0201c;Sesquiterpenoid and triterpenoid biosynthesis,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;Monoterpenoid biosynthesis,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;Flavonoid biosynthesis,&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;Phenylpropanoid biosynthesis&#x0201d; pathways (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S4a and Table S10), which are responsible for the major trait (strong fragrance) specific to wintersweet.
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Evolution of the wintersweet genome and gene families. <bold>a</bold> Phylogenetic tree of 17 plant species. The blue numbers denote divergence time of each node (MYA, million years ago), and those in brackets are 95% confidence intervals for the time of divergence between different clades. The red numbers on the branch represent bootstrap value. The pie diagram on each branch of the tree represents the proportion of gene families undergoing gain (red) or loss (green) events. The numbers below the pie diagram denote the total number of expansion and contraction gene families. Basal angiosperm (Ba). <bold>b</bold> The distribution of single-copy, multiple-copy, unique, and other orthologs in the 17 plant species. <bold>c</bold> Venn diagram represents the shared and unique gene families among five closely related magnoliids (<italic>C. praecox</italic>, <italic>C. kanehirae</italic>, <italic>L. chinense</italic>, <italic>P. nigrum</italic>, and <italic>C. chinensis</italic>). Each number represents the number of gene families</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13059_2020_2088_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par13">Defining the relationship of gene families among flowering plant species has been a powerful approach in investigating the genetic basis of plant evolution. Based on pairwise sequence similarities, we applied the predicted proteomes of wintersweet and 16 other sequenced species to identify putative orthologous gene clusters. A total of 37,137 orthologous gene families composed of 554,042 genes were identified from 17 plant species, of which 5339 clusters of genes were shared by all investigated species, representing ancestral gene families (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b). On the other hand, 8733 gene families were present across wintersweet, <italic>C. chinensis</italic>, <italic>L</italic>. <italic>chinensis</italic>, and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>kanehirae</italic>, which most likely represent the &#x0201c;core&#x0201d; proteome of the magnoliids (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>c). There are 339 gene families containing 507 proteins specific to the wintersweet genome (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S11). Gene Ontology (GO) term enrichment analyses of wintersweet-specific genes revealed that the functional categories termed &#x0201c;oxidoreductase activity&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;pectinesterase activity&#x0201d; involved in metabolism were enriched (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S4b).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Repetitive content and recent burst of LTR retrotransposons</title><p id="Par14">In the wintersweet genome, repetitive elements occupied 45.73% of the genome, of which 96.69% were annotated as transposable elements (TEs) (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S12). Long terminal repeat retrotransposons (LTRs) were the major class of TEs that accounts for 36.2% of the assembly. Among the LTRs, the LTR/Gypsy elements were the most abundant, composing 23.3% of the genome, followed by LTR/Copia elements (8.6%, Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S12). Besides the main groups of LTR elements, 3.65% of the genome was annotated as DNA elements and 3.45% as long interspersed nuclear elements, whereas the rest were assigned to other repeat families or could not be assigned (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S12). Transposable elements are unevenly distributed across the chromosomes and found to be particularly abundant in centromeric regions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b). Further comparative analysis of the distribution of TEs indicated a higher proportion in intergenic regions (79.19%) when compared to genic regions (16.04%) and regions adjoining genes (4.77%) (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S5a). Within genic regions, the TEs exhibited unequal distribution between exons and introns. 98.98% of TEs in the genic regions occurred in introns and constituted 25% of the total length of introns (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S5b). Comparison of gene structure with other species revealed that the average length and number of exons is similar, while the average length of introns is slightly longer and to some extent can be attributed to repeat accumulation. Moreover, the time of the LTR-RT burst in wintersweet was estimated using the 8812 putative complete LTR-RTs and revealed a peak substitution rate at around 0.03 (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S6). We assumed a mutation rate of 1.51&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;9</sup> per base per year [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], resulting in an insertion time of approximately 9.9&#x02009;Ma.</p><p id="Par15">In order to investigate the evolution of TEs in Magnoliids, phylogenetic trees of domains in reverse transcriptase genes were constructed for both <italic>Ty1/Copia</italic> and <italic>Ty3/Gypsy</italic> superfamily. In the phylogenetic tree of <italic>Ty3/Gypsy</italic> superfamily, the majority of LTR-RTs from wintersweet were clustered into the tork clade (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S7a). Compared with <italic>L. chinensis</italic> and <italic>C kanehirae</italic>, the LTR-RTs in wintersweet and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>chinensis</italic> exhibited higher diversity and abundance within the tork clade, indicating greater expansion and divergence in wintersweet and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>chinensis</italic> genome. The <italic>Copia</italic> superfamily displayed a different pattern, with four major clades consisting of elements from all these four species (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S7b), suggesting a conserved evolution pattern of the <italic>Copia</italic> superfamily, as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Phylogenomic placement of Magnoliids sister to eudicots</title><p id="Par16">The phylogenetic relationships of Magnoliids, monocots, and eudicots have been somewhat controversial in plant taxonomy. In an effort to infer the phylogenetic position of the Magnoliids relative to monocots and eudicots, a set of 213 evaluated single-copy ortholog sets (OSCG) were first identified with OrthoMCL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>] using genome data from 17 flowering plant species that includes 5 monocots, 6 eudicots, 5 magnoliids, and 1 basal angiosperm. We applied both coalescent and concatenation approaches to reconstruct phylogenetic trees using the 213-gene dataset. Both coalescent and concatenation analyses yielded an identical highly supported topology with magnoliids as a sister group to eudicots after their divergence from monocots (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S8a). To avoid the potential errors in ortholog identification, we also used SonicParanoid [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>] to extract single-copy genes (SSCG) from the 17 plant genomes described above. Only those genes sampled from at least 14 species were utilized for the construction of phylogenetic trees. On the basis of 216 single-copy genes, the phylogenetic trees were then similarly inferred by both coalescent and concatenation methods as those described above. The resulting species trees were topologically identical to the phylogenetic findings revealed by OrtholMCL described above (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S8b).</p><p id="Par17">Although the same set of phylogenetic relationships among Magnoliids, monocots, and eudicots was consistently recovered, the topological conflicts were also observed among coalescent-based gene trees (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S8c). To estimate the discordance among gene trees in OSCG and SSCG datasets, we took advantage of the quartet score in ASTRAL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>] to display the proportions of gene trees in support of three different branching orders for Magnoliids, monocots, and eudicots (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S8d) and found that the percentages of gene trees supporting Magnoliids and eudicots together forming a sister group with monocots is higher than the other two topologies (Additional&#x000a0;file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S8c). However, in the phylogenetic analyses of a concatenated sequence alignment of 38 chloroplast single-copy genes for 26 taxa, the magnoliids were placed as a sister group to the clade consisting of eudicots and monocots (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S9). Furthermore, the short phylogenetic branches among magnoliids, eudicots, and monocots clades, representing rapid speciation events, were also observed in these phylogenetic genes. The phylogenetic incongruence between nuclear and plastid genomes may be caused by incomplete lineage sorting (ILS), which appears more frequently during the rapid divergence of early mesangiosperms. As the inadequate taxon sampling could result in incongruent phylogeny, we improved the taxon sampling by adding additional genome data from 11 phylogenetically pivotal species and a transcriptome data set of chloranthales to reconstruct the phylogenetic tree. This approach recovered the same phylogenetic relationships among magnoliids, eudicots, and monocots (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S10). Thus, from these results, we believe the phylogenetic relationship proposed in our study is relatively accurate under the current dataset. Based on the high-confidence phylogenetic tree and calibration points selected from articles and TimeTree website, the divergence time between the magnoliids and the eudicots were estimated to be 113.0&#x02013;153.1&#x02009;Ma (95% confidence interval) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a), which overlaps with three recent estimates (114.6&#x02013;164&#x02009;Ma, 117&#x02013;189&#x02009;Ma, and 136.0&#x02013;209.4&#x02009;Ma) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Whole-genome duplication and genome evolution analysis</title><p id="Par18">Whole-genome duplication (WGD) has long been regarded as the major driving force in plant evolution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. To investigate WGD events during the evolutionary course of wintersweet, we first searched for genome-wide duplications and assigned them into four different modes with MCScanX analysis (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S11). The WGD/segmental duplication was identified as the dominant type that includes 4511 paralogous gene pairs in 265 syntenic blocks. Among these syntenic blocks, 36.09% were found to share relationships with three other blocks across the genome (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S12). The widespread synteny and well-maintained one-versus-three syntenic blocks suggest that two WGD events might have occurred during wintersweet genome evolution. It is well accepted that <italic>Amborella</italic> is a single living species that is the sister lineage to all other groups within the angiosperms, and there is no evidence of lineage-specific polyploidy after it diverged from the last common ancestor of angiosperms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Collinearity and synteny analysis between the wintersweet and <italic>Amborella</italic> genome also provided clear structural evidence for two WGDs in wintersweet with a 1:4 syntenic depth ratio in <italic>Amborella</italic>-wintersweet comparison (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a). To further elucidate the polyploidy of wintersweet genomes, we performed a comparative genomic analysis of wintersweet with <italic>C. kanehirae</italic> and <italic>L. chinensis</italic>. Syntenic depth ratios of 4:4 and 2:4 were inferred in the wintersweet-<italic>Cinnamomum</italic> and wintersweet-<italic>Liriodendron</italic> comparisons, respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b). Based on the syntenic relationships between and within each species, our analyses collectively indicate that wintersweet underwent two WGD events.
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Comparative genomics analyses. <bold>a</bold> Synteny patterns between genomic regions from wintersweet and Amborella. This pattern shows that some typical ancestral regions in the basal angiosperm Amborella have four corresponding copy regions in wintersweet. This collinear relationship is highlighted by one syntenic set shown in red and green colors. <bold>b</bold> Syntenic blocks between genomes. Dot plots of orthologs show a 4&#x02013;4 chromosomal relationship between the wintersweet genome and <italic>C. kanehirae</italic> genome, and 2&#x02013;4 chromosomal relationship between wintersweet genome and <italic>L. chinense</italic> genome. <bold>c</bold> Distribution of synonymous substitution levels (Ks) of syntenic orthologous (dashed curves) and paralogous genes (solid curves) after evolutionary rate correction. <bold>d</bold> Evolutionary model of the Laurales genomes. The Laurales ancestral chromosomes are represented by ten colors. Polyploidization events are shown by 3 dots of different colors, along with the chromosome fusions (Fu) and fissions (Fi). The modern structure of the Laurales genomes is illustrated at the bottom of the figure. In some regions, we could not determine which ancestral chromosome they derived from, and those regions were represented as white spaces</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13059_2020_2088_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p id="Par19">To estimate the timing of the two WGD events in the wintersweet genome, we characterized synonymous substitutions on synonymous nucleotide sites (Ks) between collinear homoeologs within or between wintersweet and other three species including <italic>C. chinensis</italic>, <italic>Cinnamomum kanehirae</italic>, and <italic>Liriodendron chinensis</italic> from Magnoliids. The Ks distributions of one-to-one orthologs identified between <italic>Amborella</italic> and the other four species show different Ks peaks, suggesting divergent evolutionary rates among these four species (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S13). After correction for evolutionary rate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>], the synonymous substitutions per site per year as 4.21&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;9</sup> for Laurales were calculated using the mean Ks values of syntenic blocks, resulting in the estimated time of the WGD event at approximately 77.8 million and 112.1 million years ago (Ma), respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>c). Previous analysis of the genome of <italic>Cinnamomum</italic> suggested that the ancient WGD event seems shared by Magnoliales and Laurales [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], and the absolute dating of the identified WGD events in <italic>Liriodendron tulipifera</italic> also supported this hypothesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. In our study, we also detected two and one polyploidization events in <italic>Cinnamomum</italic> and <italic>Liriodendron</italic> respectively, but no common WGD event was shared by these two species. Furthermore, the wintersweet genome shares an ancient WGD event with <italic>Cinnamomum</italic> but not with <italic>Liriodendron</italic>. Moreover, the trees of the syntenic gene groups of wintersweet and <italic>Liriodendron</italic> vs. <italic>Amborella</italic> indicated that wintersweet and <italic>Liriodendron</italic> experienced a WGD event respectively after their divergence from a common ancestor (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S14 and Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Supplementary Note 3). Thus, from these results, we conclude that the ancient wintersweet WGD event has occurred before the divergence of Calycantaceae and Lauraceae but after the divergence of Calycantaceae and Magnoliaceae.</p><p id="Par20">We also used orthologous and paralogous genes derived from the intergenomic and intragenomic analysis of the wintersweet and <italic>C. chinensis</italic> as well as <italic>C</italic>. <italic>kanehirae</italic> genomes to construct a putative ancestral genome of the Laurales, and proposed an evolutionary scenario where these three lineages were derived from a putative ancestor (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>d and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S15), which consisted of ten chromosomes and 4216 genes. This ancestor went through a WGD event to reach a 20-chromosome intermediate and then experienced chromosomal rearrangements to form present-day karyotypes. In wintersweet, all the chromosomes underwent rearrangements and every chromosome came from at least two ancient chromosomes. A minimum of 49 chromosomal fissions and 48 chromosomal fusions were predicted to have occurred in wintersweet to reach its current structure of 11 chromosomes (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>d).</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Genetic basis of floral transition, floral organ specification, and early blooming in winter</title><p id="Par21">Wintersweet is one of the perennial trees that bloom in the deep winter. It took approximately 10&#x000a0;months for <italic>C. praecox</italic> to complete its reproductive development. To investigate this whole process of the flower development that may influence the final flowering time, we first performed a systematic study on the floral ontogeny and developmental patterns by paraffin sections through observation. The results indicated that the floral bud was initiated in April, floral patterning and floral organ specification occurred from April to July, slow growth in summer, the male and female gametophytes were formed in October and December respectively, the flower bud transitioned into dormancy, then break occurred in December, and the flower bloomed in deep winter (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a). To investigate the molecular mechanisms underlying the critical flower developmental stages, we generated and analyzed RNA-seq data for representative flower developmental stages from the timing of floral initiation to maturation.
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Schematic depiction of the key developmental stages of flower bud and the analysis of floral organ identity and flowering-time related genes. <bold>a</bold> Flower developmental stages including floral transition, meristem specification, floral organ specification, floral bud dormancy and release, and blooming. Abbreviations for the flower bud developmental stages: undifferentiated flower bud stage (FBS1); flower primordium formation stage (FBS2); tepal primordium formation stage (FBS3); stamen primordium formation stage (FBS4); pistil primordium formation stage (FBS5); flower organ development and differentiation stage (FBS6); slow growth stage (FBS7); ovule appearance stage (FBS8); pollen formation stage (FBS9), blooming in winter. ap, shoot apex; fp, floral primordium; t, tepals; s, stamens; p, pistil; a, anther; o, ovule; po, pollen; es, embryonic sac. <bold>b</bold> The expression patterns of genes related to flowering time and floral organ identity at different flower developmental stages. <bold>c</bold> The phylogenetic tree of MADS-box genes and gene expression patterns of B-/C-function genes from various floral organs. The MADS-box proteins in wintersweet are marked by the yellow box</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13059_2020_2088_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p><p id="Par22">Floral initiation is controlled by the spatial and temporal expression of flowering-time-related genes in multiple pathways [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Many genes from these pathways have been identified and characterized in various herbaceous and perennial species and reported to have the conserved function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. A database of flowering-time gene networks was recently constructed in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Taking advantage of this database, we identified 594 flowering-time genes in eight pathways (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S13). Analysis of RNA-seq data shown that during the floral transition the flowering-time genes related to gibberellin biosynthesis and signaling transduction pathway were significantly activated (padj &#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01), and the expression of some genes in photoperiodic and circadian clock pathways were also upregulated (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S14) suggesting the endogenous hormone (gibberellin) and environmental factor (photoperiod) may play a major role in the switch from vegetative to reproductive growth in spring.</p><p id="Par23">After floral patterning and floral organ specification from April to July, the floral organ development processes slowly from Summer to Autumn, during which the temperature is very high and maximum temperature could reach up to 39&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S15). Therefore, the temperature may be a key factor that affects the flower organ slow development. The direct reflection is the significantly increased expression level of heat shock protein genes (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b). In addition, comparing with other developmental stages, many genes associated with cell division downregulated significantly (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S16). Heat stress transcriptional factors (HSFs) and heat responsive genes play an essential role in heat stress response [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. We have found 21 members in HSF family in <italic>C. praecox</italic>. Six <italic>HsfA1s</italic>, which serve as the master transcriptional regulators in the heat stress response, were identified (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S17). The DEHYDRATION-RESPONSIVE ELEMENT BINDING PROTEIN2A (DREB2A) regulated by the HsfA1s. Both <italic>HsfA1-1</italic> and <italic>DREB2A-1</italic> displayed an opposite expression pattern with the genes related to cell division (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S15). The DRE sequence (CTAGA motif) which is recognized by DREB2A was also detected in the promoter of the cell division genes (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S16a). These results may suggest that the heat signals can be integrated into transcriptional regulatory networks by the HSFs then to regulate expression of the genes related to the cell division, finally resulting in the slow growth of flower organs.</p><p id="Par24">In total, 58 MADS-box genes were identified in the wintersweet genome, 31 of which are MIKC-type MADS-box genes (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S13). Phylogenetic and collinearity analyses of these genes indicated that the homologs of ABCE model prototype genes, except for <italic>AP1/FUL</italic>, were all found to be duplicated (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>c). Four <italic>AGL6s</italic>, generated by WGD events, were identified in wintersweet assembly, the number of which is larger than that in Arabidopsis and rice. Among these genes, the <italic>CpAGL6a</italic> has been reported to promote flowering when overexpressed in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Meanwhile, the FLOWERING LOCUS C (<italic>FLC</italic>), which serves as a flowering repressor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>], was lost in wintersweet (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>c). The selective expanded promoter and loss of repressor of flowering-time related genes may be associated with the earlier flowering of wintersweet. The morphology between the inner and outer perianth in wintersweet displayed a slight difference, which is the same as in some basal eudicots (<italic>Ranunculus</italic> and <italic>Aquilegia</italic>). &#x0201c;Sliding boundary&#x0201d; model was proposed to explain this morphology in <italic>Ranunculus</italic>, in which the B-function homologs are expressed in those whorls that produce petaloid organ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. The B-function homologs in wintersweet displayed broad expression pattern, with <italic>AP3b</italic> preferably expressed in the outer perianth whorl (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>c), which supported the &#x0201c;sliding boundary&#x0201d; model and may complement the absence of a clear morphological distinction between sepals and petals in wintersweet. The strong expression of C-function homologs is limited to stamen and carpel, which suggests that these genes have a conserved function in stamen and carpel specification. The expression profiles of wintersweet ABCE homologs during the flower development largely agree with the gradual formation of the floral organs they specify (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b).</p><p id="Par25">The relative earlier flowing time in winter suggested the shorter chilling requirement for dormancy release and earlier bud break in wintersweet. The members of the <italic>SHORT VEGETATIVE PHASE</italic> (<italic>SVP</italic>) clade of the MADS-box gene family, including SVP and DAM genes, are well known to be associated with dormancy release and bud break [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Two homologs of <italic>SVP</italic> genes were identified in the wintersweet genome. Phylogenetic analysis of <italic>SVPs</italic> revealed that these two genes cluster close to <italic>PtSVL</italic> (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S16b), the function of which had been characterized as a repressor in the genetic network of temperature-mediated vegetative bud break in hybrid aspen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. The downstream genes of <italic>PtSVL</italic> in the network including <italic>TEOSINTE BRANCHED1</italic>, <italic>CYCLOIDEA</italic>, <italic>PCF/BRANCHED1</italic> (<italic>TCP18/BRC1</italic>), and <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS T</italic> (<italic>FT</italic>), which function as negative and positive regulators of temperature-mediated control bud break, were also identified in the wintersweet genome (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S16c). During the transition from endodormancy to flush stage, the increase in expression of <italic>CpFT1</italic> and downregulation of <italic>CpTCP18/BRC1</italic> and <italic>CpSVL1</italic> were noted (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S16d). Gibberellin acid (GA) and abscisic acid (ABA) acts as positive and negative regulators of bud break respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>], and the content of which to some extent is associated with the expression level of biosynthesis and catabolism genes. The increased expression of GA biosynthesis genes such as <italic>GA20 oxidase</italic> and the decreased expression of ABA biosynthesis genes such as the <italic>NCED</italic> (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S16d) was also observed at the bud break stage, which may coincide with their role in bud break.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Genetic basis of strong cold resistance</title><p id="Par26">Wintersweet is one of the perennial trees that bloom in the deep winter, during which the temperature always falls below the freezing point. Therefore, wintersweet has evolved a systematic mechanism to withstand cold stress. Volatile glycosylation is a common form of plant volatile compounds and plays an important role in response to abiotic stress in plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Recent studies revealed that the volatile terpene glucosylation mediated by UDP-glycosyltransferases (UGTs) was involved in the modulation of cold stress tolerance in tea plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. In wintersweet, abundant volatiles were present in glycosidically bound forms, such as linalool glucoside, benzaldehyde benzyl alcohol (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S17). The considerable expansion in the UGT family (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S10) and abundant terpene glycosides in wintersweet flowers lead to the hypothesis that the strong cold tolerance of wintersweet, to some extent, is related to the volatile glucosylation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Evolution of terpene biosynthesis and regulation-related genes</title><p id="Par27">Monoterpenes are the major components of floral volatile organic compounds (VOCs) in wintersweet, especially the linalool, which accounts for more than half of the floral scent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. In plants, monoterpenes/diterpenes and sesquiterpenes are usually generated via the 2-<italic>C</italic>-methyl-D-erythritol 4-phosphate (MEP) pathway and the mevalonate (MVA) pathway, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. A total of 46 genes in these two pathways were identified (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S18). The key genes involved in the MEP pathway such as 1-deoxy-<sc>d</sc>-xylulose 5-phosphate synthase (<italic>DXS</italic>), 1-deoxy-<sc>d</sc>-xylulose 5-phosphate reductoisomerase (<italic>DXR</italic>), and isopentenyl diphosphate isomerase (<italic>IDI</italic>) were generated through WGD events (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a). The high rate of paralog generation in these genes could increase the efficiency of catalytic reaction through dosage effects, thereby increasing the metabolic flux toward the MEP pathway. Terpene synthases (TPSs) are the enzymes responsible for the last catalytic reaction in the MVA and MEP pathway to generate terpenoid compounds. With the aid of the assembly genome, a total of 52 complete <italic>CpTPSs</italic> were identified (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S19), the number of which is approximately double that detected by transcriptomics in our previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Phylogenetic analysis of TPS from four species revealed that <italic>CpTPSs</italic> were clustered into five of six subfamilies described for land plants (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b). The majority of <italic>CpTPSs</italic> were placed in the TPS-a (18) and TPS-b (24) subfamilies, which is predominantly composed of angiosperm-specific sesquiterpene and monoterpene synthases respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. Comparative genomics analysis revealed that the TPS genes are significantly expanded, especially in the TPS-b subfamily (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S10). These lineage-specific gene expansions in the TPS-b subfamily may contribute to the monoterpene accumulation in floral VOCs in wintersweet.
<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Terpenes biosynthesis in wintersweet. <bold>a</bold> Expression profiles of genes encoding enzymes possibly involved in monoterpene and sesquiterpene biosynthesis. Abbreviations for enzymes in each catalytic step are shown in bold. The gradient color for each gene represents the gene expression levels in three floral developmental stages (S1: bud stage; S4: full open flower stage; S5: senescence stage). Homologous genes are represented by equal colored horizontal stripes and are termed from top to bottom in Arabic numerical order. The full names of enzymes are listed in the Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S18. The genes circled in green box were generated by WGD event. The non-boxed genes did not undergo this event. <bold>b</bold> Phylogeny of TPS proteins identified in wintersweet and 5 other sequenced plant genomes showing the subfamilies from a&#x02013;g. <bold>c</bold> The expression of <italic>CpTPS</italic> genes in three different floral development stages. These genes were expressed in at least one of the three developmental stages. <bold>d</bold> The chromosomes with more than one <italic>CpTPS</italic> gene. The red diamonds represent the functionally characterized genes. The green diamonds represent the genes generated by tandem duplication events. The cure with arrow linked two duplicated genes. <bold>e</bold> Identification of enzymatic products after incubating recombinant CpTPSs proteins with geranyl diphosphate (GPP)/farnesyl diphosphate (FPP). The volatile terpenes were analyzed by GC-MS analysis and comparing with authentic standards. <bold>f</bold> Increased linalool biosynthesis in the <italic>CpTPS4</italic>-overexpressed <italic>tobacco</italic> compared with wild type (WT) and empty vector control (EV). Data represent the mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SDs of three biological replicates</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13059_2020_2088_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p><p id="Par28">Expression analysis of the 52 <italic>CpTPS</italic> genes by RNA-seq revealed that six genes displayed similar expression patterns with the emission of major monoterpenes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>c and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S18). Based on the expression pattern and phylogenetic analysis, we further selected three genes from TPS-b/g subfamily for functional characterization and found that all the genes encoded versatile enzymes with multiple products (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>e). Subcellular localization analysis showed that <italic>CpTPS4</italic> and <italic>CpTPS9</italic> were localized to the plastid whereas <italic>CpTPS42</italic> was targeted to the cytosol (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S19). <italic>CpTPS42</italic> was shown to be a sesquiterpene synthase, which mainly catalyzed the formation of nerolidol, together with other sesquiterpenes (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>e). <italic>CpTPS4</italic> and <italic>CpTPS9</italic> are both monoterpene synthases and produce &#x003b2;-pinene and linalool as its main product respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>e). To further understand the function of <italic>CpTPS4</italic>, we also overexpressed the gene in tobacco. Enhanced levels of the monoterpenes including linalool, limonene, &#x003b2;-ocimene, and trans-&#x003b2;-ocimene were found in transgenic tobacco leaves in comparison with the wild type control (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>f). These results indicated that <italic>CpTPS4</italic> plays a primary role in the biosynthesis of linalool, the main components of floral scent.</p><p id="Par29">The available genome assembly allows for <italic>CpTPSs</italic> to be localized to either chromosomes or scaffold positions to consider a genomic context. The <italic>CpTPS</italic> genes are not uniformly distributed throughout the chromosomes with 44 genes located on six chromosomes and eight genes on seven scaffolds (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>d). Fourteen of the 52 <italic>CpTPS</italic> genes have at least two copies and each duplicated gene copy was located adjacent to the other. For example, <italic>CpTPS4</italic> is located on scaffold662 and has three copies including <italic>CpTPS17</italic>, <italic>CpTPS18</italic>, and <italic>CpTPS19</italic>. These three genes were arranged as a tandem array on chromosome 6 and highly expressed at the full open flower stage, which may have a similar function as <italic>CpTPS4</italic> and contribute equally to linalool production.</p><p id="Par30">Terpenoid formation does not only depend on the biochemical properties of enzymes encoded by <italic>CpTPS</italic> genes but also requires the involvement of transcription factors (TFs). A total of 1313 TFs that show differential expression during petal development have been identified. Among these, 99 display positive correlation with the emission of terpenes and are predominantly distributed in MYB, bHLH, WRKY, and bZIP families (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S20 and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S20). The transcriptional control of terpene biosynthesis genes correlates with the presence of cis-elements in their promoter regions, which were recognized and bound by specific transcription factors. When screening the 2000-bp regions upstream of the 52 <italic>CpTPS</italic> genes, several defense and stress responsive elements were found to be significantly enriched, such as bHLH- and MYB-binding elements (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S21). The results indicated that the MYB/bHLH transcription factors may serve as key factors in regulating the <italic>CpTPS</italic> genes expression and provide us with the starting point for the further studies to reveal the cross-talk in the regulation of plant secondary metabolites and stress responses.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Evolution of benzenoid/phenylpropanoid biosynthesis-related genes</title><p id="Par31">Benzenoids/phenylpropanoids are the second largest group of the floral VOCs in wintersweet, which are derived from the aromatic acid phenylalanine. Phenylalanine is synthesized via two pathways (phenylalanine pathway and aragenate pathway) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>], and these two pathways split from the plastidial shikimate pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. The genes involved in the shikimate pathway (20), phenylpyruvate pathway (7), and arogenate pathway (6) were identified as shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a. In the wintersweet genome, both WGD and tandem duplication events have considerably impacted both the upstream genes in the phenylpropanoid pathway and downstream genes involved in specific benzenoid (benzyl acetate and methyl salicylate) biosynthesis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a,b), which lead to the high rate of paralog formation in 15 gene families (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S21).
<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Evolution and expression of key genes involved in benzenoid/phenylpropanoid biosynthesis. <bold>a</bold> Expression profiles of genes encoding enzymes possibly involved in the shikimate/benzenoid pathway in wintersweet. Abbreviations for enzymes in each catalytic step are shown in bold. The gradient color for each gene represents the gene expression levels in three petal developmental stages in wintersweet (S1: bud stage; S4: full open flower stage; S5: senescence stage). Homologous genes are represented by equal colored horizontal stripes and are termed from top to bottom in Arabic numerical order. The full names of enzymes are listed in the Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S21. The genes circled in black and red boxes were generated by WGD and tandem duplication events respectively. The non-boxed genes did not undergo these events. <bold>b</bold> Schematic representation of the wintersweet chromosomes together with the positions of key genes involved in benzenoid/phenylpropanoid biosynthesis. The genes marked in brown and red were generated by WGD and tandem duplication events respectively. <bold>c</bold> Expression profiles of the 21 <italic>BEAT</italic>&#x000a0;homologous genes in three different stages (S1, S4, and S5). These genes were expressed in at least one of the three developmental stages</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13059_2020_2088_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p><p id="Par32">Benzyl acetate, the dominant compounds of floral scent in wintersweet, is synthesized from benzyl alcohol via acetyl-CoA-dependent reaction catalyzed by acetyl-CoA: benzyl alcohol acetyltransferase (BEAT) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. Comparative genomic analysis revealed that the wintersweet genome harbors 33 <italic>BEAT</italic> homologous genes (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S21), the number of which is comparable to that in <italic>Prunus mume</italic>, in which benzyl acetate is also the major component of floral scent. Similar to <italic>P. mume</italic>, the expansion of the <italic>BEAT</italic> homologous genes&#x000a0;was mainly attributed to tandem and WGD duplication events&#x000a0;[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. Of 33 <italic>BEAT</italic> homologous&#x000a0;genes found in wintersweet genome, 8 were derived from the WGD event, and 14 were amplified via tandem duplication. Transcriptome and metabolite correlation analysis showed that the expression pattern of 4 <italic>CpBEATs</italic> coincided with benzyl acetate emission (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>c and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S18). These genes might be responsible for benzyl acetate biosynthesis in the wintersweet flower. Methyl salicylate is also the major composition of floral VOCs in wintersweet. Three tandem duplication-derived salicylic acid methyltransferase (<italic>SAMTs</italic>) were identified in the wintersweet (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S22), two of which were highly expressed in the flower and their expression patterns correlated with methyl salicylate emission, suggesting that these two genes may be primarily responsible for methyl salicylate biosynthesis (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a). These observations above suggested that the expansion of specific genes and selective expression in flower could induce the heightened activity of the corresponding enzymes, which resulted in the abundant characteristic aroma formation in the flowers of wintersweet.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par33">In this study, we constructed a high-quality chromosome-level genome assembly for wintersweet by combining the long-read sequences from PacBio with highly accurate short reads from Illumina sequencing and using Hi-C data for super-scaffolding. The assembly of wintersweet adds to the growing body of genome information for the Calycantaceae family. As the relatively domesticated species in the Calycantaceae family [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>], wintersweet has a range of specific biological features such as early blooming in deep winter, strong cold resistance, and fragrant flowers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. As a representative of the Magnoliids, it also maintains a key evolutionary position on the tree of life. The availability of the wintersweet genome sequence makes it possible to consider deep angiosperm phylogenic questions, determine genome evolution signatures, and to reveal the genetic basis of interesting traits. This assembly also facilitates in-depth fundamental comparative genomic analysis to elucidate biology and gain resolution of genome evolution between wintersweet and other species within the Calycantaceae family.</p><p id="Par34">Resolution of the relationship among Magnoliids, monocots, and eudicots has not been conclusively determined, despite numerous attempts. In four independent studies, four genomes representing three orders (Magnoliales, Piperales, and Laurales) within magnoliales have been published [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], and each study attempted to resolve the phylogenetic position of magnoliidaes. Three species including <italic>Piper nigrum</italic> (representative of Piperales clade), <italic>L. tulipifera</italic> (representative of Magnoliales clade), and <italic>P. americana</italic> (representative of laurales clade) were placed as sister to the monocots and eudicots, while <italic>C. kanehirae</italic> (representative of Magnoliales clade) was found to be a sister clade to the eudicots. Many factors could be responsible for these topological differences such as taxon sample size [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>], possible incomplete lineage sorting (ILS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], and the number of retrieved orthologs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. For example, adequate taxon sampling, especially those smaller sister lineages such as Chloranthales in angiosperm clades [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>], was vital to obtain a resolved phylogeny. To account for incomplete lineage sorting, we used two complementary tools to extract the single-copy genes and two methods (coalescent and concatenation-based analysis) to reconstruct the phylogeny. In addition, we also improved taxon sampling, selected key lineages (representative of chloranthales clade) as well as additional lineages in the monocots and eudicots, and included five magnoliids to cover key representative clades. Finally, all the analyses recovered the magnoliids together with eudicots as sister to the monocots. This result is congruent with a recent study of 59 low-copy nuclear genes from 26 mesangiosperm transcriptomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>] and 410 single-copy genes nuclear gene families extracted from genomic and transcriptomic data from 1153 species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>], but disagrees with the plastid trees which supported a topology of magnoliales as the sister to monocots and eudicots. In comparison with nuclear genes, the plastid genes are uniparentally inherited and may recover different deep-level relationships resulting from ancient lineage sorting and hybridization, which might potentially introduce biases and errors to phylogenetic reconstruction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. To date, the genome data were still absent in the key clades of angiosperms, such as Chloranthales. Even though we have suggested a robust phylogeny using &#x0201c;genome-scale&#x0201d; data, sequencing of the complete angiosperm lineages will facilitate future investigations of the phylogenetic relationships of flowering plants.</p><p id="Par35">Wintersweet is one of the very few flowering plant lineages that bloom in winter, which make it an ideal perennial plant for flowering-time study. Application of database about the flowering-time gene networks in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> serves to identify the homologs of flowering-time genes in wintersweet. Comparative transcriptome analyses provide an array of resources for further flowering-time-related gene identification. Mapping quantitative trait loci (QTL) onto linkage maps, with segregating genetic populations, is a powerful strategy to dissecting complex agronomical characters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. The availability of high-quality genome and diverse germplasm of wintersweet with different flowering time makes it possible to use this genetic approach to detect flowering-time quantitative trait loci in the future. The petaloid sepal is another striking distinction of wintersweet. This flower structure also exists in some basal eudicots (such as <italic>Ranunculus</italic> and <italic>Aquilegia</italic>), some monocots (such as <italic>Liliumus</italic> and <italic>Tulipa</italic>), and basal angiosperm lineages, which was supposed to be displayed by the ancestral angiosperm flower [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. The broad expression pattern of B-function genes was shared by these species, which may represent the ancestral condition for angiosperms. The genetic network for seasonal temperature-mediated control of bud break has been elucidated in the vegetable bud of hybrid aspen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. In this genetic network, the <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>SVL</italic> are the homologs of <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>SVP</italic> in Arabidopsis respectively, both of which act as a flowering regulator [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. Similar to the vegetable buds, the floral buds are also subjected to the dormancy and bud break. The homologs of the key components in wintersweet displayed a similar expression pattern during the transition from endodormancy to bud break stage, leading us to the hypothesis that wintersweet may utilize the common signaling components in both flowering and bud break process.</p><p id="Par36">The evolution, adaptation, and domestication of wintersweet resulted in specific qualities and quantities of floral volatiles, primarily consisting of monoterpenes and benzenoids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. The diversification of terpenes is mainly determined by the <italic>TPS</italic> family genes, among which the <italic>TPS</italic>-b subfamily is well known for monoterpenes synthesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. The extensive expansion of <italic>TPS</italic>-b subfamily genes in the wintersweet genome may be one explanation for diverse monoterpene accumulation. The production of terpenes is regulated to a large extent by the transcription level of <italic>TPS</italic> genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. The results of the present expression analyses revealed a dynamic expression of the <italic>TPS</italic> genes, which may be another explanation for the monoterpene diversification. Using the genomic data, we found remarkable duplications of the metabolic genes in both terpene and benzoid/phenylpropanoid biosynthesis pathways, especially in the <italic>TPS</italic> and <italic>BEAT</italic> genes which are responsible for the major components (linalool and benzyl acetate) production. Tandem duplication is the major contributor to the expansions of <italic>TPS</italic> and <italic>BEAT</italic> genes and most of these duplicated genes are tandemly organized in clusters. In the <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> genome, the <italic>Adh</italic> gene is tandemly duplicated and shows a 2.6-fold greater expression than the single-copy gene. The overactivity caused by the tandem arrangement was proposed to be a general property of tandem gene duplicates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. The greater output of the tandem arrangement in the <italic>TPS</italic> and <italic>BEAT</italic> genes may increase transcript abundance of the tandem duplicates and thereby led to the mass production of major components. Based on our data, we speculate that the remarkable duplication, tandem clustering of gene, and gene expression dynamics may contribute to the abundant characteristic aroma formation in wintersweet.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par37">In summary, we have presented a high-quality assembly of wintersweet, the first genome reference in the Calycantaceae family. The integration of multi-omics data advanced our understanding of floral scent biochemistry as well as the molecular mechanisms underlying flowering. Over a thousand years of wintersweet cultivation, evolutionary forces have shaped abundant cultivars with novelty in floral scent and color. The available complete wintersweet genome will provide a fundamental resource for comparative genomics studies on the diversity and the evolutionary mechanisms of ornamental traits (floral scent and color) at the genome level, which will be invaluable for genetic improvement through molecular breeding in the future.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec15"><title>Plant materials, library construction, and genome sequencing</title><p id="Par38">All plant materials used in this study were collected from the campus of Huazhong Agriculture University (Wuhan, China) under natural photoperiod. High-quality, intact genomic DNA was extracted from fresh leaves of <italic>Chimonanthus praecox &#x0201c;H29&#x0201d;</italic> and <italic>Calycanthus chinensis</italic> using DNAsecure Plant Kit (TIANGEN). The isolated DNA was quantified using a NanoDrop D-100 spectrometer (Nanodrop Technologies) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol. A high-quality genome assembly for the <italic>C. praecox</italic> genome was achieved by using three sequencing methods that include Illumina paired-end and mate-pair sequencing, 10X Genomics sequencing, and single molecule real-time (SMRT) sequencing from Pacific Biosciences (PacBio).</p><p id="Par39">A total of 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of sheared DNA was used for a 20-kb insert size library subsequently sequenced on the Pacbio Sequel platform. A short-read genomic library was prepared using a Illumina TruSeq library construction kit according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions (Illumina, San Diego, CA). A total of 6 libraries with insert sizes ranging from 250&#x02009;bp to 20&#x02009;kb were constructed for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>chinensis</italic> and one library with a 350-bp insert size was constructed for <italic>C. praecox</italic>. The libraries were then sequenced on the Illumina HiSeqXTen platform. For the 10X Genomics library, about 1&#x02009;ng input DNA with an average 50&#x02009;kb length was used for the GEM reaction procedure during PCR, and 16-bp barcodes were introduced into droplets. The droplets were then fractured followed by final purification of the DNA library. A total of six libraries were finally sequenced on the Illumina HiseqXTen.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Genome assembly and assessment of the assembly quality</title><p id="Par40">De novo assembly of the PacBio reads was performed using the FALCON assembler [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>] (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/PacificBiosciences/FALCON/">https://github.com/PacificBiosciences/FALCON/</ext-link>). Before assembly, we used FALCON to correct the PacBio reads and then assemble them into contigs with parameters (length_cutoff_pr&#x02009;=&#x02009;4000, max_diff&#x02009;=&#x02009;100, max_cov&#x02009;=&#x02009;100). This resulted in primary contigs (p-contigs) that were then polished using Quiver [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>] by aligning SMRT reads. Pilon was used to perform the second round of error correction with short paired-end reads generated from Illumina HiSeq Platforms. For the scaffolding step, Long Ranger (version 2.1.2) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://support.10xgenomics.com/genome-exome/software/pipelines/latest/installation">https://support.10xgenomics.com/genome-exome/software/pipelines/latest/installation</ext-link>) was first used to build scaffolds using 10X data. FragScaff (version 1.1) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>] was further applied to build super-scaffolds using the barcoded sequencing reads.</p><p id="Par41">We applied both CEGMA (Core Eukaryotic Gene Mapping Approach) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>] and BUSCO (V3, Benchmarking Universal Single-Copy Orthologs) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>] to evaluate the completeness of the assembly.</p><p id="Par42">For the assembly of <italic>C. chinensis</italic>, we first used SOAPdenovo [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>] to filter duplicates, adaptor contamination, and low-quality bases from Illumina PE reads before assembling them into preliminary scaffolds. Then GapCloser (version 1.12) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>] from the SOAPdenovo package was used for gap filling within assembled scaffolds using all pair-end reads. Lastly, SSPACE [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>] was used to improve the assembled genome.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Chromosome assignment using Hi-C</title><p id="Par43">One Dovetail Hi-C library was prepared in a similar manner as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]. The library was sequenced on an Illumina HiSeq platform. The number and length of read pairs produced for the library was 431 million and 2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;100&#x000a0;bp respectively. The Dovetail Hi-C library reads provided 93.06&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;physical coverage of the genome (1&#x02013;50&#x02009;kb pairs). The Hi-C sequencing data was aligned to the assembled contigs with BWA-mem [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>], and then clustered onto chromosomes with LACHESIS (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://shendurelab.github.io/LACHESIS/">http://shendurelab.github.io/LACHESIS/</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Repeat and non-coding RNA annotation</title><p id="Par44">We used two complementary methods (one homology-based and de novo-based) to discover and classify transposable elements (TEs). The homology-based repeat library was generated from a known repeat library (Repbase 15.02) using RepeatMasker (version 3.3.0) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]. RepeatModeler (Vision 1.0.5) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.repeatmasker.org/">http://www.repeatmasker.org/</ext-link>), RepeatScout [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>], Piler, and LTR_FINDER [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>] were used to build the de novo-based repeat library. RepeatProteinMask was performed to detect TEs in the <italic>C. praecox</italic> and <italic>C. chinensis</italic> genome by comparing the TE protein database. The integrated repeat library was finally annotated by the Tandem Repeats Finder (TRF) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>]. The tRNA genes were predicted using tRNAscan-SE software [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]. The rRNA, miRNA, and snRNA fragments were predicted using INFERNAL software [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>] with searches against the Rfam database (release 9.1) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Structural and functional annotation of genes</title><p id="Par45">We adapted a combination of three strategies that include (1) de novo predictions, (2) homolog-based predictions, and (3) RNA-seq-based predictions to annotate the protein-coding genes in the <italic>C. praecox</italic> and <italic>C. chinensis</italic> genomes. De novo predictions were carried out using five ab initio gene prediction programs that include Augustus (version 3.0.2) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>], Genscan (version 1.0) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>], Geneid [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>], GlimmerHMM (version 3.0.2) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>], and SNAP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>]. For the homolog-based predictions, the protein sequences of six species namely <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, <italic>Oryza sativa</italic>, <italic>Nelumbo nucifera</italic>, <italic>Beta vulgaris</italic>, <italic>Solanum lycopersicuma</italic>, and <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> were aligned against the repeat-masked genome using TBLASTN [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>] with a cutoff <italic>E</italic>-value of 10<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;5</sup>. Genewise (version 2.2.0) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>] was employed to predict gene models based on the alignment sequences. We used two methods to achieve RNA-seq-based predictions. One was mapping the RNA-seq data to the <italic>C. praecox</italic> and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>chinensis</italic> genome and assembling the transcripts using Tophat (version 2.0.8) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>] and cufflinks (version 2.1.1) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cufflinks.cbcb.umd.edu/">http://cufflinks.cbcb.umd.edu/</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>]. The other was applying Trinity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>] to assemble the RNA-seq data followed by the PASA software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pasapipeline.github.io/">http://pasapipeline.github.io/</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>] to improve the gene structures. To finalize the gene set, all the predictions were combined using EVidenceModeler (EVM) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>] to produce the non-redundant gene sets.</p><p id="Par46">Functional annotation of protein-coding genes was carried out by performing BLASTP (<italic>E</italic>-value &#x02264;1e<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;5</sup>) searches against SwissProt (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.uniprot.org/">http://www.uniprot.org/</ext-link>), TrEMBL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>], and NCBI non-redundant (NR) protein databases. Motifs and domains were annotated by using InterProScan (version 4.7) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>] to search against InterPro (v29.0) databases which include Pfam, PRINTS, PROSITE, ProDom, and SMART. The GO term [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>] for each gene was achieved from the corresponding InterPro descriptions. Additionally, the gene set was mapped to the KEGG (release 53) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>] pathway database to identify the best match classification for each gene.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Gene family and phylogenomic analysis</title><p id="Par47">To identify gene family groups, we analyzed protein-coding genes from 17 species, <italic>Amborella trichopoda</italic>, <italic>Ananas comosus</italic>, <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, <italic>Camellia sinensis, C. kanehirae</italic>, <italic>Daucus carota</italic>, <italic>Elaeis guineensis</italic>, <italic>L. chinense</italic>, <italic>Musa acuminata</italic>, <italic>N. nucifera</italic>, <italic>O. sativa</italic>, <italic>Papaver somniferum</italic>, <italic>Phalaenopsis equestris</italic>, <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic>, <italic>V. vinifera</italic>, <italic>C. praecox</italic>, and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>chinensis</italic> genomes. Orthologous gene groups of <italic>C. praecox</italic> and 16 other species were identified by running OrthoMCL program (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://orthomcl.org/orthomcl/">http://orthomcl.org/orthomcl/</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. We determined the expansion and contraction of the gene families by comparing the cluster size differences between the ancestor and each species using the CAF&#x000c9; program [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>].</p><p id="Par48">To infer the phylogenetic placements of wintersweet, two sets of single-copy genes (SSCG and OSCG) were identified using SonicParanoid [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>] v.1.0 and OrthoMCL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>] v.2.0.9 from 17 seed plants respectively. For each gene, amino acid sequences were aligned using MUSCLE [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>]. For each dataset SSCG and OSCG, the phylogenetic trees were constructed by both coalescent and concatenation approaches. For the coalescent approach, gene trees were inferred by IQ-TREE [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>] v.1.6.9; these gene trees were then used by ASTRAL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>] v.5.6.1 to construct species trees. The quartet score was estimated for each node showing quartet support for the species tree. For the concatenation-based analyses, the ML trees were inferred from the concatenated amino acid sequences using IQ-TREE [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>] v.1.6.9 with ultrafast bootstrap testing (1000 replicates) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref>]. For plastid genes, the extrons of 38 single-copy genes were extracted from 26 plastid genome sequences. We aligned these genes with MUSCLE [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>]. The concatenated amino acid sequences of these genes were used to infer the ML trees with RAxML [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref>]. The mcmctree program of PAML (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://abacus.gene.ucl.ac.uk/software/paml.html">http://abacus.gene.ucl.ac.uk/software/paml.html</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref>] was applied to estimate divergence time among 17 species with main parameters (burn-in&#x02009;=&#x02009;10,000, sample-number&#x02009;=&#x02009;100,000, and sample-frequency&#x02009;=&#x02009;2). Four calibration points were selected from articles and TimeTree website (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.timetree.org">http://www.timetree.org</ext-link>) as normal priors to restrain the age of the nodes, such as 105&#x02013;115 Mya between <italic>V. vinifera</italic> and <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, 110&#x02013;124 Mya between <italic>C. sinensis</italic> and <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, 148&#x02013;173 Mya between <italic>O. sativa</italic> and <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, and 94&#x02013;115 Mya between <italic>A. comosus</italic> and <italic>O. sativa</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Analysis of genome synteny and whole-genome duplication</title><p id="Par49">We performed synteny searches to identify syntenic blocks within <italic>C. praecox</italic> and between <italic>C. praecox</italic> and <italic>Amborella</italic> using MCScanX [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>]. Synonymous substitutions per synonymous site (<italic>K</italic>s) between colinear genes were estimated using the codeml approach as implemented in the PAML package [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref>]. Calculation and correction of Ks of collinear blocks with reference to Prickly waterlily and rigid hornwort genome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>] and Paleotetraploidization study in Cucurbitaceae [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>] as follows: Firstly, the median Ks values were selected to represent each syntenic block, and the probability density distribution curve of Ks was estimated using MATLAB with the kernel smoothing density function. Multipeak fitting of the curve was performed using the Gaussian approximation function (cftool) in MATLAB. Secondly, based on Ks distribution of <italic>Liriodendron</italic> and <italic>Cinnamomum</italic> described in Prickly waterlily and rigid hornwort genome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], the Ks correction coefficient of species of <italic>Magnolia</italic> were calculated and then we got the corrected Ks rate. The Dot plots between <italic>C. praecox</italic> and <italic>C. kanehirae</italic> as well as the <italic>L. chinense</italic> genome was generated with Quota synteny alignment software [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref>] to visualize the paleopolyploidy level of <italic>C. praecox</italic> in relation to <italic>C. kanehirae</italic> and <italic>L. chinense</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Ancestral genome reconstruction</title><p id="Par50">The ancestral genome of Laurales was reconstructed according to the procedure (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S15) as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref>]. The ancestral karyotype of <italic>C. praecox</italic>, <italic>C. chinensis</italic>, and <italic>C. kanehirae</italic> was first determined by genome alignments using cumulative identity percentage (CIP) and cumulative alignment length percentage (CALP) BLAST parameters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref>]. The coordinate of conserved genes among the three genomes were extracted from these alignments that belong to syntenic blocks identified by McscanX [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>]. Then the syntenic blocks were merged using GRIMM [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">101</xref>] to get the coordinate correspondence between the three collinear groups. Finally, the MGR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">102</xref>] software was used to rearrange the multiple genomes to get the ancestral gene orders.</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Comparative analysis of LTR retrotransposons</title><p id="Par51">Intact long terminal repeat retrotransposons (LTR) were identified by searching the genomes of <italic>C. praecox</italic> with LTRharvest [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">103</xref>] (-motif tgca -motifmis 1) and LTR_Finder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>] (LTR length 100 to 5000&#x02009;nt; length between two LTRs: 1000 to 20,000&#x02009;nt). A two-step procedure was used to filter the candidate sequences to reduce false positives. First, the primer binding site (PBS) motif was identified by LTR digest [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104">104</xref>] based on the predicted tRNA sequences from tRNAscan-SE [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>], and only elements that contained PBS were retained; next, protein domains (pol, gag, and env) in candidate LTR retrotransposons were identified by searching against HMM profiles collected by Gypsy Database (GyDB) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gydb.org/">http://gydb.org/</ext-link>). Elements containing a gag domain, protease domain, reverse transcriptase (RT) domain, and integrase domain were considered as intact. Second, families of these intact LTR retrotransposons were clustered using the SiLiX software package (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lbbe.univ-lyon1.fr/SiLiX">lbbe.univ-lyon1.fr/SiLiX</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105">105</xref>]. Finally, LTRs that did not contain protein domains or that belonged to families with less than 2 members were discarded. Each nucleic acid diversity (<italic>&#x003bb;</italic>) was calculated from the MUSLCE alignment of the 5&#x02032;and 3&#x02032; LTR sequences of LTR-RTs by EMBOSS program distmat. Using a substitution rate (<italic>r</italic>) of 1.51&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;9</sup> substitutions per site per year [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], the insertion date (<italic>T</italic>) was computed for each LTR-RT (<italic>T</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;<italic>K</italic>/2<italic>r</italic>, <italic>K</italic>: genetic distance, <italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;0.75ln(1&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;4<italic>&#x003bb;</italic>/3)).</p><p id="Par52">The sequences of intact LTR-RT identified in <italic>C. praecox</italic>, <italic>C. chinensis</italic>, <italic>C. kanehirae</italic>, and <italic>L. chinense</italic> genomes were translated according to 3-frames. The translated amino acid sequences were then searched for the <italic>Ty1/Copia</italic> (PF07727) and <italic>Ty3/Gypsy</italic> (PF000078) domains using HMMER (version 3.1b2, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hmmer.org">http://hmmer.org</ext-link>) (E-value &#x02264;1e<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;5</sup>). The target hit amino acid sequences of <italic>Copia</italic> and <italic>Gypsy</italic> superfamilies were aligned using mafft (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://mafft.cbrc.jp/alignment/software/">https://mafft.cbrc.jp/alignment/software/</ext-link>) with default parameters. The phylogenetic trees of <italic>Copia</italic>-like and <italic>Gypsy</italic>-like LTR-RTs were constructed using fastTree (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.microbesonline.org/fasttree/">http://www.microbesonline.org/fasttree/</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Histological examination</title><p id="Par53">To investigate the floral developmental characteristics of wintersweet, we performed a detailed developmental study from the initiation to the opening of the flower bud. Data collection was initiated on the day that the floral buds were visible to the naked eye. The sampling of <italic>C. praecox</italic> began on April 11, 2016, and ended on February 6, 2017. Ten axillary buds on current-year-old short branches were collected at random every 7&#x02009;days from three trees. Five homogenized buds were used for histological examination and the others were frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at &#x02212;&#x02009;80&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for further RNA sequencing.</p><p id="Par54">Flower buds at various stages of development were fixed in FAA (70% ethanol: formalin: acetic acid&#x02009;=&#x02009;5:5:90) for more than 24&#x02009;h. Then, 8-&#x003bc;m-thick microtome sections were made after embedding in paraffin wax. These sections were mounted on slides and stained with 1% safranine and 0.5% fast green. Slides were visually examined and photographed using a Nikon Eclipse 80i digital imaging microscope equipped with an electronic photo system. Based on the observation and the annual morphological changes of flower buds, we divided the flower developmental process into nine stages (FBS1&#x02013;9) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a).</p></sec><sec id="Sec25"><title>RNA isolation, library construction, and sequencing</title><p id="Par55">The flower buds or whole flowers with three biological replicates were harvested at 14 stages including FBS1&#x02013;9 and S1&#x02013;5 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Fig. S18) respectively. Total RNA from flower buds or whole flowers at different stages was extracted using an RNA prep pure Plant RNA Purification Kit (Tiangen Biotech, Beijing, China). RNA quality was verified using an Agilent 2100 (Agilent Technologies, CA, USA) plus electrophoresis system. A total of 42 cDNA libraries were prepared and sequenced on an Illumina HiSeq 2500 platform using paired-end cycles.</p></sec><sec id="Sec26"><title>Analysis of genes involved in the formation of floral scent</title><p id="Par56">Using terpene and phenylpropanoid biosynthesis pathway genes in <italic>A. thaliana</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>] and <italic>Petunia hybrida</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>] as bait, the corresponding genes in <italic>C. praecox</italic> were identified based on genome annotation and local blast search against wintersweet genome with a filtered parameter (<italic>E</italic>-value &#x0003c;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;5</sup>, identity &#x02265;50%, and coverage &#x02265;30%). For larger-size gene families, the genes were determined by combining local blast reports and phylogenetic analysis to distinguish the orthologs of corresponding functionally characterized genes.</p><p id="Par57">To identify the <italic>CpTPS</italic> genes in <italic>C. praecox</italic> and <italic>C. chinensis</italic>, two Pfam domains: PF01397 and PF03936 were used to search against the proteome using HMMER [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106">106</xref>]. The target hits (<italic>E</italic>-value &#x0003c;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;5</sup>) were identified as candidate terpene synthase genes. Synteny and collinearity between these genes were analyzed using MCScanX [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>]. Based on the chromosome location in the gff files, the structure and chromosomal distribution of <italic>CpTPS</italic> genes were illustrated with TBtools [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107">107</xref>]. The 2000-bp region upstream of <italic>CpTPS</italic> genes was defined as the promoter region, in which the cis-acting regulatory elements were identified with PlantCARE [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108">108</xref>] and PLACE [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109">109</xref>] databases. A heat map was generated with the TBtools [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107">107</xref>] based on the expression level of wintersweet <italic>TPS</italic> genes at different floral developmental stages. <italic>A. thaliana</italic> and <italic>O. sativa TPSs</italic> were downloaded from phytozome (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://phytozome.jgi.doe.gov/pz/portal.html">https://phytozome.jgi.doe.gov/pz/portal.html</ext-link>). All the phylogenetic trees of functional genes were constructed by maximum likelihood method with MEGAX [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110">110</xref>] using the amino acid sequence alignments generated by ClustalX [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111">111</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec27"><title>Characterization of the <italic>TPS</italic> genes</title><p id="Par58">The ORF of the three <italic>TPS</italic> genes (<italic>CpTPS4</italic>, <italic>CpTPS9</italic>, and <italic>CpTPS42</italic>) were isolated and subcloned into the BamHI/XhoI sites of pET28a using ClonExpress II One Step Cloning Kit (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.vazymebiotech.com/index.html">http://www.vazymebiotech.com/index.html</ext-link>) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s introductions. The recombinant plasmids and pET28a lacking an insert (control) were transformed into <italic>E. coli</italic> BL21 (DE3) competent cells. After 0.5&#x02009;mM IPTG induction at 16&#x02009;&#x000b0;C overnight, the proteins were harvested and purified by affinity chromatography on nickel-nitrilotriacetic acid-agarose (Qiagen, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.qiagen.com">http://www.qiagen.com</ext-link>). The purity of the isolated proteins was verified by the densitometry of the SDS-PAGE gels after Coomassie Brilliant Blue staining. The concentration of purified proteins was determined by the Bradford method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112">112</xref>].</p><p id="Par59">Assays for TPS protein activity were carried out in a 1&#x02009;ml assay buffer (30&#x02009;mM HEPES, pH 7.5, 5&#x02009;mM DTT, 25&#x02009;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>) containing 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;g purified CpTPS proteins and 60&#x003bc;&#x0039c; GPP/FPP. The mixture was incubated at 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for an hour and then 45&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 15&#x02009;min. After incubation, the synthesized volatiles were collected using the DVB/CAR/PDMS headspace sampler and analyzed as Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Supplementary Note 2.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><sec id="Sec28"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="13059_2020_2088_MOESM1_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 1: Table S1.</bold> Summary of sequencing data of <italic>Chimonanthus praecox</italic> and <italic>Calycanthus chinensis</italic> genome. Table S2. Estimation of genome size of <italic>Chimonanthus praecox</italic> and <italic>Calycanthus chinensis</italic> using K-mer analysis. Table S3. Statistic of <italic>Chimonanthus praecox</italic> and <italic>Calycanthus chinensis</italic> genome assembly. Table S4. Chromosomes length of wintersweet using HiC reads. Table S5. Assembly results of wintersweet using Hi-C. Table S6. Validation of genome assembly using BUSCO and CEGMA method. Table S7. Statistics of predicted protein-coding genes in <italic>Chimonanthus praecox</italic> and <italic>Calycanthus chinensis</italic> genome. Table S8. Functional annotation of the wintersweet protein-coding genes. Table S9. Annotation of conserved non-coding RNA genes in the wintersweet genome. Table S10. Wintersweet-specific gene families. Table S11. The list of expansion genes in wintersweet genome. Table S12. Annotation of repeat sequences in the wintersweet genome. Table S13. List of flowering-time and floral organ identity gene candidates in wintersweet. Table S14. The upregulated expressed genes involved in flowering networks in FBS1 stage compared with FBS2 stage. Table S15. Monthly temperatures in Wuhan (March 2017&#x02013;February 2018). Table S16. Differently expressed genes between FBS6 and FBS7 stage. Table S17. List of Heat stress transcription factors (Hsf) and DEHYDRATION- RESPONSIVE ELEMENT BINDING PROTEIN (DREB) gene candidates identified in the wintersweet genome. Table S18.The candidate genes involved in the terpene synthesis pathways in wintersweet. Table S19. Terpene synthase family in wintersweet. Table S20. The candidate genes involved in the benzenoid/ phenylpropanoid synthesis pathways in wintersweet. Table S21. The list of transcription factor candidates involved in the regulation of VOCs synthesis in wintersweet. Table S22. Primers for <italic>CpTPS</italic> genes coloning and MADS-box B&#x00026;C class genes Real-Time PCR. Table S23. Transporter candidates involved in benzenoid/phenylpropanoid synthesis pathways in wintersweet genome. Table S24. Tandem duplicated gene clusters in wintersweet genome.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="13059_2020_2088_MOESM2_ESM.docx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 2: Fig. S1.</bold> Evaluation of Chimonanthus praecox genome by k-mer analysis and cell flow cytometry. Fig. S2. Hi-C map of the wintersweet genome showing genome-wide all-by-all interactions. Fig. S3. Chromosome biology of <italic>Chimonanthus praecox</italic> (a) and <italic>Calycanthus chinensis</italic>. Fig. S4. Annotation of the wintersweet-specific and expanded genes. Fig. S5. An uneven TE distribution across wintersweet genome and TE distribution in genic regions. Fig. S6. LTR insertion time estimation. Fig. S7. Phylogenetic analysis of wintersweet LTR retrotransposons. Fig. S8. Concatenated- and ASTRAL-based phylogenetic trees. Fig. S9. The phylogenetic tree based on 38 chloroplast genes from 26 species. Fig. S10. A phylogenetic tree of 29 plant species based on 2420 concatenated genes trees using RAxML. Fig. S11. Types of gene duplication in the wintersweet genome. Fig. S12. Duplications of genomic paralogous genes in wintersweet. Fig. S13. Distribution of synonymous substitution levels (Ks) of syntenic orthologous (solid curves) and paralogous genes (dashed curves). Fig. S14. Topologies of gene trees depicting the two possible scenarios of speciation among wintersweet and <italic>Liriodendron.</italic> Fig. S15. A modified pipeline of ancestral genome reconstruction. Fig. S16. Phylogenetic analysis of FT-like and SVP-like and the analysis of bud break and cell division (<italic>CpCDs</italic>) related genes and genes involved in phytohormone-related pathways. Fig. S17. Gas chromatogram of glycosidic floral volatiles from the flowers of wintersweet. Fig. S18. Changes of the major floral volatiles during flower development in wintersweet. Fig. S19. Subcellular location of CpTPS proteins. Fig. S20. Cluster and STEM analysis of differentially expressed TFs during flower development. Fig. S21. Promoter cis-element analysis of 52 <italic>CpTPSs</italic>. Fig. S22. Analysis of benzenoid carboxyl methyltransferases (<italic>BCMTs</italic>) and cell division (<italic>CpCDs</italic>) related genes. Fig. S23. Gene structure and classification of putative <italic>CpTPSs</italic>. Fig. S24. Annotation of the Tandem duplicated genes.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="13059_2020_2088_MOESM3_ESM.doc"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 3: Supplementary Note 1.</bold> Estimation of Genome Size and Chromosome Number Assessment; Identification of Orthologs of Flowering Time Genes; Identification of MADS-box Genes; Genes Expression Analysis. Supplementary Note 2. Headspace Collection and GC&#x02013;MS Analyses of Floral Volatiles; Changes of volatile compounds during flower development; Phylogenetic and Structural Analysis of TPS Family; Subcellular Location of the fused <italic>CpTPS4/9/42</italic>-fused green Fluorescent Protein; Construction of <italic>CpTPS4</italic> Overexpressed Tobacco Plants, Analysis of Transcription of Factors; Analysis of the genes involved in terpene and benzenoid biosynthesis transport. Supplementary Note 3. Tandem duplication analysis; The order of speciation and WGD event in <italic>Liriodendron</italic> and wintersweet lineage.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="13059_2020_2088_MOESM4_ESM.docx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 4.</bold> Review history.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p>Junzhong Shang, Jingpu Tian and Huihui Cheng contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p><bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1186/s13059-020-02088-y.</p></sec><ack><sec id="FPar1"><title>Review history</title><p id="Par60">The review history is available as Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Peer review information</title><p id="Par61">Barbara Cheifet was the primary editor on this article and managed its editorial process and peer review in collaboration with the rest of the editorial team.</p></sec></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>LC, XL, KZ, and SJ designed the study. HC, JS, and QY performed the analyses of the genome and transcriptome sequence. JT, JS, LL, SC, and AJ collected the samples and performed the experiments. JS wrote the manuscript. XL, KZ, and SJ revised the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This study was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 31870193, 31572165, 31272207, and 31972442) and &#x0201c;Thousand Talents Plan&#x0201d; of Yunnan Province-&#x0201c;High-End Foreign Experts&#x0201d; Project (No. 000019).</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>All raw sequencing reads have been deposited in the NCBI Sequence Read Archive (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra</ext-link>) under project PRJNA600650 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113">113</xref>].</p></notes><notes id="FPar3"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par62">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par63">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar5" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par64">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Renner</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular phylogeny and intra-and intercontinental biogeography of <italic>Calycanthaceae</italic></article-title><source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source><year>2006</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><?supplied-pmid 16495090?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16495090</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kubitzki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Kubitzki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohwer</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bittrich</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Calycanthaceae</article-title><source>The families and genera of vascular plants</source><year>1993</year><publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>200</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nicely</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A monographic study of the Calycanthaceae</article-title><source>Castanea.</source><year>1965</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>38</fpage><lpage>81</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition and biological activities of essential oil from flower of <italic>Chimonanthus praecox</italic> (L.) link</article-title><source>Lishizhen Med Material Med Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>622</fpage><lpage>625</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>LQ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptomic and proteomic approaches to explore the differences in monoterpene and benzenoid biosynthesis between scented and unscented genotypes of wintersweet</article-title><source>Physiol Plant</source><year>2019</year><volume>166</volume><fpage>478</fpage><lpage>493</lpage><?supplied-pmid 30216458?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30216458</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>ZN</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Sui</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Floral scent emission from Nectaries in the adaxial side of the innermost and middle petals in <italic>Chimonanthus praecox</italic></article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>3278</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid determination of volatile compounds emitted from <italic>Chimonanthus praecox</italic> flowers by HS-SPME-GC-MS</article-title><source>Z Naturforsch C</source><year>2004</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>636</fpage><lpage>640</lpage><?supplied-pmid 15540594?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15540594</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Azuma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Toyota</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Asakawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Floral scent chemistry and stamen movement of <italic>Chimonanthus praecox</italic> (L.) link (Calycanthaceae)</article-title><source>Acta Phytotaxonomica et Geobotanica</source><year>2005</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>201</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez-Moreiras</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Abel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sohrabi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gershenzon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tholl</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The major volatile organic compound emitted from <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> flowers, the sesquiterpene (E)-&#x003b2;-caryophyllene, is a defense against a bacterial pathogen</article-title><source>New Phytol</source><year>2012</year><volume>193</volume><fpage>997</fpage><lpage>1008</lpage><?supplied-pmid 22187939?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22187939</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>LQ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular cloning and expression of <italic>Chimonanthus praecox</italic> farnesyl pyrophosphate synthase gene and its possible involvement in the biosynthesis of floral volatile sesquiterpenoids</article-title><source>Plant Physiol Biochem</source><year>2010</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>845</fpage><lpage>850</lpage><?supplied-pmid 20855217?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20855217</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>An</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The control of flowering time by environmental factors</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2017</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>708</fpage><lpage>719</lpage><?supplied-pmid 27995671?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27995671</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The plant tree of life: an overview and some points of view</article-title><source>Am J Bot</source><year>2004</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>1437</fpage><lpage>1445</lpage><?supplied-pmid 21652302?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21652302</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaw</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Stout camphor tree genome fills gaps in understanding of flowering plant genome evolution</article-title><source>Nat Plants</source><year>2019</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>63</fpage><?supplied-pmid 30626928?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30626928</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>ZD</given-names></name><name><surname>Guang</surname><given-names>XM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>CX</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic>Liriodendron</italic> genome sheds light on angiosperm phylogeny and species&#x02013;pair differentiation</article-title><source>Nat Plants</source><year>2019</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>18</fpage><?supplied-pmid 30559417?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30559417</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rend&#x000f3;n-Anaya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibarra-Laclette</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bravo</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Carretero-Paulet</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The avocado genome informs deep angiosperm phylogeny, highlights introgressive hybridization, and reveals pathogen influenced gene space adaptation</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source><year>2019</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>17081</fpage><lpage>17089</lpage><?supplied-pmid 31387975?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31387975</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>ZP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The chromosome-scale reference genome of black pepper provides insight into piperine biosynthesis</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30602773</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ru</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prickly waterlily and rigid hornwort genomes shed light on early angiosperm evolution</article-title><source>Nat Plants</source><year>2020</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><?supplied-pmid 32094642?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32094642</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Peluso</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sedlazeck</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nattestad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Concepcion</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><name><surname>Clum</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Phased diploid genome assembly with single-molecule real-time sequencing</article-title><source>Nat Methods</source><year>2016</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1050</fpage><?supplied-pmid 27749838?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27749838</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Abeel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shea</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Priest</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Abouelliel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakthikumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pilon: an integrated tool for comprehensive microbial variant detection and genome assembly improvement</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e112963</fpage><?supplied-pmid 4237348?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25409509</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Krinsky</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New genes as drivers of phenotypic evolution</article-title><source>Nat Rev Genet</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>645</fpage><?supplied-pmid 23949544?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23949544</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wicker</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide comparative analysis of <italic>copia</italic> retrotransposons in Triticeae, rice, and Arabidopsis reveals conserved ancient evolutionary lineages and distinct dynamics of individual <italic>copia</italic> families</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1072</fpage><lpage>1081</lpage><?supplied-pmid 17556529?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17556529</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zuccolo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Scofield</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>De Paoli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgante</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Ty1-<italic>copia</italic> LTR retroelement family PARTC is highly conserved in conifers over 200 MY of evolution</article-title><source>Gene.</source><year>2015</year><volume>568</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><?supplied-pmid 25982862?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25982862</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoeckert</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>OrthoMCL: identification of ortholog groups for eukaryotic genomes</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>2178</fpage><lpage>2189</lpage><?supplied-pmid 12952885?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12952885</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cosentino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwasaki</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SonicParanoid: fast, accurate and easy orthology inference</article-title><source>Bioinformatics.</source><year>2019</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>151</lpage><?supplied-pmid 30032301?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30032301</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Massoni</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Couvreur</surname><given-names>TLP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauquet</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Five major shifts of diversification through the long evolutionary history of Magnoliidae (angiosperms)</article-title><source>BMC Evol Biol</source><year>2015</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>49</fpage><?supplied-pmid 25887386?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25887386</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Puttick</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenrick</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pressel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The timescale of early land plant evolution</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>E2274</fpage><lpage>E2283</lpage><?supplied-pmid 29463716?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29463716</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wendel</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyers</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wing</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of plant genome architecture</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>37</fpage><?supplied-pmid 26926526?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26926526</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbazuk</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><name><surname>Der</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Leebens-Mack</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Amborella genome and the evolution of flowering plants</article-title><source>Science.</source><year>2013</year><volume>342</volume><fpage>1241089</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24357323</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>QH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Statistical inference of chromosomal homology based on gene colinearity and applications to Arabidopsis and rice</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2006</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>447</fpage><?supplied-pmid 17038171?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17038171</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bouch&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lobet</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tocquin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rilleuxe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>FLOR-ID: an interactive database of flowering-time gene networks in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2015</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>D1167</fpage><lpage>D1171</lpage><?supplied-pmid 26476447?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26476447</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>No</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Strause</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>FLOWERING LOCUS T duplication coordinates reproductive and vegetative growth in perennial poplar</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2011</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>10756</fpage><lpage>10761</lpage><?supplied-pmid 21653885?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21653885</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000fc;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Control of chrysanthemum flowering through integration with an aging pathway</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>829</fpage><?supplied-pmid 29018260?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29018260</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohama</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional regulatory network of plant heat stress response</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><?supplied-pmid 27666516?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27666516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>XM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The AGL6-like gene <italic>CpAGL6</italic>, a potential regulator of floral time and organ identity in wintersweet (<italic>Chimonanthus praecox</italic>)</article-title><source>J Plant Growth Regul</source><year>2011</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>352</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruelens</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>De Maagd</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Proost</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Theien</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Geuten</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaufmann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>FLOWERING LOCUS C in monocots and the tandem origin of angiosperm-specific MADS-box genes</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>2280</fpage><?supplied-pmid 23955420?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23955420</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Stilio</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name><surname>Schl&#x000fc;ter</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complex patterns of gene duplication in the <italic>APETALA3</italic> and <italic>PISTILLATA</italic> lineages of the Ranunculaceae</article-title><source>Int J Plant Sci</source><year>2003</year><volume>164</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jim&#x000e9;nez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Reighard</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bielenberg</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene expression of <italic>DAM5</italic> and <italic>DAM6</italic> is suppressed by chilling temperatures and inversely correlated with bud break rate</article-title><source>Plant Mol Biol</source><year>2010</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>167</lpage><?supplied-pmid 20143130?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20143130</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamane</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ooka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Jotatsu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Akagi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional and expressional analyses of PmDAM genes associated with endodormancy in Japanese apricot</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2011</year><volume>157</volume><fpage>485</fpage><lpage>497</lpage><?supplied-pmid 21795580?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21795580</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Maurya</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Azeez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Miskolczi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tylewicz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stojkovi&#x0010d;</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A genetic network mediating the control of bud break in hybrid aspen</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>4173</fpage><?supplied-pmid 30301891?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30301891</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherif</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hormonal orchestration of bud dormancy cycle in deciduous woody perennials</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1136</fpage><?supplied-pmid 31620159?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31620159</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Graphery</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwab</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Attractive but toxic: emerging roles of glycosidically bound volatiles and glycosyltransferases involved in their formation</article-title><source>Mol Plant</source><year>2018</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1225</fpage><lpage>1236</lpage><?supplied-pmid 30223041?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30223041</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sesquiterpene glucosylation mediated by glucosyltransferase UGT91Q2 is involved in the modulation of cold stress tolerance in tea plants</article-title><source>New Phytol</source><year>2019</year><volume>226</volume><fpage>362</fpage><lpage>372</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vranov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Coman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruissem</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Network analysis of the MVA and MEP pathways for isoprenoid synthesis</article-title><source>Annu Rev Plant Biol</source><year>2013</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>665</fpage><lpage>700</lpage><?supplied-pmid 23451776?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23451776</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Tholl</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohlmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pichersky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The family of terpene synthases in plants: a mid-size family of genes for specialized metabolism that is highly diversified throughout the kingdom</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2011</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>212</fpage><lpage>229</lpage><?supplied-pmid 21443633?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21443633</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudareva</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The shikimate pathway and aromatic amino acid biosynthesis in plants</article-title><source>Annu Rev Plant Biol</source><year>2012</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><?supplied-pmid 22554242?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22554242</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudareva</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Completion of the cytosolic post-chorismate phenylalanine biosynthetic pathway in plants</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>15</fpage><?supplied-pmid 30604768?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30604768</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aranovich</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewinsohn</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaccai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Post-harvest enhancement of aroma in transgenic lisianthus (<italic>Eustoma grandiflorum</italic>) using the <italic>Clarkia breweri</italic> benzyl alcohol acetyltransferase (<italic>BEAT</italic>) gene</article-title><source>Postharvest Biol Technol</source><year>2007</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>255</fpage><lpage>260</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Taxonomy geographical distribution and evolution of Calycanthaceae</article-title><source>J Beijing Forestry University</source><year>1999</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>11</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sui</surname><given-names>SZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Generation and analysis of expressed sequence tags from <italic>Chimonanthus praecox</italic> (Wintersweet) flowers for discovering stress-responsive and floral development-related genes</article-title><source>Comparative Functional Genomics</source><year>2012</year><volume>2012</volume><fpage>134596</fpage><?supplied-pmid 22536115?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22536115</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leebens-Mack</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Raubeson</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuehl</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Fourcade</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Fourcade</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identifying the basal angiosperm node in chloroplast genome phylogenies: sampling one's way out of the Felsenstein zone</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2005</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1948</fpage><lpage>1963</lpage><?supplied-pmid 15944438?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15944438</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>HZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resolution of deep angiosperm phylogeny using conserved nuclear genes and estimates of early divergence times</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>4956</fpage><?supplied-pmid 25249442?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25249442</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Amborella not a &#x0201c;basal angiosperm&#x0201d;? Not so fast</article-title><source>Am J Bot</source><year>2004</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>997</fpage><lpage>1001</lpage><?supplied-pmid 21653455?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21653455</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leebens-Mack</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Deyholos</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Gitzendanner</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>One thousand plant transcriptomes and the phylogenomics of green plants</article-title><source>Nature.</source><year>2019</year><volume>574</volume><fpage>679</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31645766</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The wax gourd genomes offer insights into the genetic diversity and ancestral cucurbit karyotype</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>5158</fpage><?supplied-pmid 31727887?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31727887</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sauquet</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Balthazar</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Magall&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Endress</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailes</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The ancestral flower of angiosperms and its early diversification</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>16047</fpage><?supplied-pmid 28763051?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28763051</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of <italic>SVP</italic> in the control of flowering time by ambient temperature in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2007</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>397</fpage><lpage>402</lpage><?supplied-pmid 17322399?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17322399</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salamov</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Solovyev</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ab initio gene finding in <italic>Drosophila</italic> genomic DNA</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>516</fpage><lpage>522</lpage><?supplied-pmid 10779491?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10779491</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Marks</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Klammer</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Drake</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Heiner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nonhybrid, finished microbial genome assemblies from long-read SMRT sequencing data</article-title><source>Nat Methods</source><year>2013</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>563</fpage><?supplied-pmid 23644548?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23644548</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitzman</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Daza</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Christiansen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>In vitro, long-range sequence information for de novo genome assembly via transposase contiguity</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>2041</fpage><lpage>2049</lpage><?supplied-pmid 25327137?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25327137</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parra</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradnam</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Korf</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CEGMA: a pipeline to accurately annotate core genes in eukaryotic genomes</article-title><source>Bioinformatics.</source><year>2007</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1061</fpage><lpage>1067</lpage><?supplied-pmid 17332020?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17332020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sim&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Waterhouse</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ioannidis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kriventseva</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name><surname>Zdobnov</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BUSCO: assessing genome assembly and annotation completeness with single-copy orthologs</article-title><source>Bioinformatics.</source><year>2015</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>3210</fpage><lpage>3212</lpage><?supplied-pmid 26059717?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26059717</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>RQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>XD</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>ZB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>De novo assembly of human genomes with massively parallel short read sequencing</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>272</lpage><?supplied-pmid 20019144?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20019144</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SOAPdenovo2: an empirically improved memory-efficient short-read de novo assembler</article-title><source>Gigascience.</source><year>2012</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>18</fpage><?supplied-pmid 23587118?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23587118</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boetzer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Henkel</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name><name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pirovano</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Scaffolding pre-assembled contigs using SSPACE</article-title><source>Bioinformatics.</source><year>2010</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>578</fpage><lpage>579</lpage><?supplied-pmid 21149342?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21149342</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lieberman-Aiden</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Berkum</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Imakaev</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ragoczy</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Telling</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive mapping of long-range interactions reveals folding principles of the human genome</article-title><source>Science.</source><year>2009</year><volume>326</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>293</lpage><?supplied-pmid 19815776?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19815776</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Durbin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fast and accurate short read alignment with Burrows-Wheeler transform</article-title><source>Bioinformatics.</source><year>2009</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1754</fpage><lpage>1760</lpage><?supplied-pmid 19451168?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19451168</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Using Repeat Masker to identify repetitive elements in genomic sequences</article-title><source>Curr Protoc Bioinformatics</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>4</fpage><lpage>10</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pevzner</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>De novo identification of repeat families in large genomes</article-title><source>Bioinformatics.</source><year>2005</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>i351</fpage><lpage>i358</lpage><?supplied-pmid 15961478?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15961478</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>LTR_FINDER: an efficient tool for the prediction of full-length LTR retrotransposons</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>W265</fpage><lpage>W268</lpage><?supplied-pmid 17485477?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17485477</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tandem repeats finder: a program to analyze DNA sequences</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>573</fpage><lpage>580</lpage><?supplied-pmid 148217?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9862982</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>tRNAscan-SE: a program for improved detection of transfer RNA genes in genomic sequence</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1997</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>955</fpage><lpage>964</lpage><?supplied-pmid 9023104?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9023104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nawrocki</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolbe</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Infernal 1.0: inference of RNA alignments</article-title><source>Bioinformatics.</source><year>2009</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1335</fpage><lpage>1337</lpage><?supplied-pmid 19307242?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19307242</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Griffiths-Jones</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Moxon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Khanna</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bateman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rfam: annotating non-coding RNAs in complete genomes</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>D121</fpage><lpage>D124</lpage><?supplied-pmid 15608160?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15608160</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Stanke M, Schoffmann O, Morgenstern, B, Waack S Gene prediction in eukaryotes with a generalized hidden Markov model that uses hints from external sources. BMC Bioinformatics 2006;7:62.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parra</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanco</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Guig&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Geneid in drosophila</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>511</fpage><lpage>515</lpage><?supplied-pmid 10779490?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10779490</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Majoros</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Pertea</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TigrScan and GlimmerHMM: two open source ab initio eukaryotic gene-finders</article-title><source>Bioinformatics.</source><year>2004</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>2878</fpage><lpage>2879</lpage><?supplied-pmid 15145805?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15145805</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Korf</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene finding in novel genomes</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>59</fpage><?supplied-pmid 421630?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15144565</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR78"><label>78.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Madden</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x000e4;ffer</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gapped BLAST and PSI-BLAST: a new generation of protein database search programs</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1997</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>3389</fpage><lpage>3402</lpage><?supplied-pmid 9254694?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9254694</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR79"><label>79.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Birney</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Clamp</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Durbin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GeneWise and genomewise</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>988</fpage><lpage>995</lpage><?supplied-pmid 15123596?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15123596</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR80"><label>80.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pachter</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TopHat: discovering splice junctions with RNA-Seq</article-title><source>Bioinformatics.</source><year>2009</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1105</fpage><lpage>1111</lpage><?supplied-pmid 19289445?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19289445</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR81"><label>81.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pertea</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mortazavi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Baren</surname><given-names>MJV</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wold</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pachter</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcript assembly and quantification by RNA-Seq reveals unannotated transcripts and isoform switching during cell differentiation</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2010</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>511</fpage><?supplied-pmid 3146043?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20436464</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR82"><label>82.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grabherr</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yassour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Amit</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Full-length transcriptome assembly from RNA-Seq data without a reference genome</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2011</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>644</fpage><?supplied-pmid 3571712?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21572440</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR83"><label>83.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Haas BJ, Delcher AL, Mount SM, Wortman JR, Jr RKS, Hannick LI, et al. Improving the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> genome annotation using maximal transcript alignment assemblies. Nucleic Acids Res 2003;31:5654&#x02013;5666.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR84"><label>84.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Pertea</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Orvis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Buell</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wortman</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Automated eukaryotic gene structure annotation using EVidenceModeler and the program to assemble spliced alignments</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2008</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>R7</fpage><?supplied-pmid 2395244?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18190707</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR85"><label>85.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bairoch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Apweiler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The SWISS-PROT protein sequence database and its supplement TrEMBL in 2000</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><?supplied-pmid 10592178?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10592178</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR86"><label>86.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zdobnov</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Apweiler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>InterProScan&#x02013;an integration platform for the signature-recognition methods in InterPro</article-title><source>Bioinformatics.</source><year>2001</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>847</fpage><lpage>848</lpage><?supplied-pmid 11590104?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11590104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR87"><label>87.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashburner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Blake</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Botstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheery</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gene ontology: tool for the unification of biology</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2000</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>25</fpage><?supplied-pmid 3037419?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10802651</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR88"><label>88.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kanehisa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>KEGG: Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><?supplied-pmid 10592173?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10592173</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR89"><label>89.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bie</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Cristianini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Demuth</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CAFE: a computational tool for the study of gene family evolution</article-title><source>Bioinformatics.</source><year>2006</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1269</fpage><lpage>1271</lpage><?supplied-pmid 16543274?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16543274</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR90"><label>90.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MUSCLE: multiple sequence alignment with high accuracy and high throughput</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>1792</fpage><lpage>1797</lpage><?supplied-pmid 390337?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15034147</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR91"><label>91.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Haeseler</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Minh</surname><given-names>BQ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>IQ-TREE: a fast and effective stochastic algorithm for estimating maximum-likelihood phylogenies</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2015</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>268</fpage><lpage>274</lpage><?supplied-pmid 25371430?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25371430</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR92"><label>92.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoang</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Chernomor</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Haeseler</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Minh</surname><given-names>BQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Vinh</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>UFBoot2: improving the ultrafast bootstrap approximation</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2018</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>518</fpage><lpage>522</lpage><?supplied-pmid 29077904?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29077904</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR93"><label>93.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stamatakis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RAxML-VI-HPC: maximum likelihood-based phylogenetic analyses with thousands of taxa and mixed models</article-title><source>Bioinformatics.</source><year>2006</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>2688</fpage><lpage>2290</lpage><?supplied-pmid 16928733?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16928733</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR94"><label>94.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PAML 4: phylogenetic analysis by maximum likelihood</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2007</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1586</fpage><lpage>1591</lpage><?supplied-pmid 17483113?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17483113</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR95"><label>95.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Debarry</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MCScanX: a toolkit for detection and evolutionary analysis of gene synteny and collinearity</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>e49</fpage><?supplied-pmid 22217600?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22217600</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR96"><label>96.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An overlooked Paleotetraploidization in Cucurbitaceae</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2018</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><?supplied-pmid 29029269?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29029269</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR97"><label>97.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyons</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnable</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Paterson</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Freeling</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Screening synteny blocks in pairwise genome comparisons through integer programming</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2011</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>102</fpage><?supplied-pmid 21501495?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21501495</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR98"><label>98.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murat</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>RZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Guizard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gavranovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinbach</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Quesneville</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Karyotype and gene order evolution from reconstructed extinct ancestors highlight contrasts in genome plasticity of modern Rosid crops</article-title><source>Genome Biol Evol</source><year>2015</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>735</fpage><lpage>749</lpage><?supplied-pmid 25637221?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25637221</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR99"><label>99.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murat</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Armero</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pont</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Klopp</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Salse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reconstructing the genome of the most recent common ancestor of flowering plants</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2017</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>490</fpage><lpage>496</lpage><?supplied-pmid 28288112?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28288112</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR100"><label>100.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Abrouk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Murat</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Quraishi</surname><given-names>UM</given-names></name><name><surname>Feuillet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improved criteria and comparative genomics tool provide new insights into grass paleogenomics</article-title><source>Brief Bioinform</source><year>2009</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>619</fpage><lpage>630</lpage><?supplied-pmid 19720678?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19720678</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR101"><label>101.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bourque</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pevzner</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomescale evolution: reconstructing gene orders in the ancestral species</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>26</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><?supplied-pmid 11779828?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11779828</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR102"><label>102.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lowcay</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Shahab</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourque</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>webMGR: an online tool for the multiple genome rearrangement problem</article-title><source>Bioinformatics.</source><year>2009</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>408</fpage><lpage>410</lpage><?supplied-pmid 20022974?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20022974</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR103"><label>103.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ellinghaus</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurtz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Willhoeft</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>LTRharvest, an efficient and flexible software for de novo detection of LTR retrotransposons</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2008</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>18</fpage><?supplied-pmid 18194517?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18194517</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR104"><label>104.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steinbiss</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Willhoeft</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Gremme</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurtz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fine-grained annotation and classification of de novo predicted LTR retrotransposons</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>7002</fpage><lpage>7013</lpage><?supplied-pmid 19786494?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19786494</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR105"><label>105.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miele</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Penel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Duret</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ultra-fast sequence clustering from similarity networks with SiLiX</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2011</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>116</fpage><?supplied-pmid 21513511?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21513511</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR106"><label>106.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>nhmmer: DNA homology search with profile HMMs</article-title><source>Bioinformatics.</source><year>2013</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>2487</fpage><lpage>2489</lpage><?supplied-pmid 23842809?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23842809</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR107"><label>107.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chen CJ, Xia R, Chen H, He YH. TBtools, a toolkit for biologists integrating various biological data handling tools with a user-friendly interface. BioRxiv. 2018;289660. 10.1016/j.molp.2020.06.009.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR108"><label>108.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lescot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x000e9;hais</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Thijs</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreau</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Peer</surname><given-names>YVD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rouz&#x000e9;et</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rombauts</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PlantCARE, a database of plant cis-acting regulatory elements and a portal to tools for in silico analysis of promoter sequences</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>325</fpage><lpage>327</lpage><?supplied-pmid 11752327?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11752327</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR109"><label>109.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Higo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ugawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwamoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Korenagaet</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant cis-acting regulatory DNA elements (PLACE) database: 1999</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>297</fpage><lpage>300</lpage><?supplied-pmid 9847208?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9847208</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR110"><label>110.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Knyaz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MEGA X: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis across computing platforms</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2018</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>1547</fpage><lpage>1549</lpage><?supplied-pmid 29722887?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29722887</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR111"><label>111.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Larkin</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Blackshields</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Chenna</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>McGettiganet</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>McWilliam</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clustal W and Clustal X version 2.0</article-title><source>Bioinformatics.</source><year>2007</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>2947</fpage><lpage>2948</lpage><?supplied-pmid 17846036?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17846036</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR112"><label>112.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradford</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A rapid and sensitive method for the quantitation of microgram quantities of protein utilizing the principle of protein-dye binding</article-title><source>Anal Biochem</source><year>1976</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>248</fpage><lpage>254</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">942051</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR113"><label>113.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Shang JZ, Tian JP, Cheng HH, Yan QM, Li L, Jamal A, Xu ZP, Xiang L, Saski C, Jin SX, Zhao KG, Liu XQ, Chen LQ. Wintersweet (<italic>Chimonanthus praecox</italic>) Genome sequencing, assembly, resequencing and RNA sequencing. NCBI Sequence Read Archive, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/bioproject/PRJNA600650">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/bioproject/PRJNA600650</ext-link> (2020).</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>