<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Plant Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Plant Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-462X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6110934</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2018.01222</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Plant Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Generalist and Specialist Mite Herbivores Induce Similar Defense Responses in Maize and Barley but Differ in Susceptibility to Benzoxazinoids</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bui</surname><given-names>Huyen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn002"><sup>&#x02020;</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/584700/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Greenhalgh</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn002"><sup>&#x02020;</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ruckert</surname><given-names>Alice</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>Gunbharpur S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/568674/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Sarah</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>Ricardo A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>Richard M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/567434/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>School of Biological Sciences, University of Utah</institution>, <addr-line>Salt Lake City, UT</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Department of Biology, Utah State University</institution>, <addr-line>Logan, UT</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Center for Cell and Genome Science, University of Utah</institution>, <addr-line>Salt Lake City, UT</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Raul Antonio Sperotto, University of Taquari Valley, Brazil</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Mercedes Diaz-Mendoza, Centre for Plant Biotechnology and Genomics, Spain; Vasileios Fotopoulos, Cyprus University of Technology, Cyprus</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Richard M. Clark, <email>richard.m.clark@utah.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p><sup>&#x02020;</sup>These authors have contributed equally to this work</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn003"><p>This article was submitted to Plant Microbe Interactions, a section of the journal Frontiers in Plant Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>1222</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2018 Bui, Greenhalgh, Ruckert, Gill, Lee, Ramirez and Clark.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Bui, Greenhalgh, Ruckert, Gill, Lee, Ramirez and Clark</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>While substantial progress has been made in understanding defense responses of cereals to insect herbivores, comparatively little is known about responses to feeding by spider mites. Nevertheless, several spider mite species, including the generalist <italic>Tetranychus urticae</italic> and the grass specialist <italic>Oligonychus pratensis</italic>, cause damage on cereals such as maize and wheat, especially during drought stress. To understand defense responses of cereals to spider mites, we characterized the transcriptomic responses of maize and barley to herbivory by both mite species, and included a wounding control against which modulation of defenses could be tested. <italic>T. urticae</italic> and <italic>O. pratensis</italic> induced highly correlated changes in gene expression on both maize and barley. Within 2 h, hundreds of genes were upregulated, and thousands of genes were up- or downregulated after 24 h. In general, expression changes were similar to those induced by wounding, including for genes associated with jasmonic acid biosynthesis and signaling. Many genes encoding proteins involved in direct defenses, or those required for herbivore-induced plant volatiles, were strongly upregulated in response to mite herbivory. Further, biosynthesis genes for benzoxazinoids, which are specialized compounds of Poaceae with known roles in deterring insect herbivores, were induced in maize. Compared to chewing insects, spider mites are cell content feeders and cause grossly different patterns of tissue damage. Nonetheless, the gene expression responses of maize to both mite herbivores, including for phytohormone signaling pathways and for the synthesis of the benzoxazinoid 2-hydroxy-4,7-dimethoxy-1,4-benzoxazin-3-one glucoside, a known defensive metabolite against caterpillars, resembled those reported for a generalist chewing insect, <italic>Spodoptera exigua</italic>. On maize plants harboring mutations in several benzoxazinoid biosynthesis genes, <italic>T. urticae</italic> performance dramatically increased compared to wild-type plants. In contrast, no difference in performance was observed between mutant and wild-type plants for the specialist <italic>O. pratensis</italic>. Collectively, our data provide little evidence that maize and barley defense responses differentiate herbivory between <italic>T. urticae</italic> and <italic>O. pratensis</italic>. Further, our work suggests that the likely route to specialization for <italic>O. pratensis</italic> involved the evolution of a robust mechanism to cope with the benzoxazinoid defenses of its cereal hosts.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic> L.)</kwd><kwd><italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Tetranychus urticae</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Oligonychus pratensis</italic></kwd><kwd>benzoxazinoid</kwd><kwd>spider mite</kwd><kwd>herbivore</kwd><kwd>HDMBOA</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001">National Science Foundation<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/100000001</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn001">1444449</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn002">National Institutes of Health<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/100000001</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn002">TM32GM007464</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="7"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="101"/><page-count count="19"/><word-count count="0"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Cereal crops of the grass family (Poaceae) account for the majority of human calories, and reductions in their yield dramatically impact human welfare. Abiotic factors, such as drought, are a major source of unrealized yield (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Boyer, 1982</xref>), while another well-characterized source of loss is from herbivory by insects (<xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">Oerke, 2006</xref>). Spider mites (Acari: Tetranychidae) belong to the Chelicerata, an arthropod lineage that diverged more than 450 million years ago (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Dunlop, 2010</xref>), and hence evolved herbivory independently from insects. Crops including maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic>) and wheat (<italic>Triticum</italic> sp.) are susceptible not only to insects but also to spider mites, especially during drought conditions (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Al-Kaisi et al., 2013</xref>), where yield losses as high as 47.2% for maize have been reported (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Bacon et al., 1962</xref>). Nevertheless, relatively little is known about the molecular nature of the defenses plants use to deter spider mites, especially for grasses.</p><p>As shown by molecular studies of plant&#x02013;herbivore interactions, largely with insects and dicots such as <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> and tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>), many plants complement constitutive defenses (like trichomes) with rapid, inducible ones that negatively impact herbivores (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Howe and Jander, 2008</xref>). For instance, herbivore-associated triggers like physical damage, oral secretions, or frass, alone or in combination, lead to changes in the production of specialized metabolites or defensive proteins that deter herbivores (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Howe and Jander, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">Ray et al., 2015</xref>). In dicots, molecular responses to insect herbivores are mediated largely by phytohormones, especially jasmonates (jasmonic acid, or JA, and its derivatives or conjugates), which induce transcriptomic reprogramming within hours (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Howe and Jander, 2008</xref>). Some defenses act directly, such as toxic compounds or protease inhibitors that retard digestion in an herbivore&#x02019;s gut. Others act indirectly, like plant volatiles, which can serve as olfactory cues for predators to locate herbivores at feeding sites (<xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">Turlings and Erb, 2018</xref>).</p><p>The type and magnitude of inducible defenses is influenced by several factors. One of these is feeding guild. Chewing insects like caterpillars, for instance, cause extensive tissue damage and elicit different defense responses compared to phloem-feeding insects like aphids, which cause minimal loss of plant tissue (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Howe and Jander, 2008</xref>). Additionally, plant responses to generalist herbivores, to which &#x0223c;10% of plant-feeding insects belong (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Ali and Agrawal, 2012</xref>), can differ from those induced by specialists. Generalist herbivores feed on hosts in many plant families. They are typically thought to rely on broad detoxification capabilities to overcome the challenges they encounter on phylogenetically (and chemically) divergent plant hosts (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Dermauw et al., 2013</xref>), or to potentially suppress plant defense responses that are broadly conserved (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Ali and Agrawal, 2012</xref>). Alternatively, some specialists have evolved the ability to suppress or otherwise circumvent plant defenses, potentially ameliorating the role of detoxification, or instead have evolved highly specialized detoxification abilities to cope with the toxins they encounter in their preferred plant hosts (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Dobler et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Glas et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Maag et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">Wouters et al., 2014</xref>).</p><p>Like dicots, monocots, including grasses, are attacked by generalist and specialist herbivores of diverse feeding guilds, including leaf-chewing (e.g., caterpillars) and piercing-sucking (e.g., aphids and whiteflies). As for dicots, JA signaling and the production of specialized compounds feature prominently in monocot responses to insect herbivory (<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">Meihls et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">Tzin et al., 2015a</xref>, <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Of the downstream specialized compounds in grasses, the best studied are benzoxazinoids, which are 1,4-benzoxazin-3-one derivatives produced by cereals including maize, wheat, and rye (<xref rid="B101" ref-type="bibr">Z&#x000fa;&#x000f1;iga et al., 1983</xref>; <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">Niemeyer, 2009</xref>). In maize, levels of benzoxazinoids are highest in seedlings (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Cambier et al., 2000</xref>), but can be locally induced at feeding sites in the leaves of older plants (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">K&#x000f6;hler et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Maag et al., 2016</xref>). The most studied benzoxazinoid, 4-dihydroxy-7-methoxy-1,4-benzoxazin-3-one (DIMBOA), is stored in vacuoles as an inactive glucoside (Glc) conjugate. Upon tissue damage by herbivores, DIMBOA-Glc, as well as derivatives such as 2-hydroxy-4,7-dimethoxy-1,4-benzoxazin-3-one glucoside (HDMBOA-Glc), are exposed to glucosidases in plastids (<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">Meihls et al., 2012</xref>). This leads to the release of the aglucones, which are toxic to herbivores, potentially by several modes of action (<xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr">Wouters et al., 2016</xref>).</p><p>Several spider mite species are significant field pests on cereals. These include <italic>Tetranychus urticae</italic> (the two-spotted spider mite) on maize, and <italic>Oligonychus pratensis</italic> (the Banks grass mite) on both maize and distant relatives including wheat (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref></bold>; <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Brandenburg and Kennedy, 1982</xref>; <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Mansour and Bar-Zur, 1992</xref>; <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Archer and Bynum, 1993</xref>; <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">Tadmor et al., 1999</xref>; <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Blasi et al., 2015</xref>). <italic>T. urticae</italic> is an extreme generalist that has been documented on more than 100 plant families (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Grbi&#x00107; et al., 2011</xref>). In contrast, <italic>O. pratensis</italic> is a specialist on plants in the Poaceae, though it has been reported on a few non-grass hosts including date palm (which is also a monocot) (<xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">Ward et al., 1972</xref>; <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Foster et al., 1977</xref>; <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Chandler et al., 1979</xref>; <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Holtzer et al., 1984</xref>; <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Archer and Bynum, 1993</xref>; <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Bynum et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">Negm et al., 2015</xref>). As cell-content feeders, spider mites belong to a different feeding guild than the best studied insect herbivores (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Bensoussan et al., 2016</xref>). Currently, knowledge of plant responses to spider mites comes mainly from <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, tomato, and grapevine (<italic>Vitis vinifera</italic>), where <italic>T. urticae</italic> feeding was shown to induce robust JA responses (<xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr">Zhurov et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Martel et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">D&#x000ed;az-Riquelme et al., 2016</xref>). This suggests that <italic>T. urticae</italic> relies in large part on a broad detoxification capacity to enable its exceptionally wide host range. Nonetheless, the sister species <italic>T. evansi</italic>, a specialist of plants in the Solanaceae, has been documented to suppress plant defenses in tomato (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Alba et al., 2015</xref>). Further, another specialist mite herbivore of tomato, <italic>Aculops lycopersici</italic>, is able to potently suppress plant defenses (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Glas et al., 2014</xref>). While <italic>O. pratensis</italic> is a pest on diverse cereal crops like maize and wheat, little is known about its ancestral host range within Poaceae. Whether the grass specialist <italic>O. pratensis</italic> relies on detoxification, suppression of plant defenses, or both, to colonize its Poaceae hosts is unknown.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p><italic>O. pratensis</italic> and <italic>T. urticae</italic> morphology, tissue damage, and feeding strategy. <bold>(A)</bold>
<italic>O. pratensis</italic> and <italic>T. urticae</italic> feeding causes light colored (chlorotic) spotting on barley leaves, as well as on maize (see also <bold>Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">2</xref></bold>) (scale bars: 2.5 mm). Insets show adult <italic>O. pratensis</italic> and <italic>T. urticae</italic> females (scale bars: 100 &#x003bc;m). <bold>(B,C)</bold> Total area of damage on barley and maize leaf enclosures, respectively, for uninfested leaves (C, control), and those subjected to <italic>O. pratensis</italic> (<italic>Op</italic>) and <italic>T. urticae</italic> (<italic>Tu</italic>) feeding at 24 h. <italic>P</italic>-values are from an ANOVA, and letters indicate significant differences between comparisons (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, Tukey&#x02019;s HSD test; <italic>n</italic>: number of biological replicates). In the boxplots, circles represent individual data points. <bold>(D)</bold> Leaf cell damage caused by <italic>O. pratensis</italic> and <italic>T. urticae</italic> feeding on barley. Clusters of empty mesophyll cells at mite feeding sites (left) are denoted by dashed lines; a focal plane through the epidermis is shown at right with nuclei visualized by propidium iodide staining (white arrows). Scale bar: 100 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01222-g001"/></fig><p>In this study, we have characterized defense responses to herbivory by <italic>O. pratensis</italic> and <italic>T. urticae</italic> in grasses. As a plant host, we chose maize, for which defense responses to insects have been comparatively well studied (<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">Meihls et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">Tzin et al., 2015a</xref>, <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). We also included barley (<italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic>) as it is a close relative of wheat with a more tractable genome (<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">Mayer et al., 2012</xref>). By including both maize and barley, we were able to compare variation in plant defense responses to both mite species in each of two major cereal crops in phylogenetically distant lineages within Poaceae (subfamilies Panicoideae and Pooideae, respectively).</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s1"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Biological Materials and Maintenance of Stocks</title><p>Seeds for barley (cultivar Morex) were kindly provided by A. Fischer (Montana State University, Bozeman, MT, United States), while those for maize inbred B73 were kindly provided by G. Drews (University of Utah, Salt Lake City, UT, United States). Seed stocks for maize inbred W22, as well as homozygous lines for previously characterized <italic>Ds</italic> insertions in <italic>BX1</italic>, <italic>BX2</italic>, and <italic>BX6</italic> on the W22 background (<xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">Tzin et al., 2015a</xref>), were kindly provided by G. Jander (Boyce Thompson Institute, Ithaca, NY, United States). For the study, a <italic>T. urticae</italic> colony (strain W-GR) was established from <italic>T. urticae</italic> collected from a community garden and from a greenhouse site in Salt Lake City, UT, United States. Prior to this study, the W-GR strain was maintained on whole kidney bean plants (<italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic>) for more than 30 generations using established rearing methods (<xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">Van Leeuwen et al., 2012</xref>). Before being used as a source of mites for plant infestation experiments (see below), mites of W-GR were acclimated on barley (Morex) or maize (B73) for at least two generations to remove possible maternal effects on host use that might impact plant responses. For propagation, 8&#x02013;10 week old barley and maize plants were used to maintain bulk populations of at least several thousand mites. For <italic>O. pratensis</italic>, a field-collected strain was acquired from maize (Logan, UT, United States); propagation of the <italic>O. pratensis</italic> strain, and acclimation prior to the respective experiments on barley and maize, was as for <italic>T. urticae</italic> except that <italic>O. pratensis</italic> was never maintained on kidney beans, which are not a host.</p><p>For maintaining mite colonies, barley and maize plants were germinated and grown in Metro-Mix<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> 900 growing mix (Sun Gro<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>, Agawam, MA, United States) and watered from below as needed (pots were placed in trays to which water was added). Barley plants were germinated and grown in a walk-in growth chamber with a 16-h light/8-h dark photoperiod with 170&#x02013;200 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>-2</sup> s<sup>-1</sup> light at 20&#x000b0;C and 60% humidity. Maize plants were germinated and propagated in a greenhouse with a 16-h light/8-h dark photoperiod at an approximate temperature of 25&#x000b0;C. Maize and barley plants were fertilized weekly with 200 ppm NutriCulture Cal-Mag Special 16N-3P-16K (for maize) and NutriCulture Mag-Iron Special 18N-6P-18K (for barley) (Plant Marvel Laboratories, Chicago Heights, IL, United States). At the respective leaf stage, plants were moved to an isolated room maintained at room temperature (&#x0223c;22&#x000b0;C) for mite propagation, with new plants placed next to and touching previously infested plants to allow mites to move to fresh hosts. Mites from these colonies were used for all experiments unless otherwise noted.</p></sec><sec><title>Quantification of Feeding Damage</title><p>To assess the extent of foliar damage caused by mite feeding, mites of each species were placed on either the fifth leaves of 30-day-old barley plants or on the fourth leaves of 22-day-old maize plants. The studies for barley and maize were performed in a walk-in growth chamber or a greenhouse, respectively, under the conditions described above. Briefly, barley and maize seeds were sown 1&#x02013;2 cm deep in 5 &#x000d7; 5 cm plastic pots in Metro-Mix<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> 900 growing mix. Ten days after sowing, seedlings were transplanted into 20 cm diameter pots. As the maize plants were grown in a greenhouse bay, plants were maintained inside insect-free enclosures until the day before the experiment to exclude potential greenhouse pests (insect enclosures were constructed with PVC piping and No-See-Um nylon netting, BioQuip Products, Compton, CA, United States, catalog number 7250NSB). To minimize the impact of environmental variation, a randomized block design was employed.</p><p>While mites cannot fly, they can disperse quickly by crawling on leaves. Therefore, for both control plants and those used for mite infestations, we established leaf enclosures using non-phytotoxic wax barriers that mites do not cross, an approach previously employed in studies with both mite species (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Feese and Wilde, 1977</xref>; <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Mansour and Bar-Zur, 1992</xref>). For our study, we used Tree Tanglefoot wax (The Scotts Miracle-Gro Company, Marysville, OH, United States), with two barriers established perpendicular to the length of the leaf blades (Tanglefoot was placed in stripes across the adaxial and abaxial surfaces of leaves and joined at the edges; <bold>Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">1</xref></bold>). Mites added between the two barriers were thus free to move along and between the leaf surfaces internal to the Tanglefoot boundaries. Maize leaves are well separated, and hence enclosures were easily established on free-standing plants. However, the plant architecture of barley presented an additional challenge, necessitating immobilization of leaf-harboring enclosures as shown in <bold>Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">1</xref></bold>.</p><p>Twenty-four hours after establishing 12.5 cm Tanglefoot enclosures, 250 and 350 female mites were used to infest barley and maize leaves, respectively; as maize leaves are wider, more mites were added to keep mite density roughly constant (no mites were added to enclosures on the control plants). Adult mites of both species, which are only &#x0223c;0.6 mm in length (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref></bold>, insets), were collected under dissection microscopes from the bulk populations maintained on the respective hosts. To do this, defined numbers of adult females were harvested into 200 &#x003bc;L barrier pipet tips by suction (the large ends of pipet tips were attached to vacuum lines). At the time of collection, tips with mites were immediately placed onto ice. On ice, mites are less physically active and less likely to spin webs, which can otherwise lead to complications for subsequent release. To release mites onto leaf enclosures, pipet tips with mites were removed from ice, the tops of the tips were cut off with scissors (to increase the bore size for release), and mites were gently poured onto the leaf surface along the length of the enclosures.</p><p>At 24 h post-infestation, leaf enclosures were harvested by cutting across the leaf blade immediately internal to the Tanglefoot barriers. Both sides of each leaf segment were then scanned at 1200 dpi using an Epson Perfection V550 Photo scanner (Epson, Suwa, Japan). To ensure the mite damage was quantified from leaf segments of exactly the same length, the leaf segments were immobilized to a frame to reveal the middle 7.5 and 10 cm for barley and maize enclosures, respectively, before scanning. Barley leaf segments were sufficiently flat to be scanned without additional manipulation. In contrast, maize leaf segments could not be scanned directly due to pronounced midribs; therefore, leaf segments harvested from the enclosures were cut along the midrib, and the midrib and two halves of the leaf blade were pressed flat for scanning (<bold>Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">2</xref></bold>). The resulting images were processed using the thresholding function of the FIJI software (<xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">Schindelin et al., 2012</xref>), which allowed selection of light colored spots caused by mite feeding. The total area of damage on the adaxial and abaxial leaf surfaces was then quantified. Statistical analyses of leaf feeding damage were performed with analysis of variance (ANOVA) in R version 3.3.2 (<xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">R Core Team, 2016</xref>), with pairwise comparisons among treatments subsequently performed with Tukey&#x02019;s HSD test.</p></sec><sec><title>Cell Imaging at Mite Feeding Sites</title><p>Barley leaves were infested with <italic>T. urticae</italic> and <italic>O. pratensis</italic> for 24 h as described for quantification of mite feeding damage. Uninfested leaves were used as controls. Barley leaf segments with and without mite feeding were dehydrated through an ethanol series (15, 50, 75, and 95%) for 30 min each under vacuum, then decolorized in 200 proof ethanol overnight at 4&#x000b0;C. Decolorized leaf segments were rinsed twice in water, then incubated in 1 &#x003bc;g/mL propidium iodide for an hour. Stained leaf segments were then rinsed and mounted in water for imaging, and Z-series images were collected at 2 &#x003bc;m intervals through the epidermis and mesophyll layers of the leaf specimens using a Zeiss Axio Observer Z1 microscope (Zeiss, Baden-W&#x000fc;rttemberg, Germany). Fluorescence signal from propidium iodide was detected using an excitation filter of 559&#x02013;585 nm and an emission filter of 600&#x02013;690 nm. Images were processed using FIJI (<xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">Schindelin et al., 2012</xref>), Adobe Photoshop CC 2017, and Adobe Illustrator CC 2017 (Adobe, San Jose, CA, United States).</p></sec><sec><title>Collection of Plant Tissue for Transcriptomic Studies</title><p>Plant leaf tissue was collected from barley (Morex) and maize (B73) plants with the following treatments: (1) control (uninfested leaves), (2) wounding, (3) <italic>T. urticae</italic> infestation, and (4) <italic>O. pratensis</italic> infestation. As a time course, we selected 2- and 24-h time points because dynamic expression changes in defense genes in response to <italic>T. urticae</italic> were observed in the dicots <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, tomato, and grapevine within 24 h (<xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr">Zhurov et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Martel et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">D&#x000ed;az-Riquelme et al., 2016</xref>). Further, in maize, time points for analogous studies with insects from several feeding guilds were similar, and included 24-h time points (<xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">Tzin et al., 2015a</xref>, <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). The experimental design employed for assessing transcriptomic responses was similar to that for assessing quantification of feeding damage with several modifications. For barley, 30-day-old plants were used with enclosures of length 10 cm on the fifth leaves, and for maize, 22-day-old plants were used with enclosures of length 9 cm on the fourth leaves (mite density was therefore held roughly constant). A randomized block design was used to minimize environmental variation. For the wounding treatments, plant tissue in enclosures was gently pressed between 2 pieces of 60 grit sandpaper (particle size &#x0223c;260 &#x003bc;m; the blades on each side of the midrib were wounded along the lengths of the enclosed leaf segments). For mite infestation, 400 and 200 adult female mites were used per leaf enclosure for the 2- and 24-h time points, respectively. Briefly, because it takes tens of minutes to several hours for released mites to fully untangle themselves, disperse, and start feeding, the density of applied mites was doubled for the 2-h time point to ensure feeding by 2 h. For RNA preparation, we collected tissue from within the enclosures as a major component of induced plant defense responses is local (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Maag et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">Tzin et al., 2017</xref>). Following best practices in the field (<xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">Tzin et al., 2015a</xref>, <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>), mite infestation and wounding treatments were staggered prior to a single collection time (<bold>Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">3</xref></bold>). In all cases, a biological replicate consisted of the entire leaf enclosure from a single leaf. To minimize the effects of the circadian cycle, for both the barley and maize experiments all samples were collected within a 15-min time window 3 h into the 16-h light period.</p></sec><sec><title>RNA Isolation, RNA-Seq Library Construction, and Sequencing</title><p>Total RNA was prepared from leaf material from Tanglefoot enclosures with the DirectZol RNA extraction kit (Zymo Research, Irvine, CA, United States). Barcoded RNA-seq libraries were constructed at the High-Throughput Genomics Core Facility (University of Utah) using the Illumina (Illumina, San Diego, CA, United States) TruSeq Stranded mRNA Library Preparation Kit with poly(A) selection, and 125 bp paired-end reads were generated on an Illumina HiSeq 2500 sequencer with HiSeq SBS Kit v4 sequencing reagents. Briefly, four lanes were run in total for each of the barley and maize experiments, each consisting of 28 samples (four replicates each for the control, wounding at 2 and 24 h, <italic>T. urticae</italic> infestation at 2 and 24 h, and <italic>O. pratensis</italic> infestation at 2 and 24 h). Biological replicates were evenly distributed across the four sequencing lanes to reduce the possibility of confounding due to lane-level effects.</p></sec><sec><title>Detection of Differentially Expressed Genes</title><p>The barley genome version ASM3268v1 (Release 33) (<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">Mayer et al., 2012</xref>) and the maize genome version AGPv3 (Release 31) (<xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">Schnable et al., 2009</xref>) were downloaded from Ensembl (<xref rid="B99" ref-type="bibr">Yates et al., 2016</xref>). To examine expression of benzoxazinoid biosynthesis genes in maize, the gene model for <italic>BX7</italic> (<italic>GRMZM2G441753</italic>) was taken from an earlier annotation (Ensembl Release 20), as it was considered a low-confidence model and not included in the newer AGPv3 release. RNA-seq reads were aligned to their respective genomes using the two-pass alignment mode of STAR 2.5.2b (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Dobin et al., 2013</xref>) with a maximum intron size of 20 kb. The number of reads uniquely aligned to each locus was counted using HTSeq 0.6.0 (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Anders et al., 2015</xref>) with &#x0201c;--strand reverse&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;--feature transcript&#x0201d;. Differentially expressed genes (DEGs) were detected using the DESeq2 package (version 1.14.0) (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Love et al., 2014</xref>) with a false discovery rate (FDR) adjusted <italic>P</italic>-value of 0.01 and an absolute value log<sub>2</sub> fold change cutoff of 1. Fragments per kilobase of transcript per million mapped reads (FPKM) (<xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">Mortazavi et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">Trapnell et al., 2010</xref>) values were calculated with Python scripts using the BCBio<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn01">1</xref></sup> GFF parser.</p></sec><sec><title>Cluster Analyses</title><p>Independently for each of the maize and barley time course RNA-seq data sets, gene-level <italic>k</italic>-means clustering was performed on the set of genes that was differentially expressed in at least one treatment. Briefly, the log<sub>2</sub> fold change estimates of each gene across treatments compared to the control were used as the input to the <italic>kmeans</italic> function of the base &#x0201c;stat&#x0201d; package in R with the default Hartigan and Wong algorithm. Different <italic>k</italic> numbers were tested with <italic>k</italic> = 6 chosen as it resulted in clusters with distinct expression profiles across the treatments. The <italic>kmeans</italic> function was run with 100 iterations (nstart = 100) of the algorithm to optimize the clustering output. To compare the expression profiles across host species, the centers of the barley and maize gene <italic>k</italic>-means clusters were subjected to hierarchical clustering using the <italic>hclust</italic> function in R (distance: squared Euclidean; linkage: complete). While the <italic>k</italic>-means clusters were numbered arbitrarily by the <italic>kmeans</italic> function, barley and maize gene clusters with similar expression patterns identified by hierarchical clustering were manually renumbered for simplicity of comparison.</p></sec><sec><title>Gene Ontology Annotations and Gene Set Enrichment Analysis</title><p>Gene ontology (GO) annotations of the barley genome version ASM3268v1 (Release 33) and maize genome version AGPv3 (Release 31) were obtained by parsing the respective EMBL flat files provided by Ensembl (Biopython package SeqIO, version 1.69; <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Cock et al., 2009</xref>). The GO annotations were used to classify gene sets using the biological process (BP) and molecular function (MF) ontologies. The MF ontology was used to identify genes encoding defensive proteins and enzymes (i.e., protease inhibitors, chitinases, and terpene synthases).</p><p>Gene set enrichment analysis was performed using the BP ontology. To enable a comparison of gene set enrichments between barley and maize gene sets, we modified the BP ontology annotation of each species so that one-to-one orthologs between barley and maize were associated with the same GO terms. The one-to-one orthologs were determined by reciprocal BLASTP (BLAST+ version 2.5.0+; <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Camacho et al., 2009</xref>) searches with an <italic>E</italic>-value cut-off &#x0003c;10<sup>-5</sup>. The search was limited to the longest isoform of each protein. For each gene with a best reciprocal BLASTP hit, the list of BP ontology terms was updated to contain the union of annotated BP ontology terms from the barley and maize orthologs. Gene set enrichment analyses were performed using the &#x0201c;weight01&#x0201d; algorithm with Fisher&#x02019;s test statistic as implemented in the topGO 2.32.0 package (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Alexa et al., 2006</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Hormonometer Analyses</title><p>We adapted the Hormonometer tool (<xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">Volodarsky et al., 2009</xref>) to assess plant hormone signaling in barley and maize following the approach used by <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">Tzin et al. (2015a</xref>, <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>) in studies of maize responses to herbivory by insects. This tool searches for the similarity of gene expression changes to signatures of transcriptomic responses diagnostic for specific plant hormone signaling pathways. Briefly, experimentally assessed reference expression data sets are available from <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, and were generated by exogenous application of plant hormones (or hormone precursors) that induce JA, salicylic acid (SA), ethylene, abscisic acid (ABA), brassinosteroid, cytokinin, auxin, and gibberellic acid (GA) signaling (<xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">Volodarsky et al., 2009</xref>). As the Hormonometer tool was developed with <italic>A. thaliana</italic> expression data, to use the tool with barley and maize we performed reciprocal BLASTP searches with <italic>A. thaliana</italic> proteins to identify orthologs in both grass species. As a result, we identified 8236 barley genes and 8904 maize genes expressed in our study that had corresponding <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> Probeset IDs (<bold>Supplementary Data Sheets <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM6">1</xref></bold>, <bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM7">2</xref></bold>, respectively), and we used these as input for the Hormonometer tool to assess the similarity of gene sets induced by spider mite feeding and wounding to those induced by specific phytohormones.</p></sec><sec><title>Peroxidase Activity Assays</title><p>Plants were grown and infested with mites as described for damage quantification. The leaf samples were collected 24 h after infestation and ground to a fine powder in liquid nitrogen. Peroxidase activity in leaf samples was quantified with a microplate reader (Biotek EPOCH, Winooski, VT, United States) as described previously (<xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">Ramirez and Spears, 2014</xref>). Briefly, frozen leaf powder was thawed and suspended in 1 mL of sodium phosphate buffer (0.05 M, pH 7.0). Leaf homogenates were centrifuged for 12 min at 12,000 rpm to extract soluble leaf proteins in the supernatant. Peroxidase activity was detected in soluble protein at 470 nm following the oxidation of guaiacol for 1 min (<xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">Moran and Cipollini, 1999</xref>), and expressed as the change in absorbance per mg of total protein. The impacts of the treatments on peroxidase activity were assessed by ANOVA factoring in the block design; where significant effects were observed, Tukey&#x02019;s HSD tests were performed.</p></sec><sec><title>Mite Productivity on <italic>bx</italic> Mutant Plants</title><p>To assess the impact of mutations in genes in the maize benzoxazinoid pathway on mite infestation, seeds of W22, <italic>bx1::Ds</italic>, <italic>bx2::Ds</italic>, and <italic>bx6::Ds</italic> (<xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">Tzin et al., 2015a</xref>) were germinated directly in 15 cm diameter pots. At 2 weeks (approximately the three-leaf stage), plants of the four genotypes were arranged in a randomized block design with 16 replicates of each genotype (eight plants per block). Three 1&#x02013;2-day-old adult females from synchronized mite populations were then added to each plant. To do this, three mites were sucked into barrier pipet tips as described previously, and the mites were tapped to the bottom of the tips against the barriers. The tops of the tips were then cut off to allow mites to escape, and single tips were immediately taped to the bottom of individual plants with the top of the cut tip pointing up and touching the second leaf. Synchronized mite populations were obtained by placing fertilized female mites on detached B73 maize leaves, allowing the females to lay eggs for 2 days, and then removing them (the resulting population of female mites was thus approximately synchronized). To prevent detached leaves from drying out, they were placed on wet cotton and their edges were sealed with Tanglefoot wax. Eighteen days after adding tips with mites to plants, entire plants were collected and kept at 4&#x000b0;C (which arrests mite reproduction and development). The number of eggs and viable mites (larvae, nymphs, and adults) found on each plant was then subsequently counted under a dissecting microscope. The impact of maize genotype on mite productivity by species per plant was assessed with ANOVA factoring in the block design. Subsequent pairwise tests were performed with Tukey&#x02019;s HSD method.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title><italic>O. pratensis</italic> and <italic>T. urticae</italic> Cause Similar Patterns of Tissue Damage</title><p>To assess responses of barley (cultivar Morex) and maize (inbred B73) to specialist and generalist spider mite herbivores, we examined transcriptomic responses to <italic>O. pratensis</italic> and <italic>T. urticae</italic> feeding at 2 and 24 h. As the magnitude of wounding can impact interpretation of transcriptomic responses, we first assessed the extent of plant tissue damage from both mite species. For <italic>O. pratensis</italic> and <italic>T. urticae</italic>, and for barley and maize, macroscopic damage from mite feeding at 24 h consisted of fine white stippling (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref></bold> and <bold>Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">2</xref></bold>). For both plant hosts and for both mite herbivores, significant plant damage was observed compared to uninfested leaves following damage quantification from leaf scans (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, ANOVA with Tukey&#x02019;s HSD method to correct for multiple tests; <bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B,C</xref></bold>). At 24 h, areas of stippling caused by <italic>O. pratensis</italic> and <italic>T. urticae</italic> on barley were not significantly different (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref></bold>). In contrast, a significant albeit modest increase in damage was observed for maize leaves infested with <italic>T. urticae</italic> relative to those exposed to <italic>O. pratensis</italic> (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1C</xref></bold>). It should be noted, however, that the sample size, and hence power to detect an effect, was larger for maize; this was a function of performing maize studies in a large greenhouse as opposed to a growth chamber as was used for barley (see the section &#x0201c;Materials and Methods&#x0201d;).</p><p>We also examined the microscopic pattern of damage caused by <italic>O. pratensis</italic> and <italic>T. urticae</italic> on barley leaves, for which the even epidermis is straightforward to image with differential interference contrast and fluorescence microscopy in cleared tissue. For both mite species, clusters of mesophyll cells were empty at feeding sites (or minimally, were devoid of chloroplasts that are dark in appearance; <bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1D</xref></bold>). The overlying epidermis, in which cells lack chloroplasts, nonetheless appeared to be intact as assessed by the presence of propidium iodide stained nuclei in pavement cells.</p></sec><sec><title>Spider Mite Herbivores Induce Similar Transcriptomic Responses on Barley and Maize</title><p>To examine transcriptomic responses to herbivory by <italic>O. pratensis</italic> and <italic>T. urticae</italic>, we collected plant tissue from within leaf enclosures at 2 and 24 h after mite infestation. Quantification of gene expression from alignments of the resultant RNA-seq reads from four biological replicates for controls and treatments revealed that 21,472 of 26,066 (82.4%) high-quality barley genes were expressed (i.e., had non-zero read counts), as were 30,279 of 39,625 (76.4%) high-quality genes in maize (see the section &#x0201c;Materials and Methods&#x0201d;).</p><p>As assessed with a principal component analysis (PCA) using controls and all treatments, biological replicates were tightly clustered (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A,B</xref></bold>). For the 2-h time point, replicates for both <italic>O. pratensis</italic> and <italic>T. urticae</italic> clustered nearby but were separate from controls in both barley and maize. A similar but more distinct pattern was observed at 24 h. Although dramatic differences in plant responses to the two mite species were not readily apparent for most contrasts, <italic>O. pratensis</italic> replicates at 24 h clustered farther away from control samples in barley than did those for <italic>T. urticae</italic>, albeit along the same PCA axis.</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p>Dynamic gene expression changes in barley and maize in response to mite herbivory and wounding. <bold>(A,B)</bold> PCAs of expression data for control, mite infested, and wounded leaves in barley and maize, respectively. Treatments and time points are as indicated in the legend (center; hour: hr). <bold>(C,D)</bold> Number of significantly up- and downregulated genes detected in each treatment for barley and maize, respectively (FDR-adjusted <italic>P</italic>-value of 0.01, absolute value log<sub>2</sub> fold change cutoff of 1). Expression differences are broken out by time points (2 and 24 h, left and right for each plant host), and Venn diagrams show the overlap of DEGs among treatments (bottom).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01222-g002"/></fig><p>We used DESeq2 (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Love et al., 2014</xref>) to detect DEGs &#x02013; as assessed with a FDR-adjusted <italic>P</italic>-value of 0.01 and an absolute value log<sub>2</sub> fold change cutoff of 1 &#x02013; between treatments and controls for barley and maize (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C,D</xref></bold>, respectively; results of DEG analyses for all comparisons are given in <bold>Supplementary Data Sheet <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM8">3</xref></bold> for barley and <bold>Supplementary Data Sheet <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM9">4</xref></bold> for maize). In response to feeding by both <italic>O. pratensis</italic> and <italic>T. urticae</italic>, hundreds and thousands of DEGs were detected in both barley and maize at 2 and 24 h, respectively. In contrast to the 2-h time point, for which nearly all expression changes involved upregulation, both up- and downregulation were observed at 24 h.</p><p>The partial overlap of DEGs between mite treatments (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C,D</xref></bold>) raised the possibility that components of plant defense responses to the generalist and specialist mites differed. To investigate this further, we generated scatter plots of log<sub>2</sub> fold changes for genes responding to mite herbivory at the 2- and 24-h time points for combinations of plant and mite species (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref></bold>). Consistent with the PCAs (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A,B</xref></bold>), transcriptomic responses to feeding by <italic>O. pratensis</italic> and <italic>T. urticae</italic> were highly correlated at both time points in each species (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>-values between 0.8 and 0.9, all <italic>P-</italic>values &#x0003c; 10<sup>-16</sup>; <bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref></bold>). Our findings, therefore, revealed no compelling evidence for large-scale, qualitative differences in plant gene expression responses between the specialist and generalist mites.</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>FIGURE 3</label><caption><p><italic>O. pratensis</italic> and <italic>T. urticae</italic> induce similar changes in gene expression in both barley and maize. Scatter plots of log<sub>2</sub> fold changes for DEGs (FDR-adjusted <italic>P</italic>-value of 0.01, absolute value log<sub>2</sub> fold change cutoff of 1) in barley <bold>(A,B)</bold> and maize <bold>(C,D)</bold> in response to <italic>T. urticae</italic> and <italic>O. pratensis</italic> herbivory at two time points (2 h: <bold>A</bold>,<bold>C</bold>; 24 h: <bold>B</bold>,<bold>D</bold>). For inclusion in a given analysis, a gene had to be detected as differentially expressed in response to at least one herbivore (see Venn diagram insets, and legend, bottom left).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01222-g003"/></fig><p>Nonetheless, at the quantitative level, <italic>O. pratensis</italic> induced modestly stronger transcriptomic responses than did <italic>T. urticae</italic>, as assessed by the magnitude of fold changes, in barley at 24 h (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref></bold>). Likewise, in maize at the 2-h time point, a similar pattern was observed for the grass specialist (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref></bold>). These trends were also apparent in measurements of the activity of peroxidase, which has been reported to increase in response to <italic>T. urticae</italic> herbivory in several dicots (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Hildebrand et al., 1986</xref>; <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Liang et al., 2017</xref>). In both barley and maize at 24 h, herbivory by both <italic>O. pratensis</italic> and <italic>T. urticae</italic> elevated peroxidase activity relative to control leaves (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, ANOVA and Tukey&#x02019;s HSD test; <bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref></bold>). Paralleling the difference in the relative magnitude observed for gene expression responses in barley (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref></bold>), including for genes encoding peroxidase enzymes (<bold>Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">4</xref></bold>), <italic>O. pratensis</italic> induced significantly greater peroxidase activity compared to <italic>T. urticae</italic> at 24 h (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref></bold>).</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>FIGURE 4</label><caption><p>Peroxidase activity increases in response to spider mite herbivory. Peroxidase activity in response to <italic>O. pratensis</italic> (<italic>Op</italic>) and <italic>T. urticae</italic> (<italic>Tu</italic>) herbivory at 24 h in barley <bold>(A)</bold> and maize <bold>(B)</bold>. <italic>P</italic>-values are from an ANOVA, and different letters reflect significant differences among controls (C) and the treatments (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, Tukey&#x02019;s HSD test). In the boxplots, circles represent individual data points.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01222-g004"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Comparison of Plant Responses Induced by Mites to Those Induced by Mechanical Wounding</title><p>While mechanical wounding cannot fully replicate the intricacies of physical damage caused by herbivores (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Howe and Jander, 2008</xref>), our wounding treatment, which consisted of gently pressing leaf blades with sandpaper, mimicked the dispersed nature of spider mite damage to plant leaves (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref></bold> and <bold>Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">2</xref></bold>). As assessed by PCAs, at 2 h wounding treatments in both barley and maize clustered separately and further from controls compared to the mite treatments, and more genes were differentially regulated (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>). In contrast, at 24 h, biological replicates for wounding treatments clustered nearer control samples in both barley and maize, and fewer genes were detected as differentially expressed compared to wounding at 2 h, or to <italic>O. pratensis</italic> and <italic>T. urticae</italic> feeding at 24 h (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>). However, despite differences in the number of DEGs between the wounding and mite feeding treatments, the direction of changes in gene expression and their fold-induction were correlated in both barley and maize between wounding and mite feeding at 2 as well as 24 h (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>-values between 0.12 and 0.52, with all <italic>P</italic>-values &#x0003c; 10<sup>-15</sup>; <bold>Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">5</xref></bold>).</p></sec><sec><title>Defense Pathways That Respond to Mite Herbivory in Barley and Maize</title><p>To further characterize gene expression changes across treatments, time points, and plant hosts, we performed <italic>k-</italic>means clustering in barley and maize using expression levels for all genes significantly differentially expressed in at least one treatment. For <italic>k</italic> = 6, and as assessed subsequently with hierarchical clustering (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref></bold>), analogous clusters with similar patterns of RNA abundances were readily observed between barley and maize (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref></bold>). Clusters 1&#x02013;5 contain genes that were mostly upregulated in response to either herbivory or wounding, whereas genes in cluster 6 were mostly downregulated (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A,B</xref></bold>; clusters 4 and 5, which contain genes with relatively modest fold changes, are shown in <bold>Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">6</xref></bold>).</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>FIGURE 5</label><caption><p>Global patterns of gene expression in response to spider mite herbivory and wounding are similar between barley and maize. <bold>(A)</bold> By plant host, <italic>k</italic>-means clusters (<italic>k</italic> = 6) for DEGs (FDR-adjusted <italic>P</italic>-value of 0.01, absolute value log<sub>2</sub> fold change cutoff of 1) between treatments and controls (gene numbers in clusters are given in parentheses). For inclusion in the analysis for either barley or maize, a gene had to be significantly differentially expressed in at least one treatment relative to the respective control. Shown is a hierarchical clustering of the barley and maize clusters based on the mean expression values of each cluster. <bold>(B)</bold> Gene expression profiles for barley and maize genes in clusters 1, 2, 3, and 6 as indicated (for clusters 4 and 5, see <bold>Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">6</xref></bold>). Lines reflect expression changes (log<sub>2</sub> fold change relative to controls) for individual genes across treatments. The mean changes of expression by cluster are shown with black lines. <italic>Hv</italic>, <italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic> (barley); <italic>Zm</italic>, <italic>Zea mays</italic> (maize); O2 and O24, <italic>O. pratensis</italic> herbivory at 2 and 24 h; T2 and T24, <italic>T. urticae</italic> herbivory at 2 and 24 h; and W2 and W24, wounding at 2 and 24 h.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01222-g005"/></fig><p>To relate genes in clusters to biological functions, we performed a GO enrichment analysis for BPs as implemented in the topGO package (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Alexa et al., 2006</xref>). Significantly enriched GO terms for all clusters for both barley and maize are given in <bold>Supplementary Tables <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">1</xref></bold>, <bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">2</xref></bold>, respectively. This analysis revealed that herbivory by <italic>O. pratensis</italic> and <italic>T. urticae</italic>, as well as wounding, led to a general switch in transcriptomic programs from processes such as development to those associated with response to the environment. For example, cluster 6, representing mostly downregulated genes in the treatments, was enriched for GO terms related to photosynthesis and development. In contrast, clusters with genes upregulated in response to mite herbivory or wounding, such as clusters 1 and 2, were enriched for GO terms associated with abiotic or biotic defense responses in barley, maize, or both. These included ontology terms such as &#x0201c;JA biosynthetic process,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;response to JA,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;response to SA,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;response to fungus,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;response to wounding,&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;hyperosmotic salinity response.&#x0201d; Of the genes in the six clusters, fold changes for those in cluster 1 were most dramatic with respect to mite feeding across the time course (strong upregulation at 2 h, and even greater upregulation at 24 h). Genes in this cluster were also highly upregulated in response to wounding, especially at 2 h. A reduced correspondence between the magnitude of gene expression changes to mite feeding and wounding was observed in other clusters (e.g., clusters 2 and 3).</p><p>We also examined whether the composition of analogous clusters between barley and maize was enriched in orthologous genes, which would suggest common response pathways. To do this, we identified 14,087 genes as orthologs between barley and maize as assessed with a reciprocal best BLASTP hit analysis. For each of clusters 1&#x02013;6, orthologous gene pairs were enriched between barley and maize (all <italic>P-</italic>values &#x0003c; 10<sup>-12</sup> as determined with hypergeometric tests; <bold>Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM3">3</xref></bold>).</p></sec><sec><title>Genes for JA Biosynthesis and Signaling Respond Rapidly to Mite Herbivores and Wounding</title><p>The GO enrichment analysis suggested a prominent role for phytohormone signaling in responses to both mite herbivores and wounding. Therefore, we adapted the Hormonometer tool (<xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">Volodarsky et al., 2009</xref>) to relate mite- and wounding-induced changes in gene expression to those induced by diverse phytohormones. As displayed in dendrograms for both plant hosts (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A,B</xref></bold>), changes in most phytohormone response pathways were readily apparent by 2 h in response to herbivory by <italic>O. pratensis</italic> and <italic>T. urticae</italic>, as well as wounding. In general, patterns of up- or downregulation for plant hormone responsive genes were similar between barley and maize, and at 24 h responses were generally attenuated. Response genes for JA, SA, ABA, and auxin were most dramatically upregulated, while response genes associated with ethylene, GA, cytokinin, and brassinosteroid signaling were either downregulated, variable, or largely unaffected.</p><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>FIGURE 6</label><caption><p>Phytohormone responses to spider mite herbivory and wounding. <bold>(A,B)</bold> Hormonometer analyses for plant hormone signatures based on transcriptomic responses of barley <bold>(A)</bold> and maize <bold>(B)</bold> to <italic>O. pratensis</italic> (<italic>Op</italic>) and <italic>T. urticae</italic> (<italic>Tu</italic>) herbivory as well as wounding (W) at 2 and 24 hours (hr) as indicated in parentheses. The colors indicate similarity between the herbivory/wounding treatments and a particular hormone response (blue and red for negative and positive correlations, respectively, see bottom). MJ: methyl jasmonate; ACC: 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylic acid (a precursor of ethylene); ABA: abscisic acid; IAA: indole-3-acetic acid; GA3: gibberellin A3; BR: brassinosteroid; and SA: salicylic acid. <bold>(C)</bold> Schematic of the JA biosynthesis and signaling pathway after <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Borrego and Kolomiets (2016)</xref> (left) with heat maps of log<sub>2</sub> fold changes for DEGs, right (FDR adjusted <italic>P</italic>-value of 0.01, absolute value log<sub>2</sub> fold change cutoff of 1). Upregulation or downregulation of marker genes for JA signaling is given in red and blue, respectively, see bottom, for treatments as compared to the control (only genes differentially regulated in at least one contrast are shown). The mean expression level of each gene among control replicates, as assessed by FPKM values, is as indicated (C, control). Where no differential expression was observed for a given gene and treatment, cells are shaded gray. Black arrows indicate chemical transformations (solid: one reaction; dashed: multiple reactions) and blue and red arrows indicate signal transduction (activation and inhibition, respectively).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01222-g006"/></fig><p>Because of the strong JA responses, and functional-genetic studies demonstrating a role for JA signaling in deterring <italic>T. urticae</italic> feeding on <italic>A. thaliana</italic> and tomato (<xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr">Zhurov et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Martel et al., 2015</xref>), we characterized transcriptomic responses of this pathway further. While the JA pathway is well characterized in dicots, less about it is known in monocots. However, candidate genes for JA biosynthesis, signal transduction, and mediation of transcriptional changes have been identified in maize (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Borrego and Kolomiets, 2016</xref>), and genetic studies provide functional evidence for the involvement of several of these genes in JA biosynthesis and signaling (<xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr">Yan et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">Tzin et al., 2017</xref>). Initially, we focused our analysis on the JA pathway in maize (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6C</xref></bold>), describing general patterns of responses to both mite species as induced gene expression is highly correlated between them (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref></bold>).</p><p>Lipoxygenases (LOXs) catalyze the production of oxylipins, which are involved in multiple aspects of plant defense (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Borrego and Kolomiets, 2016</xref>). The first step in the JA biosynthesis pathway is the production of the oxylipin 13(<italic>S</italic>)-hydroperoxylinolenate (13-HPOT) from &#x003b1;-linolenic acid. Putative LOXs for catalyzing this reaction belong to the 13-LOX group, of which maize has five (<italic>LOX7</italic>, <italic>8</italic>, <italic>9</italic>, <italic>10</italic>, <italic>11</italic>, <italic>13</italic>) (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Borrego and Kolomiets, 2016</xref>). Of these, all but <italic>LOX11</italic> were induced at one or more time points, albeit with modest fold changes. As assessed by normalized expression values (FPKMs), basal levels of <italic>LOX10</italic> were &#x0223c;90-fold higher than for other 13-LOX genes, consistent with its role in the production of green leaf volatiles (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Christensen et al., 2013</xref>), which are abundant in grasses. The next two steps in JA synthesis involve the conversion of 13-HPOT to 12,13(<italic>S</italic>)-epoxylinolenic acid (12,13-EOT), followed by cyclization to yield 12-oxo-phytodienoic acid (12-OPDA) (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Borrego and Kolomiets, 2016</xref>). Differential expression was also observed for putative genes mediating these steps, including the upregulation of four <italic>ALLENE OXIDE SYNTHASE</italic> (<italic>AOS</italic>) genes and two <italic>ALLENE OXIDE CYCLASE</italic> (<italic>AOC</italic>) genes, respectively. As compared to <italic>13-LOX</italic> and <italic>AOC</italic> genes, the <italic>AOS</italic> genes were more highly upregulated at both 2- and 24-h time points. This included genes in the <italic>AOS1</italic> clade, but also genes in clade 2 for which a role in JA biosynthesis is uncertain (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Borrego and Kolomiets, 2016</xref>). The next step in JA synthesis involves the conversion of 12-OPDA to 3-oxo-2-(<italic>cis</italic>-2&#x02032;-pentenyl)-cyclopentane-1-octanoic acid (OPC-8:0), which is mediated by oxophytodienoate reductase (OPR). In maize, this step requires the products of <italic>OPR7</italic> and <italic>OPR8</italic>, for which JA levels are dramatically reduced in tissues of the double mutant, including in leaves (<xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr">Yan et al., 2012</xref>). One of these genes, <italic>OPR7</italic>, was modestly upregulated at 24 h in response to mite herbivory. The conjugation of JA to isoleucine, which is carried out by the JASMONATE RESISTANT1 (JAR1) protein in <italic>A. thaliana</italic> (<xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">Staswick, 2002</xref>), produces JA-Ile, the most biologically active form of JA in plants (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Koo and Howe, 2012</xref>). One maize gene encoding a JAR protein, <italic>JAR2a</italic>, was weakly downregulated at 24 h after <italic>T. urticae</italic> feeding, mirroring its downregulation in response to <italic>S. exigua</italic> herbivory (<xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">Tzin et al., 2017</xref>).</p><p>To assess JA signaling, we examined expression changes for genes downstream of JA-Ile, including ones that were identified as not being inducible (or being less induced) in response to wounding in <italic>OPR7</italic>/<italic>8</italic> double mutant maize plants (<xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr">Yan et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Borrego and Kolomiets, 2016</xref>). Many of these genes increased in expression in response to mite feeding, albeit moderately (i.e., the transcriptional regulators <italic>MYC7</italic>, <italic>WRKY14</italic>, and <italic>WRKY46</italic>). Nevertheless, genes in several families showed dramatic upregulation. For instance, <italic>JAZ3</italic>, <italic>4</italic>, <italic>5</italic>, <italic>6</italic>, <italic>7</italic>, <italic>8</italic>, and <italic>12</italic> were strongly upregulated at both the 2- and 24-h time points. Further, members of the 9-LOX clade, including <italic>LOX3</italic>, <italic>4</italic>, and <italic>5</italic>, were also upregulated at both time points, with <italic>LOX3</italic> and <italic>5</italic> exhibiting strong upregulation at 24 h. <italic>LOX1</italic>, which encodes a dual activity lipoxygenase (13-LOX and 9-LOX) of unknown function (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Borrego and Kolomiets, 2016</xref>), was also upregulated at both time points.</p><p>Collectively, gene expression changes for JA biosynthesis and downstream responses were induced similarly between <italic>O. pratensis</italic> and <italic>T. urticae</italic>, with patterns at 2 and 24 h essentially identical where strong differential gene expression was observed (e.g., for most <italic>LOX</italic>, <italic>AOS</italic>, and <italic>JAZ</italic> genes). Further, responses to wounding at 2 h closely mirrored those of responses to mite herbivory (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6C</xref></bold>). While we focused on the JA pathway in maize, for which more is known, an analysis of putative orthologs in barley revealed similar responses (<bold>Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">7</xref></bold>). Finally, mirroring our analysis of genes involved in JA signaling, we performed a similar one for SA, another key plant hormone mediating biotic interactions. Many candidate genes for SA biosynthesis (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Martel et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">Tzin et al., 2015a</xref>) were upregulated in response to mite herbivory and wounding at both the 2- and 24-h time points. Examples from maize included genes encoding putative prephenate dehydratases (<italic>GRMZM2G437912</italic> and <italic>GRMZM2G125923)</italic>, Phe ammonia-lyase <italic>(GRMZM2G063917)</italic>, and <italic>trans</italic>-cinnamate 4-monooxygenases (<italic>GRMZM2G147245</italic> and <italic>GRMZM2G010468)</italic> (<bold>Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">8</xref></bold>).</p></sec><sec><title>Upregulation of Defensive Proteins</title><p>Expression of protease inhibitors and chitinases has been shown to retard the growth of insects, spider mites, or both (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Lawrence and Novak, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Carrillo et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">Santamar&#x000ed;a et al., 2012</xref>), and about half of cysteine protease inhibitors (cystatins) and serine protease inhibitors were expressed in barley or maize leaves in controls or treatments (<bold>Supplementary Data Sheets <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM8">3</xref></bold>, <bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref></bold>, respectively). In barley, no cystatin genes changed in expression in response to herbivory by <italic>O. pratensis</italic> or <italic>T. urticae</italic>, although two genes were moderately upregulated in response to wounding at 2 h (<bold>Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">9A</xref></bold>). In contrast, eight maize cystatin genes were modestly upregulated, primarily at 24 h, in response to <italic>O. pratensis</italic> or <italic>T. urticae</italic> herbivory (<bold>Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">9A</xref></bold>). Most of these were also upregulated at either 2 or 24 h in response to wounding. As opposed to the pattern observed for cystatins, higher-fold upregulation of serine protease inhibitors was observed in leaves of both plant hosts in response to feeding by <italic>O. pratensis</italic> and <italic>T. urticae</italic>. Among the upregulated genes were several previously reported to be responsive to wounding or JA signaling, including <italic>WOUND INDUCED PROTEIN1</italic> (<italic>WPI</italic>) and <italic>MAIZE PROTEASE INHIBITOR</italic> (<italic>MPI</italic>) (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Eckelkamp et al., 1993</xref>; <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">Rohrmeier and Lehle, 1993</xref>; <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">Tamayo et al., 2000</xref>) (<bold>Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">9B</xref></bold>). A pattern shared with the cystatins in maize was that serine protease inhibitor genes were upregulated at the 24-h time point (or if they were significantly induced at 2 h, induction was higher at 24 h). Most serine protease inhibitors induced by mite herbivory were upregulated by wounding at 2 or 24 h. Twenty-one chitinase genes changed in expression in response to herbivory by <italic>O. pratensis</italic> or <italic>T. urticae</italic>, or wounding, in maize (<bold>Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">10A</xref></bold>). The majority of genes were upregulated, many at 24 h only, although <italic>GRMZM2G129189</italic>, <italic>GRMZM2G145461</italic>, and <italic>GRMZM2G162359</italic> were induced at both time points. The upregulated genes belonged to several glycoside hydrolase families that hydrolyze chitin (GH-18 and GH-19) (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Hawkins et al., 2015</xref>). A similar pattern of dynamic responses of chitinase genes to mite herbivory and wounding was also apparent for barley (<bold>Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">10B</xref></bold>).</p></sec><sec><title>A Functional Benzoxazinoid Pathway Deters the Generalist but Not the Specialist Mite Herbivore</title><p>Domesticated varieties of barley, including the cultivar Morex used in our study, lack benzoxazinoids (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Glawischnig et al., 1999</xref>; <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">Niemeyer, 2009</xref>). In maize, however, at least 14 genes are involved in the benzoxazinoid biosynthesis pathway, and several participate at multiple steps, as shown in <bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7A</xref></bold> (the schematic of the pathway is after <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">Tzin et al., 2017</xref>). In B73, the <italic>BX12</italic> gene is disrupted, although HDMBOA-Glc can still be produced (<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">Meihls et al., 2013</xref>).</p><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>FIGURE 7</label><caption><p>A role for benzoxazinoids in deterring the generalist spider mite, <italic>T. urticae</italic>. <bold>(A)</bold> Biosynthesis pathway for benzoxazinoids after <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">Tzin et al. (2017)</xref>. Arrows indicate chemical transformations (solid lines, one reaction; dashed line, multiple reactions). <bold>(B)</bold> Heat maps for DEGs (FDR-adjusted <italic>P</italic>-value of 0.01, absolute value log<sub>2</sub> fold change cutoff of 1) in the biosynthesis pathway for benzoxazinoids in response to herbivory by <italic>O. pratensis</italic> (<italic>Op</italic>) and <italic>T. urticae</italic> (<italic>Tu</italic>) or to wounding (W) at 2 or 24 hours (hr) as indicated. For the control samples (C), the mean expression level among replicates of each gene, as assessed by FPKM values, is given. The colors correspond to log<sub>2</sub> fold changes of individual genes in each treatment (blue, downregulation; red, upregulation). Where genes were not significantly differentially expressed, cells are gray. <bold>(C,D)</bold> Boxplots showing the number of progeny produced by <italic>O. pratensis</italic> and <italic>T. urticae</italic>, respectively, on W22 (wild-type) and homozygous Ds transposon insertion mutants in <italic>BX1</italic>, <italic>BX2</italic>, and <italic>BX6</italic> on the W22 background. Circles represent individual data points. <italic>P</italic>-values were determined by ANOVA, with letters indicating significant differences among contrasts (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, Tukey&#x02019;s HSD test).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01222-g007"/></fig><p>In all cases, genes for the synthesis of DIMBOA-Glc were expressed in control B73 tissue, with <italic>BX1</italic> and <italic>BX2</italic> having the lowest expression levels (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7B</xref></bold>). In response to herbivory by either <italic>O. pratensis</italic> or <italic>T. urticae</italic>, six of the genes needed for synthesis of DIMBOA-Glc were induced weakly at 24 h (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7B</xref></bold>; <italic>BX6</italic> was also differentially expressed at 2 h in response to <italic>O. pratensis</italic>, albeit with a small fold change). Seven of these genes were also induced weakly by wounding at 2 h, but none remained upregulated at 24 h post-wounding. In contrast to genes needed for DIMBOA-Glc synthesis, those for the modification of DIMBOA-Glc to produce HDMBOA-Glc and HDM2BOA-Glc had very low basal expression levels in control tissue (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7B</xref></bold>). However, two genes involved in the production of HDMBOA-Glc, <italic>BX10</italic> and <italic>BX11</italic>, were dramatically upregulated in response to <italic>O. pratensis</italic> and <italic>T. urticae</italic> herbivory as well as wounding at 2 h, and remained strongly induced at 24 h. Two other genes, <italic>BX13</italic> and <italic>BX14</italic> that are needed for the production of HDM2BOA-Glc, were also induced by mite herbivory, but with upregulation only observed at 24 h; in response to wounding, <italic>BX13</italic> was also upregulated at 24 h, albeit only moderately. We also compared the relative upregulation of benzoxazinoid biosynthesis genes in response to spider mite herbivory at 24 h to those reported for <italic>S. exigua</italic> feeding at the same time point (<xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">Tzin et al., 2017</xref>). Although different stage plants were used (see the section &#x0201c;Discussion&#x0201d;), genes for the synthesis of DIMBOA-Glc (e.g., <italic>BX1</italic> and <italic>BX2</italic>) were less strongly induced by spider mites, while those for the conversion of DIMBOA-Glu to HDMBOA-Glc and HDM2BOA-Glc (especially <italic>BX10</italic> and <italic>BX11</italic>) were induced strongly by both mites as well as the caterpillar herbivore (<bold>Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM4">4</xref></bold>).</p><p>In the W22 maize inbred, <italic>Ds</italic> transposon insertions have been recovered in three genes responsible for DIMBOA-Glc synthesis &#x02013; <italic>BX1</italic>, <italic>BX2</italic>, and <italic>BX6</italic> (<xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">Tzin et al., 2015a</xref>). For <italic>O. pratensis</italic>, reproductive performance, as assessed by the number of progeny per female, did not differ significantly following infestation of wild-type and <italic>bx</italic> mutant plants (ANOVA, <italic>P</italic> = 0.313; <bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7C</xref></bold>). In contrast, for <italic>T. urticae</italic> stark differences were observed (ANOVA, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 10<sup>-7</sup>; <bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7D</xref></bold>). While the number of <italic>T. urticae</italic> progeny did not differ between wild-type (W22) and <italic>bx6::Ds</italic> plants, significantly more progeny were observed on both <italic>bx1::Ds</italic> and <italic>bx2::Ds</italic> plants compared to wild-type, and significantly more progeny were observed on <italic>bx2::Ds</italic> compared to <italic>bx1::Ds</italic> plants (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 after correction for multiple comparisons with Tukey&#x02019;s HSD method).</p></sec><sec><title>Genes Required for the Production of Volatile Plant Compounds Are Induced by Mite Herbivory</title><p>In addition to green leaf volatiles and methyl salicylate (MeSA) &#x02013; volatile organic compounds whose biosynthesis genes were either constitutively expressed or induced by mite herbivory (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref></bold> and <bold>Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">8</xref></bold>) &#x02013; terpenes are well-characterized herbivore-induced plant volatiles (HIPVs) that mediate plant responses to herbivory, including indirect defenses (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Kessler and Baldwin, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">Singh and Sharma, 2015</xref>). In maize, the <italic>TERPENE SYNTHASE</italic> (<italic>TPS</italic>) genes <italic>TPS10</italic>, <italic>TPS2</italic>, and <italic>TPS3</italic> were highly induced at 2 h in response to <italic>O. pratensis</italic> and <italic>T. urticae</italic>, as well as by wounding (each gene remained induced at 24 h; <bold>Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">11</xref></bold>). Additionally, 14 other putative maize <italic>TPS</italic> genes were induced with lesser fold changes, primarily at 24 h, in response to mite herbivory, or at 2 h in response to wounding. Patterns were similar for barley <italic>TPS</italic> genes including <italic>MLOC_56812</italic> and <italic>MLOC_76989</italic>, which were strongly induced by <italic>O. pratensis</italic> and <italic>T. urticae</italic> herbivory at both time points, and <italic>MLOC_13618</italic> at 24 h. In maize, TPS2 and TPS10 synthesize multiple products. For TPS2, two products are (E)-nerolidol and (E,E)-geranyllinalool, which are subsequently converted to the homoterpenes (E)-3,8-dimethyl-1,4,7-nonatriene (DMNT) and (E,E)-4,8,12-trimethyltrideca-1,3,7,11-tetraene (TMTT), respectively. Recently, <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">Richter et al. (2016)</xref> implicated the cytochrome P450 genes <italic>CYP92C5</italic> and <italic>CYP92C6</italic> in the final step for the production of DMNT and TMTT. Both genes were induced in response to mite herbivory at 2 or 24 h, and <italic>CYP92C5</italic> was upregulated by wounding at 2 h (<bold>Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">11</xref></bold>).</p><p>In maize, <italic>IGL</italic> is responsible for volatile indole, which is inducible by an insect trigger, and was recently shown to prime defenses within and between maize plants (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Erb et al., 2015</xref>). In response to herbivory by <italic>O. pratensis</italic> and <italic>T. urticae</italic> in maize, <italic>IGL</italic> was modestly upregulated at 24 h (log<sub>2</sub> fold changes &#x0223c;2) but not at 2 h; in the wounding treatment, <italic>IGL</italic> was upregulated by a similar fold change at 2 h, but was not significantly changed in expression at 24 h (<bold>Supplementary Data Sheet <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM9">4</xref></bold>).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Whether specialist and generalist herbivores induce different plant responses, and if so, to what degree the herbivore or the plant benefits, has attracted long-standing interest (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Ali and Agrawal, 2012</xref>). Experimental approaches to tackle these questions have often been confounded by factors including differences in feeding guild, comparisons between phylogenetically divergent herbivores, inclusion of single plant hosts, variation in the extent of tissue damage, and the lack of an expectation of plant defense responses in the absence of (potential) manipulation by herbivores (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Ali and Agrawal, 2012</xref>). Our study addresses several of these confounding factors. While <italic>O. pratensis</italic> and <italic>T. urticae</italic> are in different genera, they are closely related within the family Tetranychidae (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Matsuda et al., 2014</xref>), differ little in size and morphology, and cause similar levels of tissue damage on barley and maize leaves. At the cellular level, we found that both species feed on mesophyll cells. This pattern of damage agrees with reports for <italic>Tetranychus</italic> mites in dicots, where empty mesophyll cells were reported at feeding sites (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Bensoussan et al., 2016</xref>, and references therein). Further, <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Bensoussan et al. (2016)</xref> showed that adult <italic>T. urticae</italic> females feed on mesophyll cells in <italic>A. thaliana</italic> and bean by inserting their stylets either through stomata or between epidermal pavement cells. Our observation of a seemingly intact epidermis overlying empty mesophyll cells in barley suggests that spider mites use a similar feeding mechanism in grasses.</p><p>Although spider mites cause less dramatic tissue damage than insects like caterpillars, both <italic>O. pratensis</italic> and <italic>T. urticae</italic> induced pronounced changes in gene expression and peroxidase activity in barley and maize. Strikingly, the DEG sets induced by the two mite species in both plant hosts were similar in composition as well as in the direction (up- or downregulation) and magnitude of fold changes. For the latter, several modest differences in magnitude were apparent. For instance, <italic>O. pratensis</italic> induced a slightly stronger transcriptomic response than <italic>T. urticae</italic> at 24 h in barley, and at 2 h in maize. Whether these differences reflect modulation of plant responses by either herbivore, or alternatively arise from behavioral differences or other factors, is not clear. Nevertheless, neither mite species appears to differentially manipulate barley or maize defenses to a great extent (or alternatively, the two plants do not distinguish between the two mite species to mount different responses). A caveat is that our study does not rule out the possibility that manipulation could occur post-transcriptionally. It should further be noted that our study used only one strain of <italic>T. urticae</italic>, which we maintained on bean until several generations before collecting barley and maize transcriptomic data. Several experimental studies have documented that the generalist <italic>T. urticae</italic> can adapt to its hosts when continuously maintained over many generations (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Gould, 1979</xref>; <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Fry, 1989</xref>; <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Agrawal, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Magalh&#x000e3;es et al., 2007</xref>). If <italic>T. urticae</italic> (and possibly <italic>O. pratensis</italic>) populations adapt to specific grass hosts, potentially by gaining the ability to modulate plant defenses, is not known. Therefore, whether our findings generalize to all <italic>T. urticae</italic> and <italic>O. pratensis</italic> populations is an outstanding question. However, our experimental design mimicked the agriculturally relevant setting for cereal crops in which spider mites invade fields from weeds or other crops, persist during the growing season for a modest number of generations, and then move to other hosts for overwintering (<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Margolies and Kennedy, 1985</xref>).</p><p>Our findings of similar barley and maize responses to <italic>O. pratensis</italic> and <italic>T. urticae</italic> herbivory do not rule out the possibility that both suppress plant responses similarly. To test this, as well as to understand how grasses perceive mite herbivores, we also included a wounding treatment against which potential suppression of defenses could be assessed (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Howe and Jander, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Ali and Agrawal, 2012</xref>). The utility of a wounding treatment depends largely on how well the treatment mimics patterns of herbivore tissue damage (<xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">Mithofer et al., 2005</xref>). In the case of mites, mimicking mechanical damage to individual mesophyll cells is not possible. Further, our wounding treatments did not replicate the continuous nature of mite feeding, and consisted instead of marked and instantaneous tissue damage at the beginning of treatments. Despite these caveats, in both barley and maize, genes that responded most strongly to herbivory at both 2 and 24 h also responded strongly to wounding alone. This suggests that grasses readily perceive physical tissue damage by spider mites and mount strong defense responses. Additionally, for many known defensive genes, it was striking that expression changes induced by wounding (up- or downregulation, as well as magnitude of fold changes) were similar to those induced by mite feeding. Therefore, within the limits of our experimental design, we found no obvious signs that <italic>O. pratensis</italic> or <italic>T. urticae</italic> suppress plant defenses associated with tissue disruption.</p><p>In both barley and maize, reprogramming of the transcriptome in response to mite feeding was dynamic over a 24-h time period. At 2 h, most DEGs were upregulated, including genes associated with JA and other phytohormone signaling, the production of some specialized metabolites, and the synthesis of HIPVs. More dramatic changes in gene expression were observed at 24 h, including a mix of up- and downregulated genes. These dynamics resemble those reported previously in studies with <italic>T. urticae</italic> in dicots including <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, tomato, and grapevine (<xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr">Zhurov et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Martel et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">D&#x000ed;az-Riquelme et al., 2016</xref>). Recently, <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">Santamar&#x000ed;a et al. (2018)</xref> examined transcriptomic responses to <italic>T. urticae</italic> in barley in a design that examined both biotic and abiotic stresses. Although their experimental design differed markedly from ours, with transcriptomic responses assessed at long time points (RNA-seq data were collected after 7 days of herbivore exposure), they also observed upregulation of genes associated with JA biosynthesis and signaling. In maize, our findings are also consistent with those of <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">Szczepaniec et al. (2013)</xref>, who found by reverse transcription quantitative polymerase chain reaction that several marker genes for JA and SA signaling were upregulated after 3 days of herbivory by <italic>T. urticae</italic>. More generally, at the whole transcriptome level for maize, the transcriptomic changes we observed following herbivory by spider mites are also similar to those reported for herbivory by the caterpillar <italic>S. exigua</italic> (<xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">Tzin et al., 2017</xref>). These similarities encompassed rapid induction of diverse LOX genes, including but not limited to those involved in JA biosynthesis and signaling. This suggests that chewing insects and mesophyll-feeding mites induce globally similar transcriptomic responses even though patterns of tissue damage differ radically. The downregulation of genes involved in photosynthesis that we observed in response to mite herbivory has been reported to be a general response to biotic stress (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Bilgin et al., 2010</xref>).</p><p>We found that genes in several families encoding defensive proteins, including protease inhibitors and chitinases, were upregulated in our study. Transgenic expression of plant protease inhibitors has been shown to reduce <italic>T. urticae</italic>&#x02019;s performance on several plant hosts (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Carrillo et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">Santamar&#x000ed;a et al., 2012</xref>). The same was also observed for transgenic expression of a chitinase, albeit from an insect source (<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">McCafferty et al., 2006</xref>), although it should be noted that plant-produced chitinases in the frass of <italic>S. frugiperda</italic> were found to suppress plant defenses and favor the herbivore (<xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">Ray et al., 2016</xref>). These transgenic studies relied on overexpression, however, and the extent to which endogenous production of protease inhibitors or chitinases in barley and maize leaves impacts spider mites is not known. In insects, protease overexpression or expression of alternative proteases is one route to overcome ingested, plant-produced inhibitors (e.g., <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Kuwar et al., 2015</xref>). This mechanism is likely relevant for <italic>T. urticae</italic>, as sequencing of the <italic>T. urticae</italic> genome revealed expansions of protease families, some of which were found to be highly induced upon plant host shifts (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Grbi&#x00107; et al., 2011</xref>). Whether protease families are expanded in <italic>O. pratensis</italic>, or whether this specialist has evolved specialized digestive proteases to overcome the inhibitors produced by its hosts in Poaceae, is an outstanding question.</p><p>Beyond defensive proteins, HIPVs released from feeding sites on grass leaves may play important roles in indirect defenses against mites. In both barley and maize, genes for the synthesis of SA (the precursor to the volatile MeSA), as well as for the synthesis of terpenes, were upregulated in response to mite herbivory. These can serve as cues to predators of spider mites, which include predatory mites as well as winged ladybird beetles (family Coccinellidae). Within Coccinellidae, minute species of the tribe Stethorini feed primarily on mites in the Tetranychidae family (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Biddinger et al., 2009</xref>). For instance, <italic>Parastethorus nigripes</italic> is an introduced species that has established on <italic>O. pratensis</italic> on maize in the southern United States (<xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">Pollock and Michels, 2002</xref>). In Y-tube olfactometer experiments, predatory mites were attracted by MeSA or terpenes (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">De Boer et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Kappers et al., 2005</xref>), and synthetic MeSA was shown to attract a Stethorini species (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">James and Price, 2004</xref>). <italic>IGL</italic> was also modestly upregulated in maize in response to herbivory, suggesting that volatile indole is released at mite feeding sites. While indole is a priming agent in maize (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Erb et al., 2015</xref>), whether it also serves as an attractant for predators of spider mites is unknown.</p><p>Apart from defensive proteins and HIPVs, several specialized compounds are likely to play roles in defense against mite herbivores. Mirroring findings reported for herbivory by <italic>S. exigua</italic> (<xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">Tzin et al., 2017</xref>), genes encoding 9-LOX proteins were rapidly induced by mite feeding. Unlike 13-LOX proteins involved in JA synthesis or the production of green leaf volatiles, LOX3, 4, and 5 belong to the 9-LOX clade, which likely has diverse functions including the production of &#x0201c;death acid&#x0201d; compounds; 10-OPEA, one such compound, was shown to reduce the performance of fungal pathogens and the lepidopteran herbivore <italic>Helicoverpa zea</italic> (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Christensen et al., 2015</xref>). More recently, it was shown that <italic>S. exigua</italic> growth increased on maize plants with transposon insertions in <italic>LOX4</italic> as compared to wild-type plants (<xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr">Woldemariam et al., 2018</xref>). These findings, coupled with the upregulation of <italic>LOX3</italic>, <italic>4</italic>, and <italic>5</italic> that we observed in our study, suggest that members of the 9-LOX clade should also be assessed for roles in deterring spider mites.</p><p>Additionally, we observed modest upregulation of genes involved in the synthesis of DIMBOA-Glc. However, we found dramatic and rapid upregulation of <italic>BX10</italic> and <italic>BX11</italic> that modify DIMBOA-Glc to produce HDMBOA-Glc, which has been associated with resistance to multiple lepidopteran species that feed on maize (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Glauser et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">Tzin et al., 2015b</xref>). In contrast, we did not observe as rapid or as strong an induction for genes needed for the synthesis of HDM2BOA-Glc. This may suggest different transcriptional regulation of the biosynthesis genes for major classes of benzoxazinoids derived from DIMBOA. Further, despite globally similar transcriptomic responses to mite herbivory in our study compared to those reported for <italic>S. exigua</italic> (<xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">Tzin et al., 2017</xref>), some <italic>BX</italic> genes, especially those required for DIMBOA-Glc and HDM2BOA-Glc synthesis (e.g., <italic>BX1</italic> and <italic>BX14</italic>, respectively), were more strongly induced by <italic>S. exigua</italic>. In <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">Tzin et al.&#x02019;s (2017)</xref> study, younger plants were used for the transcriptomic analysis, and the inducibility of benzoxazinoids has been shown to decrease as maize plants age (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">K&#x000f6;hler et al., 2015</xref>). Whether differences in plant stage, the scope of tissue damage, or other factors explain differences in relative induction for some benzoxazinoid synthesis genes between our study and that of <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">Tzin et al. (2017)</xref> warrants additional investigation.</p><p>Mutations in the benzoxazinoid pathway in maize allowed us to test if benzoxazinoids deter <italic>O. pratensis</italic> or <italic>T. urticae</italic>, both, or neither. For <italic>T. urticae</italic>, performance was markedly reduced on wild-type plants compared to homozygous <italic>bx1::Ds</italic> and <italic>bx2::Ds</italic> plants. Our finding that <italic>T. urticae</italic> performed better on <italic>bx2::Ds</italic> plants than on <italic>bx1::Ds</italic> plants was unexpected, as both are reported to reduce DIMBOA to the same low level in W22 (<xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">Tzin et al., 2017</xref>). One possibility is that indole produced by BX1, which would be anticipated to accumulate in <italic>bx2::Ds</italic> mutant plants, negatively affects <italic>T. urticae</italic>. Previously, <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">Tzin et al. (2015a)</xref> found that DIMBOA-Glc levels were only modestly reduced (&#x0223c;70%) in <italic>bx6::Ds</italic> plants, suggesting substantial functional redundancy at the respective step in the benzoxazinoid pathway. This likely explains our finding that mite performance was not significantly different on <italic>bx6::Ds</italic> compared to wild-type plants.</p><p>In line with our finding for <italic>T. urticae</italic> and benzoxazinoids in maize, <italic>A. thaliana</italic> plants unable to make indole glucosinolates &#x02013; a class of specialized compounds in the Brassicaceae &#x02013; are less resistant to <italic>T. urticae</italic> (<xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr">Zhurov et al., 2014</xref>). Combined with results from our study, this observation is at odds with the supposition, for which there is mixed experimental support in insects, that generalists should be good at suppressing phylogenetically conserved plant defense pathways (like canonical phytohormone signaling upstream of plant family-specific defensive compounds) (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Ali and Agrawal, 2012</xref>). It is consistent, however, with an important role for detoxification in underlying <italic>T. urticae</italic>&#x02019;s extreme host range, as supported by the finding of expansions of diverse detoxification genes in this species&#x02019; genome (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Grbi&#x00107; et al., 2011</xref>), and its known ability to detoxify compounds from diverse chemical classes (<xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">Van Leeuwen and Dermauw, 2016</xref>). However, specialized compounds that typify plant families, like benzoxazinoids in Poaceae, nonetheless appear to be costly for <italic>T. urticae</italic>. It should also be noted that our performance assessments for <italic>T. urticae</italic> on <italic>bx</italic> mutants were performed on young plants, in which levels of benzoxazinoids are expected to be higher than in older plants (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Cambier et al., 2000</xref>; <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">K&#x000f6;hler et al., 2015</xref>). Although benzoxazinoid synthesis can be induced in maize (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">K&#x000f6;hler et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Maag et al., 2016</xref>), screens of maize lines for resistance to <italic>T. urticae</italic> have shown that while many lines are resistant when young, resistance is ameliorated or essentially lost in older plants for some, although not all, inbred lines (<xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">Tadmor et al., 1999</xref>). Therefore, determining the extent to which benzoxazinoids deter herbivory by <italic>T. urticae</italic> in field settings &#x02013; where infestation and significant plant damage typically occur later in the growing season &#x02013; requires further study.</p><p>In contrast, our characterization of <italic>O. pratensis</italic> performance on wild-type and <italic>bx</italic> mutant plants suggests that <italic>O. pratensis</italic> is not affected by benzoxazinoids. The simplest interpretation of this finding is that the route to specialization for <italic>O. pratensis</italic>, at least with respect to this class of toxic compounds, lies in a specialized mechanism of detoxification or inactivation. Precedence for this comes from insects, where several caterpillars have been shown to enzymatically render ingested benzoxazinoids non-toxic (or less toxic) by glucosylation (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Glauser et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Maag et al., 2014</xref>). Our findings with <italic>O. pratensis</italic> contrast with those of other specialist mite herbivores like <italic>T. evansi</italic> and <italic>A. lycopersici</italic>, for which suppression of host plant defenses has been documented (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Glas et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Alba et al., 2015</xref>). Thus, multiple paths to specialization appear to have been taken by different herbivorous mites.</p></sec><sec><title>Concluding Remarks and Future Directions</title><p>Our findings revealed dynamic yet highly correlated transcriptomic responses of two major cereal crops to two spider mite herbivores. Further, the plant responses resembled those observed for wounding, a physical component of herbivory. Taken together, these results suggest that neither mite species manipulates defense responses of these grasses, nor that the grass hosts distinguish between the generalist and specialist mites to initiate different (and potentially adaptive) defensive programs. Nevertheless, we found that the generalist <italic>T. urticae</italic> is negatively impacted by the benzoxazinoid defenses of maize. Our study included the widely used maize inbreds B73 and W22, both of which are readily fed upon by <italic>T. urticae</italic>. These lines are representative of most maize inbred lines in that they are comparatively sensitive to <italic>T. urticae</italic>; nevertheless, a small number of lines have been reported to be resistant throughout their ontogeny (<xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">Tadmor et al., 1999</xref>). Our findings suggest that variation in benzoxazinoid levels or types should be investigated as a potential factor in explaining resistance in maize to <italic>T. urticae</italic>, and intraspecific variation in benzoxazinoid biosynthesis or accumulation in maize has been documented (<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">Meihls et al., 2012</xref>, <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Further, in agriculture, economic damage to maize from spider mites is typically observed under drought conditions. As we did not include drought stress as a factor in our experimental design, a future challenge will be to test whether this key abiotic stress influences the relative defense responses of cereals to generalist and specialist spider mites. Given the importance of resistant germplasm for breeding programs, these studies should be extended as well to examine maize varieties previously reported to be mite resistant.</p></sec><sec><title>Data Availability</title><p>The RNA-seq data sets for barley and maize generated and analyzed for this study are available through Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) under accession numbers <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="GSE83676">GSE83676</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="GSE100121">GSE100121</ext-link>, respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Author Contributions</title><p>HB, RR, and RC conceived the research. HB, RG, RC, SL, AR, GG, and RR performed the experiments. Analysis of the data was performed primarily by HB and RG. HB, RG, and RC assumed primary responsibility for writing the manuscript, with input from all authors.</p></sec><sec><title>Conflict of Interest Statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> This work was supported by National Science Foundation PGRP award 1444449 to RC and RR. RG was supported by the National Institutes of Health Genetics Training Grant TM32GM007464.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><p>We thank A. Kurlovs for assistance in maintaining the W-GR strain, G. Jander for providing homozygous <italic>bx::Ds</italic> mutant seed stocks, and V. Grbi&#x00107; and V. Zhurov for providing helpful comments on the manuscript.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="fn01"><label>1</label><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://Github.com/chapmanb/bcbio-nextgen">https://Github.com/chapmanb/bcbio-nextgen</ext-link></p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="supplementary material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpls.2018.01222/full#supplementary-material">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpls.2018.01222/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1"><media xlink:href="Table_1.XLSX"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM2"><media xlink:href="Table_2.XLSX"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM3"><media xlink:href="Table_3.XLSX"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM4"><media xlink:href="Table_4.XLSX"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM5"><media xlink:href="Presentation_1.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM6"><media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM7"><media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_2.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM8"><media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_3.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM9"><media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_4.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Host-range evolution: adaptation and trade-offs in fitness of mites on alternative hosts.</article-title>
<source><italic>Ecology</italic></source>
<volume>81</volume>
<fpage>500</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>508</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alba</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schimmel</surname><given-names>B. C. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Glas</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ataide</surname><given-names>L. M. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pappas</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Villarroel</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Spider mites suppress tomato defenses downstream of jasmonate and salicylate independently of hormonal crosstalk.</article-title>
<source><italic>New Phytol.</italic></source>
<volume>205</volume>
<fpage>828</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>840</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.13075</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25297722?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25297722</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alexa</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahnenfuhrer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lengauer</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Improved scoring of functional groups from gene expression data by decorrelating GO graph structure.</article-title>
<source><italic>Bioinformatics</italic></source>
<volume>22</volume>
<fpage>1600</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1607</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btl140</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16606683?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16606683</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Specialist versus generalist insect herbivores and plant defense.</article-title>
<source><italic>Trends Plant Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>17</volume>
<fpage>293</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>302</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2012.02.006</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22425020?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22425020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Kaisi</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elmore</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guzman</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanna</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Helmers</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Drought impact on crop production and the soil environment: 2012 experiences from Iowa.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Soil Water Conserv.</italic></source>
<volume>68</volume>
<fpage>19A</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24A</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2489/jswc.68.1.19A</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pyl</surname><given-names>P. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>HTSeq&#x02014;a Python framework to work with high-throughput sequencing data.</article-title>
<source><italic>Bioinformatics</italic></source>
<volume>31</volume>
<fpage>166</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>169</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu638</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25260700?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25260700</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Archer</surname><given-names>T. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bynum</surname><given-names>E. D.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Yield loss to corn from feeding by the Banks grass mite and two-spotted spider mite (Acari: Tetranychidae).</article-title>
<source><italic>Exp. Appl. Acarol.</italic></source>
<volume>17</volume>
<fpage>895</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>903</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02328066</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bacon</surname><given-names>O. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyons</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baskett</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1962</year>). <article-title>Effects of spider mite infestations on dent corn in California.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Econ. Entomol.</italic></source>
<volume>55</volume>
<fpage>823</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>825</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jee/55.6.823</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bensoussan</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Santamar&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhurov</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x000ed;az</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grbi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grbi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Plant-herbivore interaction: dissection of the cellular pattern of Tetranychus urticae feeding on the host plant.</article-title>
<source><italic>Front. Plant Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>7</volume>:<issue>1105</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2016.01105</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27512397?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27512397</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Biddinger</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hull</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Coccinellidae as predators of mites: stethorini in biological control.</article-title>
<source><italic>Biol. Control</italic></source>
<volume>51</volume>
<fpage>268</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>283</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biocontrol.2009.05.014</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bilgin</surname><given-names>D. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zavala</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clough</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ort</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>DeLUCIA</surname><given-names>E. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Biotic stress globally downregulates photosynthesis genes.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell Environ.</italic></source>
<volume>33</volume>
<fpage>1597</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1613</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-3040.2010.02167.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20444224?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20444224</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blasi</surname><given-names>&#x000c9;. A. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buffon</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>R. Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dametto</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferla</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Alterations in rice, corn and wheat plants infested by phytophagous mite.</article-title>
<source><italic>Int. J. Acarol.</italic></source>
<volume>41</volume>
<fpage>10</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01647954.2014.988643</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borrego</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolomiets</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Synthesis and functions of jasmonates in maize.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plants</italic></source>
<volume>5</volume>:<issue>41</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/plants5040041</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27916835?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27916835</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boyer</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1982</year>). <article-title>Plant productivity and environment.</article-title>
<source><italic>Science</italic></source>
<volume>218</volume>
<fpage>443</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>448</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.218.4571.443</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 17808529?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17808529</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brandenburg</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>G. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1982</year>). <article-title>Intercrop relationships and spider mite dispersal in a corn/peanut agro-ecosystem.</article-title>
<source><italic>Entomol. Exp. Appl.</italic></source>
<volume>32</volume>
<fpage>269</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>276</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1570-7458.1982.tb03217.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bynum</surname><given-names>E. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Michels</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bible</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Impact of Banks grass mite damage to yield and quality of maize silage.</article-title>
<source><italic>Southwest. Entomol.</italic></source>
<volume>40</volume>
<fpage>251</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>262</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3958/059.040.0202</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Camacho</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coulouris</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Avagyan</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Papadopoulos</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bealer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>BLAST+: architecture and applications.</article-title>
<source><italic>BMC Bioinformatics</italic></source>
<volume>10</volume>
<issue>421</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-10-421</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20003500?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20003500</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cambier</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hance</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Hoffmann</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Variation of DIMBOA and related compounds content in relation to the age and plant organ in maize.</article-title>
<source><italic>Phytochemistry</italic></source>
<volume>53</volume>
<fpage>223</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>229</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0031-9422(99)00498-7</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 10680175?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10680175</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carrillo</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramessar</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cambra</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Casta&#x000f1;era</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortego</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Expression of a barley cystatin gene in maize enhances resistance against phytophagous mites by altering their cysteine-proteases.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell Rep.</italic></source>
<volume>30</volume>
<fpage>101</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>112</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00299-010-0948-z</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21082183?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21082183</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>L. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Archer</surname><given-names>T. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyle</surname><given-names>W. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1979</year>). <article-title>Influences of irrigation practices on spider mite densities on field corn.</article-title>
<source><italic>Environ. Entomol.</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>196</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>201</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ee/8.2.196</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huffaker</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sims</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziemann</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Doehlemann</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Maize death acids, 9-lipoxygenase&#x02013;derived cyclopente(a)nones, display activity as cytotoxic phytoalexins and transcriptional mediators.</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</italic></source>
<volume>112</volume>
<fpage>11407</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11412</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1511131112</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26305953?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26305953</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nemchenko</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borrego</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sobhy</surname><given-names>I. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosak</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>The maize lipoxygenase, ZmLOX 10, mediates green leaf volatile, jasmonate and herbivore-induced plant volatile production for defense against insect attack.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant J.</italic></source>
<volume>74</volume>
<fpage>59</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.12101</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23279660?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23279660</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cock</surname><given-names>P. J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Antao</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalke</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Biopython: freely available python tools for computational molecular biology and bioinformatics.</article-title>
<source><italic>Bioinformatics</italic></source>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>1422</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1423</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp163</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19304878?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19304878</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Boer</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Posthumus</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dicke</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Identification of volatiles that are used in discrimination between plants infested with prey or nonprey herbivores by a predatory mite.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Chem. Ecol.</italic></source>
<volume>30</volume>
<fpage>2215</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2230</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/B:JOEC.0000048784.79031.5e</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15672666</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dermauw</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wybouw</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rombauts</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Menten</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vontas</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grbi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>A link between host plant adaptation and pesticide resistance in the polyphagous spider mite Tetranychus urticae.</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</italic></source>
<volume>110</volume>
<fpage>E113</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>E122</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1213214110</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23248300?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23248300</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>D&#x000ed;az-Riquelme</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhurov</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rioja</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-Moreno</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Torres-P&#x000e9;rez</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grimplet</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Comparative genome-wide transcriptome analysis of <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> responses to adapted and non-adapted strains of two-spotted spider mite, Tetranyhus urticae.</article-title>
<source><italic>BMC Genomics</italic></source>
<volume>17</volume>:<issue>74</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-016-2401-3</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26801623?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26801623</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dobin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlesinger</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Drenkow</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaleski</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jha</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>STAR: ultrafast universal RNA-seq aligner.</article-title>
<source><italic>Bioinformatics</italic></source>
<volume>29</volume>
<fpage>15</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts635</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23104886?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23104886</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dobler</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalla</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagschal</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Community-wide convergent evolution in insect adaptation to toxic cardenolides by substitutions in the Na,K-ATPase.</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</italic></source>
<volume>109</volume>
<fpage>13040</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13045</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1202111109</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22826239?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22826239</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dunlop</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Geological history and phylogeny of Chelicerata.</article-title>
<source><italic>Arthropod Struct. Dev.</italic></source>
<volume>39</volume>
<fpage>124</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>142</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.asd.2010.01.003</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20093195?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20093195</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eckelkamp</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehmann</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schopfer</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Wound-induced systemic accumulation of a transcript coding for a Bowman-Birk trypsin inhibitor-related protein in maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic> L.) <italic>seedlings</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>FEBS Lett.</italic></source>
<volume>323</volume>
<fpage>73</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>76</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0014-5793(93)81451-5</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 8495751?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8495751</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erb</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Veyrat</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>C. A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frey</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ton</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Indole is an essential herbivore-induced volatile priming signal in maize.</article-title>
<source><italic>Nat. Commun.</italic></source>
<volume>6</volume>:<issue>6273</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms7273</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25683900?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25683900</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feese</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilde</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1977</year>). <article-title>Factors affecting survival and reproduction of the Banks grass mite.</article-title>
<source><italic>Oligonychus pratensis. Environ. Entomol.</italic></source>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>53</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>56</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ee/6.1.53</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Teetes</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1977</year>). <article-title>Resistance in sorghums to the Banks grass mite.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Econ. Entomol.</italic></source>
<volume>70</volume>
<fpage>259</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>262</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jee/70.2.259</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fry</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Evolutionary adaptation to host plants in a laboratory population of the phytophagous mite Tetranychus urticae Koch.</article-title>
<source><italic>Oecologia</italic></source>
<volume>81</volume>
<fpage>559</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>565</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00378969</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28312654?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28312654</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glas</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alba</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Simoni</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Villarroel</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoops</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schimmel</surname><given-names>B. C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Defense suppression benefits herbivores that have a monopoly on their feeding site but can backfire within natural communities.</article-title>
<source><italic>BMC Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>12</volume>:<issue>98</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12915-014-0098-9</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25403155?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25403155</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glauser</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marti</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Villard</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Doyen</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfender</surname><given-names>J.-L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turlings</surname><given-names>T. C. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Induction and detoxification of maize 1,4-benzoxazin-3-ones by insect herbivores.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant J.</italic></source>
<volume>68</volume>
<fpage>901</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>911</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2011.04740.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21838747?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21838747</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glawischnig</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gr&#x000fc;n</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frey</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gierl</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Cytochrome P450 monooxygenases of DIBOA biosynthesis: specificity and conservation among grasses.</article-title>
<source><italic>Phytochemistry</italic></source>
<volume>50</volume>
<fpage>925</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>930</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0031-9422(98)00318-5</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 10385992?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10385992</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1979</year>). <article-title>Rapid host range evolution in a population of the phytophagous mite <italic>Tetranychus urticae</italic> Koch.</article-title>
<source><italic>Evolution</italic></source>
<volume>33</volume>
<fpage>791</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>802</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2407646</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28568440?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28568440</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grbi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Leeuwen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rombauts</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rouz&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grbi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The genome of <italic>Tetranychus urticae</italic> reveals herbivorous pest adaptations.</article-title>
<source><italic>Nature</italic></source>
<volume>479</volume>
<fpage>487</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>492</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature10640</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22113690?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22113690</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>L. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mylroie</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozkan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Windham</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Characterization of the maize chitinase genes and their effect on <italic>Aspergillus flavus</italic> and aflatoxin accumulation resistance.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS One</italic></source>
<volume>10</volume>:<issue>e0126185</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0126185</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26090679?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26090679</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hildebrand</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>G. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luu</surname><given-names>K. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Volden</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <article-title>Peroxidative responses of leaves in two soybean genotypes injured by twospotted spider mites (Acari: Tetranychidae).</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Econ. Entomol.</italic></source>
<volume>79</volume>
<fpage>1459</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1465</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jee/79.6.1459</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holtzer</surname><given-names>T. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perring</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>). <article-title>Winter and spring distribution and density of Banks grass mite (Acari: Tetranychidae) in adjacent wheat and corn.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Kans. Entomol. Soc.</italic></source>
<volume>57</volume>
<fpage>333</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>335</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jander</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Plant immunity to insect herbivores.</article-title>
<source><italic>Annu. Rev. Plant Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>59</volume>
<fpage>41</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>66</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.arplant.59.032607.092825</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18031220?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18031220</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>T. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Field-testing of methyl salicylate for recruitment and retention of beneficial insects in grapes and hops.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Chem. Ecol.</italic></source>
<volume>30</volume>
<fpage>1613</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1628</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15537163?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15537163</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kappers</surname><given-names>I. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aharoni</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Herpen</surname><given-names>T. W. J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luckerhoff</surname><given-names>L. L. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dicke</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouwmeester</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Genetic engineering of terpenoid metabolism attracts bodyguards to <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Science</italic></source>
<volume>309</volume>
<fpage>2070</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2072</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1116232</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16179482?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16179482</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>I. T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Plant responses to insect herbivory: the emerging molecular analysis.</article-title>
<source><italic>Annu. Rev. Plant Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>53</volume>
<fpage>299</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>328</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.arplant.53.100301.135207</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 12221978?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12221978</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>K&#x000f6;hler</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maag</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Veyrat</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Glauser</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfender</surname><given-names>J.-L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turlings</surname><given-names>T. C. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Within-plant distribution of 1,4-benzoxazin-3-ones contributes to herbivore niche differentiation in maize.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell Environ.</italic></source>
<volume>38</volume>
<fpage>1081</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1093</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pce.12464</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25293400?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25293400</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>A. J. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Catabolism and deactivation of the lipid-derived hormone jasmonoyl-isoleucine.</article-title>
<source><italic>Front. Plant Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>3</volume>:<issue>19</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2012.00019</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22639640?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22639640</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuwar</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pauchet</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heckel</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Adaptive regulation of digestive serine proteases in the larval midgut of Helicoverpa armigera in response to a plant protease inhibitor.</article-title>
<source><italic>Insect Biochem. Mol. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>59</volume>
<fpage>18</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>29</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ibmb.2015.01.016</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25662099?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25662099</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Novak</surname><given-names>N. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Expression of poplar chitinase in tomato leads to inhibition of development in colorado potato beetle.</article-title>
<source><italic>Biotechnol. Lett.</italic></source>
<volume>28</volume>
<fpage>593</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>599</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10529-006-0022-7</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16614898?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16614898</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Increased activities of peroxidase and polyphenol oxidase enhance cassava resistance to <italic>Tetranychus urticae</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Exp. Appl. Acarol.</italic></source>
<volume>71</volume>
<fpage>195</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>209</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10493-017-0125-y</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28405840?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28405840</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Love</surname><given-names>M. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Moderated estimation of fold change and dispersion for RNA-seq data with DESeq2.</article-title>
<source><italic>Genome Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>15</volume>:<issue>550</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-014-0550-8</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25516281?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25516281</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maag</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalvit</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thevenet</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000f6;hler</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wouters</surname><given-names>F. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vass&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>3-&#x003b2;-d-Glucopyranosyl-6-methoxy-2-benzoxazolinone (MBOA-N-Glc) is an insect detoxification product of maize 1,4-benzoxazin-3-ones.</article-title>
<source><italic>Phytochemistry</italic></source>
<volume>102</volume>
<fpage>97</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>105</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2014.03.018</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24713572?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24713572</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maag</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000f6;hler</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>C. A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frey</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfender</surname><given-names>J.-L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turlings</surname><given-names>T. C. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Highly localized and persistent induction of <italic>Bx1</italic>-dependent herbivore resistance factors in maize.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant J.</italic></source>
<volume>88</volume>
<fpage>976</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>991</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.13308</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27538820?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27538820</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Magalh&#x000e3;es</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fayard</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carbonell</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olivieri</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Adaptation in a spider mite population after long-term evolution on a single host plant.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Evol. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>20</volume>
<fpage>2016</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2027</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1420-9101.2007.01365.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 17714318?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17714318</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mansour</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bar-Zur</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Resistance of maize inbred lines to the carmine spider mite, <italic>Tetranychus cinnabarinus</italic> (Acari: Tetranychidae).</article-title>
<source><italic>Maydica</italic></source>
<volume>37</volume>
<fpage>343</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>345</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Margolies</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>G. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>Movement of the twospotted spider mite, <italic>Tetranychus urticae</italic>, among hosts in a corn-peanut agroecosystem.</article-title>
<source><italic>Entomol. Exp. Appl.</italic></source>
<volume>37</volume>
<fpage>55</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1570-7458.1985.tb03452.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martel</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhurov</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Navarro</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cazaux</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Auger</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Tomato whole genome transcriptional response to <italic>Tetranychus urticae</italic> identifies divergence of spider mite-induced responses between tomato and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Mol. Plant. Microbe Interact.</italic></source>
<volume>28</volume>
<fpage>343</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>361</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/MPMI-09-14-0291-FI</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25679539?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25679539</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morishita</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinomoto</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gotoh</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Phylogenetic analysis of the spider mite sub-family <italic>Tetranychinae</italic> (Acari: Tetranychidae) based on the mitochondrial COI gene and the 18S and the 5&#x02032; end of the 28S rRNA genes indicates that several genera are polyphyletic.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS One</italic></source>
<volume>9</volume>:<issue>e108672</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108672</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25289639?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25289639</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>K. F. X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Waugh</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Langridge</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Close</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wise</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Graner</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>A physical, genetic and functional sequence assembly of the barley genome.</article-title>
<source><italic>Nature</italic></source>
<volume>491</volume>
<fpage>711</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>716</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11543</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23075845?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23075845</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCafferty</surname><given-names>H. R. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>P. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Improved Carica papaya tolerance to carmine spider mite by the expression of Manduca sexta chitinase transgene.</article-title>
<source><italic>Transgenic Res.</italic></source>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>337</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>347</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11248-006-0005-4</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16779649?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16779649</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meihls</surname><given-names>L. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Handrick</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Glauser</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbier</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haribal</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Natural variation in maize aphid resistance is associated with 2,4-dihydroxy-7-methoxy-1,4-benzoxazin-3-one glucoside methyltransferase activity.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell</italic></source>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>2341</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2355</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.113.112409</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23898034?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23898034</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meihls</surname><given-names>L. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jander</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Natural variation in maize defense against insect herbivores.</article-title>
<source><italic>Cold Spring Harb. Symp. Quant. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>77</volume>
<fpage>269</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>283</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/sqb.2012.77.014662</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23223408?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23223408</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mithofer</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wanner</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boland</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Effects of feeding Spodoptera littoralis on lima bean leaves. II. Continuous mechanical wounding resembling insect feeding is sufficient to elicit herbivory-related volatile emission.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>137</volume>
<fpage>1160</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1168</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.104.054460</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15728342?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15728342</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cipollini</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Effect of wind-induced mechanical stress on soluble peroxidase activity and resistance to pests in cucumber.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Phytopathol.</italic></source>
<volume>147</volume>
<fpage>313</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>316</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1439-0434.1999.147005313.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mortazavi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>McCue</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaeffer</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wold</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Mapping and quantifying mammalian transcriptomes by RNA-Seq.</article-title>
<source><italic>Nat. Methods</italic></source>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>621</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>628</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1226</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18516045?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18516045</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Negm</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Moraes</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perring</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>&#x0201c;Mite pests of date palms,&#x0201d; in</article-title>
<source><italic>Sustainable Pest Management in Date Palm: Current Status and Emerging Challenges</italic></source>, <role>eds</role>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Wakil</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Romeno Faleiro</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name>), <fpage>347</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>389</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-319-24397-9_12</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niemeyer</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Hydroxamic acids derived from 2-hydroxy-2 H -1,4-benzoxazin-3(4 H)-one: key defense chemicals of cereals.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Agric. Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>57</volume>
<fpage>1677</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1696</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf8034034</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19199602?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19199602</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oerke</surname><given-names>E.-C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Crop losses to pests.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Agric. Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>144</volume>
<fpage>31</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>43</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0021859605005708</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pollock</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Michels</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Distributions of Stethorus nigripes Kapur (Coleoptera: Coccinellidae), a predator of Banks grass mite [Oligonychus pratensis (Banks)] in the southern United States.</article-title>
<source><italic>Southwest. Entomol.</italic></source>
<volume>27</volume>
<fpage>217</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>220</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B71"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>R Core Team</collab> (<year>2016</year>). <source><italic>R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing</italic>.</source>
<publisher-loc>Vienna</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>R Core Team</publisher-name> Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.r-project.org/">https://www.r-project.org/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B72"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spears</surname><given-names>L. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Stem nematode counteracts plant resistance of aphids in alfalfa.</article-title>
<source><italic>Medicago sativa. J. Chem. Ecol.</italic></source>
<volume>40</volume>
<fpage>1099</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1109</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10886-014-0504-3</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25261892?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25261892</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B73"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>P. C. M. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaffoor</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Acevedo</surname><given-names>F. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peiffer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Turnabout Is fair play: herbivory-induced plant chitinases excreted in fall armyworm frass suppress herbivore defenses in maize.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>171</volume>
<fpage>694</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>706</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.15.01854</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26979328?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26979328</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B74"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaffor</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Acevedo</surname><given-names>F. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Helms</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chuang</surname><given-names>W.-P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tooker</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Maize plants recognize herbivore-associated cues from caterpillar frass.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Chem. Ecol.</italic></source>
<volume>41</volume>
<fpage>781</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>792</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10886-015-0619-1</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26306592?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26306592</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B75"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaff</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipka</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000f6;llner</surname><given-names>T. G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Characterization of biosynthetic pathways for the production of the volatile homoterpenes DMNT and TMTT in <italic>Zea mays</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell</italic></source>
<volume>28</volume>
<fpage>2651</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2665</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.15.00919</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27662898?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27662898</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B76"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rohrmeier</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehle</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>WIP 1, a wound-inducible gene from maize with homology to Bowman-Birk proteinase inhibitors.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Mol. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>22</volume>
<fpage>783</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>792</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00027365</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8358030</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B77"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santamar&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cambra</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pozancos</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Melendi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grbi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Gene pyramiding of peptidase inhibitors enhances plant resistance to the spider mite Tetranychus urticae.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS One</italic></source>
<volume>7</volume>:<issue>e43011</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0043011</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22900081?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22900081</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B78"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santamar&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Dehydration stress contributes to the enhancement of plant defense response and mite performance on barley.</article-title>
<source><italic>Front. Plant Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>9</volume>:<issue>458</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2018.00458</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29681917?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29681917</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B79"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schindelin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arganda-Carreras</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frise</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaynig</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Longair</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pietzsch</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Fiji: an open-source platform for biological-image analysis.</article-title>
<source><italic>Nat. Methods</italic></source>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>676</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>682</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.2019</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22743772?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22743772</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B80"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schnable</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ware</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasternak</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The B73 maize genome: complexity, diversity, and dynamics.</article-title>
<source><italic>Science</italic></source>
<volume>326</volume>
<fpage>1112</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1115</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1178534</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19965430?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19965430</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B81"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Plant terpenes: defense responses, phylogenetic analysis, regulation and clinical applications.</article-title>
<source><italic>3 Biotech</italic></source>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>129</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>151</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13205-014-0220-2</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28324581?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28324581</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B82"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Staswick</surname><given-names>P. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Jasmonate response locus JAR1 and several related <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> genes encode enzymes of the firefly luciferase superfamily that show activity on jasmonic, salicylic, and indole-3-acetic acids in an assay for adenylation.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell Online</italic></source>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>1405</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1415</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.000885</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 12084835?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12084835</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B83"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szczepaniec</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raupp</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerns</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eubanks</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Neonicotinoid insecticides alter induced defenses and increase susceptibility to spider mites in distantly related crop plants.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS One</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>:<issue>e62620</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062620</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23658754?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23658754</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B84"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tadmor</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewinsohn</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abo-Moch</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bar-Zur</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mansour</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Antibiosis of maize inbred lines to the carmine spider mite, <italic>Tetranychus cinnabarinus. Phytoparasitica</italic></article-title>
<volume>27</volume>
<fpage>35</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02980725</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B85"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamayo</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rufat</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bravo</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>San Segundo</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Accumulation of a maize proteinase inhibitor in response to wounding and insect feeding, and characterization of its activity toward digestive proteinases of Spodoptera littoralis larvae.</article-title>
<source><italic>Planta</italic></source>
<volume>211</volume>
<fpage>62</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004250000258</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 10923704?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10923704</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B86"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pertea</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mortazavi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Baren</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Transcript assembly and quantification by RNA-Seq reveals unannotated transcripts and isoform switching during cell differentiation.</article-title>
<source><italic>Nat. Biotechnol.</italic></source>
<volume>28</volume>
<fpage>511</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>515</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.1621</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20436464?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20436464</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B87"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turlings</surname><given-names>T. C. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Erb</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Tritrophic interactions mediated by herbivore-induced plant volatiles: mechanisms, ecological relevance, and application potential.</article-title>
<source><italic>Annu. Rev. Entomol.</italic></source>
<volume>63</volume>
<fpage>433</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>452</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-ento-020117-043507</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29324043?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29324043</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B88"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tzin</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez-Pozo</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmelz</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoettner</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x000e4;fer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015a</year>). <article-title>Dynamic maize responses to aphid feeding are revealed by a time series of transcriptomic and metabolomic assays.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>169</volume>
<fpage>1727</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1743</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.15.01039</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26378100?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26378100</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B89"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tzin</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindsay</surname><given-names>P. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meihls</surname><given-names>L. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blue</surname><given-names>L. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jander</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015b</year>). <article-title>Genetic mapping shows intraspecific variation and transgressive segregation for caterpillar-induced aphid resistance in maize.</article-title>
<source><italic>Mol. Ecol.</italic></source>
<volume>24</volume>
<fpage>5739</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5750</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/mec.13418</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26462033?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26462033</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B90"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tzin</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hojo</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strickler</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartsch</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Archer</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahern</surname><given-names>K. R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Rapid defense responses in maize leaves induced by <italic>Spodoptera exigua</italic> caterpillar feeding.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Exp. Bot.</italic></source>
<volume>68</volume>
<fpage>4709</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4723</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erx274</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28981781?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28981781</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B91"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Leeuwen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Demaeght</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Osborne</surname><given-names>E. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dermauw</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gohlke</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nauen</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Population bulk segregant mapping uncovers resistance mutations and the mode of action of a chitin synthesis inhibitor in arthropods.</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</italic></source>
<volume>109</volume>
<fpage>4407</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4412</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1200068109</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22393009?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22393009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B92"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Leeuwen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dermauw</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>The molecular evolution of xenobiotic metabolism and resistance in chelicerate mites.</article-title>
<source><italic>Annu. Rev. Entomol.</italic></source>
<volume>61</volume>
<fpage>475</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>498</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-ento-010715-023907</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26982444?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26982444</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B93"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Volodarsky</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leviatan</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Otcheretianski</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fluhr</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>HORMONOMETER: a tool for discerning transcript signatures of hormone action in the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> transcriptome.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>150</volume>
<fpage>1796</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1805</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.109.138289</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19535475?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19535475</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B94"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huddleston</surname><given-names>E. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Owens</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillis</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashdown</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1972</year>). <article-title>Control of the Banks grass mite attacking grain sorghum and corn in west Texas.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Econ. Entomol.</italic></source>
<volume>65</volume>
<fpage>523</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>529</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jee/65.2.523</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B95"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woldemariam</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahern</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jander</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tzin</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>A role for 9-lipoxygenases in maize defense against insect herbivory.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Signal. Behav.</italic></source>
<volume>13</volume>:<issue>e1422462</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15592324.2017.1422462</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29293391?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29293391</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B96"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wouters</surname><given-names>F. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanchette</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gershenzon</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vass&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Plant defense and herbivore counter-defense: benzoxazinoids and insect herbivores.</article-title>
<source><italic>Phytochem. Rev.</italic></source>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>1127</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1151</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11101-016-9481-1</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27932939?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27932939</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B97"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wouters</surname><given-names>F. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reichelt</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Glauser</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Erb</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gershenzon</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Reglucosylation of the benzoxazinoid DIMBOA with inversion of stereochemical configuration is a detoxification strategy in lepidopteran herbivores.</article-title>
<source><italic>Angew. Chem. Int. Ed.</italic></source>
<volume>53</volume>
<fpage>11320</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11324</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/anie.201406643</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25196135?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25196135</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B98"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Isakeit</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelberth</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meeley</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayward</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Disruption of OPR7 and OPR8 reveals the versatile functions of jasmonic acid in maize development and defense.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell</italic></source>
<volume>24</volume>
<fpage>1420</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1436</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.111.094151</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22523204?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22523204</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B99"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yates</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akanni</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amode</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrell</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Billis</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho-Silva</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Ensembl 2016.</article-title>
<source><italic>Nucleic Acids Res.</italic></source>
<volume>44</volume>
<fpage>D710</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D716</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkv1157</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26687719?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26687719</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B100"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhurov</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Navarro</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruinsma</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arbona</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Santamar&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cazaux</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Reciprocal responses in the interaction between <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and the cell-content-feeding chelicerate herbivore spider mite.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>164</volume>
<fpage>384</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>399</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.113.231555</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24285850?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24285850</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B101"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Z&#x000fa;&#x000f1;iga</surname><given-names>G. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Argando&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>V. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Niemeyer</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Corcuera</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>). <article-title>Hydroxamic acid content in wild and cultivated gramineae.</article-title>
<source><italic>Phytochemistry</italic></source>
<volume>22</volume>
<fpage>2665</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2668</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0031-9422(00)97669-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>