<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Plant Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Plant Biol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Plant Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2229</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5291992</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">988</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-017-0988-4</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Largely different contents of terpenoids in beef red-flesh tangerine and its wild type</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Wenyun</given-names></name><address><email>46530551@qq.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Cuihua</given-names></name><address><email>liucuihua86@126.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Min</given-names></name><address><email>heminsweet@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Jinqiang</given-names></name><address><email>2997485401@qq.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Yongqiang</given-names></name><address><email>caiyq2010@sohu.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Yuhua</given-names></name><address><email>360181050@qq.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Juan</given-names></name><address><phone>86-27-87286965</phone><email>xujuan@mail.hzau.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1790 4137</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.35155.37</institution-id><institution/><institution>Key Laboratory of Horticultural Plant Biology (Ministry of Education), College of Horticulture and Forestry, Huazhong Agricultural University, </institution></institution-wrap>Wuhan, 430070 China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.464326.1</institution-id><institution/><institution>Guizhou Fruit Institute,Guizhou Academy of Agricultural Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>Guiyang, Guizhou Province 550006 China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1760 4150</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.144022.1</institution-id><institution/><institution>College of Horticulture, Northwest A &#x00026; F University, </institution></institution-wrap>Yangling, Shanxi Province 712100 China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>3</day><month>2</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>3</day><month>2</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><elocation-id>36</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>1</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>1</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2017</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p>Niurouhong (<italic>Citrus reticulata</italic> Blanco. Niurouhong) (NRH) is a spontaneous beef-red flesh mutant with distinctive flavor compared with its wild type orange-red flesh Zhuhongju (ZHJ). To illustrate the biochemical mechanism of its special flesh color and flavor, fruits at commercial mature stage were used to profile the volatiles in the flavedo and determine the levels of carotenoids, limonoid aglycones and phytohormones in the juice sacs in two seasons.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Our results showed the content of total volatile terpenoids in NRH was 1.27-fold that in ZHJ. The components of volatiles were found to be common between the two tangerines. This result indicates that the distinctive flavor of NRH might not be derived from the presence/absence of specific volatiles; instead, it was derived from the altered concentrations or balance of <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-citral, <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-citral, 2-cyclohexen-1-one, (S)-3-methyl-6-(1-methylethenyl) and n-hexadecanoic acid. Analyses of the contents of total and specific carotenoids indicated that the beef-red color of NRH flesh might be largely attributed to the over accumulation of <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-cryptoxanthin and <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-carotene. However, lower ABA level was found in NRH than in ZHJ, reflecting a possible feedback regulation of ABA biosynthesis on carotenogenesis and the balance in the metabolism among terpenoids.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Collectively, our study suggested that the MEP pathway was enhanced in NRH tangerine. However, a certain unknown co-regulatory mechanism might be present in the metabolism pathway of secondary metabolites (especially terpenoids) in beef-red flesh mutant. Our study provides new insights into the regulatory network of terpenoid metabolism and mutation mechanism of red-fleshed citrus.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>Citrus reticulate</italic> Blanco</kwd><kwd>Niurouhong</kwd><kwd>Terpenoids</kwd><kwd>Volatile</kwd><kwd>Carotenoids</kwd><kwd>Phytohormone</kwd><kwd>Limonoid aglycones</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001809</institution-id><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>NSFC Grant Nos. 31521092</award-id><award-id>NSFC Grant Nos. 31272122</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Juan</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100004602</institution-id><institution>Program for New Century Excellent Talents in University</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>NCET-13-0810</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Juan</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2017</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p>Plant terpenoids are important metabolites, and represent a class of hydrocarbons that have functions in photosynthesis, respiration and regulation of plant growth and development. They also have substantial economic values to serve as essential oils, colorants, flavors and anti-oxidative drugs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. All terpenoids are derived from the condensation of two common 5-carbon precursors in MEP and/or MVA pathway to produce monoterpenes (C10), sesquiterpenes (C15) and diterpenes (C20) under the catalysis of various terpene synthases (TPSs) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, TPS21 and TPS11 are responsible for the biosynthesis of nearly all 20 sesquiterpenes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Citrus plants are rich of terpenoids, and volatile organic compounds, phytohormones, carotenoids, limonoid aglycones are produced in leaves, flowers, roots and fruits. Monoterpenes and sesquiterpenes account for more than 80% of the total volatiles in citrus (Yamamoto et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]), and carotenoids (C<sub>30</sub> and C<sub>40</sub>) and limonoid aglycones are the derivatives of tetraterpenoids and triterpenoids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>], while ABA is regarded as a sesquiterpene usually produced from the degradation of carotenoids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Terpenoids in citrus play key roles in photosynthesis, plant growth regulation, plant-environment interactions and fruit quality.</p><p>Most citrus fruits are generally colored by yellow or orange carotenoids particularly xanthophylls in the plastids during maturation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Some red-fleshed citrus cultivars, such as &#x0201c;Cara Cara&#x0201d; navel orange (<italic>C. sinensis</italic> Osbeck) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>] and and red-fleshed pummelo (<italic>C. grandis</italic> Osbeck) predominantly accumulate lycopene and <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-carotene [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], whereas blood orange (<italic>C. sinensis</italic> Osbeck) is characterized by the accumulation of anthocyanin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Red-fleshed fruit is not only special in flesh color, but also distinctive in other qualities compared with wild-type fruit. Chen et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] reported that the contents of some flavonoids are significantly different between red-fleshed and blonde-fleshed sweet oranges. Yoo et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] revealed the differences in the contents of ascorbic acid, sugar, soluble solid and total carotenoid among 11 watermelons with different pulp colors, while different carotenoid, limonoid and aroma profiles of two pummelos (<italic>Citrus</italic> maxima) with different flesh color were also reported in citrus by Liu et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>].</p><p>Tangerine (<italic>C. reticulata</italic> Blanco) is well known as one of the four main cultivated citrus species for its wide application in juice industry. Its fresh fruits can be processed or marketed owing to the traits of easy peeling, appealing color, pleasant aroma and good taste. Tangerine fruit quality is usually determined by several characters such as color, aroma and bitterness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. A great part of these characters are determined by the composition of terpenoids, which constitute the largest and most diverse class of secondary or specialized metabolites mainly represented by phytohormones of abscisic acid (ABA) and gibberellic acid (GA), carotenoids, volatile terpenoids and bitterness compounds of limonoid aglycones in Citrus species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Citrus fruit color is mainly derived from the accumulation of carotenoids while flavonoids contribute to the yellow background color. Its aroma is mainly derived from volatile organic compounds (VOCs), whereas delayed bitterness usually results from the accumulation of limonin.</p><p>NRH tangerine (<italic>C. reticulate</italic> Blanco. Niurouhong), a spontaneous mutant originated from ZHJ tangerine (<italic>C. reticulate</italic> Blanco. Zhuhongju) in Haohuahong town, Huishui County, Guizhou Province, China, has drawn extensive attention for its attractive traits of beef-red color in fruit rind and flesh, distinctive flavor and fewer seeds (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). However, the physiological and biochemical bases of these quality characters are poorly understood. Here, to investigate the physiological and biochemical mechanisms of the fruit quality of NRH tangerine, contents of terpenoids including volatiles, carotenoids, limonoid aglycones and phytohormones were determined to fully investigate the differences in the MEP and/or MVA networks of terpenoid metabolism between NRH tangerine and its wild type.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Mature fruit of NRH tangerine (<bold>a</bold>) and its wild type ZHJ tangerine (<bold>b</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2017_988_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Materials</title><p>Fruits of NRH and ZHJ were collected in 2&#x000a0;years (2010 and 2011) from trees grown in the same orchard (Haohuahong town, Huishui County, Guizhou Province, China) both at the commercially mature stage under the same management conditions. Thirty fruits were harvested randomly from the peripheral canopy of at least 3 trees for each cultivar, and transported quickly to the laboratory in an ice-box. Fruit flavedo and juice sacs were separated with a sharp scalpel, and then were immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at &#x02212;80&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C until analysis. Samples were prepared in triplicates unless otherwise indicated.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Extraction and determination of volatile compounds</title><p>In citrus, flavors are largely determined by the peel oil, especially in the flavedo part of a fruit. Thus, flavedo of fruits harvested in 2011 was used for volatile constituent analysis. Volatile extraction and detection were conducted according to Liu et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Three grams of powder was dipped in 15&#x000a0;ml of Methyl Tert Butyl Ether (MTBE) containing 8697&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g chlorononane and 400&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g methyl nonanoate that served as an internal standard. After 1&#x000a0;h of microwave-assisted extraction (FS60 ultrasonic cleaner, Fisher Scientific, Pittsburgh, PA, USA), the organic layer was dried by Na<sub>2</sub>SO4. Finally, the final volume of the extracted liquid was blown to 1.4&#x000a0;mL under stable nitrogen gas flow.</p><p>The profiling of volatiles was performed by using TRACE Ultra gas chromatograph (GC) combined with a DSQ II mass spectrometer (MS) (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA) with a TRACE TR-5 MS chromatographic column (30&#x000a0;mm&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;0.25&#x000a0;mm&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;0.25&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m, Thermo Scientific, Bellefonte, PA, USA). The operational parameters of GC-MS and quantitative parameters of volatiles followed the protocol of Liu et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Extraction and determination of carotenoids</title><p>The authentic standards of violaxanthin, 9-Z-violaxanthin, antheraxanthin, xanthophyll, <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-carotene, <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-cryptoxanthin, phytoene were obtained from CaroteNature (Lupsingen, Switzerland), while <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-carotene and lycopene were purchased from Sigma Co. Ltd (St Louis, MO, USA).</p><p>To determine the pigments accounting for the beef-red color of NRH flesh, juice sacs in fruits were separated for carotenoids analysis.</p><p>Carotenoids were extracted and analyzed as described by Liu et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. One gram of juice sacs powder was dissolved in 15&#x000a0;mL extraction solvent (hexane/acetone/ethanol&#x02009;=&#x02009;2:1:1&#x000a0;v/v/v, containing 0.1&#x000a0;g&#x000a0;L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> butylatedhydroxytoluene). After centrifugation for 30&#x000a0;min at 4000&#x000a0;g, the supernatant was washed by saturated NaCl solution and concentrated to dryness. Then 4&#x000a0;mL MTBE was added and the sample was saponified with 2&#x000a0;mL of KOH/water/methanol (10:25:75&#x000a0;w/v/v). After the saponification, water-soluble extracts were removed from the extract by adding NaCl-saturated water. After evaporation under vacuum Eppendorf 5301 concentrator (Eppendorf, Hamburg, Germany), the residue was re-dissolved in 0.6&#x000a0;mL MTBE solution.</p><p>The carotenoid extracts (20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L) were separated by a Waters 1525 reverse phase high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) system equipped with a 2996 photodiode array detector, a YMC C<sub>30</sub> carotenoid column (150&#x000a0;mm&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;4.6&#x000a0;mm, 3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m; YMC, Wilmington, NC, USA) and a 717 Plus autosampler. The data were analyzed by Empower Chromatography Manager software (Waters Co., Milford, MA, USA). The carotenoids were gradient eluted with methanol/acetonitrile (1:3&#x000a0;v/v; eluent A) and MTBE (eluent B).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Extraction and determination of limonoid aglycones</title><p>The authentic standards of limonin and nomilin were purchased from Sigma Co. Ltd (St Louis, MO, USA). Three grams of powder of juice sacs were extracted for limonin and nomilin analysis as demonstrated by Li et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. A Soxhlet extractor (IKA-Werke GmbH and Co. KG, Staufen, German) was employed for 15&#x000a0;cycles of Soxhlet extraction, then the filtered solution was collected and dried by using Eppendorf 5301 concentrator (Eppendorf, Hamburg, Germany) at 30&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. The dried extracts were added with 1&#x000a0;mL acetonitrile before HPLC analysis. 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L samples were determined by using the same HPLC system but separated with a C<sub>18</sub> HPLC column (150&#x000a0;mm&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;4.6&#x000a0;mm, 5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m; Agilent, Wilmington, DE, USA).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Determine of Phytohormone composition by using LC-MS</title><p>The standards of abscisic acid (ABA), jasmonic acid (JA), indole-3-acetic acid (IAA) and salicylic acid (SA) were purchased from OlChemImm (OlChemIm, Olomouc, Czech Republic). Phytohormones were extracted according to previously method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. A 50&#x000a0;mg portion of lyophilized juice sacs were homogenized with 0.5&#x000a0;mL extraction solvent (isopropanol: water: HCl&#x02009;=&#x02009;100: 50: 0.1). After extraction for 12&#x000a0;h at 0&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, the samples were dipped in 0.5&#x000a0;mL extraction solvent, shaken for 1&#x000a0;h at 230&#x000a0;r/min, followed by the addition of 2&#x000a0;mL dichloromethane and shaking for another 1&#x000a0;h. After 10&#x000a0;min of centrifugation at 4000&#x000a0;g under 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, the layers were transferred into a new 1.5&#x000a0;mL tube and dried with a gentle stream of nitrogen. The resulting residue was re-dissolved in 0.15&#x000a0;mL methanol, and then subjected to 15&#x000a0;min of centrifugation at 4000&#x000a0;g under 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. 10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of the supernatant was taken out for analysis by using a UPLC-ESI-MS (Shimadzu Corporation, Kyoto, Japan) equipped with a C<sub>30</sub> column (4.6&#x000a0;mm&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;150&#x000a0;mm, 5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m, YMC) as described before [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. 0.02% acetic acid was prepared as mobile phase A, and 0.02% acetic acid-acetonitrile was prepared for mobile phase B. Gas flow was set to 250&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L&#x000a0;min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Xcalibur software was used to analyze the volatile compounds in selective ion monitoring (SIM) and total ion current (TIC) Modes. The volatiles, carotenoid, limonoid aglycones and Phytohormone were identified by specific retention times and the standard curves were compared with the authentic standard. Data of the significant difference analysis were presented by means of ANOVA with Fisher&#x02019;s least-significant-difference test.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>Volatile compounds of two tangerines</title><p>The same 72 volatile compounds were observed in the flavedo of two cultivars, among which 47 were accurately quantified and 25 were tentatively quantified. These volatile compounds were divided into 12 classes, including 20 sesquiterpenes, 16 monoterpenes, 6 monoterpene alcohols, 5 monoterpene aldehydes, 3 monoterpene ketones, 3 monoterpene esters, 3 monoterpene oxides, 6 aldehydes, 4 esters, 3 alcohols, 3 acids and 1 unknown compound (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Volatile profiles (&#x0feff;Fresh Weight&#x0feff;)&#x0feff; in flavedo of NRH and ZHJ</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">RT (min) <sup>a</sup>
</th><th/><th colspan="2">Concentration (&#x003bc;g/g)</th></tr><tr><th>Volatile Compounds<sup>b</sup>
</th><th>NRH</th><th>ZHJ</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td/><td>Monoterpenes</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>15.91</td><td>
<italic>d</italic>-limonene</td><td>67384.04&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;20472.24</td><td>51399.87&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;10955.84</td></tr><tr><td>17.23</td><td>
<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>-terpiene</td><td>5453.92&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;550.84</td><td>5527.90&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;835.14</td></tr><tr><td>13.76</td><td>
<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-myrcene</td><td>786.47&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;114.29</td><td>692.36&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;127.94</td></tr><tr><td>10.94</td><td>
<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-pinene</td><td>326.29&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;37.78</td><td>310.62&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;53.49</td></tr><tr><td>13.12</td><td>
<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-pinene</td><td>233.32&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;41.10</td><td>261.16&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;40.17</td></tr><tr><td>16.61</td><td>
<italic>trans</italic>-ocimene</td><td>192.21&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;20.61</td><td>239.32&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;26.44</td></tr><tr><td>15.11</td><td>
<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-terpinene</td><td>124.29&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;12.58</td><td>127.07&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;20.84</td></tr><tr><td>18.49</td><td>terpinolene</td><td>122.22&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;13.18</td><td>127.58&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;20.00</td></tr><tr><td>10.60</td><td>
<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-thujene<sup>T10</sup>
</td><td>72.33&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.51</td><td>73.70&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;11.52</td></tr><tr><td>15.59</td><td>
<italic>p</italic>-cymene</td><td>67.80&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;67.34</td><td>116.42&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;15.02</td></tr><tr><td>14.59</td><td>
<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-phellandrene</td><td>24.55&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.22</td><td>23.56&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.68</td></tr><tr><td>12.91</td><td>sabinene<sup>T11</sup>
</td><td>21.78&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.01</td><td>20.74&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.47</td></tr><tr><td>11.76</td><td>camphene</td><td>6.04&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.45</td><td>6.00&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.18</td></tr><tr><td>16.11</td><td>
<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-cis-ocimene<sup>*</sup>
</td><td>5.29&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.58</td><td>6.19&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.34</td></tr><tr><td>14.46</td><td>
<italic>&#x003c8;</italic>-limonene <sup>T11</sup>
</td><td>5.25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.54</td><td>5.26&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.45</td></tr><tr><td>15.95</td><td>
<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-phellandrene<sup>*</sup>
<sup>T11</sup>
</td><td>4.96&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.05</td><td>5.35&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.17</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Sum</td><td>74830.76</td><td>58943.10</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Monoterpene alcohols</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>19.33</td><td>
<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-linalool</td><td>148.35&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;12.96</td><td>134.82&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;13.93</td></tr><tr><td>24.08</td><td>
<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-terpineol<sup>*</sup>
</td><td>69.29&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.57</td><td>46.59&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;9.21</td></tr><tr><td>25.44</td><td>citronella</td><td>23.23&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.84</td><td>21.59&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.62</td></tr><tr><td>17.87</td><td>
<italic>cis</italic>-sabinene hydrate</td><td>20.53&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.62</td><td>16.05&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.77</td></tr><tr><td>23.31</td><td>4-terpinenol</td><td>2.43&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.16</td><td>2.05&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.24</td></tr><tr><td>28.56</td><td>
<italic>p</italic>-mentha-1 (7),8 (10)-dien-9-ol <sup>T1</sup>
</td><td>1.99&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.20</td><td>1.74&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.35</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Sum</td><td>265.82</td><td>222.84</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Monoterpene aldehydes</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>21.95</td><td>citronellal</td><td>101.00&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;10.47</td><td>85.77&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;15.28</td></tr><tr><td>27.50</td><td>
<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-citral<sup>**</sup>
</td><td>86.66&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8.28</td><td>41.23&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8.78</td></tr><tr><td>26.10</td><td>
<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-citral<sup>**</sup>
</td><td>33.43&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.45</td><td>16.46&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.15</td></tr><tr><td>7.94</td><td>(<italic>E</italic>)-2-hexenal</td><td>26.78&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.53</td><td>27.31&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.78</td></tr><tr><td>27.99</td><td>perillal<sup>* T13</sup>
</td><td>7.92&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.33</td><td>6.19&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.66</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Sum</td><td>255.79</td><td>176.96</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Monoterpene ketones</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>26.94</td><td>piperitone <sup>T9</sup>
</td><td>5.00&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td>5.06&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04</td></tr><tr><td>26.50</td><td>carvone<sup>T1</sup>
</td><td>4.26&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.58</td><td>3.35&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.51</td></tr><tr><td>27.67</td><td>2-cyclohexen-1-one, 3-methyl-6-(1-methylethenyl)-, (S)-<sup>**</sup>
<sup>T1</sup>
</td><td>2.59&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.26</td><td>0.68&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.19</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Sum</td><td>11.85</td><td>9.09</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Monoterpene oxides</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>21.20</td><td>
<italic>trans</italic>-limonene oxide</td><td>4.78&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.21</td><td>5.74&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.79</td></tr><tr><td>20.97</td><td>
<italic>cis</italic>-limonene oxide <sup>*</sup>
</td><td>2.17&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.41</td><td>1.48&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.18</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Sum</td><td>6.95</td><td>7.22</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Monoterpene esters</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>32.15</td><td>geraniol acetate</td><td>18.00&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.22</td><td>15.70&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.79</td></tr><tr><td>31.27</td><td>nerol acetate</td><td>9.74&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.39</td><td>10.23&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.23</td></tr><tr><td>30.85</td><td>citronellol acetate</td><td>5.08&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.74</td><td>4.73&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.63</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Sum</td><td>32.82</td><td>30.66</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Sesquiterpenes</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>39.54</td><td>germacrene B <sup>T13</sup>
</td><td>76.01&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.96</td><td>68.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;11.67</td></tr><tr><td>35.11</td><td>
<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-farnesene</td><td>51.57&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.19</td><td>47.15&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.01</td></tr><tr><td>30.06</td><td>
<italic>&#x003b4;</italic>-elemene<sup>T13</sup>
</td><td>49.69&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.61</td><td>45.23&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.93</td></tr><tr><td>36.38</td><td>germacrene D <sup>T2</sup>
</td><td>48.13&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.19</td><td>42.60&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.47</td></tr><tr><td>32.48</td><td>
<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-elemene <sup>T13</sup>
</td><td>42.96&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.06</td><td>42.50&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.77</td></tr><tr><td>44.84</td><td>
<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-sinensal <sup>T13</sup>
</td><td>40.41&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.80</td><td>33.85&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.49</td></tr><tr><td>35.31</td><td>
<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-caryophyllene</td><td>23.95&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.91</td><td>23.45&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.68</td></tr><tr><td>34.18</td><td>
<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>-elemene <sup>T13</sup>
</td><td>23.74&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.95</td><td>21.12&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.34</td></tr><tr><td>37.88</td><td>
<italic>&#x003b4;</italic>-cadinene <sup>T13</sup>
</td><td>11.64&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.87</td><td>11.46&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.67</td></tr><tr><td>33.76</td><td>
<italic>trans</italic>-caryophyllene</td><td>11.24&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.70</td><td>7.12&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.60</td></tr><tr><td>31.87</td><td>copaene <sup>T13</sup>
</td><td>10.82&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.89</td><td>10.42&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.62</td></tr><tr><td>37.48</td><td>8-isopropenyl-1,5-dimethyl-cyclodeca-1,5-diene <sup>T13</sup>
</td><td>8.10&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.16</td><td>8.27&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.83</td></tr><tr><td>37.19</td><td>
<italic>&#x003b4;</italic>-guaiene <sup>T2</sup>
</td><td>5.59&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.22</td><td>5.08&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.40</td></tr><tr><td>36.97</td><td>elixene <sup>T13</sup>
</td><td>5.49&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.19</td><td>5.48&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.56</td></tr><tr><td>38.10</td><td>
<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-sesquiphellandrene</td><td>5.29&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.30</td><td>4.64&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.55</td></tr><tr><td>32.95</td><td>
<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-bergamotene<sup>*</sup>
<sup>T13</sup>
</td><td>5.20&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.20</td><td>4.50&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.21</td></tr><tr><td>43.39</td><td>
<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-eudesmol <sup>T13</sup>
</td><td>5.04&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.19</td><td>4.68&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.33</td></tr><tr><td>39.19</td><td>
<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-elemol <sup>T2</sup>
</td><td>4.93&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.10</td><td>4.66&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.46</td></tr><tr><td>34.38</td><td>
<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-guaiene <sup>T2</sup>
</td><td>4.22&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.24</td><td>4.00&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.38</td></tr><tr><td>40.28</td><td>germacrene<italic>d</italic>-4-ol <sup>T3</sup>
</td><td>2.45&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.31</td><td>2.16&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Sum</td><td>436.47</td><td>396.39</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Alcohols</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>7.84</td><td>
<italic>cis</italic>-3-hexen-1-ol</td><td>27.00&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;16.76</td><td>45.09&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.81</td></tr><tr><td>17.99</td><td>1-octanol<sup>*</sup>
</td><td>25.80&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.12</td><td>12.10&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.46</td></tr><tr><td>8.45</td><td>1-hexanol</td><td>12.16&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.19</td><td>13.77&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.36</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Sum</td><td>64.96</td><td>70.96</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Aldehydes</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>19.69</td><td>nonanal<sup>*</sup>
</td><td>92.56&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;10.32</td><td>65.70&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;10.91</td></tr><tr><td>24.52</td><td>decanal<sup>*</sup>
</td><td>59.24&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.97</td><td>38.97&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8.22</td></tr><tr><td>33.55</td><td>dodecanal</td><td>37.41&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.53</td><td>73.66&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;37.94</td></tr><tr><td>5.80</td><td>(<italic>Z</italic>)-3-hexenal</td><td>14.35&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.20</td><td>17.82&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.58</td></tr><tr><td>5.85</td><td>hexenal</td><td>11.66&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.24</td><td>20.72&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.09</td></tr><tr><td>29.16</td><td>hendecanal<sup>*</sup>
</td><td>4.72&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.54</td><td>3.62&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.54</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Sum</td><td>219.94</td><td>220.49</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Acids</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>50.31</td><td>2-propenoic acid, 3-(4-hydroxy-3-methoxyphenyl)-</td><td>2.22&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.45</td><td>1.82&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.15</td></tr><tr><td>47.08</td><td>tetradecanoic acid</td><td>1.11&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.21</td><td>1.31&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.06</td></tr><tr><td>51.44</td><td>
<italic>n</italic>-hexadecanoic acid<sup>**</sup>
</td><td>5.50&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.00</td><td>1.07&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Sum</td><td>8.83</td><td>4.20</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Esters</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>51.37</td><td>hexadecanoic acid, methyl ester<sup>*</sup>
</td><td>1.29&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.29</td><td>5.20&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.58</td></tr><tr><td>55.23</td><td>methyl octadeca-9,12-dienoate</td><td>2.53&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.20</td><td>2.31&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.45</td></tr><tr><td>55.36<break/>55.45</td><td>methyl <italic>cis</italic>-6-octadecenoate<break/>methyl (10<italic>E</italic>)-10-octadecenoate</td><td>1.49&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.06<break/>1.31&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03</td><td>1.46&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.16<break/>1.21&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.09</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Sum</td><td>6.62</td><td>10.18</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Unknowns</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>20.46</td><td>
<italic>trans</italic>-p-mentha-2,8-dienol<sup>*T12</sup>
</td><td>2.96&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.59</td><td>1.25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.27</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Sum</td><td>2.96</td><td>1.25</td></tr><tr><td>Monoterpenes</td><td/><td>75403.98</td><td>59389.87</td></tr><tr><td>Sesquiterpenes</td><td/><td>436.47</td><td>396.39</td></tr><tr><td>Terpenoids</td><td/><td>75840.46</td><td>59786.27</td></tr><tr><td>Total others</td><td/><td>303.31</td><td>307.08</td></tr><tr><td>Total volatiles</td><td/><td>76143.77</td><td>60093.35</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Compounds marked with <sup>*</sup> indicate significant difference at 0.05 level (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), and <sup>**</sup> indicate extremely significant differences at 0.01 level (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01)</p><p>
<sup>a</sup>Retention Time</p><p>
<sup>b</sup>Compounds labeled with Tn were quantified by total ion current (TIC) mode, while unlabeled compounds were quantified by selective ion monitoring (SIM) mode according to Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> in previous published paper [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Data were analyzed with t-test (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p>However, concentrations varied largely among different volatile compounds. For example, in NRH, the concentrations varied from 67384.04&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;20472.24&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/g (<italic>d</italic>-limonene) to 1.11&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.21&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/g (tetradecanoic acid). Additionally, the concentrations of specific volatile compounds also varied between NRH and ZHJ. Except for monoterpene oxides, alcohols, aldehydes and esters, all other 8 classes of volatiles had significantly higher total concentrations in NRH than in ZHJ. For example, the total concentrations of monoterpene aldehydes, monoterpene ketones, acids and the unknown compound in NRH were 1.45-, 1.30-, 2.10- and 2.37-fold of those in ZHJ, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Volatile terpenoids in both tangerines</title><p>The predominant volatile organic compounds detected in two cultivars were terpenoids. The total terpenoid concentrations in NRH and ZHJ were 75840.46&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/g and 59786.27&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/g, respectively, accounting for about 99.60 and 99.48% of the total volatiles (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><p>The 16 detected monoterpenes accounted for the highest proportion (&#x0003e;98%) of the total volatiles in both tangerines (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>), while others only accounted for 1.72 and 1.91% of the total volatiles in NRH and ZHJ, respectively. Notably, the concentrations of 10 out of the 16 monoterpenes were higher in NRH, with <italic>d</italic>-limonene being the most abundant in both cultivars, followed by <italic>&#x003b3;</italic>-terpiene, <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-myrcene, <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-pinene and <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-pinene (&#x0003e;200&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/g). However, the concentrations of both <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-<italic>cis</italic>-ocimene and <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-phellandrene were significantly higher in ZHJ than in NRH.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Classes and proportions of volatile compounds in fruit flavedo of NRH (<bold>a</bold>) and ZHJ (<bold>b</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2017_988_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig>
</p><p>As for the 6 monoterpene alcohols detected in both tangerines, they were at higher concentrations in NRH, particularly <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-terpineol. Both tangerines accumulated the highest level of <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-linalool among all monoterpene alcohols, which amounted to 148.35&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;12.96&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/g in NRH and 134.82&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;13.93&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/g in ZHJ, respectively.</p><p>The total amount of monoterpene aldehydes in NRH was 1.45-fold that in ZHJ. Citronellal was found to be the major component of monoterpene aldehydes, whose concentration was 101.00&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;10.47&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/g and 85.77&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;15.28&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/g in two cultivars, respectively; while for other monoterpene aldehydes, including <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-citral, <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-citral, (<italic>E</italic>)-2-hexenal and perillal, their concentrations varied from 6.19&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/g to 86.66&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/g. Except for citronellal and (<italic>E</italic>)-2-hexenal, other 3 monoterpene aldehydes were significantly different in concentration between the two tangerines, with relatively higher levels being detected in NRH.</p><p>A total of 3 monoterpene ketones, namely piperitone, carvone and 2-cyclohexen-1-one, (S)-3-methyl-6-(1-methylethenyl), were identified. Each of the three monoterpene ketones had higher concentration in NRH, especially 2-cyclohexen-1-one, (S)-3-methyl-6-(1-methylethenyl) (3.81-fold that in ZHJ; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01), and their total concentration in NRH was 1.30-fold that in ZHJ.</p><p>Two monoterpene oxides were identified, including <italic>trans</italic>-limonene oxide and <italic>cis</italic>-limonene oxide. Total monoterpene oxide concentration was lower in NRH than in ZHJ.</p><p>Three monoterpene esters were detectable in both tangerines, and their total concentration was similar in NRH and ZHJ (32.82&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/g and 30.66&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/g, respectively).</p><p>Sesquiterpenes were detected to be the richest class, which included 20 volatile compounds from the two tangerines. Germacrene B was the dominant sesquiterpene, followed by <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-farnesene, <italic>&#x003b4;</italic>-elemene, germacrene D and <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-elemene, whose concentrations were all above 40&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/g. However, only <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-bergamotene was at a significantly higher level in NRH (1.16-fold that in ZHJ).</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Non-terpenoidsvolatile compounds determined in both tangerines</title><sec id="Sec13"><title>Non-terpenoid volatile compounds detected in both tangerines</title><p>A total of 17 non-terpenoid volatiles were identified, including 3 alcohols, 6 aldehydes, 3 acids, 4 esters and 1 unknown. Among these volatile compounds, aldehydes showed the highest abundance, which was up to 219.94&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/g and 220.49&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/g and accounted for 72.5 and 71.8% of the total non-terpenoid volatiles in NRH and ZHJ, respectively. NRH contained significantly higher 1-octanol, nonanal, decanal, hendecanal and <italic>trans</italic>-<italic>p</italic>-mentha-2,8-dienol than ZHJ (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), while the concentration of <italic>n</italic>-hexadecanoic acid was extremely significantly different between the two tangerines (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Carotenoid profiles</title><p>Seven carotenoids were determined in both years (2010 and 2011), including violaxanthin, 9-Z-violaxanthin, antheraxanthin, lutein, <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-cryptoxanthin, <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-carotene and phytoene (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). NRH accumulated higher levels of total carotenoids (456.87&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/g in 2010, 395.49&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/g in 2011). <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-cryptoxanthin was the most abundant carotenoid, accounting for more than 30% of total carotenoids in both tangerines, followed by 9-Z-violaxanthin (77.73&#x02013;108.84&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/g). All carotenoids, except for antheraxanthin and lutein, were higher in NRH than in ZHJ. In 2010, the contents of violaxanthin, 9-Z-violaxanthin, <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-cryptoxanthin, <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-carotene, phytoene and total carotenoids in NRH were significantly higher than those in ZHJ. NRH had lower contents of antheraxanthin and lutein than ZHJ, and the difference in lutein content reached significant level. Similar results were obtained in 2011.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Carotenoid profiles in juice sacs of NRH and ZHJ in years of 2010 and 2011</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Harvest<break/>Year</th><th>Cultivar</th><th>Violaxanthin</th><th>9-Z-violaxanthin</th><th>Antheraxanthin</th><th>Lutein</th><th>
<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-cryptoxanthin</th><th>
<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-carotene</th><th>Phytoene</th><th>Total<break/>Carotenoids</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2">2010</td><td>NRH</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">29.73&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.56<sup>**</sup>
</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">106.40&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.40</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">18.64&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.55</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.56&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.24<sup>*</sup>
</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">173.15&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.14<sup>**</sup>
</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">45.67&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.93<sup>**</sup>
</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">79.73&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.59<sup>*</sup>
</td><td char="." align="char">456.87</td></tr><tr><td>ZHJ</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">22.00&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.02</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">88.44&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.53</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">19.71&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.61</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">7.41&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.81</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">103.37&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.7</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">28.27&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.55</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">62.34&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.22</td><td char="." align="char">328.55</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">2011</td><td>NRH</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">48.34&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.72<sup>*</sup>
</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">108.84&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.60<sup>**</sup>
</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">11.10&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.10<sup>*</sup>
</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.01&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.12<sup>**</sup>
</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">134.69&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.48<sup>**</sup>
</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">49.99&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.76<sup>**</sup>
</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">37.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.24</td><td char="." align="char">395.49</td></tr><tr><td>ZHJ</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">46.37&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.68</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">77.73&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.91</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">13.27&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.67</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6.64&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.55</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">104.79&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.25</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">19.82&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.75</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">34.93&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.53</td><td char="." align="char">303.55</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Note: Data shown are means (&#x003bc;g/g DW)&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3). Data were analyzed by using ANOVA with Fisher&#x02019;s least-significant-difference test. Compounds marked with <sup>*</sup> indicate significant difference at 0.05 level (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) between cultivar of each year, while <sup>**</sup> indicate extremely significant differences at 0.01 level (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Limonoid aglycones in both tangerines</title><p>Two limonoid aglycones (limonin and nomilin) were also detected in the juice sacs of NRH and ZHJ in 2010 and 2011 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). ZHJ showed significantly higher concentration of limoninin in both seasons. In contrast, nomilin concentration was significantly higher in NRH in both years.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Limonoid aglyconescontents (Dry Weight) in juice sacs of NRH and ZHJ in years of 2010 and 2011</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Harvest Year</th><th>Cultivar</th><th>Limonin</th><th>Nomilin</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2">2010</td><td>NRH</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">234.31&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;27.68<sup>**</sup>
</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.51&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.54<sup>**</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td>ZHJ</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">407.76&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;18.58</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.48&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.08</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">2011</td><td>NRH</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1065.66&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;67.31<sup>*</sup>
</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">19.38&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.99<sup>*</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td>ZHJ</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1369.82&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;145.13</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">16.33&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.31</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Note: Data shown are means (&#x003bc;g/g DW)&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3). Data were analyzed by using ANOVA with Fisher&#x02019;s least-significant-difference test. Compounds marked with <sup>*</sup>indicate significant difference at 0.05 level (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) between cultivars of each year, while <sup>**</sup>indicate extremely significant differences at 0.01 level (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Phytohormones in NRH and ZHJ</title><p>The concentrations of ABA, JA, IAA and SA were evaluated in the juice sacs of fruits in 2010 and 2011 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). ABA was the most abundant (&#x0003e;900&#x000a0;ng/g) among all the phytohormones investigated; JA was at the second abundant among the 4 phytohormones; and SA was detected in trace or very low levels; while IAA was undetectable in 2&#x000a0;years.<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Phytohormone compositions and concentrations in juice sacs of NRH and ZHJ in years of 2010 and 2011</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Harvest Year</th><th>Cultivar</th><th>ABA</th><th>JA</th><th>SA</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2">2010</td><td>NRH</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1273.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;44.78<sup>**</sup>
</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">36.64&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.65</td><td>0.24&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.08</td></tr><tr><td>ZHJ</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1827.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;35.29</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">39.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.00</td><td>trace</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">2011</td><td>NRH</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">895.60&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;66.80<sup>**</sup>
</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">49.70&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.10<sup>*</sup>
</td><td>trace</td></tr><tr><td>ZHJ</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1670.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;72.59</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">59.93&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.17</td><td>trace</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<italic>ABA</italic> Abscisic acid, <italic>JA</italic> Jasmonic acid, <italic>SA</italic> Salicylic acid</p><p>Data shown are means (ng/g DW)&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3). Data were analyzed by ANOVA with Fisher&#x02019;s least-significant-difference test. Compounds marked with <sup>*</sup> indicate significant difference at 0.05 level (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) between cultivars of each year, while <sup>**</sup> indicate extremely significant differences at 0.01 level (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p>The levels of ABA and JA in ZHJ were all significantly higher than those in NRH. ZHJ accumulated extremely significantly higher ABA than NRH in both years (2010, 1.4-fold; 2011, 1.9-fold; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01). Concentrations of JA in ZHJ and NRH were at the same levels in 2010, while a 1.2-fold significant difference was observed in 2011.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Discussion</title><p>Seventy-two volatile compounds were detected in both tangerines with different concentrations. Among them, monoterpenoids (including monoterpene alcohols, monoterpene aldehydes, monoterpene ketones, monoterpene oxides and monoterpene esters) accounted for the largest proportion of total volatile compounds (&#x0003e;98% in both tangerines), while others (including sesquiterpenes, aldehydes, esters, alcohols and acids) only accounted for the rest (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). <italic>d</italic>-limonene was the most abundant terpenoid (67,384.04&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;20,472.24&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/g in NRH and 51,399.87&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;10,955.84&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/g in ZHJ), taking up more than 86% of the total volatile compounds. These results are consistent with our previous study of Mangshanyegan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>] and that of in tangerines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. In both tangerines, sesquiterpenes were the most abundant in types, while their total concentration only accounted for less than 1% of the total volatile compounds.</p><p>However, our previous reports on Mangshanyegan (<italic>C.nobilis</italic> Lauriro) revealed that special volatiles of <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-myrcene and linalool oxides are attributing to the balsamic and floral notes of aroma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Since no special volatile compound was found to be responsible for the distinctive flavor of NRH tangerine, it could be deduced that with a 1.27-fold increase of total volatile terpenoids, the distinctive flavor of NRH might not be derived from the presence/absence of special volatiles; instead, it may be derived from the significantly altered concentrations or proportions of <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-citral, <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-citral, 2-cyclohexen-1-one, (S)-3-methyl-6-(1-methylethenyl) and n-hexadecanoic acid in the background of increased monoterpene aldehydes, monoterpene ketones, acids and unknown compounds. Thus, further experiment of aroma reconstitution will help to reveal the proportion of each volatile that contributes to the distinctive flavor of NRH.</p><sec id="Sec18"><title>Carotenoids contribute to the beef-red color of NRH flesh</title><p>Components of carotenoids were found to be common between the two tangerines. Among the 7 carotenoids investigated in the 2 seasons, 5 and 2 (antheraxanthin and lutein) respectively had higher and lower levels in NRH than in ZHJ. Carotenoids are generally C<sub>40</sub> terpenoid compounds. Phytoene and phytofluene are colorless; xanthophylls including lutein, antheraxanthin and violaxanthin are responsible for the yellowish color; and <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-carotene is an orange pigment while <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-cryptoxanthin and <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-citraurin are red pigments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. The majority of citrus fruits exhibit characteristic yellow or orange color, which is mainly derived from various carotenoids. There are also some small populations of red-fleshed cultivars primarily due to the accumulation of upstream carotenoids represented by lycopene and <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-carotene, such as &#x0201c;Cara Cara&#x0201d; navel orange [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>] and red-fleshed pomelo [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. In blood orange, the red flesh color is caused by the accumulation of anthocyanins (a group of colored flavonoids) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>], and similar case was also found in Zipi pomelo in Hubei, China (data not published). Ikoma et al. reported that <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-cryptoxanthin is an important determinant in the classification of citrus genotypes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Some evidences were observed in loose skin mandarins such as Satsuma mandarin, Ponkan and Dancy tangerine to suggest that the degradation of <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-cryptoxanthin via the catalysis of CCD4 generates <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-citraurin, which is responsible for the red-pigmentation of citrus peel [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].</p><p>In our study, <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-crytoxanthin was predominantly accumulated, which is consistent with the reddish color of juice sacs in NRH, as its content ranged from 134.69 to 173.15&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/g DW in 2&#x000a0;years, and was significantly higher than that of ZHJ. Thus, based on the results that the contents of total carotenoids and 5 individual carotenoids were higher while that of antheraxanthin and lutein was lower in NRH, and that <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-citraurin was undetectable in the juice sacs of both tangerine, the beef-red color of NRH flesh might be largely attributed to the over accumulation of <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-cryptoxanthin and <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-carotene.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Terpernoids metabolism might be regulated by common regulators</title><p>In our study, terpernoids including volatile compounds, carotenoids, ABA and limonoid aglycones were identified, which are essential components of fruit quality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Plant terpenoids are originated from the same precursor isopentenyl diphosphate (IPP) or dimethylallyl diphosphate (DMAPP) by head-to-tailor or head-to-head condensations via MVA and/or MEP pathway. The MVA pathway located in the cytosol was identified to provide C5 units for the synthesis of sesquiterpenes, diterpenoids, triterpenes; while in the plastid, MEP pathway is thought to provide IPP for monoterpene, diterpenoid, carotenoid, phytohormone ABA and polyprenol synthesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). From the perspective of the terpenoid pathway, volatile terpenoid compounds, carotenoids, ABA and limonoid aglycones should all belong to the branches of the above mentioned pathways. In our study, monoterpenes (accounting for the largest proportion of volatile compounds) in the flavedo and carotenoids in the juice sacs were synthesized through MEP pathway, and were significantly higher in NRH. However, ABA, the dominant degradation product of carotenoids in plants, was at lower levels in the juice sacs of NRH. Additionally, limonin, which is yielded from the MVA pathway, was significantly lower in the juice sacs of NRH in two consecutive seasons.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Volatiles, carotenoids, imonoid aglycones and phytohormones in metabolic network of terpenoids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Note: MVA, mevalonate; MEP, 2-C-methyl-D-erythritol 4-phosphate; IPP, isopentenyl diphosphate; IPPI, isopentenyl diphosphate Delta-isomerase; FPS, farnesyl diphosphatesynthase; GGPS, geranylgeranyl diphosphate synthase; SPS, solanesyl diphosphate synthase; DMAPP, dimethylallyl diphosphate; IPT, isopentenyl transferase; FPP, farnesyl diphosphate; SS, sesquiterpenoid synthase; SQS, squalene synthase; GGPP, geranylgeranyl diphosphate; DS, diterpenoid synthase; PPP, polyprenyl diphosphate; GPS, geranyl diphosphate synthase; PPS, polyprenyl diphosphate synthase; GPP, geranyl diphosphate; SPP, solanesyl diphosphate; MS, monoterpenoid synthase; PSY, phytoene synthase; HST, homogentisate solanesyl transferase; CCD, carotenoid cleavage dioxygenase; NXS, neoxanthin synthase; NCED, 9-cis-epoxycarotenoid dioxygenase. Solid lines indicate a single enzymatic step, and dashed lines indicate several steps. Terpenoids investigated in this study are shown in red font</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2017_988_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig>
</p><p>Thus, it could be suggested that both MEP and MVA pathways had been altered in the flavedo and juice sacs of beef-red flesh NRH tangerine. There have been increasing evidences showing the &#x0201c;cross-talk&#x0201d; of terpenoids between the two pathways, particularly in the direction from plastids to cytosol [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Our results suggest the possibility that the enhancement of MEP pathway might inhibit the MVA pathway via a certain unknown co-regulatory mechanism, and vice versa. Moreover, a metabolic flux in the forms of IPP, DMAPP and other unknown intermediates together with a possible dynamic balance might be present between the two closely linked pathways.</p><p>It is interesting to note that ABA was the most abundant among the detected phytohormones, and had lower level in NRH. ABA was reported to be mainly produced from the cleavage of 9-Z-violaxanthin to produce xanthoxin, which is further oxidized to generate ABA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. In our study, the content of 9-Z-violaxanthin was significantly higher in NRH than in ZHJ, suggesting that the amount of 9-Z-violaxanthin in the pulp is not a limiting factor for ABA biosynthesis. This is not in agreement with previous report of Alquezar et al. on Cara Cara orange [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>], who suggested that ABA level was in parallel with the changes in the level of 9-Z-violaxanthin. In this study, the ABA level in NRH was significantly lower than that in ZHJ, indicating a possible feedback regulation of ABA biosynthesis on carotenoid metabolism. Collectively, carotenoids play roles in the synthesis of Phytohormones, volatiles (derived from terpenoids) and some defense compounds. Carotenoid accumulation levels are partly determined by the degradation rate of cleavage dioxygenases (CCDs) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. CCD4 is believed to be involved in the degradation of carotenoids to produce apocarotenoid, which is further oxidized to phytohormone ABA and volatiles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seeds, CCDs may contribute to the apocarotenoid-derived flavors especially in maturing seeds, while loss of function of CCDs leads to significantly higher carotenoid levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Reports had proposed that some volatile compounds are derived from carotenoids, especially from the degradation of <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-carotene and lycopene, such as <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-ionone, geranylacetone, pseudoionone, <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-cyclocitral, geranial, theaspirone, <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-damascenone and <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-damascenone, linalool and other terpenoid aldehydes and ketones [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. In our study, the total carotenoid content and total volatile concentration in NRH were significantly higher than those in ZHJ, while the ABA level in NRH was significantly lower than that in ZHJ, suggesting a favored pathway for terpenoid-derived volatiles rather than the ABA synthesis pathway, though both pathways are closely related to carotenoid degradation.</p><p>What&#x02019;s more, as we described above, some citrus are, although similarly altered to present red-flesh fruit color which previously known as the parallel mutation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>] as if similar mutation mechanisms were behind. However, through comparing our metabolite analysis with that on red-flesh citrus, we can speculate that the actual mechanisms of the transformation to red flesh color might vary among different cultivars. Notably, an interesting question that remains to be answered is whether carotenoid biosynthesis is prone to be regulated by various factors or by mutations. At least, since carotenoids are a group of antioxidants and precursors of some Phytohormones and volatiles, the accumulation of total or specific carotenoids may enhance the resistance of plants against certain stresses including various mutations, and consequently change the terpenoid metabolism and related pathways, or vice versa. Thus, terpenoid metabolisms should be considered as a network in the studies of the mechanisms in such red-flesh citrus.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Our study suggested that the MEP pathway was enhanced in NRH tangerine, while the MVA pathway was relatively inhibited. However, a certain unknown co-regulatory mechanism might be present in the metabolism pathway of secondary metabolites (especially terpenoids) in beef-red flesh mutant. Our study provides new insights into the regulatory network of terpenoid metabolism and mutation mechanism of red-fleshed citrus.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>ABA</term><def><p>Abscisic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CCD</term><def><p>Carotenoid cleavage dioxygenase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DMAPP</term><def><p>Dimethylallyl diphosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DS</term><def><p>Diterpenoid synthase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FPP</term><def><p>Farnesyl diphosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FPS</term><def><p>Farnesyl diphosphatesynthase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GGPP</term><def><p>Geranylgeranyl diphosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GGPS</term><def><p>Geranylgeranyl diphosphate synthase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GPP</term><def><p>Geranyl diphosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GPS</term><def><p>Geranyl diphosphate synthase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HST</term><def><p>Homogentisate solanesyl transferase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IAA</term><def><p>Indole-3-acetic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IPP</term><def><p>Isopentenyl diphosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IPPI</term><def><p>Isopentenyl diphosphate Delta-isomerase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IPT</term><def><p>Isopentenyl transferase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>JA</term><def><p>Jasmonic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MEP</term><def><p>2-C-methyl-D-erythritol 4-phosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MS</term><def><p>Monoterpenoid synthase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MVA</term><def><p>Mevalonate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NCED</term><def><p>9-cis-epoxycarotenoid dioxygenase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NRH</term><def><p>Niurouhong</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NXS</term><def><p>Neoxanthin synthase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PPP</term><def><p>Polyprenyl diphosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PPS</term><def><p>Polyprenyl diphosphate synthase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PSY</term><def><p>Phytoene synthase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SA</term><def><p>Salicylic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SPP</term><def><p>Solanesyl diphosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SPS</term><def><p>Solanesyl diphosphate synthase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SQS</term><def><p>Squalene synthase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SS</term><def><p>Sesquiterpenoid synthase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ZHJ</term><def><p>Zhuhongju</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We should give our thanks to Prof. Zuoxiong Liu who edits the English language throughout the manuscript. Pictures of ZHJ fruits were kindly provided by Dr. Zhaoxin Peng.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p>The study is financially supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (NSFC Grant Nos. 31501724, 31521092 and 31272122); Program for New Century Excellent Talents in University (NCET-13-0810).</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>All data generated or analysed during this study are included in this published article and its supplementary information files.</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>JX, WL and CL designed the experiments; CL performed the detection of volatile compounds, MH performed the detection of carotenoids, phytohormone, limonoid aglycones. JL, YC and YM provided materials. WL and JX wrote the manuscript. WL and CL contributed equally to this manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Consent for publication</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vranov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Coman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruissem</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure and dynamics of the isoprenoid pathway network</article-title><source>Mol Plant</source><year>2012</year><volume>5</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>318</fpage><lpage>333</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/mp/sss015</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22442388?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22442388</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tholl</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Terpene synthases and the regulation, diversity and biological roles of terpene metabolism</article-title><source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>297</fpage><lpage>304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2006.03.014</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16600670?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16600670</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tholl</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Petri</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gershenzon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pichersky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Two sesquiterpene synthases are responsible for the complex mixture of sesquiterpenes emitted from Arabidopsis flowers</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2005</year><volume>42</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>757</fpage><lpage>771</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2005.02417.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15918888?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15918888</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yahada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakamoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohta</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multivariate analyses and characterization of volatile components in citrus species</article-title><source>Food Sci Technol Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>19</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3136/fstr.19.39</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nisar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Khin</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pogson</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Carotenoid metabolism in plants</article-title><source>Mol Plant</source><year>2015</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>68</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molp.2014.12.007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25578273?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25578273</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bramley</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differences in the carotenoid content of ordinary citrus and lycopene-accumulating mutants</article-title><source>J Agric Food Chem</source><year>2006</year><volume>54</volume><issue>15</issue><fpage>5474</fpage><lpage>5481</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf060702t</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16848534?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16848534</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of phytoene synthase gene (Psy) is enhanced during fruit mature of Cara Cara navel orange (<italic>Citrus sinensis</italic> Osbeck)</article-title><source>Plant Cell Rep</source><year>2007</year><volume>26</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>837</fpage><lpage>843</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00299-006-0289-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17226057?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17226057</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A spontaneous bud mutant that causes lycopene and <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-carotene accumulation in the juice sacs of the parental Guanxi pummelo fruits (<italic>Citrus grandis</italic> (L.) Osbeck)</article-title><source>Sci Hortic</source><year>2016</year><volume>198</volume><fpage>379</fpage><lpage>384</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scienta.2015.09.050</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rapisarda</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pannuzzo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Romano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Juice components of a new pigmented citrus hybrid Citrus sinensis (L.) Osbeck&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;Citrus clementina Hort. ex Tan</article-title><source>J Agric Food Chem</source><year>2003</year><volume>51</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1611</fpage><lpage>1616</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf020871n</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12617593?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12617593</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>XX</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative study of flavonoid production in lycopene-accumulated and blonde-flesh sweet oranges (<italic>Citrus sinensis</italic>) during fruit development</article-title><source>Food Chem</source><year>2015</year><volume>184</volume><fpage>238</fpage><lpage>246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2015.03.087</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25872450?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25872450</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Crosby</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Variation of carotenoid, sugar, and ascorbic acid concentrations in watermelon genotypes and genetic analysis</article-title><source>Hortic Environ Biotechnol</source><year>2012</year><volume>53</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>552</fpage><lpage>560</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13580-012-0014-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>XX</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Features of citrus terpenoid production as revealed by carotenoid, limonoid and aroma profiles of two pummelos (Citrus maxima) with different flesh color</article-title><source>J Sci Food Agr</source><year>2015</year><volume>95</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jsfa.6689</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24723118</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tietel</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Plotto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fallik</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewinsohn</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Porat</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Taste and aroma of fresh and stored mandarins</article-title><source>J Sci Food Agr</source><year>2011</year><volume>91</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jsfa.4146</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20812381</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yahyaa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tholl</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cormier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibdah</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and characterization of terpene synthases potentially involved in the formation of volatile terpenes in carrot (<italic>Daucuscarota</italic> L.) roots</article-title><source>J Agric Food Chem</source><year>2015</year><volume>63</volume><issue>19</issue><fpage>4870</fpage><lpage>4878</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jafc.5b00546</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25924989?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25924989</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Content changes of bitter compounds in &#x02018;Guoqing No.1&#x02019; Satsuma mandarin (<italic>Citrus unshiu</italic> Marc.) during fruit development of consecutive 3 seasons</article-title><source>Food Chem</source><year>2014</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>963</fpage><lpage>969</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2013.09.040</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24128570?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24128570</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Welti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative analysis of major plant hormones in crude plant extracts by high-performance liquid chromatography&#x02013;mass spectrometry</article-title><source>Nat Protoc</source><year>2010</year><volume>5</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>986</fpage><lpage>992</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2010.37</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20448544?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20448544</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>XX</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Volatile constituents of wild citrus Mangshanyegan (<italic>Citrus nobilis</italic> Lauriro) peel oil</article-title><source>J Agric Food Chem</source><year>2012</year><volume>60</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>2617</fpage><lpage>2628</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf2039197</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22352344?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22352344</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miyazaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Plotto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gmitter</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution of aroma volatile compounds in tangerine hybrids and proposed inheritance</article-title><source>J Sci Food Agr</source><year>2011</year><volume>91</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>449</fpage><lpage>460</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jsfa.4205</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21218478</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bartley</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Scolnik</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant carotenoids: pigments for photoprotection, visual attraction, and human health</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>1995</year><volume>7</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1027</fpage><lpage>1038</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.7.7.1027</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7640523?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7640523</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>XX</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Red juice sac of citrus and its main pigments</article-title><source>J Fruit Sci</source><year>2002</year><volume>19</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>313</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ikoma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The characteristics of carotenoid biosynthesis in Citrus fruit</article-title><source>JARQ</source><year>2014</year><volume>48</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6090/jarq.48.9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsutani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamawaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yahata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wahyudi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Motohashi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enzymatic formation of <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-citraurin from <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-cryptoxanthin and zeaxanthin by carotenoid cleavage dioxygenase4 in the flavedo of citrus fruit</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>163</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>682</fpage><lpage>695</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.113.223297</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23966550?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23966550</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calandra</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Impellizzeri</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Laumer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Leocata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaintreau</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Terpene hydroperoxide chemistry in citrus oils; reaction with endogenous aldehydes to form peroxyhemiacetals</article-title><source>Flavour Fragr J</source><year>2016</year><volume>31</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ffj.3310</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hemmerlin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoeffler</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Tritsch</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kagan</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Grosdemange-Billiard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohmer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bach</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cross-talk between the cytosolic mevalonate and the plastidialmethylerythritol phosphate pathways in tobacco bright yellow-2 cells</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2003</year><volume>278</volume><issue>29</issue><fpage>26666</fpage><lpage>26676</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M302526200</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12736259?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12736259</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nambara</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Marion-Poll</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Abscisic acid biosynthesis and catabolism</article-title><source>Annu Rev Plant Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.arplant.56.032604.144046</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15862093?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15862093</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeevaart</surname><given-names>JAD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Elucidation of the indirect pathway of abscisic acid biosynthesis by mutants, genes, and enzymes</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>131</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1591</fpage><lpage>1601</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.102.017921</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12692318?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12692318</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alquezar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigo</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zacar&#x000ed;as</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of carotenoid biosynthesis during fruit maturation in the red-fleshed orange mutant Cara Cara</article-title><source>Phytochemistry</source><year>2008</year><volume>69</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1997</fpage><lpage>2007</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2008.04.020</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18538806?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18538806</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cazzonelli</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><name><surname>Pogson</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Source to sink: regulation of carotenoid biosynthesis in plants</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci</source><year>2010</year><volume>15</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>266</fpage><lpage>274</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2010.02.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20303820?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20303820</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Le&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>McQuinn</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pogson</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis and function of apocarotenoid signals in plants</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci</source><year>2016</year><volume>21</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>792</fpage><lpage>803</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2016.06.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27344539?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27344539</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ilg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Beyer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Babili</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tomato carotenoid cleavage dioxygenases 1A and 1B: Relaxed double bond specificity leads to a plenitude of dialdehydes, mono-apocarotenoids and isoprenoid volatiles</article-title><source>Febs Open Bio</source><year>2014</year><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>584</fpage><lpage>593</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fob.2014.06.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25057464?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25057464</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Auldridge</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Block</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Dabney-Smith</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mila</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouzayen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Magallanes-Lundback</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Penna</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Mccarty</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Klee</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of three members of the Arabidopsis carotenoid cleavage dioxygenase family demonstrates the divergent roles of this multifunctional enzyme family</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2006</year><volume>45</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>982</fpage><lpage>993</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2006.02666.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16507088?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16507088</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Floss</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Strack</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Apocarotenoids: hormones, mycorrhizal metabolites and aroma volatiles</article-title><source>Planta</source><year>2010</year><volume>232</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00425-010-1156-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20396903?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20396903</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Plotto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhaliwal</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gmitter</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proteomic and metabolomic analyses provide insight into production of volatile and non-volatile flavor components in mandarin hybrid fruit</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol</source><year>2015</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>76</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-015-0466-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25848837?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25848837</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ravichandran</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Carotenoid composition, distribution and degradation to flavour volatiles during black tea manufacture and the effect of carotenoid supplementation on tea quality and aroma</article-title><source>Food Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>78</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0308-8146(01)00303-X</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kanasawud</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Crouzet</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanism of formation of volatile compounds by thermal degradation of carotenoids in aqueous medium. 1.beta.-Carotene degradation</article-title><source>J Agric Food Chem</source><year>1990</year><volume>38</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>243</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf00091a052</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asins</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Monforte</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mestre</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Carbonell</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Citrus and Prunus copia-like retrotransposons</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>1999</year><volume>99</volume><issue>3&#x02013;4</issue><fpage>503</fpage><lpage>510</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s001220051263</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22665184?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22665184</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>