<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Hortic Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Hortic Res</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Horticulture Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2052-7276</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5802726</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">14</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41438-017-0014-x</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A comprehensive proteomic analysis of elaioplasts from citrus fruits reveals insights into elaioplast biogenesis and function</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Man</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Jiajia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Junli</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Rui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Chao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>Jinli</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Yun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Chongling</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Ping</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Chuanwu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Yunjiang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4490-4514</contrib-id><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Xiuxin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Yunliu</given-names></name><address><email>zengyl@mail.hzau.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1790 4137</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.35155.37</institution-id><institution>Key Laboratory of Horticultural Plant Biology (Ministry of Education), College of Horticulture and Forestry Science, </institution><institution>Huazhong Agricultural University, </institution></institution-wrap>Wuhan, 430070 China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1790 4137</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.35155.37</institution-id><institution>Institute of Citrus Science, </institution><institution>Huazhong Agricultural University, </institution></institution-wrap>Wuhan, 430070 China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Shanghai Applied Protein Technology Co. Ltd, Shanghai, 200233 China </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.464254.5</institution-id><institution>Guangxi Citrus Research Institute, </institution></institution-wrap>Guangxi, 541004 China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>7</day><month>2</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>7</day><month>2</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>6</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>8</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>7</day><month>12</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>12</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Elaioplasts of citrus peel are colorless plastids which accumulate significant amounts of terpenes. However, other functions of elaioplasts have not been fully characterized to date. Here, a LC&#x02013;MS/MS shotgun technology was applied to identify the proteins from elaioplasts that were highly purified from young fruit peel of kumquat. A total of 655 putative plastid proteins were identified from elaioplasts according to sequence homology <italic>in silico</italic> and manual curation. Based on functional classification via Mapman, ~50% of the identified proteins fall into six categories, including protein metabolism, transport, and lipid metabolism. Of note, elaioplasts contained ATP synthase and ADP, ATP carrier proteins at high abundance, indicating important roles for ATP generation and transport in elaioplast biogenesis. Additionally, a comparison of proteins between citrus chromoplast and elaioplast proteomes suggest a high level of functional conservation. However, some distinctive protein profiles were also observed in both types of plastids notably for isoprene biosynthesis in elaioplasts, and carotenoid metabolism in chromoplasts. In conclusion, this comprehensive proteomic study provides new insights into the major metabolic pathways and unique characteristics of elaioplasts and chromoplasts in citrus fruit.</p></abstract><abstract id="Abs2" abstract-type="LongSummary"><title>Citrus fruits: The proteins of elaioplasts</title><p id="Par2">A study of the proteins in bodies called elaioplasts in citrus fruit cells will help to clarify elaioplast formation and functions. Plant cells contain several types of membrane-bound bodies called plastids, with elaioplasts being an incompletely characterized type. They are known to store oils in the cells, especially molecules called terpenes that influence the fragrances and flavors of citrus fruits. Researchers in China, led by Yunliu Zeng at Huazhong Agricultural University, analyzed the protein molecules in elaioplasts of kumquat peel to investigate possible roles for elaioplasts other than oil storage. They identified more than 600 proteins and assigned likely functions to many. The results suggest the proteins are involved in chemical energy transactions and the manufacture of various categories of biomolecules. This will guide research to fully characterize the activities and significance of elaioplasts.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par34">Plants contain several kinds of plastids, such as chloroplasts in photosynthetic tissues (e.g., leaves and green fruit), chromoplasts in pigment-containing fruits, as well as colorless leucoplasts in starch-storing or lipid-storing seeds<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. These plastids are reported as the sites for several essential processes, including carbon fixation, nitrogen assimilation, and the biosynthesis of isoprenoids, starches, fatty acids (FA), and amino acids. Although plastids are a family of organelles possessing the same plastid genome (encoding approximately 100 proteins), the majority (&#x0003e;95%) of the 2000&#x02013;3500 different proteins are imported from the surrounding cytoplasm rather than being synthesized <italic>in situ</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. It is the imported proteins that define the developmental fate of plastids, leading to the different morphologies and special functions within specific plastids<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. Recently, large-scale proteomics analysis has become an efficient approach for the investigating subcellular organelles at the protein level<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. Special attention has been given to chloroplasts as well as chromoplasts in several species, including tomato, citrus, pepper, papaya, watermelon, carrot, and orange curd cauliflower<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. In contrast, relatively few proteomics studies have focused on other types of plastid.</p><p id="Par3">Leucoplasts are colorless plastids that include amyloplasts, elaioplasts, and proteoplasts that store starches, lipids, or proteins, respectively. Amyloplasts have been well studied and have been shown to be enriched in many storage tissues, including seeds, tubers/root vegetables, and fruits. In contrast, elaioplasts are much less studied in plants. Besides their role in storage, elaioplasts were also reported to possess crucial biosynthetic functions, for example in the biosynthesis of long-chain FAs in developing castor seeds<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup> and terpenes in the outer peel of citrus<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. Plastid isolation is a prerequisite not only for assessing proteome composition, but also for understanding metabolic processes, enzyme localization, metabolite transporters, and biogenesis. Although protocols for the isolation of elaioplasts are available for some plant tissues, including petals of snapdragon flowers (<italic>Antirrhinum majus</italic>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>, developing seeds of mustard (<italic>Brassica campestris</italic>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>, and maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>, as well as the outer peel of citrus (<italic>Citrofortunella mitis</italic>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>, the proteome profile of elaioplasts in these tissues is still unknown.</p><p id="Par4">Citrus are one of the most important horticultural crops around the world, and have a unique anatomical structure, which consists of the pericarp (peel) and an edible endocarp (flesh). The endocarp accumulates large amounts of carotenoids within chromoplasts, which not only bring the red, yellow, and orange colors of fruit flesh, but also provide several important groups of nutrients. The pigmented region of pericarp contains active secretory cells that are characterized by numerous elaioplasts. Elaioplasts have been demonstrated to be involved in the biosynthesis of terpenes in essential oil, which are then exported into the secretory pocket, greatly affecting the aroma and taste of the fruit<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. As the major component of essential oil, terpenes have been employed for manufacturing of perfumes and flavorings, and they are also used as antiseptic preservative agents to improve the safety and shelf-life of fruit during storage<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. Although significant progress has been made in understanding chromoplast differentiation in the peel of citrus fruits<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>, little information is available about the regulatory mechanisms underlying elaioplast biogenesis.</p><p id="Par5">In the present study, a comprehensive proteomic analysis using nLC-MS/MS-Q Exactive technology was used to identify proteins in elaioplasts isolated from the peel of kumquat by density gradient centrifugation. A total of 655 plastid protein candidates were detected that were predicted to participate in the general metabolism or unique metabolic pathways in elaioplasts, including flavor synthesis and fruit maturation. Overall, the present study provides an important insight into elaioplast biogenesis and formation of essential flavors.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Plant materials</title><p id="Par6">The outer peel of ~150 earlier-stage green fruits (0.5&#x02013;0.8&#x02009;cm in diameter) of &#x02018;Rong An&#x02019; kumquat (<italic>Fortunella margarita</italic> Swingle) was used for elaioplast isolation. Fresh mature pulp of &#x02018;Hong Anliu&#x02019; orange (<italic>C. sinensis</italic>) was used for chromoplast isolation. Both citrus cultivars were collected from Guangxi Institute of Citrus Research, located at Guilin city, Guangxi, China.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Elaioplast and chromoplast purification</title><p id="Par7">Elaioplasts were purified according to the procedure described by Michel et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup> with minor modifications. Approximately 10&#x02009;g of tissue was cut into pieces at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C and then gently homogenized in pre-cooled SPBTK buffer (50&#x02009;mM Tricine-NaOH pH 7.8, 5&#x02009;mM KCl, 0.3&#x02009;M sucrose, 0.5% (w/v) soluble polyvinylpyrrolidone 360, and 0.1% (w/v) bovine serum albumin). The homogenized sample was passed through two layers of Micracloth (Calbiochem). The pooled filtrate was centrifuged for 8&#x02009;min at 5000&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;<italic>g</italic>. The pellet was carefully re-suspended in SPBTK buffer at pH 7 and then centrifuged for 90&#x02009;s at 800&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;<italic>g</italic>. The resulting supernatant was centrifuged at 5000&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;<italic>g</italic> for 10&#x02009;min. The suspension containing most of the plastids was gently layered onto the top of a discontinuous gradient of 0.75, 0.92, 1.20, 1.50&#x02009;M sucrose in 50&#x02009;mM Tricine-NaOH (pH 6.5) and then centrifuged at 100,000&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;<italic>g</italic> for 90&#x02009;min in a Hitachi P40ST rotor. Four zones, designated as bands 1, 2, 3, 4 from the top to the bottom of the gradient, were clearly separated by sucrose gradient centrifugation. Each band was carefully recovered and examined under an optical microscope at &#x000d7;100 magnification (Cover-018; Olympus, Tokyo). The purity of each fraction was tested by western blot analysis (described below). The elaioplast layer (band 1) was recovered. Chromoplast isolation from sweet orange was performed as described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. The final pellets containing elaioplast or chromoplast fractions were collected and flash-frozen in liquid nitrogen and kept at &#x02212;80&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. The plastid samples were prepared in two biological replicates.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Western blot analysis</title><p id="Par8">Polyclonal antibodies were diluted as appropriate against plastid Rubisco large subunit (RubcL; 53&#x02009;kDa, 1:3000), cytosolic UDP-glucose pyrophosphorylase (UDPase; 51.6&#x02009;kDa, 1:2000), vacuolar ATPase (V-ATPase; 26&#x02013;31&#x02009;kDa, 1:2000), and mitochondrial voltage-dependent anion-selective channel protein 1 (VDAC1; 29&#x02009;kDa, 1:2000), as well as two photosynthesis-related antibodies (light-harvesting complex (Lhca1 and Lhca4), 1:5000) from Agrisera<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>. A total of 30&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of proteins were used for immunoblot analysis as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. At least two independent replicate experiments were performed for each immunoblot with similar result.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Protein extraction and digestion in solution</title><p id="Par9">Protein extraction was performed as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. The filter-assisted sample preparation method was adapted for protein digestion. Briefly, 200&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of proteins were mixed with 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of 100&#x02009;mM dithiothreitol (DTT), 150&#x02009;mM Tris&#x02013;HCl pH 8, 4% (w/v) SDS, incubated at 100&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 10&#x02009;min, and then cooled to 25&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. Next, UA buffer (150&#x02009;mM Tris&#x02013;HCl, pH 8.0, 8&#x02009;M Urea) was used to remove detergent, DTT, and other low-molecular-mass substances by repeated ultrafiltrate (10&#x02009;kDa; Microcon units), and then centrifuged for 30&#x02009;min at 14,000&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;<italic>g</italic>. The samples were washed using 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of UA buffer followed by centrifugation for 30&#x02009;min at 14,000&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;<italic>g</italic>, and then incubated under darkness for 30&#x02009;min by adding 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of UAI buffer (8&#x02009;M Urea, 150&#x02009;mM Tris&#x02013;HCl, pH 8.0, 50&#x02009;mM iodoacetamide). Further washes (three times) with 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of UA buffer followed by two washes using 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of 50&#x02009;mM NH<sub>4</sub>HCO<sub>3</sub> (pH 8.5) were performed. Finally, the resulting proteins were digested with 4&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of trypsin (Promega) overnight (16&#x02013;18&#x02009;h) at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. The concentration of peptide mix was estimated by UV absorbance at 280&#x02009;nm as described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Q Exactive-based LC&#x02013;MS/MS analysis</title><p id="Par10">nLC-MS/MS analysis was performed on an Easy-nLC system equipped with a Thermo Scientific Q Exactive mass spectrometer. 5&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of peptide mixture was injected onto an Acclaim PepMap100 trap column (nanoViper C18, 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;m&#x000d7;2&#x02009;cm, Thermo Scientific) fitted with a C18-reversed phase analytical column (Easy Column, 75&#x02009;&#x003bc;m&#x000d7;10&#x02009;cm, 3&#x02009;&#x003bc;m resin, Thermo Scientific) in mobile phase A (0.1% formic acid in water). Peptides were eluted with a linear 120-min gradient of mobile phase B (0.1% formic acid in 84% acetonitrile) at a flow rate of 0.3&#x02009;&#x003bc;l/min. The separated MS data were obtained as described in ref. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup></p><p id="Par11">MS/MS spectra were searched with the MaxQuant software package (version 1.1.0.36) against non-redundant protein databases of <italic>Citrus sinensis</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pytozome.com">http://www.pytozome.com</ext-link> or <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://citrus.hzau.edu.cn">http://citrus.hzau.edu.cn</ext-link>), and the complete chloroplast genome sequence of <italic>C. sinensis</italic> (accession no. NC_008334). The search parameters were performed as described in ref. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup> Only the proteins identified by two or more peptides in two bio-replicates were retained for further analysis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Functional categorization</title><p id="Par12">Detected proteins were categorized based on Mapman functional bins (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://mapman.gabipd.org/mapman">https://mapman.gabipd.org/mapman</ext-link>). Additional curation was performed according to classifications in PPDB (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ppdb.tc.cornell.edu">http://ppdb.tc.cornell.edu</ext-link>). The proteins identified in citrus plastids were queried against three comprehensive plastid proteome databanks (AT_CHLORO, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.grenoble.prabi.fr/at_chloro/">http://www.grenoble.prabi.fr/at_chloro/</ext-link>; PPDB (Plastid Proteome Database, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ppdb.tc.cornell.edu/">http://ppdb.tc.cornell.edu/</ext-link>); Plprot (Plastid Protein Database, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plprot.ethz.ch/">http://www.plprot.ethz.ch/</ext-link>); downloaded in October 2016); and two plastidial protein subset databanks (Uniprot, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.uniprot.org/">http://www.uniprot.org/</ext-link>; SUBA, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://suba.plantenergy.uwa.edu.au/">http://suba.plantenergy.uwa.edu.au/</ext-link>; downloaded in October 2016). There were 2816 plastid proteins in plprot, 1265 AT-CHLORO, 2292 in PPDB, 2977 in SUBA and 2038 in Uniprot.</p><p id="Par13">Subcellular localization analysis was carried out using three software programs: Predotar (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://urgi.versailles.inra.fr/predotar/">https://urgi.versailles.inra.fr/predotar/</ext-link>), Target P (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/TargetP/">http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/TargetP/</ext-link>), and WoLF PSORT (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genscript.com/wolf-psort.html">http://www.genscript.com/wolf-psort.html</ext-link>). Proteins were tentatively assigned as plastidial (i) if predicted to be plastid targeted by at least one of the three programs, and/or (ii) if homologous to plastid proteins annotated in at least two plastidial databanks. Additionally, sequence information was manually curated if they were available in the literature. The putative plastid proteins of elaioplast and chromoplast were listed in Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">S1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Microscopy observation and analysis</title><p id="Par14">Isolated plastids were carefully layered onto microscope slides and visualized using a DP70 camera coupled to an Olympus BX61 microscope. Plastid samples for transmission electron microscopy (TEM) analysis were prepared and examined as described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. The plastid diameter was calculated by (minor axis&#x02009;+&#x02009;major axis)/2 with ImageJ (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rsbweb.nih.gov/ij/">http://rsbweb.nih.gov/ij/</ext-link>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10" sec-type="results"><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>Isolation of highly purified elaioplasts from kumquat peel with density gradient centrifugations</title><p id="Par15">Kumquat, a major citrus cultivar in southern China, bears the smallest fruits in the <italic>Citrus</italic> genus. Ripened fruits can be eaten as a whole (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>), and elaioplasts with several plastoglobules were frequently found in the outer peel (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Fruits of kumquat and elaioplasts in the outer peel.</title><p><bold>a</bold> A representative photograph of kumquat fruits used for elaioplasts isolation. <bold>b</bold> Transmission electron microscopic (TEM) picture showing the ultrastructural features of elaioplasts in the outer peel of kumquat</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41438_2017_14_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e621"/></fig></p><p id="Par16">In this study, we initially isolated elaioplasts from the outer peel of kumquat. The recovered pellet containing elaioplasts was separated into four fractions on a discontinuous gradient comprising 0.75, 0.92, 1.20, 1.50&#x02009;M sucrose (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). The elaioplasts pooled from band 1 were characterized by abundant colorless plastids with several sphere substructures clustering together, and their sizes ranged from 1 to 4&#x02009;&#x003bc;m as measured under light microscopy and TEM (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b, c</xref>). Analysis of the other bands indicated they were contaminated by either cell debris with few elaioplasts, or chloroplasts (Supplementary Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Isolation and ultrastructure of citrus peel elaioplasts.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Separation of elaioplasts on a discontinuous sucrose gradient (0.75, 0.92, 1.20, 1.50&#x02009;M, Bands 1&#x02013;4). <bold>b</bold> Light microscopy of purified elaioplasts. A representative micrograph of band 1 by density gradient contains a clean fraction of elaioplasts. Arrows indicate abundant colorless plastids with several sphere substructures clustering together. <bold>c</bold> An electron micrograph showing the ultrastructure of elaioplasts. The arrow indicates a plastoglobule</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41438_2017_14_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e651"/></fig></p><p id="Par17">The purity of the elaioplast-enriched protein fractions was monitored by immunoblot analysis with antibodies against marker proteins for the plastid stroma (RbcL), cytosol (UDPase), vacuole (V-ATPase), and mitochondrion (VDAC1), as well as chloroplast (Lhca1 and Lhca4). As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, proteins extracted from the purified elaioplast fraction readily reacted with the antibody of RbcL. By contrast, no reaction could be detected with the cytosolic UGPase, mitochondrial VDAC1, or vacuolar V-ATPase. Additionally, no reaction was detected with antibodies to PSI type I chlorophyll a/b-binding proteins (Lhca1 and Lhca4) involved in photosynthesis within the chloroplasts. Reactions with these antibodies were observed in the total proteins extracted from the kumquat peel which contained both chloroplasts and elaioplasts. The above results suggest that the isolated elaioplasts used for the subsequent proteome analysis were of high purity without contamination by mitochondria, cytosol, vacuole, and chloroplasts.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>Assessment of the purity of isolated elaioplasts using immunoblots.</title><p>Different fractions of the sucrose gradient (Band 1 to Band 4) are compared to peel proteins using antibodies for plastid stroma large Rubisco subunit (RbcL), cytosolic UGPase, vacuolar (v)-ATPase, mitochondrial voltage-dependent anion-selective channel protein 1 (VDAC1), and photosynthesis Light-harvesting complex (Lhca1 and Lhca4); <bold>b</bold> Coomassie blue protein profiles of purified elaioplasts (Band 1 to Band 4) from kumquat peel, as compared with purified chromoplast (Chro.) from sweet orange flesh and total kumquat peel proteins</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41438_2017_14_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e670"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>An inventory of proteins in elaioplasts by functional classification and subcellular localization</title><p id="Par18">We conducted a comprehensive proteomic analysis to characterize the proteins found in elaioplasts. A total of 1239 proteins with at least two detected peptides in two bio-replicates, were identified from purified elaioplasts. The raw data obtained from the elaioplast proteins were refined by searches against five plastid databanks (Plprot, AT-CHLORO, SUBA, PPDB, and Uniprot) and by three targeting predictors (WoLF PSORT, Predotar, and Target P). Based on the chosen criteria for plastid-localized proteins (Materials and Methods), an inventory of 655 putative plastid proteins was constructed, accounting for 52% of all identified proteins (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). Among them, 562 proteins (accounting for 85.8% of these identified proteins) were predicted to be plastid targeted by at least one predictor program. WoLF PSORT, Target P, and Predotar predicted plastid-localization of 76.0% (498 proteins), 38.2% (250 proteins), and 31.9% (209 proteins) of the 655 identified proteins, respectively. Two hundred and twenty-nine proteins (35.0%) were predicted to be plastid targeted by at least two predictors, suggesting that these proteins are highly likely to be plastid localized. As shown in Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">S1</xref> and in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, the 655 putative elaioplast proteins were categorized into 32 functional classes according to MapMan bins.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>Functional categories of proteins identified from elaioplasts.</title><p>Proteins were categorized into 32 functional classifications according to MapMan (verified by PPDB, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://mapman.gabipd.org/mapman">https://mapman.gabipd.org/mapman</ext-link>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41438_2017_14_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e700"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Major metabolic functions in the citrus elaioplast proteome</title><p id="Par19">The identification of proteome profiles allows an overview of proteins involved in various metabolic pathways<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, the major metabolic pathways in citrus elaioplasts are protein metabolism and process, transport, secondary metabolism, lipid metabolism, redox and stress, amino acid metabolism, photosynthesis, DNA and RNA, and miscellaneous.</p><p id="Par20">Elaioplasts are a type of heterotrophic plastid, wherein all the metabolic precursors are either generated via oxidative metabolism or actively imported from the cytosol to sustain anabolic reactions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. The proteins of the Calvin cycle are involved in providing intermediates for glycolysis, and proteins of the oxidative pentose phosphate pathway (OPPP) serve as a major source of reducing power for various metabolic pathways. As expected, we identified several proteins involved in the Calvin cycle within elaioplasts, such as fructose-bisphosphate aldolase, phosphoglycerate kinase, and transketolase. Furthermore, proteins participated in oxidative metabolism were well presented, including glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase, 6-phosphogluconolactonase, and 6-phosphogluconate dehydrogenase. Of note, transketolase and transaldolase (key enzymes of the non-oxidative part of OPPP), which are reported to feed the processes of anabolism or glycolysis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>, were also identified in the present study. Glycolysis also occurs in plastids to generate ATP and pyruvate in plants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. Several glycolysis enzymes including aldolase, phosphoglycerate kinase, enolase, and pyruvate kinase were observed. Consistent with previous findings in non-photosynthetic plastids, a substantial number of proteins responsible for the generation of ATP and reducing power were observed<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>, indicating their high conservation among different plastid types. Taken together, the observation of many proteins involved in essential biosynthetic activities suggests an active metabolism in elaioplasts to produce reducing power and energy, as well as the supply of precursors for the biosynthesis of metabolites.</p><p id="Par21">Several proteins involved in photosynthesis were found in elaioplasts although the presence of chloroplasts was not observed using light microscopy and there was no signal obtained by immunoblotting using two photosynthesis-related antibodies (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a</xref>). This suggests that these proteins serve roles in processes other than photosynthesis in elaioplasts. It is no surprise to find photosynthetic proteins in elaioplasts, since similar observations have been made in other types of non-photosynthetic plastids, such as chromoplasts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup> and amyloplasts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par22">FA are known to be synthesized in plastids<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. We detected several enzymes for the synthesis of FA as well as glycolipids and phospholipids in elaioplasts, such as acetyl E1 beta pyruvate dehydrogenase complex, E2-dihydrolipoamide acetyltransferase, E3-dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase 1, long-chain acyl-CoA synthetase 7/8/9, and plastidial ketoacyl-ACP reductase (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). The accumulated FA could be converted into phosphatidic acid and/or imported into plastids via the trigalactosyldiacylglycerol (TDG) complex transporter, which is targeted to the plastid envelope membrane<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. As expected, several key enzymes involved in lipid metabolism and homeostasis were detected in elaioplasts, such as TDG2, phosphatidylglycerolphosphate synthase 1, sulfoquinovosyldiacylglycerol synthase, as well as 3-ketoacyl-CoA thiolase, enoyl-CoA hydratase, phospholipase D&#x003b1;1, and cyclopropane-fatty-acyl-phospholipid synthase. These results indicate that the elaioplasts have the ability to synthesize FAs and polar lipids that might relate to the formation of new membranes during elaioplast development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. This finding is also in agreement with a recent metabolic analysis in isolated tomato fruit chromoplasts using radiolabeled precursors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>, which suggests a highly conservative mechanism for lipid biosynthesis and homeostasis in both chromoplasts and elaioplasts. It has been well documented that lipoxygenases (LOX), which are associated with generation of polyunsaturated FA hydroperoxides, could contribute to the biosynthesis of jasmonic acid (JA)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup> and FA-derived flavor compounds<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. In the present study, several enzymes involved in the LOX pathway (such as LOX1, LOX2, and LOX6) and JA metabolism (allene oxide cyclase 4) were detected. Therefore, it is possible that the presence of lipoxygenases in citrus elaioplasts and chromoplasts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup> may play a key role in generating odor or flavor through production of LOX-derived volatiles in the outer peel and flesh of a fruit, respectively. A similar role for lipoxygenases in chromoplasts of tomato has been proposed<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par23">Elaioplasts are also important sites for amino acids synthesis. A large number of proteins responsible for amino acid metabolism were identified in elaioplasts, such as threonine synthase, aspartate aminotransferase, alanine transaminase, argininosuccinate synthase, cystathionine beta-lyase, 3-dehydroquinate synthase, isopropylmalate isomerase, isopropylmalate dehydrogenase, and ketol-acid reductoisomerase (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). Consistently, proteins of amino acid metabolism were also extensively found in non-photosynthetic plastids<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. Taken together, our data suggest that these proteins involved in the biosynthesis of several types of amino acids, including aromatic amino acids have important functions in the active synthesis of amino acids within the elaioplasts.</p><p id="Par24">Active redox system is a key regulator for plant development and fruit senescence and has a wide range of functions in gene expression, enzyme activities, and protein import in plastids<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. In the elaioplast proteome, proteins involved in redox &#x00026; stress constituted one of the top five functional classes. Several essential components in maintaining homeostasis of cell redox were found in the elaioplast proteome. These include the proteins involved in ascorbate-glutathione (AsA-GSH) cycle and antioxidant system of plastids, such as glutathione peroxidases, peroxiredoxins (PRXs), superoxide dismutases (SODs), and thioredoxin. Additionally, several key enzymes involved in second active oxygen species scavenging system were identified in elaioplasts, including the AsA-GSH cycle catalyzed by ascorbate peroxidases (APXs), as well as the AsA-dependent generation systems catalyzed by (momo)dehydroascorbate reductase<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. Like in photosynthetic chloroplasts, APXs encountered in elaioplasts may indicate the presence of the AsA-dependent system involves the reduction of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> using AsA as reductant<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>. The activation of plastid SOD expression was detected to be dependent on a copper chaperone for SOD<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. Thus, as expected, Fe-SOD and Mn-SOD were detected and their overexpression induced an enhancement of plant tolerance in response to environmental stresses<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. The presence of a large number of enzymes involved in oxidative stress response indicates a functionally active redox system in citrus elaioplasts and suggests the roles of these proteins in ROS metabolism, allowing the plastid to adapt to various environmental signals and processes during elaioplast development as fruit maturation proceeds.</p><p id="Par25">Protein synthesis, degradation, and translocation regulate the biogenesis of plastids. In this study, proteins associated with import, ribosome assembly and proteases account for 16.9% of the total plastid proteins (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). (1) Import of nuclear-encoded precursor proteins into plastids is mediated by translocon complexes at the outer and inner envelope membrane of chloroplasts (TOC/TIC complexes)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>, which is important for the biogenesis of either chloroplasts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup> or chromoplasts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. However, the import machinery remains unclear in elaioplasts. In this study, numerous translocons including TOC33/75/159 and TIC62/55/40/22/110 in the protein import machinery were identified in elaioplast proteome (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). Among the TOC complex members, TOC75, which is deeply embedded within outer membrane of plastid, plays a major role to form protein translocation channel<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. TIC110, the major translocon component for protein translocation, plays a critical role in protein import into plastids<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>. The extensive identification of TOC/TIC complex likely plays an important role in elaioplast biogenesis on basis of protein import machinery. (2) Thirty ribosomal proteins of translation machinery were identified in citrus elaioplasts. These proteins are represented by plastid-encoded 30S and 50S subunit, together with nucleus-encoded 40S and 60S subunit. These findings suggest the presence of translation machinery in elaioplast biogenesis. (3) Maintaining a balance between protein synthesis, import, turnover, and processing is an important factor determining plastid fate and maintaining their homeostasis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. As expected, we identified numerous caseinolytic peptidase (Clp) proteases in the study (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">S1</xref>), which have been well reported to form a chaperone complex to drive protein import, processing, and recycle plastid components. The knock-out of most members of Arabidopsis Clp proteases resulted in variegated/pale-green leaf phenotype, indicating their crucial roles in chloroplast development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. Elaioplast proteome also consists of several membrane-bound ATP-dependent metalloproteases (FtsH2, FtsH4, FtsH5, FtsH9, and FtsHi4), which have been described as critical for plastid development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>. The extensive presence of Clp protease family in elaioplasts might contribute to elaioplast biogenesis by processing and/or cleavage of transit peptides of proteins in the plastids.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Abundant proteins in citrus elaioplasts</title><p id="Par26">The protein abundance for all proteins detected in kumquat elaioplasts was determined based on intensity-based absolute quantification (iBAQ). The 30 most abundant proteins of kumquat elaioplasts are listed in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Among them, we identified four enzymes involving in secondary metabolism. Three enzymes (i.e. DXS, HDS, and GGPS) belong to the 2-C-methyl-<sc>d</sc>-erythritol 4-phosphate (MEP) pathway, which provides precursors to synthesize monoterpenes within plastids. The fourth (orange1.1t03905) was a putative terpene synthase, which might be responsible for the accumulation of <sc>d</sc>-limonene (accounting for up to 90% among monoterpene compounds) in outer peel of citrus<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>. The importance of DXS in regulating MEP substrate flux in kiwifruit and grape has previously been reported<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup> and the identification of MEP pathway proteins and TPS genes in citrus elaioplasts indicates the key role that elaioplasts play in basic metabolism.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Thirty most abundant proteins identified from elaioplasts</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Accession</th><th>Rep. 1</th><th>Rep. 2</th><th>Protein description</th><th>Mapman</th><th>iBAQ in Rep. 1</th><th>iBAQ in Rep. 2</th><th>Average iBAQ</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Cs7g01840</td><td>13</td><td>11</td><td>ADP, ATP carrier protein 2</td><td>Transport</td><td>27.7</td><td>27.4</td><td>27.6</td></tr><tr><td>Cs1g10270</td><td>27</td><td>28</td><td>Obsolete gene model variant (ATPase 70&#x02009;kDa)</td><td>Transport</td><td>27.5</td><td>27.4</td><td>27.4</td></tr><tr><td>Cs3g24640</td><td>5</td><td>7</td><td>OEP24-II</td><td>Transport</td><td>27.0</td><td>26.8</td><td>26.9</td></tr><tr><td>orange1.1t02891</td><td>4</td><td>4</td><td>HP30-2 (PRAT family)</td><td>Transport</td><td>26.7</td><td>26.7</td><td>26.7</td></tr><tr><td>Cs2g14350</td><td>12</td><td>12</td><td>Phosphate transporter (PHT3-1 or PIC1)</td><td>Transport</td><td>26.6</td><td>26.7</td><td>26.7</td></tr><tr><td>Cs6g15300</td><td>42</td><td>44</td><td>ATP-binding cassette transporter</td><td>Transport</td><td>26.7</td><td>26.6</td><td>26.6</td></tr><tr><td>Cs2g13550</td><td>24</td><td>25</td><td>H<sup>+</sup>-transporting ATP synthase beta chain</td><td>Electron transport/ATP synthesis</td><td>28.6</td><td>28.7</td><td>28.6</td></tr><tr><td>orange1.1t01329</td><td>2</td><td>2</td><td>ATP synthase epsilon chain</td><td>Electron transport/ATP synthesis</td><td>27.5</td><td>27.4</td><td>27.4</td></tr><tr><td>Cs1g20530</td><td>15</td><td>15</td><td>1-deoxy-<sc>d</sc>-xylulose 5-phosphate synthase (DXS1)</td><td>Secondary metabolism</td><td>27.7</td><td>27.9</td><td>27.8</td></tr><tr><td>orange1.1t03905</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>(R)-limonene synthase 1</td><td>Secondary metabolism</td><td>27.9</td><td>27.5</td><td>27.7</td></tr><tr><td>Cs6g17510</td><td>11</td><td>11</td><td>Geranylgeranyl pyrophosphate synthase (GGPS1)</td><td>Secondary metabolism</td><td>27.5</td><td>27.4</td><td>27.5</td></tr><tr><td>Cs8g16700</td><td>29</td><td>28</td><td>4-hydroxy-3-methylbutyl diphosphate synthase (HDS)</td><td>Secondary metabolism</td><td>26.8</td><td>26.8</td><td>26.8</td></tr><tr><td>Cs5g33860</td><td>9</td><td>10</td><td>Thioredoxin family protein</td><td>Redox and stress</td><td>27.0</td><td>27.2</td><td>27.1</td></tr><tr><td>Cs7g16410</td><td>7</td><td>7</td><td>NADH-cytochrome b5 reductase</td><td>Redox and stress</td><td>26.6</td><td>26.5</td><td>26.5</td></tr><tr><td>Cs6g15550</td><td>8</td><td>6</td><td>Peroxiredoxin IIE (PrxII E)</td><td>Redox and stress</td><td>26.6</td><td>26.4</td><td>26.5</td></tr><tr><td>gi|113952630</td><td>17</td><td>19</td><td>Ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase/oxygenase large subunit</td><td>PS</td><td>29.3</td><td>29.6</td><td>29.4</td></tr><tr><td>Cs2g03780</td><td>6</td><td>6</td><td>LHCII-1.2</td><td>PS</td><td>29.3</td><td>29.5</td><td>29.4</td></tr><tr><td>Cs6g18680</td><td>9</td><td>9</td><td>Rubisco small subunit 3b</td><td>PS</td><td>28.4</td><td>28.4</td><td>28.4</td></tr><tr><td>orange1.1t00226</td><td>15</td><td>14</td><td>Transketolase-2 (TKL-2)</td><td>PS</td><td>26.8</td><td>26.6</td><td>26.7</td></tr><tr><td>Cs6g14330</td><td>6</td><td>8</td><td>40&#x02009;S ribosomal protein S14 (RPS14C)</td><td>Protein synthesis</td><td>27.4</td><td>27.3</td><td>27.4</td></tr><tr><td>Cs5g16780</td><td>8</td><td>10</td><td>Kunitz-type protease inhibitor</td><td>Protein degradation</td><td>27.0</td><td>27.1</td><td>27.1</td></tr><tr><td>orange1.1t01459</td><td>31</td><td>31</td><td>Cpn60 subunits</td><td>Protein assembly &#x00026; folding</td><td>27.4</td><td>27.5</td><td>27.4</td></tr><tr><td>Cs7g29010</td><td>20</td><td>24</td><td>HSP70-1</td><td>Protein assembly &#x00026; folding</td><td>26.7</td><td>26.8</td><td>26.7</td></tr><tr><td>Cs2g28210</td><td>13</td><td>15</td><td>Formate dehydrogenase</td><td>Others</td><td>27.7</td><td>27.6</td><td>27.7</td></tr><tr><td>Cs3g27530</td><td>3</td><td>2</td><td>Hp17</td><td>Not assigned</td><td>27.1</td><td>27.0</td><td>27.1</td></tr><tr><td>Cs2g21000</td><td>17</td><td>14</td><td>Hydroperoxide lyase1</td><td>Not assigned</td><td>26.9</td><td>27.0</td><td>27.0</td></tr><tr><td>Cs2g02520</td><td>13</td><td>14</td><td>Fibrillin 1b (FBN1b)</td><td>Misc</td><td>27.1</td><td>27.1</td><td>27.1</td></tr><tr><td>orange1.1t04376</td><td>31</td><td>35</td><td>Lipoxygenase AtLOX2, plastid</td><td>Hormone metabolism</td><td>27.9</td><td>27.7</td><td>27.8</td></tr><tr><td>Cs8g03410</td><td>9</td><td>11</td><td>Branched-chain amino acid transaminase 2</td><td>Amino acid metabolism</td><td>26.4</td><td>26.5</td><td>26.4</td></tr><tr><td>Cs9g14610</td><td>9</td><td>8</td><td>BCL-2-associated athanogene 7 (ATBAG7)</td><td>Signaling</td><td>27.4</td><td>27.3</td><td>27.4</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par27">Eight proteins involved in transport or electron transport categories, such as ADP, ATP carrier protein, ATP-binding cassette transporter, ATPase, as well as ATP synthase beta/epsilon chain were also detected in kumquat elaioplasts. ATPase acts as an essential regulator of membrane trafficking, which couples free energy generated from ATP hydrolysis to transport of substances across the membranes of many organelles<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>. ATP synthases are involved in energy production and proton transport. The identification of these proteins at high abundance suggests they may play an important role in active energy production and transport during elaioplast development. The presence of an active ATP generation system that is also necessary for the formation of membranes in plastids<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>. Elevated energy production has also be observed in other heterotrophic plastids, such as chromoplasts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup> and proplastids<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>The citrus elaioplast proteome compared with citrus chromoplast proteome</title><p id="Par28">To determine whether the ultrastructure was different between elaioplasts and chromoplasts, we purified chromoplasts from citrus flesh for comparison with elaioplasts. TEM analysis showed that the size of elaioplasts was 2.15&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.70&#x02009;&#x003bc;m in diameter, which was significantly smaller than that of chromoplast (2.59&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.60&#x02009;&#x003bc;m) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref>; Supplementary Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). The number of plastoglobules (5.86&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.65) per elaioplast was approximately half that per chromoplast (11.59&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.94) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5b</xref>). However, the size of plastoglobules within elaioplasts was 0.48&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.25&#x02009;&#x003bc;m in diameter, which was about threefold greater than the diameter of plastoglobules within a chromoplast (0.14&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.06&#x02009;&#x003bc;m) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5c</xref>). Taken together, the above results suggest that there are differences in ultrastructure between elaioplasts and chromoplasts.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><title>Ultrastructural differences between elaioplasts and chromoplasts.</title><p><bold>a</bold> The size of elaioplasts and chromoplasts in diameter. <bold>b</bold> The number of plastoglobules versus that of chromoplasts. <bold>c</bold> The size of plastoglobule of elaioplasts versus that of chromoplasts. Data are indicated as means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD and <italic>p</italic> values were calculated using Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic> test in Microsoft Excel. ***<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001; number (<italic>N</italic>) in the bars represents the number of plastids measured by using ImageJ software</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41438_2017_14_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e1781"/></fig></p><p id="Par29">Given the structural differences between elaioplasts and chromoplasts, it was not surprising that differences in protein distribution patterns on SDS-PAGE gels were also observed (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b</xref>). We further explored these differences by comparing the elaioplast proteome with that of chromoplast at the mass spectrometric level (Supplementary Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). Distinct proteome profiles for the biosynthesis and accumulation of different secondary metabolites was observed between elaioplasts and chromoplasts. A total of 42 and 40 core enzymes involved in secondary metabolism were identified in elaioplasts and chromoplasts, respectively (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). The MEP pathway provides substrates to synthesize terpenes, tocopherols, and carotenoids (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). In this study, an entire set of enzymes responsible for the MEP pathway were found in both elaioplasts and chromoplasts, including DXS, DXR, CMK, MCT, MDS, HDS, and HDR. Terpenoids are specifically accumulated in elaioplasts. We found seven proteins involved in terpenoid biosynthesis, such as myrcene synthase, 1,8-cineole synthase, germacrene synthase, and limonene synthase which accounted for more than 16.7% of total proteins involved in secondary metabolism (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). By contrast, only limonene synthase (accounting for 2.5%) was identified in chromoplasts. With regard to carotenoid metabolism, ten enzymes (accounting for 25%) involved in carotenoid synthesis were identified in the chromopasts, including the rate limiting enzyme phytoene synthase, &#x003b6;-carotene desaturase (ZDS), phytoene desaturase, lycopene &#x003b2;-cyclase, carotenoid isomerase (CRTISO), and &#x003b2;-carotene hydroxylase. By contrast, only CRTISO and ZDS were identified in elaioplasts. The synthesis of volatile apocarotenoids enhances dramatically during plastid development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>. Consistently, CCD1 was detected in elaioplasts and chromoplasts.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><title>Schematic illustration of the biosynthesis of secondary metabolites in elaioplasts and chromoplasts.</title><p>Proteins in boldface were identified in the proteomes of both plastid types. The full name of enzymes was listed in Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">S2</xref>. DXP 1-deoxy-<sc>d</sc>-xylulose 5-phosphate, MEP 2C-methylerythritol 4-phosphate, IPP isopentenyl diphosphate, DMAPP dimethylallyl pyrophosphate, GPP geranyl diphosphate, FPP farnesyl disphosphate, GGPP geranylgeranyl diphosphate, MPBQ 2-Methyl-6-phytyl-1,4-hydroquinol, DMPBQ 2,3-Dimethyl-5-phytyl-1,4-hydroquinol</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41438_2017_14_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e1823"/></fig></p><p id="Par30">The extensive formation of plastoglobules within chromoplasts of citrus flesh is the most representative feature during chromoplast biogenesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>, which is confirmed by the present study (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5b</xref>). Thirty plastoglobule-localized proteins have been established in Arabidopsis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>, and in our previous chromoplast proteome analysis we identified citrus homologs for 24 of these 30 proteins<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. In this study, we identified five additional plastoglobule-localized proteins (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">S4</xref>). However, it remains unclear whether plastoglobules within elaioplasts have a protein composition similar to that in chromoplasts. In elaioplasts, we only identified eight proteins that are predicted to be plastoglobule-localized using the same method. They include fibrillin 1 (FBN1), FBN7, tocopherol cyclase, flavin reductase-related 1/2, PLAT/LH2-1, and diacylglycerol acyltransferase. The FBN family is required for the development of leaf and fruit, and is involved in regulation of the extension of plastoglobules<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>. In pepper, it is reported to be important for the formation of carotenoid-lipoprotein sequestration substructures and contributes to elevated levels of carotenoid accumulation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup>. Fibrillin and its homologs were identified at high abundance in elaioplasts (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), suggesting a possible role in the formation of plastoglobules. Since lipid-rich colorless elaioplasts likely have specialized but unknown functions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup>, they might possess a unique plastoglobule proteome. Therefore, the further determination of plastoglobule proteomes of this colorless, non-photosynthetic plastid is necessary and meaningful.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec16" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par31">The present study reveals several important characteristics of the elaioplasts of kumquat peel. An inventory of 655 candidate proteins predicted to be localized in citrus elaioplasts was constructed based on <italic>in silico</italic> homology analyses, and the majority of these proteins share similar distribution patterns in Mapman functional classes between elaioplast and chromoplast. The identification of the abundant proteins associated with the MEP pathway and terpene biosynthesis in elaioplasts suggest that this biochemical process may define a basic feature of elaioplasts. In conclusion, this proteomic analysis provides a comprehensive understanding of citrus elaioplasts as a key step towards uncovering the biogenesis of the elaioplast and its terpene metabolism.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec17"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41438_2017_14_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplemental Figures 1-3</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="41438_2017_14_MOESM2_ESM.xls"><caption><p>Supplementary Table S1: Characteristics of the identified citrus plastid proteins</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="41438_2017_14_MOESM3_ESM.xls"><caption><p>Supplementary Table S2: The proteome profiles of &#x02018;secondary metabolism&#x02019; class proteins in elaioplasts and chromoplasts</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="41438_2017_14_MOESM4_ESM.xls"><caption><p>Supplementary Table S3: Comparative protein profiling involved in secondary metabolites in plastids</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5"><media xlink:href="41438_2017_14_MOESM5_ESM.xls"><caption><p>Supplementary Table S4: The core proteome of plastoglobules of elaioplasts and chromoplasts</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Electronic supplementary material</bold></p><p><bold>Supplementary Information</bold> accompanies this paper at (10.1038/s41438-017-0014-x).</p></fn></fn-group><ack><p>This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (NSFC, grant nos. 31501739), the National Basic Research Program of China (973 project No. 2013CB127105), and Huazhong Agricultural University Scientific &#x00026; Technological Self-innovation Foundation (No. 2662015BQ034). We are grateful to Prof. Zuoxiong Liu (Foreign Language College of Huazhong Agricultural University), Ross Atkinson (Plant and Food research, New Zealand), and Prof. Shunyuan Xiao (Center for Biosystems Research, University of Maryland Biotechnology Institute, USA) for their critical review of the manuscript.</p></ack><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p id="Par32">The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Egea</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chromoplast differentiation: current status and perspectives</article-title><source>Plant Cell. Physiol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>1601</fpage><lpage>1611</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcq136</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20801922?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20801922</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Wijk</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Baginsky</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plastid proteomics in higher plants: current state and future goals</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>155</volume><fpage>1578</fpage><lpage>1588</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.111.172932</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21350036?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21350036</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plastids and carotenoid accumulation</article-title><source>Subcell. Biochem.</source><year>2016</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-319-39126-7_10</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27485226?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27485226</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Whelan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Small</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recent surprises in protein targeting to mitochondria and plastids</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Plant Biol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>610</fpage><lpage>615</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2006.09.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17008120?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17008120</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siddique</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruissem</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Baginsky</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proteome analysis of bell pepper (<italic>Capsicum annuum</italic> L.) chromoplasts</article-title><source>Plant Cell. Physiol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>1663</fpage><lpage>1673</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcl033</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17098784?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17098784</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barsan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characteristics of the tomato chromoplast revealed by proteomic analysis</article-title><source>J. Exp. Bot.</source><year>2010</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>2413</fpage><lpage>2431</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erq070</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20363867?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20363867</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barsan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Proteomic analysis of chloroplast-to-chromoplast transition in tomato reveals metabolic shifts coupled with disrupted thylakoid biogenesis machinery and elevated energy-production components</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>160</volume><fpage>708</fpage><lpage>725</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.112.203679</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22908117?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22908117</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Proteomic analysis of chromoplasts from six crop species reveals insights into chromoplast function and development</article-title><source>J. Exp. Bot.</source><year>2013</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>949</fpage><lpage>961</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ers375</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23314817?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23314817</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A comprehensive analysis of chromoplast differentiation reveals complex protein changes associated with plastoglobule biogenesis and remodeling of protein systems in sweet orange flesh</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>168</volume><fpage>1648</fpage><lpage>1665</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.15.00645</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26056088?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26056088</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A proteomic analysis of the chromoplasts isolated from sweet orange fruits <italic>Citrus sinensis (L.)</italic> Osbeck</article-title><source>J. Exp. Bot.</source><year>2011</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>5297</fpage><lpage>5309</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/err140</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21841170?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21841170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Phosphoproteomic analysis of chromoplasts from sweet orange during fruit ripening</article-title><source>Physiol. Plant.</source><year>2014</year><volume>150</volume><fpage>252</fpage><lpage>270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ppl.12080</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23786612?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23786612</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eastmond</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Rawsthorne</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence that a malate/inorganic phosphate exchange translocator imports carbon across the leucoplast envelope for fatty acid synthesis in developing castor seed endosperm</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>1997</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>851</fpage><lpage>856</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.114.3.851</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12223747?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12223747</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamasaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Akimitsu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In situ localization of gene transcriptions for monoterpene synthesis in irregular parenchymic cells surrounding the secretory cavities in rough lemon (<italic>Citrus jambhiri</italic>)</article-title><source>J. Plant Physiol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>164</volume><fpage>1436</fpage><lpage>1448</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jplph.2006.10.008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17223221?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17223221</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ginette</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jean-Pierre</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Anne</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Colette</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Monoterpene hydrocarbon biosynthesis by isolated leucoplasts of <italic>Citrofortunella mitis</italic></article-title><source>Planta</source><year>1983</year><volume>159</volume><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>381</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00393177</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24258236</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagegowda</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gutensohn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkerson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudareva</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Two nearly identical terpene synthases catalyze the formation of nerolidol and linalool in snapdragon flowers</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2008</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>224</fpage><lpage>239</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2008.03496.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18363779?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18363779</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fatty acid synthesis in leucoplasts isolated from developing seeds of <italic>Brassica campestris</italic></article-title><source>J. Plant Biochem. Biot.</source><year>1996</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF03262998</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fatty acid synthesis in isolated leucoplasts of developing seeds of <italic>Brassica campestris</italic> L</article-title><source>Acta Physiol. Plant</source><year>2003</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>240</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11738-003-0003-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lara-N&#x000fa;&#x000f1;ez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of a dicarboxylate exchange system able to exchange pyrophosphate for L-malate in non-photosynthetic plastids from developing maize embryos</article-title><source>Plant Sci.</source><year>2004</year><volume>166</volume><fpage>1335</fpage><lpage>1343</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plantsci.2004.01.015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Voo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Grimes</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessing the biosynthetic capabilities of secretory glands in Citrus peel</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>159</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.112.194233</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22452856?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22452856</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-fungal activity of Citrus reticulata Blanco essential oil against <italic>Penicillium italicum</italic> and <italic>Penicillium digitatum</italic></article-title><source>Food Chem.</source><year>2014</year><volume>153</volume><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>271</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2013.12.070</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24491729?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24491729</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patrignani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Siroli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Serrazanetti</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gardini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanciotti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Innovative strategies based on the use of essential oils and their components to improve safety, shelf-life and quality of minimally processed fruits and vegetables</article-title><source>Trend Food Sci. Tech.</source><year>2015</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>311</fpage><lpage>319</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2015.03.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eilati</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>SP</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Budowski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seasonal development of external color and carotenoid content in the peel of ripening &#x02018;Shamouti&#x02019; oranges</article-title><source>J. Am. Soc. Hortic. Sci.</source><year>1969</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>346</fpage><lpage>348</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iglesias</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Physiology of citrus fruiting</article-title><source>Braz. J. Plant Physiol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1677-04202007000400006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kleffmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> chloroplast proteome reveals pathway abundance and novel protein functions</article-title><source>Curr. Biol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>354</fpage><lpage>362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2004.02.039</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15028209?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15028209</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>von Zychlinski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Proteome analysis of the rice etioplast metabolic and regulatory networks and novel protein functions</article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Proteom.</source><year>2005</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1072</fpage><lpage>1084</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/mcp.M500018-MCP200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balmer</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Vensel</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>DuPont</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Buchanan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurkman</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proteome of amyloplasts isolated from developing wheat endosperm presents evidence of broad metabolic capability</article-title><source>J. Exp. Bot.</source><year>2006</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>1591</fpage><lpage>1602</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erj156</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16595579?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16595579</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Daher</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Proteomic analysis of Medicago truncatula root plastids</article-title><source>Proteomics</source><year>2010</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>2123</fpage><lpage>2137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pmic.200900345</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20336678?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20336678</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chromoplast biogenesis and carotenoid accumulation</article-title><source>Arch. Biochem. Biophys.</source><year>2013</year><volume>539</volume><fpage>102</fpage><lpage>109</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.abb.2013.07.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23851381?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23851381</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neuhaus</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Emes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nonphotosynthetic metabolism in plastids</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Plant Biol.</source><year>2000</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.arplant.51.1.111</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stincone</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The return of metabolism: biochemistry and physiology of the pentose phosphate pathway</article-title><source>Biol. Rev.</source><year>2015</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>927</fpage><lpage>963</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/brv.12140</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25243985?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25243985</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plaxton</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The organization and regulation of plant glycolysis</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Plant Biol.</source><year>1996</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>214</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.arplant.47.1.185</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benning</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms of lipid transport involved in organelle biogenesis in plant cells</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Cell. Dev. Biol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.cellbio.042308.113414</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19572810?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19572810</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benning</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A role for lipid trafficking in chloroplast biogenesis</article-title><source>Prog. Lipid Res.</source><year>2008</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>381</fpage><lpage>389</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plipres.2008.04.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18440317?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18440317</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Angaman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Precursor uptake assays and metabolic analyses in isolated tomato fruit chromoplasts</article-title><source>Plant Methods</source><year>2012</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4811-8-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22243738?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22243738</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wasternack</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Jasmonates: An update on biosynthesis, signal transduction and action in plant stress response, growth and development</article-title><source>Ann. Bot.</source><year>2007</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>681</fpage><lpage>697</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aob/mcm079</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17513307?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17513307</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of a specific isoform of tomato lipoxygenase (TomloxC) involved in the generation of fatty acid-derived flavor compounds</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>2641</fpage><lpage>2651</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.104.041608</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15347800?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15347800</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balsera</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Soll</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Buchanan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Redox extends its regulatory reach to chloroplast protein import</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci.</source><year>2010</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>515</fpage><lpage>521</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2010.06.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20688558?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20688558</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yabuta</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Thylakoid membrane&#x02010;bound ascorbate peroxidase is a limiting factor of antioxidative systems under photo&#x02010;oxidative stress</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2002</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>915</fpage><lpage>925</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313X.2002.01476.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12492834?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12492834</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Production and scavenging of reactive oxygen species in chloroplasts and their functions</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>141</volume><fpage>391</fpage><lpage>396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.106.082040</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16760493?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16760493</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jinn</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Copper chaperone-dependent and -independent activation of three Copper-Zinc superoxide dismutase homologs localized in different cellular compartments in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>158</volume><fpage>737</fpage><lpage>746</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.111.190223</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22186608?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22186608</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Over-expression of ScMnSOD, a SOD gene derived from Jojoba, improve drought tolerance in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>J. Integr. Agr.</source><year>2013</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1722</fpage><lpage>1730</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2095-3119(13)60404-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McKersie</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Murnaghan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Iron-superoxide dismutase expression in transgenic alfalfa increases winter survival without a detectable increase in photosynthetic oxidative stress tolerance</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2000</year><volume>122</volume><fpage>1427</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.122.4.1427</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10759538?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10759538</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jarvis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Targeting of nucleus&#x02010;encoded proteins to chloroplasts in plants</article-title><source>New Phytol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>179</volume><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>285</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2008.02452.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19086173?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19086173</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarvis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functions of plastid protein import and the ubiquitin-proteasome system in plastid development</article-title><source>Biochim. Et. Biophys. Acta</source><year>2015</year><volume>1847</volume><fpage>939</fpage><lpage>948</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbabio.2015.02.017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Inaba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Arabidopsis Tic110 is essential for the assembly and function of the protein import machinery of plastids</article-title><source>Plant Cell.</source><year>2005</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1482</fpage><lpage>1496</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.105.030700</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15829604?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15829604</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakamoto</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protein degradation machineries in plastids</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Plant Biol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>599</fpage><lpage>621</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.arplant.57.032905.105401</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16669775?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16669775</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olinares</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>van Wijk</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Clp protease system; a central component of the chloroplast protease network</article-title><source>Biochim. Et. Biophys. Acta</source><year>2011</year><volume>1807</volume><fpage>999</fpage><lpage>1011</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbabio.2010.12.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakamoto</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New insights into the types and function of proteases in plastids</article-title><source>Int. Rev. Cell. Mol. Biol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>280</volume><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1937-6448(10)80004-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20797683?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20797683</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive comparative analysis of volatile compounds in citrus fruits of different species</article-title><source>Food Chem.</source><year>2017</year><volume>230</volume><fpage>316</fpage><lpage>326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2017.03.040</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28407917?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28407917</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Terpene down-regulation triggers defense responses in transgenic orange leading to resistance against fungal pathogens</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>164</volume><fpage>321</fpage><lpage>339</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.113.224279</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24192451?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24192451</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Nieuwenhuizen, N. J. et al., Natural variation in monoterpene synthesis in kiwifruit: transcriptional regulation of terpene synthases by NAC and EIN3-like transcription factors. <italic>Plant Physiol.</italic> 167, 1243-58 (2015).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duch&#x000ea;ne</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A grapevine (<italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> L.) deoxy-<sc>d</sc>-xylulose synthase gene colocates with a major quantitative trait loci for terpenol content</article-title><source>Theor. Appl. Genet.</source><year>2009</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>541</fpage><lpage>552</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-008-0919-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19002427?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19002427</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schumacher</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Krebs</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The V-ATPase: small cargo, large effects</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Plant Biol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>724</fpage><lpage>730</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2010.07.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20801076?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20801076</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morstadt</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chemiosmotic ATP synthesis in photosynthetically inactive chromoplasts from <italic>Narcissus pseudonarcissus</italic> L. linked to a redox pathway potentially also involved in carotene desaturation</article-title><source>Planta</source><year>2002</year><volume>215</volume><fpage>134</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00425-001-0724-y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12012250?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12012250</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brautigam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proteomic analysis of the proplastid envelope membrane provides novel insights into small molecule and protein transport across proplastid membranes</article-title><source>Mol. Plant</source><year>2009</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>1247</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/mp/ssp070</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19995728?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19995728</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simkin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Auldridge</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Klee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The tomato carotenoid cleavage dioxygenase 1 genes contribute to the formation of the flavor volatiles beta-ionone, pseudoionone, and geranylacetone</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2004</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>882</fpage><lpage>892</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2004.02263.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15584954?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15584954</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ibdah</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Functional characterization of CmCCD1, a carotenoid cleavage dioxygenase from melon</article-title><source>Phytochemistry</source><year>2006</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>1579</fpage><lpage>1589</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2006.02.009</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16563447?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16563447</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lundquist</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The functional network of the Arabidopsis plastoglobule proteome based on quantitative proteomics and genome-wide coexpression analysis</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>158</volume><fpage>1172</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.111.193144</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22274653?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22274653</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deru&#x000e8;re</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fibril assembly and carotenoid overaccumulation in chromoplasts: a model for supramolecular lipoprotein structures</article-title><source>Plant Cell.</source><year>1994</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>133</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.6.1.119</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8130642?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8130642</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Wijk</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plastoglobuli: plastid microcompartments with integrated functions in metabolism, plastid developmental transitions, and environmental adaptation</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Plant Biol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>11.1</fpage><lpage>11.37</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>