<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ACS//DTD ACS Journal DTD v1.02 20061031//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName ACSJournal-v102.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.02?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName acs2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">ACS Catal</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">ACS Catal</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">cs</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="coden">accacs</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>ACS Catalysis</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2155-5435</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American
Chemical Society</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5617326</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acscatal.7b01924</article-id><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Structural Basis of Catalysis in the Bacterial Monoterpene
Synthases Linalool Synthase and 1,8-Cineole Synthase</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath1"><name><surname>Karuppiah</surname><given-names>Vijaykumar</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath2"><name><surname>Ranaghan</surname><given-names>Kara E.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath3"><name><surname>Leferink</surname><given-names>Nicole G. H.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath4"><name><surname>Johannissen</surname><given-names>Linus O.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath5"><name><surname>Shanmugam</surname><given-names>Muralidharan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath6"><name><surname>N&#x000ed; Cheallaigh</surname><given-names>Aisling</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath7"><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>Nathan J.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath8"><name><surname>Kearsey</surname><given-names>Lewis J.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath9"><name><surname>Takano</surname><given-names>Eriko</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath10"><name><surname>Gardiner</surname><given-names>John M.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath11"><name><surname>van der Kamp</surname><given-names>Marc W.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath12"><name><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>Sam</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath13"><name><surname>Mulholland</surname><given-names>Adrian J.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath14"><name><surname>Leys</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="ath15"><name><surname>Scrutton</surname><given-names>Nigel S.</given-names></name><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="other">*</xref><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>&#x02020;</label>BBSRC/EPSRC
Manchester Synthetic Biology Research Centre for Fine and Specialty
Chemicals (SYNBIOCHEM), Manchester Institute of Biotechnology, School
of Chemistry, Faculty of Science and Engineering, <institution>University of Manchester</institution>, 131 Princess Street, Manchester M1 7DN, <country>U.K.</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>&#x02021;</label>Centre
for Computational Chemistry, School of Chemistry, <institution>University of Bristol</institution>, Cantock&#x02019;s Close, Bristol BS8 1TS, <country>U.K.</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>E-mail: <email>nigel.scrutton@manchester.ac.uk</email>; Tel.: <phone>+ 44 161 306 5152</phone>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>09</day><month>08</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>01</day><month>09</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>6268</fpage><lpage>6282</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>06</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>04</day><month>08</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2017 American Chemical Society</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><copyright-holder>American Chemical Society</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open access article published under a Creative Commons Attribution (CC-BY) <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/page/policy/authorchoice_ccby_termsofuse.html">License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the author and source are cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p content-type="toc-graphic"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="cs-2017-019242_0010" id="ab-d30e236"/></p><p>Terpenoids form the
largest and stereochemically most diverse class
of natural products, and there is considerable interest in producing
these by biocatalysis with whole cells or purified enzymes, and by
metabolic engineering. The monoterpenes are an important class of
terpenes and are industrially important as flavors and fragrances.
We report here structures for the recently discovered <italic>Streptomyces clavuligerus</italic> monoterpene synthases linalool
synthase (bLinS) and 1,8-cineole synthase (bCinS), and we show that
these are active biocatalysts for monoterpene production using biocatalysis
and metabolic engineering platforms. In metabolically engineered monoterpene-producing <italic>E. coli</italic> strains, use of bLinS leads to 300-fold higher
linalool production compared with the corresponding plant monoterpene
synthase. With bCinS, 1,8-cineole is produced with 96% purity compared
to 67% from plant species. Structures of bLinS and bCinS, and their
complexes with fluorinated substrate analogues, show that these bacterial
monoterpene synthases are similar to previously characterized sesquiterpene
synthases. Molecular dynamics simulations suggest that these monoterpene
synthases do not undergo large-scale conformational changes during
the reaction cycle, making them attractive targets for structured-based
protein engineering to expand the catalytic scope of these enzymes
toward alternative monoterpene scaffolds. Comparison of the bLinS
and bCinS structures indicates how their active sites steer reactive
carbocation intermediates to the desired acyclic linalool (bLinS)
or bicyclic 1,8-cineole (bCinS) products. The work reported here provides
the analysis of structures for this important class of monoterpene
synthase. This should now guide exploitation of the bacterial enzymes
as gateway biocatalysts for the production of other monoterpenes and
monoterpenoids.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>monoterpene synthase</kwd><kwd>monoterpenoids</kwd><kwd>sesquiterpene
synthase</kwd><kwd>terpenes</kwd><kwd>protein crystallography</kwd><kwd>molecular dynamics simulations</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>document-id-old-9</meta-name><meta-value>cs7b01924</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>document-id-new-14</meta-name><meta-value>cs-2017-019242</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>ccc-price</meta-name><meta-value/></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Terpenoids
are the most abundant and largest class (&#x0003e;75000) of
natural products. Most are commonly found in plants, and their biological
roles range from interspecies communication to intracellular signaling
and defense against predatory species.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref></sup> Their use is wide ranging as pharmaceuticals, herbicides, flavorings,
fragrances, and biofuels.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref></sup> Despite the
commercial interest in terpenoids, efforts to produce these in high
yields have been hampered by lack of availability of sufficiently
robust and high-activity terpene synthase enzymes, although efforts
to synthesize terpenoids by synthetic biology routes have gathered
pace in recent years.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref></sup></p><p>Terpenoids are synthesized from the isoprene building blocks
dimethylallyl
pyrophosphate (DMAPP) and isopentenyl pyrophosphate (IPP). Combination
of DMAPP and IPP generates pyrophosphate substrates of varying carbon
lengths, which are then utilized by terpene synthases to produce either
monoterpenes (C10), sesquiterpenes (C15), diterpenes (C20), and others.
Geranyl pyrophosphate (GPP), the substrate used by monoterpene synthases
is formed by coupling one molecule of DMAPP with IPP, while farnesyl
pyrophosphate (FPP), the substrate for sesquiterpenes, is synthesized
by coupling three individual isoprene precursors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref></sup></p><p>The class I terpene synthases share a common &#x003b1;-helical
fold
and use a cluster of three Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions to assist with substrate
ionization and release of the pyrophosphate moiety (PP<sub>i</sub>). This generates a reactive allylic carbocation and triggers a cyclization
cascade that likely involves multiple carbocation intermediates.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref></sup> In many cases, substrate and Mg<sup>2+</sup> binding lead to a closed active site conformation, which guides
substrate orientation and protects the carbocation intermediates from
premature quenching.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref></sup> The exact architecture
and mobility of the active site is thought to control the cyclization
cascade to the final carbocation intermediate with high fidelity.
The latter is usually subject to deprotonation or addition of a water
molecule, leading to formation of a single product. However, some
natural terpene synthases and engineered variant forms have been shown
to form multiple reaction products.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref></sup></p><p>To date,
available crystallographic structures for the monoterpene
cyclases/synthases (mTC/S) that accept GPP as the substrate has been
derived only for plant enzymes. Structures have been reported for
bornyl diphosphate synthase (<italic>Salvia officinalis</italic>),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref></sup> limonene synthase (<italic>Mentha spicata</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref></sup> and <italic>Citrus sinensis</italic>),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref></sup> 1,8-cineole
synthase (<italic>Salvia fruticosa</italic>),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref></sup> and &#x003b3;-terpinene synthase (<italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic>).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref></sup> Without
exception, plant mTC/S contains two domains: a C-terminal &#x003b1;-helical
catalytic domain that belongs to the class I terpenoid fold, and a
N-terminal &#x003b1;-barrel domain with unclear function and that appears
to be relictual. Though the overall sequence conservation is low,
the structure of the &#x003b1;-helical fold is highly conserved. The
active site has two conserved regions, the aspartate-rich (DDXX(X)(D,E))
motif and the NSE (NDXXSXX(R,K)(E,D)) triad, required for binding
three catalytically essential Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions. Structures of
bornyl diphosphate synthase and limonene synthases have been solved
in complex with substrate analogues. In each case, GPP-analogues bind
with their pyrophosphate moieties coordinated by the Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions and a network of residues that are proposed to assist with
catalysis.</p><p>Recent reports have shown that terpene synthases
are also widely
distributed in bacteria, but the majority of these accept FPP as substrate
and produce sesquiterpenes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref></sup> Ohnishi and co-workers
characterized two bacterial mTC/S from <italic>Streptomyces
calvuligerus</italic>, namely, 1,8-cineole synthase<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref></sup> and linalool/nerolidol synthase, which can accept
either GPP or FPP as substrate, leading to linalool or nerolidol products,
respectively.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref></sup> Heterologous expression
of these enzymes in <italic>Streptomyces avermitilis</italic> resulted in 1,8-cineole synthase (bCinS) producing 1,8-cineole and
linalool/nerolidol synthase (bLinS) producing only linalool, indicating
that bLinS is likely to function only as a mTC/S in this host.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref></sup> The sequences of both bCinS and bLinS reveal
they comprise &#x0223c;330 amino acids in a single catalytic domain
and lack the additional N-terminal &#x003b1;-barrel domain characteristic
of plant enzymes. Surprisingly, no closely related homologues of both
enzymes have been found in other bacteria.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref></sup> The bacterial mTC/S 2-methylisoborneol synthase is present in many
bacteria. It accepts 2-methyl-GPP as substrate to produce 2-methylisoborneol.
Unlike the bacterial mTC/S reported here, 2-methylisoborneol synthase
has a considerably longer amino acid sequence (&#x0223c;400&#x02013;500),
and crystal structures have revealed a N-terminal proline-rich domain
that is disordered along with a class I terpenoid fold C-terminal
domain.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref></sup></p><p>Linalool is mainly used
as a fragrance material in 60&#x02013;80%
of perfumed hygiene products. It is widely used in cosmetic products
like perfumes, lotions, soaps, and shampoos and also in noncosmetic
products like detergents and cleaning agents. Furthermore, during
the manufacturing process of Vitamin E, linalool is a vital intermediate.
As an important ingredient in a wide range of commercial products,
the worldwide use of linalool exceeds 1000 metric tonnes per annum.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26">26</xref></sup> Both <italic>R</italic> and <italic>S</italic> isomers of linalool are found in nature with <italic>R</italic>-(&#x02212;)-linalool
being the most widely distributed in plant and flower extracts. To
our knowledge, for industrial use as a fragrance, the isomeric mixture
is used. 1,8-Cineole (also called eucalyptol) is used as a flavoring
in food products, in cosmetics, and also has medicinal properties.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref></sup></p><p>This study integrates synthetic biology
with biocatalysis and analysis
of enzyme structures and mechanisms. Here we describe high-resolution
crystal structures of bLinS and bCinS from <italic>Streptomyces
calvuligerus</italic> and complexes with fluorinated substrate
analogues. These structures define the active site architectures required
to steer reactive carbocation intermediates to the desired product
outcomes. Expression of bLinS and bCinS in <italic>E. coli</italic> monoterpene-producing strains leads to improved production of linalool
and 1,8-cineole compared with plant monoterpene synthases, and the
structures help to both rationalize product outcomes and guide future
exploitation of these enzymes in monoterpene/monoterpenoid production.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Experimental
Section</title><sec id="sec2.1"><title>Expression and Purification of bCinS and bLinS</title><p>The
full-length genes coding for 1,8-Cineole synthase (bCinS; WP_003952918)
and Linalool synthase (bLinS; WP_0003957954) from <italic>Streptomyces
clavuligerus</italic> ATCC 27064 were codon optimized and synthesized
from GeneArt (Life Technologies). The genes were amplified using PCR
and subcloned into pETM11 vector digested with NcoI and XhoI using
Infusion cloning (Clontech). The final construct coded for either
1,8-Cineole synthase (bCinS) or Linalool synthase (bLinS) with a 6X-His
tag followed by a TEV protease cleavage site at the N-terminus. The
expression and purification method explained below was identical for
both the proteins. The plasmid was transformed into <italic>E. coli</italic> ArcticExpress (DE3) cells (Agilent), and
a few colonies were inoculated into 100 mL of 2X-YT media containing
40 &#x003bc;g/mL of kanamycin and 20 &#x003bc;g/mL of gentamycin and grown
for 3&#x02013;4 h at 37 <bold>&#x000b0;</bold>C. The culture was diluted
into 3 L of fresh 2X-YT media containing 40 &#x003bc;g/mL of kanamycin
and allowed to grow at 37 <bold>&#x000b0;</bold>C until the OD at 600
nm reached 0.6&#x02013;0.8. At this stage, the temperature was reduced
to 16<bold>&#x000b0;</bold>C and 0.1 mM Isopropyl &#x003b2;-D-1-thiogalactopyranoside
(IPTG) was added and incubated for 14&#x02013;18 h. The cells were
harvested by centrifugation at 6000<italic>g</italic> for 10 min,
and the pellet was resuspended in buffer A (25 mM Tris pH 8.0, 150
mM NaCl, 1 mM DTT, 4 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, and 5% (v/v) glycerol).
The cells were lysed by sonication, and the debris was removed by
centrifugation at 30&#x0202f;000<italic>g</italic> for 30 min. The
supernatant was filtered through a 0.2 &#x003bc;m filter and loaded
onto a 5 mL HisTrap column (GE Healthcare) pre-equilibrated with buffer
A. The column was washed with buffer A containing 10 mM imidazole
(pH 8.0) and increasing up to 40 mM imidazole by step gradients with
3 column volume for each concentration. Increasing the concentration
of imidazole to 200&#x02013;500 mM eluted the protein. The purified
protein was desalted using a Centripure P100 column (emp Biotech GmbH)
equilibrated with buffer A. To remove the His tag, TEV protease was
added (1:1000 (w/w)) to the protein and incubated at 4 <bold>&#x000b0;</bold>C with gentle mixing for 24 h. The TEV protease was removed by passing
the protein mixture through a 5 mL HisTrap column, and the flow through
was collected. The His-tag removed protein was concentrated and loaded
onto a Hiload Superdex (26/60) S75 column (GE Healthcare) pre-equilibrated
with buffer A. Pure fractions from the gel filtration column were
concentrated to 13&#x02013;15 mg/mL and stored at &#x02212;80 <bold>&#x000b0;</bold>C as aliquots. Samples for EPR experiments were prepared
as explained above except buffer A was lacking MgCl<sub>2</sub>.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title>Biotransformations</title><p>Biotransformation reactions (0.25
mL) were prepared using buffer A and set up in glass vials containing
2 mM GPP and 20 &#x003bc;M of bCinS or bLinS. The vials were incubated
at 25 <bold>&#x000b0;</bold>C with gentle shaking for 16 h. The vials
were cooled to 4 &#x000b0;C, and 0.25 mL of ethyl acetate containing
0.01% (v/v) <italic>sec</italic>-butyl benzene as internal standard
was added. The samples were vortexed for 2 min and then spun at 18&#x0202f;000<italic>g</italic> for 5 min. Supernatant fractions containing the ethyl
acetate layer were removed and dried over anhydrous magnesium sulfate.
Samples were analyzed by GC-MS.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><title>Monoterpenoid Production
in <italic>E. coli</italic></title><p>Both bLinS and
bCinS genes, including RBS, were amplified
from their respective pETM-11 expression vectors using primers pET_IF_Fw
(5&#x02032;-CAT CCC CAC TAC TGA GAA TC-3&#x02032;) and pET_IF_Rv (5&#x02032;-
GGT GGT GGT GCT CGA GTT A-3&#x02032;) and cloned using InFusion (Takara)
into plasmid pGPPSmTC/S15 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acscatal.7b01924/suppl_file/cs7b01924_si_001.pdf">Table S1</ext-link>), which
was PCR linearized using the primer pair Vector_IF_Fw (5&#x02032;-TAA
CTC GAG CAC CAC CAC CAC C-3&#x02032;) and Vector_IF_Rv (5&#x02032;-TCA
GTA GTG GGG ATG TCG TAA TCG-3&#x02032;) resulting in plasmids pGPPSmTC/S38
and pGPPSmTC/S39, respectively (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acscatal.7b01924/suppl_file/cs7b01924_si_001.pdf">Table S1</ext-link>). Correct insertion was confirmed by automated sequencing (Eurofins).</p><p>For monoterpenoid production, the pGPPSmTC/S plasmids were cotransformed
with pMVA into <italic>E. coli</italic> DH5&#x003b1; and
grown as described before.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref></sup> Briefly, expression
strains were inoculated in terrific broth (TB) supplemented with 0.4%
glucose in glass screw capped vials, and induced for 72 h at 30 &#x000b0;C
with 50 &#x003bc;M IPTG and 25 nM anhydro-tetracycline. A 20% <italic>n</italic>-nonane layer was added to capture the volatile terpenoids
products. After induction, the nonane overlay was collected, dried
over anhydrous MgSO<sub>4</sub>, and mixed at a 1:1 ratio with ethyl
acetate containing 0.1% (v/v) <italic>sec</italic>-butyl benzene as
internal standard.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><title>GC-MS Analysis</title><p>Samples were injected
onto an Agilent
Technologies 7890B GC equipped with an Agilent Technologies 5977A
MSD. The products were separated on a DB-WAX column (30 m &#x000d7; 0.32
mm i.d., 0.25 &#x003bc;m film thickness, Agilent Technologies). The
injector temperature was set at 240 &#x000b0;C with a split ratio of
20:1 (1 &#x003bc;L injection). The carrier gas was helium with a flow
rate of 1 mL/min and a pressure of 5.1 psi. The following oven program
was used: 50 &#x000b0;C (1 min hold), ramp to 68 &#x000b0;C at 5 &#x000b0;C/min
(2 min hold), and ramp to 230 &#x000b0;C at 25 &#x000b0;C/min (2 min hold).
The ion source temperature of the mass spectrometer (MS) was set to
230 &#x000b0;C, and spectra were recorded from <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> 50 to <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> 250. Compound
identification was carried out using authentic standards and comparison
to reference spectra in the NIST library of MS spectra and fragmentation
patterns as described previously.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><title>GC Analysis</title><p>To determine the chirality of linalool
and nerolidol produced by bLinS, samples were analyzed by gas chromatography
on an Agilent Technologies 7890A GC system equipped with an FID detector,
a 7693 autosampler, and a CP-Chirasil-DEX-CB column (25 m &#x000d7; 0.25
mm i.d., 0.25 &#x003bc;m film thickness). The biotransformation samples
and isomers of linalool and nerolidol standards were analyzed using
GC. In this method, the injector temperature was at 180 &#x000b0;C, and
1 &#x003bc;L of sample was injected split-less. The carrier gas was
helium with a flow rate of 1 mL/min and a pressure of 11.3 psi. For
nerolidol-containing samples, the program began at a temperature of
70 &#x000b0;C and then increased to 150 &#x000b0;C at 8 &#x000b0;C/min (2 min
hold). This was followed by an increase in temperature to 190 &#x000b0;C
at 10 &#x000b0;C/min (3 min hold). For linalool-containing samples, the
program began at a temperature of 70 &#x000b0;C which was then increased
to 90 &#x000b0;C at 8 &#x000b0;C/min. This was followed by an increase in
temperature to 150 &#x000b0;C at a rate of 2 &#x000b0;C/min and then to
190 &#x000b0;C at 40 &#x000b0;C/min (1 min hold). The FID detector was maintained
at a temperature of 200 &#x000b0;C with a flow of hydrogen at 30 mL/min.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.6"><title>Chemical Synthesis of Fluorinated Substrate Analogues</title><p>Unless
otherwise stated, all reactions were carried out in oven-dried
glassware. Reactions were monitored by thin-layer chromatography (TLC)
on silica gel 60 F<sub>254</sub> plates, visualized with phosphomolybdic
acid stain (10 g of phosphomolybdic acid in 100 mL of ethanol). Column
chromatography was performed on Merck silica Gel 60 (particle size
40&#x02013;63 &#x003bc;m). <sup>1</sup>H NMR, <sup>13</sup>C NMR, <sup>31</sup>P, and <sup>19</sup>F spectra were obtained using a combination
of 400 and 500 MHz spectrometers and are reported as chemical shift
on the parts per million scale. Multiplicity abbreviated (br = broad,
s = singlet, d = doublet, dd = double doublet, t = triplet, m = multiplet,
etc.) and coupling constants were obtained in Hertz. Assignments were
aided by COSY and HSQC. All mass spectrometry results are reported
as the mass to charge ratio and are reported with % abundance against
the base peak (100%).</p><sec id="sec2.6.1"><title>Synthesis of 2-Fluorogeraniol and 2-Fluoronerol</title><p>Sodium
hydride (538 mg, 60% dispersion, 13.5 mmol) was washed with petroleum
ether and suspended in THF (40 mL). The suspension was cooled to 0
&#x000b0;C, and a solution of the ethyl (diethoxyphosphoryl) fluoroacetate
(2.48 mL, 12.2 mmol) in THF (13.4 mL) was added dropwise over 10 min.
The reaction was stirred for 30 min before adding 6-methyl-5-hepten-2-one
(1.5 mL, 10.2 mmol) dropwise over 30 min. The reaction was stirred
overnight at room temperature. The reaction was cooled back to 0 &#x000b0;C
and quenched by pouring on to ice water. The product was extracted
with diethyl ether (3 &#x000d7; 30 mL), dried over MgSO<sub>4</sub> and
then reduced to dryness. The crude product was then dissolved in THF
(64 mL), cooled to 0 &#x000b0;C, and LiAlH<sub>4</sub> (541 mg, 14.3
mmol) was added. The reaction was stirred at room temperature for
3 h then quenched with the addition of saturated aqueous NH<sub>4</sub>Cl. The solution was extracted with diethyl ether (3 &#x000d7; 30 mL)
and the subsequent combined organic phases were washed with brine
(30 mL). The product was purified by column chromatography (hexane/diethyl
ether, 95/5, v/v) to give 2-fluorogeraniol (783 mg, 41%) and 2-fluoronerol
(856 mg, 45%) with a total yield of 86%<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref></sup> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acscatal.7b01924/suppl_file/cs7b01924_si_001.pdf">Scheme S1</ext-link>). <bold>2-fluorogeraniol</bold>: <sup>1</sup>H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>) &#x003b4; 5.17&#x02013;5.05
(m, 1H, H7), 4.24 (dd, <italic>J</italic> = 22.3, 3.2 Hz, 2H, H1),
2.10 (m, 4H, H5, H6), 1.68 (s, 3H, H4), 1.67 (d, <italic>J</italic> = 2.9 Hz, 3H, H9/10), 1.61 (s, 3H, H9/10). <sup>13</sup>C NMR (101
MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>) &#x003b4; 132.2, 123.6, 116.1 (d, <italic>J</italic> = 16.2 Hz), 58.2 (d, <italic>J</italic> = 29.3 Hz), 29.8 (d, <italic>J</italic> = 7.07 Hz), 25.9 (d, <italic>J</italic> = 4.0 Hz), 25.7,
17.6, 15.4 (d, <italic>J</italic> = 6.01 Hz). <sup>19</sup>F NMR (471
MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>) &#x003b4; &#x02212;121.3 (t, <italic>J</italic> = 22.4 Hz) (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acscatal.7b01924/suppl_file/cs7b01924_si_001.pdf">Figure S1a&#x02013;e</ext-link>). <bold>2-fluoronerol:</bold><sup>1</sup>H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>) &#x003b4; 5.16&#x02013;5.02 (m, 1H, H7), 4.19 (dd, <italic>J</italic> = 22.9, 5.3 Hz, 2H, H1), 2.16&#x02013;2.00 (m, 4H, H5, H6), 1.70
(s, 3H, H4), 1.60 (s, 3H, H9/10), 1.57 (s, 3H, H9/10). <sup>13</sup>C NMR (101 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>) &#x003b4; 133.3, 123.5, 115.9 (d, <italic>J</italic> = 14.1 Hz), 58.0 (d, <italic>J</italic> = 29.2 Hz), 31.9
(d, <italic>J</italic> = 5.1 Hz), 26.6 (d, <italic>J</italic> = 5.1
Hz), 25.8, 17.9, 13.7 (d, <italic>J</italic> = 9.1 Hz). <sup>19</sup>F NMR (471 MHz, CDCl<sub>3</sub>) &#x003b4; &#x02013; 119.4 (t, <italic>J</italic> = 22.6 Hz) (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acscatal.7b01924/suppl_file/cs7b01924_si_001.pdf">Figure S2a&#x02013;e</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.6.2"><title>Synthesis of 2-Fluorogeranyl Pyrophosphate (FGPP) and 2-Fluoroneryl
Pyrophosphate (FNPP)</title><p>Acetonitrile (60 mL) was added to 2-fluorogeraniol
or 2-fluoronerol (400 mg, 2.3 mmol). To this, trichloroacetonitrile
(2 mL) was added followed by H<sub>3</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>(Et<sub>3</sub>N)<sub>2</sub> salt (2.1 g). The reaction was stirred overnight.
It was then poured on to diethyl ether (50 mL) and washed with concentrated
aqueous ammonia (3 &#x000d7; 100 mL). The ammonia washes were combined
and washed once with diethyl ether (50 mL). The aqueous phase was
reduced to dryness. The crude product was loaded on to a silica gel
column, and the starting material was recovered using petroleum ether/diethyl
ether (9/1, v/v). The eluent system was then switched to propanol/concentrated
aqueous ammonia/water (7/2/1, v/v/v) to isolate mono and pyrophosphate
derivatives (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acscatal.7b01924/suppl_file/cs7b01924_si_001.pdf">Scheme S1</ext-link>). When 2-fluorogeraniol
was used, 2-fluorogeranyl monophosphate (93 mg, 0.37 mmol, 16%) and
2-fluorogeranyl pyrophosphate (74 mg, 0.2 mmol, 10%) were obtained.
When 2-fluoronerol was used, 2-fluoroneryl monophosphate (117 mg,
0.47 mmol, 20%) and 2-fluoro neryl pyrophosphate (200 mg, 0.54 mmol,
27%) were obtained. <bold>2-fluorogeraniol pyrophosphate</bold>: <sup>1</sup>H NMR (500 MHz, D<sub>2</sub>O) &#x003b4; 5.29&#x02013;5.15 (m,
1H, H7), 4.59 (dd, <italic>J</italic> = 23.6, 6.2 Hz, 2H, H1), 2.22&#x02013;2.09
(m, 4H, H5, H6), 1.72 (d, <italic>J</italic> = 2.8 Hz, 3H, H4), 1.69
(s, 3H, H9/10), 1.62 (s, 3H, H9/10). <sup>13</sup>C NMR (126 MHz,
D<sub>2</sub>O) &#x003b4; 133.9 (s), 123.7 (s), 119.5 (d, <italic>J</italic> = 15.0 Hz), 60.9 (dd, <italic>J</italic> = 31.6, 5.0 Hz), 29.1 (d, <italic>J</italic> = 6.4 Hz), 25.1 (s), 24.8 (s), 16.9 (s), 14.6 (d, <italic>J</italic> = 4.9 Hz). <sup>31</sup>P NMR (162 MHz, D<sub>2</sub>O)
&#x003b4; &#x02013; 8.37 (d, <italic>J</italic> = 21.5 Hz), &#x02013;
10.95 (d, <italic>J</italic> = 21.6 Hz). <sup>19</sup>F NMR (471 MHz,
D<sub>2</sub>O) &#x003b4; &#x02212;120.44 (t, <italic>J</italic> = 23.6
Hz). HRMS ESI C<sub>10</sub>H<sub>18</sub>FO<sub>7</sub>P<sub>2</sub> [M&#x02013;H]<sup>&#x02212;</sup> calculated: 331.0512, found: 331.0517
(<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acscatal.7b01924/suppl_file/cs7b01924_si_001.pdf">Figure S3a&#x02013;g</ext-link>). Data was found to
be in accordance with the literature.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29">29</xref></sup><bold>2-fluoronerol
pyrophosphate</bold>: <sup>1</sup>H NMR (400 MHz, D<sub>2</sub>O)
&#x003b4; 5.14&#x02013;5.06 (m, 1H, H7), 4.50 (dd, <italic>J</italic> = 23.6, 6.1 Hz, 2H, H1), 2.07 (br s, 4H, H5, H6), 1.62 (s, 6H, H4,
H9/10), 1.54 (s, 3H, H9/10). <sup>13</sup>C NMR (126 MHz, D<sub>2</sub>O) &#x003b4; 134.3 (s), 123.3 (s), 119.1 (d, <italic>J</italic> = 13.2
Hz), 60.4 (dd, <italic>J</italic> = 31.0, 4.3 Hz), 30.8 (d, <italic>J</italic> = 4.6 Hz), 25.7 (d, <italic>J</italic> = 2.7 Hz), 24.8
(s), 16.9 (s), 12.8 (d, <italic>J</italic> = 8.6 Hz) <sup>31</sup>P NMR (162 MHz, D<sub>2</sub>O) &#x003b4; &#x02013; 7.64 (d, <italic>J</italic> = 21.4 Hz), &#x02013; 10.93 (d, <italic>J</italic> = 20.9
Hz) <sup>19</sup>F NMR (471 MHz, D<sub>2</sub>O) &#x003b4; &#x02013;
119.13 (t, <italic>J</italic> = 23.1 Hz). HRMS ESI C<sub>10</sub>H<sub>18</sub>FO<sub>7</sub>P<sub>2</sub> [M&#x02013;H]<sup>&#x02212;</sup> calculated: 331.0512, found: 331.0517 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acscatal.7b01924/suppl_file/cs7b01924_si_001.pdf">Figure S4a&#x02013;h</ext-link>). Data was found to be in accordance with the
literature.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29">29</xref></sup></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2.7"><title>Crystallization of bCinS
and bLinS</title><p>Crystallization
trials containing 200 nl of protein and 200 nl of precipitant solution
were set up in 3-well swissci plates using a mosquito robot (TTP Labtech).
Five commercial screens, namely, Morpheus I and II, JCSG+, PACT premier
and SG1 (Molecular Dimensions Ltd.) were used in initial trails. For
both enzymes, three distinct samples were screened: the <italic>apo</italic>-enzyme, the enzyme in the presence of 2 mM FGPP, and the enzyme
in the presence of 2 mM FNPP. The bCinS-FNPP crystallized in Morpheus
II A4 condition (90 mM of LiNaK (0.3 M lithium sulfate, 0.3 M sodium
sulfate, 0.3 M potassium sulfate), 0.1 M of buffer system 4 (1 M MOPSO,
1 M Bis-Tris) pH 6.5 and 50% precipitant mix 8 (10% PEG 20000, 50%
trimethylpropane, 2% NDSB 195)). The bLinS-FGPP crystallized in Morpheus
D7 condition (0.12 M Alcohols (0.2 M 1,6-hexanediol, 0.2 M 1-nutanol,
0.2 M 1,2-propanediol, 0.2 M 2-propanol, 0.2 M 1,4-butanediol, 0.2
M 1,3-propanediol), 0.1 M Buffer System 2 (1.0 M sodium HEPES, MOPS
(acid)) pH 7.5 and 50% v/v precipitant Mix 3 (40% v/v glycerol, 20%
w/v PEG 4000)). The <italic>apo</italic>-LinS crystallized in SG1
E2 condition (25% w/v PEG3350). Although <italic>apo</italic>-bCinS
crystallized, optimization of growth conditions failed to produce
single crystals of sufficient size for further study. In an attempt
to obtain the bCinS-FGPP structure, bCinS-FNPP crystals were soaked
overnight in the presence of 2 mM FGPP prior to cryo-cooling. The <italic>apo</italic>-bLinS crystals were cryo-protected by soaking in mother
liquor supplemented with 20% glycerol. For all FGPP and FNPP complexes,
the ligands were included in the cryo-solution.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.8"><title>Structure Solution</title><p>All data were collected at Diamond
Light Source (DLS). Diffraction images were integrated and scaled
by xia2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">30</xref></sup> automated data processing pipeline,
using XDS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31">31</xref></sup> and XSCALE. Crystals of bCinS
contained two molecules in the asymmetrical unit and belonged to P1
space group. Crystals of bLinS belonged to the tetragonal system (spacegroup <italic>I</italic>4) and also contained two molecules in asymmetrical unit.
The bLinS structures (<italic>apo</italic>-bLinS and bLinS-FGPP) were
solved by molecular replacement using the Pentalenene synthase structure
(PDB: 1PS1(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref32">32</xref>)) as the search model in Phaser.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref33">33</xref></sup> The bCinS-FNPP structure was solved by model replacement
using the <italic>apo</italic>-bLinS structure as the search model.
The <italic>apo</italic>-bLinS, bLinS-FGPP, bCinS-FNPP and bCinS-FNPP/FGPP
models were built using Autobuild in Phenix.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref34">34</xref></sup> The structures were completed using iterative rounds of manual model
building in coot<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref35">35</xref></sup> and refinement in phenix.refine.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref36">36</xref></sup> The structures were analyzed using PDB_REDO<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref37">37</xref></sup> and validated using molprobity tools.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref38">38</xref></sup> The refinement statistics are provided in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">1</xref></xref>. The atomic coordinates
and structure factors have been deposited in the Protein Data Bank
with accession codes 5NX4, 5NX5, 5NX6 and 5NX7.</p><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>X-ray Data Collection and Refinement
Statistics</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="0"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th style="border:none;" align="center">&#x000a0;</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">bLinS (apo)</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">bLinS-FGPP</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">bCinS-FNPP</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">bCinS-FNPP/FGPP</th></tr><tr><th style="border:none;" align="center">data collection</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">&#x000a0;</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">&#x000a0;</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">&#x000a0;</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">&#x000a0;</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">space group</td><td style="border:none;" align="left"><italic>I</italic>4</td><td style="border:none;" align="left"><italic>I</italic>4</td><td style="border:none;" align="left"><italic>P</italic>1</td><td style="border:none;" align="left"><italic>P</italic>1</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">unit cell dimensions</td><td style="border:none;" align="left"><italic>a</italic> = <italic>b</italic> = 140.15 &#x000c5;, <italic>c</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;87.18</td><td style="border:none;" align="left"><italic>a</italic> = <italic>b</italic> = 139.37 &#x000c5;, <italic>c</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;86.06</td><td style="border:none;" align="left"><italic>a</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;60.81 &#x000c5;, <italic>b</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;60.83 &#x000c5;,</td><td style="border:none;" align="left"><italic>a</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;60.75 &#x000c5;, <italic>b</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;60.83 &#x000c5;,</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">&#x000c5;; &#x003b1; = &#x003b2;
= &#x003b3; = 90&#x000b0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">&#x000c5;; &#x003b1; = &#x003b2;
= &#x003b3; = 90&#x000b0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="left"><italic>c</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;64.10 &#x000c5;;
&#x003b1; = 90.04&#x000b0;,</td><td style="border:none;" align="left"><italic>c</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;64.26 &#x000c5;;
&#x003b1; = 92.67&#x000b0;,</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">&#x003b2;&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;92.89&#x000b0;,&#x000a0;&#x003b3;&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;101.98&#x000b0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">&#x003b2;&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;89.98&#x000b0;,&#x000a0;&#x003b3;&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;101.77&#x000b0;</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">X-ray source</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">DLS I04-1</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">DLS I04</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">DLS I04</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">DLS I04</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">wavelength (&#x000c5;)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">0.92819</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">0.99</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">0.99</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">0.9795</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">resolution range
(&#x000c5;)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">50.90&#x02013;2.38 (2.42&#x02013;2.38)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">36.62&#x02013;1.82 (1.85&#x02013;1.82)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">32.27&#x02013;1.63 (1.66&#x02013;1.63)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">64.19&#x02013;1.51 (1.53&#x02013;1.51)</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">multiplicity</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">4.5&#x000a0;(3.9)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">6.8&#x000a0;(6.9)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">1.8&#x000a0;(1.8)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">2&#x000a0;(2)</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left"><italic>I</italic>/&#x003c3; <italic>I</italic></td><td style="border:none;" align="left">14.6&#x000a0;(1.7)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">18.2&#x000a0;(1.4)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">6.7&#x000a0;(1.2)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">10&#x000a0;(2.1)</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">completeness (%)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">99.7&#x000a0;(99.7)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">100&#x000a0;(100)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">96&#x000a0;(94.6)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">95.9&#x000a0;(93.4)</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left"><italic>R</italic><sub>merge</sub></td><td style="border:none;" align="left">0.082&#x000a0;(0.766)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">0.057&#x000a0;(1.371)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">0.09&#x000a0;(0.639)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">0.035&#x000a0;(0.315)</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left"><italic>R</italic><sub>meas</sub></td><td style="border:none;" align="left">0.093&#x000a0;(0.889)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">0.062&#x000a0;(1.483)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">0.127&#x000a0;(0.904)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">0.047&#x000a0;(0.428)</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left"><italic>R</italic><sub>pim</sub></td><td style="border:none;" align="left">0.043&#x000a0;(0.44)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">0.024&#x000a0;(0.563)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">0.09&#x000a0;(0.639)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">0.032&#x000a0;(0.287)</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left"><italic>CC</italic><sub>1/2</sub></td><td style="border:none;" align="left">0.998&#x000a0;(0.576)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">0.999&#x000a0;(0.51)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">0.987&#x000a0;(0.479)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">0.999&#x000a0;(0.824)</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">total observations</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">152818&#x000a0;(6641)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">502331&#x000a0;(25222)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">193529&#x000a0;(9539)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">270436&#x000a0;(13510)</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">total
unique</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">33849&#x000a0;(1697)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">73739&#x000a0;(3654)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">107492&#x000a0;(5258)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">136704&#x000a0;(6737)</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="0"><colgroup><col/><col/><col/><col/><col/></colgroup><thead><tr><th style="border:none;" align="center">refinement</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">&#x000a0;</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">&#x000a0;</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">&#x000a0;</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">&#x000a0;</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td style="border:none;">R-work</td><td style="border:none;">0.1850</td><td style="border:none;">0.1667</td><td style="border:none;">0.1662</td><td style="border:none;">0.1492</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;">R-free</td><td style="border:none;">0.2240</td><td style="border:none;">0.1950</td><td style="border:none;">0.20</td><td style="border:none;">0.1830</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;">RMS (bonds)</td><td style="border:none;">0.002</td><td style="border:none;">0.009</td><td style="border:none;">0.013</td><td style="border:none;">0.008</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;">RMS (angles)</td><td style="border:none;">0.45</td><td style="border:none;">0.94</td><td style="border:none;">1.15</td><td style="border:none;">0.96</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;">average B-factor (&#x000c5;<sup>2</sup>)</td><td style="border:none;">52.5</td><td style="border:none;">42.8</td><td style="border:none;">24.8</td><td style="border:none;">27.8</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="0"><colgroup><col/><col/><col/><col/><col/></colgroup><thead><tr><th style="border:none;" align="center">Ramachandran
plot</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">&#x000a0;</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">&#x000a0;</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">&#x000a0;</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">&#x000a0;</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td style="border:none;">favored</td><td style="border:none;">98.94</td><td style="border:none;">99.29</td><td style="border:none;">98.98</td><td style="border:none;">98.45</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;">allowed</td><td style="border:none;">1.06</td><td style="border:none;">0.71</td><td style="border:none;">1.02</td><td style="border:none;">1.35</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;">outliers</td><td style="border:none;">0</td><td style="border:none;">0</td><td style="border:none;">0</td><td style="border:none;">0.2</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;">&#x000a0;</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec2.9"><title>EPR Spectroscopy</title><p>Electron paramagnetic
resonance (EPR)
measurements were carried out using a Bruker ELEXSYS-500 X-band EPR
spectrometer operating in both cw and pulsed modes, equipped with
an Oxford variable-temperature unit and ESR900 cryostat with Super
High-Q resonator. All EPR samples were prepared in the quartz capillary
tubes (outer diameter; 4.0 mm, inner diameter 3.0 mm) and frozen in
liquid N<sub>2</sub>. The X-band EPR tubes were then transferred into
the EPR probe head, which was precooled to 20 K. The low-temperature
EPR spectra were measured at 20 K as a frozen solution. A microwave
power of 36 dB (50 mW) and modulation of 5 G appear to be optimal
for recording the EPR spectrum of the bLinS and bCinS protein samples
prepared using various ratios of protein to Mn<sup>2+</sup> concentration
in the presence of 10-fold excess of FGPP. The concentrations of the
proteins (bLinS and bCinS) and FGPP in all the samples were 0.400
mM and 1.5 mM, respectively, whereas the ratio to the Mn<sup>2+</sup> concentration was systematically varied from 1 to 6. The low-temperature
EPR spectra were acquired using the following conditions: sweep time
of 84 s, microwave power of 50 mW, time constant of 41 ms, and modulation
amplitude of 5 G. All the spectra have been normalized to account
for the different numbers of scans accumulated for each sample. The
data analysis was performed using EasySpin toolbox for the Matlab
program package.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.10"><title>Simulations of <italic>Apo</italic>-bCinS
and bLinS</title><p>Molecular dynamics (MD) simulations of <italic>apo</italic>-bCinS
and bLinS were carried out in AMBER14 using the CHARMM27 force field.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref40">40</xref></sup> The protonation states of titratable residues were estimated using
the PDB 2PQR server with proPKA, and the enzymes were solvated using a box of
minimum 12 &#x000c5; around the protein with counterions added. Two sets
of isothermal&#x02013;isobaric ensemble (NPT) MD simulations were performed
at 298 K for each enzyme, using different starting velocities, following
the system setup. Langevin dynamics was used for temperature control
(collision frequency of 5 ps<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> for equilibration
and 2 ps<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> for production), and pressure was controlled
by coupling to an external bath (AMBER14 default settings) for NPT
conditions. The system setup consisted of: (i) energy minimization
of the solvent; (ii) 50 ps of (NPT) solvent equilibration; (iii) energy
minimization of the entire system with positional restraints of 5
kcal mol<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> &#x000c5;<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> applied to
all C&#x003b1; atoms; (iv) canonical ensemble (NVT) thermalisation to
298 K over 20 ps with positional restraints of 5 kcal mol<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> &#x000c5;<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> on C&#x003b1; atoms; (v) 40 ps of NPT equilibration
with decreasing restraints on the C&#x003b1; atoms; (vi) 1 ns unconstrained
NPT equilibration; (vii) 100 ns production simulation. Average linkage
hierarchical clustering (after alignment of structures based on C&#x003b1;
positions) was used to identify representative structures to illustrate
protein conformational sampling during the simulations.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.11"><title>Simulations
of the Ternary Complexes of bCinS with Three Mg<sup>2+</sup> Ions
and GPP or NPP</title><p>The protonation states of titratable
residues were estimated using PropKA3.1,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref42">42</xref></sup> and the enzyme was solvated using a box of TIP3P<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref43">43</xref></sup> water molecules (with a minimum buffer or 13 &#x000c5; around
the protein) using the solvate plugin of the VMD package.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref44">44</xref></sup> Counterions were added to neutralize the system
using autoionize plugin of VMD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref44">44</xref></sup> The CHARMM27
forcefield<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref39">39</xref></sup> was used to describe the protein
with parameters for GPP and NPP that were adapted from those used
for FPP in the work of van der Kamp et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref45">45</xref></sup> The position of the GPP or NPP substrate was based on the position
of the fluorinated analogue resolved in the crystal structure. Due
to the minimal differences in the structure of the inhibitor and substrate
(F vs H), the position in the crystal structure was considered a suitable
starting point for the simulations. It has been suggested that many
terpene cyclase/synthase structures contain substrates bound in unreactive
conformations;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref46">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref47">47</xref></sup> however, structures containing
the larger and more flexible FPP, the building block for sesquiterpenes
are more prevalent than monoterpenes. The parameter set developed
by Allner et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref48">48</xref></sup> was used to describe
the three Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions. The setup of the model consisted of
the following: (i) minimization of the positions of the hydrogen atoms
(all heavy atoms fixed); (ii) minimization of the solvent (with all
protein heavy atoms fixed); (iii) energy minimization of the entire
system with positional restraints of 5 kcal mol<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> &#x000c5;<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> applied to all C&#x003b1; atoms; (iv) canonical
ensemble (NVT) thermalisation to 300 K over 20 ps with positional
restraints of 5 kcal mol<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> &#x000c5;<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> on C&#x003b1; atoms; (v) thermal equilibration at 300 K for 100 ps
with positional restraints of 5 kcal mol<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> &#x000c5;<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> on C&#x003b1; atoms; (vi) 140 ps of NPT equilibration
with decreasing restraints on the C&#x003b1; atoms; (vi) 100 ns production
simulation. Two sets of isothermal&#x02013;isobaric ensemble (NPT)
MD simulations were performed at 300 K for each enzyme, repeating
steps (iv)&#x02013;(vi) to obtain two models with different initial
conditions. MD simulations were carried out on GPUs using the PMEMD
code<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref49">49</xref></sup> of AMBER16.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref50">50</xref></sup> Langevin dynamics was used for temperature control (collision frequency
of 5 ps<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> for equilibration and 2 ps<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> for production), and pressure was controlled by coupling to an external
bath (AMBER16 default settings) for NPT conditions. Average linkage
hierarchical clustering (after alignment of structures based on positions
of active site residues) was carried out using the CPPTRAJ utility
of AMBERTOOLS 16<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref50">50</xref></sup> to identify representative
structures of the ternary complex over the course of the simulations.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.12"><title>Simulations of the Ternary Complexes of bLinS with Three Mg<sup>2+</sup> Ions and GPP or FPP</title><p>The models of bLinS were built
from the coordinates of chain B of the protein, with positions of
the Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions determined on the basis of alignment with
the structures of sesquiterpene synthases aristocholene synthase (ATAS,
PDB 4KUX<sup>51</sup>) and Epi-isozizaene synthase (PDB 3KB9(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref52">52</xref>)). GPP was built into the model on the basis of the position
of the phosphate ion observed in the bLinS chain B structure and using
the geometry of FGPP observed in the bCinS-FGPP structure. The FPP
model was generated on the basis of the position of farnesyl thiolodiphosphate
FSPP in ATAS.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref51">51</xref></sup> Some positional restraints
were then applied to the Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions and coordinating protein
residues in the NSD and DDXXD motifs in order to form the correct
binding pattern. The Mg<sup>2+</sup> to oxygen atom distance (for
Asn218, Ser222, Asp226 and Asp79) was restrained to a value of 2.3
&#x000c5; with a force constant <italic>k</italic> = 20 kcal mol<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> &#x000c5;<sup>&#x02013;2</sup>. The same procedure as
used for the bCinS models was then followed to perform the MD simulations
of bLinS with GPP and FPP.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec id="sec3.1"><title>Linalool
and 1,8-Cineole Production in <italic>E. coli</italic></title><p>Biotransformation reactions showed that purified bLinS
and bCinS produced linalool and 1,8-cineole, respectively, when supplied
with GPP. No byproducts were observed when analyzed by GC-MS (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref></xref>). To investigate
the suitability of both enzymes for monoterpenoid production in engineered <italic>E. coli</italic> strains, bLinS and bCinS were inserted in
an <italic>E. coli</italic> &#x0201c;plug-and-play&#x0201d;
monoterpenoid production platform, which consists of two gene modules.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref></sup> The first module (pMVA) contains a hybrid mevalonate
(MVA) pathway under regulation of IPTG-inducible promoters,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref53">53</xref></sup> and the second (plasmid series pGPPSmTC/S, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acscatal.7b01924/suppl_file/cs7b01924_si_001.pdf">Table S1</ext-link>) comprises a refactored, N-terminally
truncated geranyl diphosphate synthase (GPPS) gene from <italic>Abies grandis</italic> (AgtrGPPS2) followed by an mTC/S gene
(in this case bLinS or bCinS, respectively) under control of a tetracycline-inducible
promoter. Strains containing both the pMVA and pGPPS-bLinS or pGPPS-bCinS
plasmids, respectively, were grown in a two-phase shake flask system
using glucose as the feedstock and <italic>n</italic>-nonane as an
organic phase to facilitate product capture. Products accumulated
in the organic phase were identified and quantified by GC-MS analysis.</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>GC-MS
analysis of bCinS and bLinS. (A) bCinS product profile when
inserted in an engineered <italic>E. coli</italic> strain
capable of overproducing GPP. (B) bCinS conversion of GPP (2 mM) <italic>in vitro</italic>. (C) bCinS conversion of NPP (2 mM) <italic>in
vitro</italic>. D) 1,8-cineole standard (0.1 mg/mL). E) bLinS product
profile when inserted in an engineered <italic>E. coli</italic> strain capable of overproducing GPP. F) bLinS conversion of GPP
(2 mM) <italic>in vitro</italic>. G) <italic>R-(</italic>&#x02212;)-linalool
standard (0.1 mg/mL). H) <italic>cis</italic>- and <italic>trans</italic>-nerolidol standards (0.1 mg/mL). IS = internal standard (<italic>sec</italic>-butyl benzene).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="cs-2017-019242_0001" id="gr1" position="float"/></fig><p>Product profiles and titers obtained with bLinS and bCinS
were
compared with previously obtained profiles using mTC/S enzymes obtained
from plants (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref></xref>), i.e. LinS from <italic>Artemisia annua</italic> (RLinS_Aa)
and CinS from <italic>Salvia fruticosa</italic> (CinS_Sf), <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (CinS_At), and <italic>Citrus unshiu</italic> (CinS_Cu).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref></sup> Both bacterial enzymes outperformed the plant enzymes: bLinS produced
about 300-fold more linalool than RLinS_Aa (363.3 &#x000b1; 57.9 versus
1.3 mg L<sub>org</sub><sup>&#x02013;1</sup>). With bCinS, 1,8-cineole
was produced in considerably purer form compared to that produced
using the plant enzymes. Strains containing bCinS produced 116.8 &#x000b1;
36.4 mg L<sub>org</sub><sup>&#x02013;1</sup> (96% pure); this compares
to 118.2 mg L<sub>org</sub><sup>&#x02013;1</sup> (67% pure) for CinS_Sf,
46.6 mg L<sub>org</sub><sup>&#x02013;1</sup> (42% pure) for CinS_At,
and 18.2 (63% pure) for CinS_Cu for the strains containing the corresponding
plant CinS enzymes.</p><p>As well as GPP formation catalyzed by the
heterologous GPPS, the
engineered <italic>E. coli</italic> strains also produce
the sesquiterpene precursor farnesyl diphosphate (FPP) from native
host encoded enzymes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref54">54</xref></sup> Strains containing
bLinS were able to convert FPP to nerolidol (159.1 &#x000b1; 7.3 mg L<sub>org</sub><sup>&#x02013;1</sup>), indicating that bLinS acts as both
a monoterpene and sesquiterpene synthase. We demonstrated that bLinS
makes <italic>R</italic>-(&#x02212;)-linalool and <italic>trans</italic>-nerolidol with GPP and FPP, respectively (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acscatal.7b01924/suppl_file/cs7b01924_si_001.pdf">Figure S5a&#x02013;f</ext-link>). In contrast, no sesquiterpene products were
detected with <italic>E. coli</italic> strains containing
bCinS indicating it is restricted to the production of monoterpene
products. With each of the strains, geraniol and farnesol (and their
derivatives) were detected in organic overlays of cultures alongside
the expected terpenoids. An unidentified endogenous <italic>E. coli</italic> pathway has previously been shown to convert
both GPP and FPP into geraniol and farnesol respectively,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref></sup> which are subsequently converted into oxidative
byproducts by endogenous dehydrogenation and isomerization reactions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref55">55</xref></sup> In particular, <italic>E. coli</italic> PhoA phosphatase was implicated in converting GPP to geraniol<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref56">56</xref></sup> and two integral membrane phosphatases (PgpB
and YbjG) were shown to convert FPP to farnesol.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref57">57</xref></sup></p><p>The reported product profiles and yields suggest
that bacterial
monoterpene synthases are better suited compared to the corresponding
plant enzymes for monoterpenoid production using engineered <italic>E. coli</italic> strains. Armed with this information we set
out to determine the structures of bLinS and bCinS, in both ligand-free
and complexed with fluorinated substrate analogues, with the objective
of informing on mechanism, and guiding future engineering/exploitation
in biocatalysis and metabolic engineering programmes.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><title>Structure of
the bCinS FNPP Complex</title><p>Crystals of bCinS
were obtained when cocrystallized with 2-fluoro neryl pyrophosphate
(FNPP), a fluorinated GPP isomer. Unfortunately, bCinS crystallized
poorly when not bound to a substrate analogue. This suggests a conformational
change occurs between an open (<italic>apo</italic>)-form and a closed
(substrate-inhibitor bound) complex similar to that seen with other
terpene cyclases.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref45">45</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref58">58</xref></sup> Previous studies have indicated
that some terpene cyclases/synthases can also accept neryl pyrophosphate
(NPP) as substrate.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref></sup> In the case of bCinS,
incubation with NPP also leads to 1,8 cineole (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref></xref>). As observed with other terpene synthases,
fluorination of the substrate blocks the key ionization step, blocking
diphosphate release and formation of the geranyl/neryl cation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref></sup> The bCinS-FNPP structure was determined to 1.63
&#x000c5; and reveals the enzyme is a dimer of a typical class I terpenoid
&#x003b1;-helical domain, with the active sites oriented in an antiparallel
fashion (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>a).
Analysis of the bCinS dimer revealed a total buried surface area of
4114 &#x000c5;<sup>2</sup>, indicating the oligomeric state is biologically
relevant (using PISA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref59">59</xref></sup>). Both monomers
are similar in structure (rmsd of 0.25 &#x000c5; over 315 C&#x003b1; atoms),
with residues that constitute one of the loops close to the active
site disordered. The bound FNPP is clearly defined in the electron
density of both active sites, with no significant differences in conformation
between both monomers (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>b). The pyrophosphate moiety of FNPP makes extensive interactions
with residues in the active site, in addition to coordination by two
Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions and interactions with several water molecules.
While one Mg<sup>2+</sup> is bound by the conserved NSE motif (Mg<sup>2+</sup> B), the other is bound by the aspartate rich motif (Mg<sup>2+</sup> A). No clear density could be observed that corresponds
to the location of the third metal ion (Mg<sup>2+</sup> C).</p><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Structure of
bCinS in complex with FNPP. (A) Cartoon representation
of the bCinS dimer with the solvent accessible surface shown color
coded per monomer. (B) Stereoview of the FNPP-Mg<sup>2+</sup> ion
binding site. Key polar interactions are shown by dotted lines. The
electron density indicates multiple positions of the diphosphate moiety
as well as several Mg<sup>2+</sup> binding residues. (C) Stereoview
of the FNPP hydrophobic binding pocket. A single water molecule is
present, located close to the C6 atom.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="cs-2017-019242_0002" id="gr2" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><title>EPR Reveals Binding of 3 Mn<sup>2+</sup> Ions to bCinS</title><p>To
ascertain whether bCinS binds to two or three Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions,
we employed EPR spectroscopy by titrating bCinS purified in the absence
of MgCl<sub>2</sub> with Mn<sup>2+</sup>. The Mn<sup>2+</sup> ion
serves as a valuable probe of the Mg<sup>2+</sup> ion binding sites.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref60">60</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref62">62</xref></sup> This substitution allowed application of cw-EPR spectroscopy to
investigate the number of potential metal binding sites in bCinS.
Comparison of the EPR spectra of the aqueous MnCl<sub>2</sub> and
bCinS with and without the inhibitor FGPP indicates that the spectrum
of the 1:1 bCinS-FGPP:Mn<sup>2+</sup> sample contains a highly resolved
multiplet structure (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref></xref>a; red spectrum). This multiplet structure is the<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref55">55</xref></sup>Mn hyperfine coupling which is due to the interaction
of electron spin (S = 5/2) of the Mn<sup>2+</sup> ion with the nuclear
spin (I = 5/2) of <sup>55</sup> Mn nucleus. It is a characteristic
signature of binding of FGPP to Mn<sup>2+</sup> ion, which is centered
at <italic>g</italic> &#x0223c; 2.0. This multiplet feature increases
in intensity only until the ratio of Mn<sup>2+</sup> ion concentration
relative to bCinS-FGPP reaches 3. However, where the relative concentration
of Mn<sup>2+</sup> ion is greater than 3, the EPR spectra show overall
increase in intensity due to the contribution from free/unbound Mn<sup>2+</sup> ion. The EPR spectrum of the 1:6 bCinS-FGPP:Mn<sup>2+</sup> sample (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref></xref>a;
magenta spectrum) can be simulated (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref></xref>a; cyan spectrum) by 1:1 addition of the
EPR spectra of 1:3 bCinS-FGPP:Mn<sup>2+</sup> sample with (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref></xref>a; blue spectrum)
the 1:3 bCinS:Mn<sup>2+</sup> (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref></xref>a; black spectrum). This indicates that there are 3
potential metal binding sites available in bCinS. Detailed analysis
and assignment of the various transitions in the EPR spectra (Figures
S6a,b and S7a,b) are provided in the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acscatal.7b01924/suppl_file/cs7b01924_si_001.pdf">Supporting Information</ext-link>.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>EPR confirms binding of 3 Mn<sup>2+</sup> in solution.
cw-EPR spectra
of &#x02018;Mn<sup>2+</sup>&#x02019; substituted bCinS (A) and bLinS
(B) protein samples with varying equivalents of Mn<sup>2+</sup> concentration
with or without FGPP measured as a frozen solution along with standard
MnCl<sub>2</sub>. The plot shows the multiplet EPR signal arise from
the Mn<sup>2+</sup> ion around the <italic>g</italic> = 2 region (from
250 to 400 mT).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="cs-2017-019242_0003" id="gr3" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><title>Structure of the bCinS-FGPP
Complex and bCinS Mechanism</title><p>Soaking of the bCinS-FNPP crystals
with FGPP led to the partial exchange
of the inhibitor in both monomers (structure determined to 1.51 &#x000c5;
resolution). Besides the obvious reorientation of the carbon skeleton,
the presence of FGPP does not lead to active site reconfiguration.
However, the soaking protocol used has led to clear electron density
of a partially occupied third Mg<sup>2+</sup> ion (Mg<sup>2+</sup> C; <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref></xref>). This
in turn is accompanied by a modest change in conformation of the E155
region (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref></xref>a),
bringing the E155 side chain into close contact with water molecules
ligating Mg<sup>2+</sup> C. Given the partial occupancy of the inhibitors
and of the E155/Mg<sup>2+</sup> C, it is unclear whether there is
a direct link between the nature of the ligand bound in the active
site and the binding of Mg<sup>2+</sup> C. However, as both GPP and
NPP act as substrates for bCinS, presumably both requiring binding
of three Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions, it seems plausible the soaking procedure
used is responsible for the observed changes in the E155 region and
the associated Mg<sup>2+</sup> C binding.</p><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Structure of bCinS in
complex with FGPP. (A) Cartoon representation
of an overlay of the bCinS-FNPP complex structure (in gray) with the
bCinS-FGPP/FNPP structure obtained by soaking bCinS-FNPP with GFPP
(in blue). A loop region C-terminal to D85 as well as the region surrounding
E155 adopt distinct conformations in response to binding of Mg<sup>2+</sup> C, these regions are colored in red. (B) Stereoview of the
FGPP/FNPP-Mg<sup>2+</sup> ion binding site. Key polar interactions
are shown by dotted lines.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="cs-2017-019242_0004" id="gr4" position="float"/></fig><p>On the basis of the bCinS-FNPP and bCinsS-FGPP/FNPP structures,
a mechanism for the bacterial 1,8-cineole synthesis can be proposed,
by analogy to observations made with plant monoterpene synthases<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref></sup> (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref></xref>). Unlike FGPP, the carbon chain conformation of FNPP (and
by extension the NPP substrate) is compatible with cyclization of
the initial carbocation (in this case linalyl) derived from substrate
ionization to form the (<italic>R</italic>)-terpinyl cation. Indeed,
the FNPP C1 and C6 atoms are placed at a distance of &#x0223c;3.6 &#x000c5;.
In contrast, steric constraints require the FGPP carbon skeleton to
undergo an isomerization step following substrate ionization and geranyl
carbocation formation prior to cyclization. For other monoterpene
cyclase enzymes, this has been proposed to occur via transient formation
of linalyldiphosphate and concomitant change from the transoid to
cisoid configuration.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref></sup> A second substrate ionization
step then generates the linalyl carbocation species, which can proceed
to the cyclization step. The fact that both GPP and NPP result in
the same product suggests the exact configuration of the respective
linalyl carbocation species (GPP versus NPP derived) and resulting
terpinyl carbocation are similar, resembling the carbon chain configuration
of the FNPP inhibitor. However, recent solution studies using labeled
GPP have suggested bCinS proceeds via the (<italic>S</italic>)-terpinyl
cation, in contrast to the (<italic>R</italic>)-terpinyl configuration
proposed on the basis of the bCinS-FNPP crystal structure.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref63">63</xref></sup> Following formation of the terpinyl carbocation,
conversion via the final cyclization step to the 1,8-cineol product
is proposed to occur via a <italic>syn</italic> addition.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref63">63</xref></sup> With the exception of a single water molecule,
coordinated by Trp58 and Asn305, the hydrophobic binding pocket is
devoid of solvent. This water molecule is placed at a distance of
&#x0223c;3.6 &#x000c5; to the C6 of FNPP (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>c), and thus appears the most likely candidate
for nucleophilic attack on the terpinyl cation. MD simulations show
that this water molecule remains at an average distance of 3.84 (&#x000b1;0.45
run1, (&#x000b1;0.53 run2) &#x000c5; from C7 of GPP throughout the 100 ns
simulation (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref></xref>). The water molecule interacts with Asn305, but no longer interacts
with Trp58. <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref></xref>A&#x02013;C show the different positions of the hydrocarbon tail of
GPP and NPP in the representative structure from the dominant cluster
for the 100 ns simulations. The hydrocarbon tail of NPP occupies the
position adopted by the side chain of Phe77 in the simulations of
bCinS with GPP. There are more water molecules near to C7 of NPP and
the shortest distance is not with a single water molecule throughout
the entire simulation, as was observed for GPP. However, simulations
with NPP show that the average position of the water molecule is more
distant than in the bCinS/GPP system with an average C7&#x02013;WAT
O distance of 4.26 &#x000b1; 0.59 &#x000c5; run1 and 4.42 &#x000b1; 0.59 &#x000c5;
in run2 (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref></xref>d,e).
Formation of the neutral &#x003b1;-terpineol through deprotonation is
avoided by the lack of any suitable acid&#x02013;base group in close
proximity of this water molecule. Production of the bicyclic 1,8-cineole
from the protonated &#x003b1;-terpineol species is proposed to occur
via intramolecular proton transfer to C2, followed by C2&#x02013;O
bond formation leading to formation of the second cycle. Considering
the relative position of the water molecule and the C2 atom in the
FNPP structure, this scenario will require some conformational changes
to occur. This is distinct from the proposed mechanism for the plant
1,8 cineole synthase, for which a <italic>syn</italic> addition of
water is proposed, requiring no significant conformational changes
prior the ensuing heterocyclization step.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref64">64</xref></sup></p><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Mechanistic
proposal for bCinS. A schematic outline of a putative
mechanism for the conversion of GPP and NPP to the 1,8 cineole product
by bCinS. Taking into account the observed position and orientation
of the bCinS ligands and adjacent water molecules, we propose that
the (<italic>R</italic>)-terpinyl carbocation intermediate is formed,
followed by the <italic>anti</italic>-addition of water, requiring
a rotation step prior to hetercyclization.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="cs-2017-019242_0005" id="gr5" position="float"/></fig><fig id="fig6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>MD of bCinS with three Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions and GPP or NPP. (A)
Active site of bCinS in the dominant cluster from MD simulations with
of bCinS/GPP (purple) and bCinS/NPP (cyan). Water molecules within
5 &#x000c5; of GPP are shown in stick form and the closest water molecule
to C7, the site of attack by the water molecule, is colored in purple
for bCinS/GPP and cyan for bCinS/NPP. (B) and (C) show the same view
of bCinS/GPP and bCinS/NPP alone, respectively. (D) The distance between
C7 and O of WAT364 over the course of two 100 ns MD simulations of
bCinS/GPP. (E) The distance between C7 and O of the closest water
molecule to C7 of NPP over the course of two 100 ns MD simulations.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="cs-2017-019242_0006" id="gr6" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec3.5"><title>Structures of <italic>Apo</italic>-bLinS and bLinS-FGPP Complex</title><p>The bLinS could be crystallized
in both the <italic>apo</italic> form (2.4 &#x000c5;) as well as in complex
with the substrate analogue
FGPP (1.82 &#x000c5;, <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">1</xref></xref>). The bLinS structure reveals a dimer in the asymmetric unit,
but the monomer interface is distinct to that observed for the bCinS
enzyme (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref></xref>a).
The individual bLinS monomers overlay with rmsd of 0.83 &#x000c5; for
293 C&#x003b1; atoms, with a small shift in position of the N-terminal
region encompassing the first two alpha helices (residues 1&#x02013;62)
located furthest away from the dimer interface. Co-crystallization
with FGPP leads to crystals with similar packing. Unexpectedly, clear
electron density corresponding to FGPP is only present in monomer
A (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref></xref>b). In contrast,
electron density occupying the active site of monomer B is weak, and
only a single phosphate ion could be modeled that might be associated
with a disordered binding of the FGPP diphosphate moiety (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref></xref>c).</p><fig id="fig7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Structure of bLinS in <italic>apo</italic> and FGPP complex form.
(A) Cartoon representation of the <italic>apo</italic> bLinS dimer,
with one monomer colored in green and the second monomer in blue.
The latter is overlaid with the first monomer (in gray) revealing
small changes in conformation occur distant from the dimer interface.
(B) Cartoon representation of monomer A bound to FGPP. The N-terminal
region is shown in blue and the (here disordered) C-terminal region
in red. (C) Cartoon representation of the monomer B bound to phosphate.
Orientation and color coding are as in panel B. The ordering of the
C-terminus and the partial closing of the N-terminal regions occludes
the phosphate from solvent, in contrast to the solvent exposed nature
of the diphosphate group in monomer A. (D) Stereoview of the active
site of bLinS monomer A in complex with FGPP. Key polar interactions
are shown by black dotted lines. (E) Stereoview of the active site
of bLinS monomer B (in blue) in overlay with the active site of bCinS
in complex with FGPP/FNPP (in gray).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="cs-2017-019242_0007" id="gr7" position="float"/></fig><p>The FGPP is bound to the bLinS active site of chain A in
an extended
conformation compared to the FGPP/FNPP configuration observed in the
bCinS structures (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref></xref>d). Only one Mg<sup>2+</sup> ion coordinating the pyrophosphate
moiety could be unambiguously modeled. This Mg<sup>2+</sup> ion sits
on the concave side of the PP<sub>i</sub> moiety and hydrogen bonds
with Asp80 of the aspartate-rich motif in helix D. The direct interactions
between the diphosphate moiety of FGPP and bLinS are limited to a
polar interaction with Lys225. The hydrophobic moiety of FGPP is located
in a predominantly hydrophobic pocket at the core of the bLinS structure,
with a polar interaction observed between Asn218 of the Mg<sup>2+</sup> B binding NSE motif and the FGPP fluorine atom. The lack of Mg<sup>2+</sup> binding to the NSE motif, and the unusual position of the
diphosphate moiety, suggests the FGPP is bound in a noncatalytic mode.
We again used EPR to establish bLinS binds to three Mn<sup>2+</sup> ions (and by extension three Mg<sup>2+</sup>) in solution, similar
to other terpene synthases (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref></xref>b). While the electron density in the active site of
bLinS monomer B corresponds to a disordered species, the position
of the single phosphate that is visible is more akin to what can be
expected for the catalytic binding mode when superimposing bLinS on
the bCinS ligand complex structures (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref></xref>e). The phosphate in the bLinS monomer B
establishes a network of polar contacts with the C-terminal region
(R308, Y309) that is disordered in the <italic>apo</italic>-bLinS
structure. It is furthermore positioned adjacent to the NSE motif,
although a Mg<sup>2+</sup> B ion could not be unambiguously located
in this area. The ordering of the C-terminal region is incompatible
with crystal packing for bLinS monomer A, possibly contributing to
the noncatalytic conformation observed for the bound FGPP in the corresponding
active site. A comparison with the <italic>apo</italic>-bLinS structure
reveals the overall conformation for both monomers is similar, with
the notable exception of the C-terminal region. However, class I terpenoid
synthase structures have been found to alternate between an &#x0201c;open&#x0201d;
state (i.e., <italic>apo</italic>) and a &#x0201c;closed&#x0201d; (i.e.,
ligand) bound state<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref58">58</xref></sup>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref65">65</xref></sup> This calls into question whether the <italic>apo</italic>-bLinS structure is reflective of the open state, or whether the
bLinS-FGPP complex corresponds to the closed state. The fact neither
of the monomers in the bLinS-FGPP complex binds to the required three
metal ions strongly suggests both <italic>apo</italic> bLinS and the
bLinS-FGPP structures are in the open state, possibly stabilized by
crystal packing contacts.</p><p>MD simulations suggest that, unlike
other terpene synthases, neither
bLinS nor bCinS undergo major conformational changes to between &#x0201c;open&#x0201d;
and &#x0201c;closed&#x0201d; states, (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acscatal.7b01924/suppl_file/cs7b01924_si_001.pdf">Figures S8a&#x02013;c and S9a&#x02013;c</ext-link>). Although bLinS-FGPP is likely to correspond
to the open state, the carbon chain of the bound FGPP (in monomer
A) occupies a similar region as observed in the bCinS-FGPP/FNPP complexes
(<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref></xref>e). This likely
indicates the position of the active site hydrophobic pocket in bLinS,
and might even reflect the corresponding conformation of carbon chain
of the bound FGPP in the closed state. As linalool is an acyclic monoterpene
product, the bLinS catalytic mechanism does not require a cyclization
process. Instead, the geranyl cation attacks a nearby water molecule
leading to linalool following deprotonation (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref></xref>a). In the bLinS-FNPP structure, several
water molecules are located within a distance of &#x0223c;4.5 &#x000c5;
from the FGPP (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref></xref>d), and representing likely candidates for this process in case the
FGPP carbon chain conformation is reflective of the catalytically
relevant species. In contrast to the closed nature of the bCinS structure,
the bLinS is relatively open, and we cannot rule out further closure
might occur upon substrate binding in solution. Keeping this caveat
in mind, the most likely candidate for the water attack is the molecule
that is coordinated by Asp79 and Arg172 and is at a distance of 3.6
&#x000c5; from C3 of FGPP. The position of the water molecule with respect
to FGPP suggests production of <italic>R</italic>-(&#x02212;)-linalool,
which matches with the biochemical characterization. MD simulations
show that the closest water molecule to C3 of GPP remains at an average
distance of 3.29 (&#x000b1;0.21) &#x000c5; in run1 and 3.93 (&#x000b1;0.52)
&#x000c5; in run2 (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref></xref>c). MD simulations of bLinS in complex with FPP (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acscatal.7b01924/suppl_file/cs7b01924_si_001.pdf">Figure S9</ext-link>), the precursor to sesquiterpenes, shows that the
active site is sufficiently large to accommodate a sesquiterpene,
explaining the fact bLinS also accepts FPP as a substrate.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref></sup></p><fig id="fig8" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Mechanistic proposal for bLinS and MD of bLinS with GPP
and three
Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions. (A) Schematic outline representing the conversion
of GPP to the linalool product by bLinS. (B) Active site of bLinS
in the dominant cluster from MD simulations with GPP and three Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions. GPP is shown with cyan carbon atoms, bLinS is shown
in purple in cartoon form and the Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions are shown as
green spheres. Water molecules within 5 &#x000c5; of GPP are shown in
stick form, with the water molecule closest to C3 of GPP shown in
red. (C) The distance between C3 and O of WAT430 over the course of
two 100 ns MD simulations.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="cs-2017-019242_0008" id="gr8" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec3.6"><title>Bacterial mTC/S Are Structurally Similar to Sesquiterpene Synthases</title><p>The bLinS and bCinS are single domain (&#x003b1;) enzymes, whereas
the plant mTC(S) typically contain two domains (&#x003b1; and &#x003b2;).
This makes them structurally more similar to the sesquiterpene synthases
(<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref></xref>a), which
are also usually composed of only a single class I terpenoid fold
domain.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref></sup> It is notable that genome mining
for bacterial terpene synthase-like genes followed by heterologous
expression revealed the majority of these enzymes made sesquiterpenes
as products.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref></sup> So far, bLinS and bCinS
are the only characterized bacterial mTC(S) that accept GPP as substrate
and thus lead to monoterpene formation. The bCinS-FNPP complex is
specifically compared to the structures of plant limonene synthases<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref></sup> and bornyl diphosphate synthase<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref></sup> for
which complexes with the substrate analogues are available. When comparing
the corresponding C-terminal catalytic domains with the bCinS complexes,
it is clear that the orientation of GPP/NPP analogue in bCinS is such
that the beta phosphate occupies the location comparable to the alpha
phosphate binding site in the plant enzymes and <italic>vice versa</italic>, and resembles the orientation observed in sesquiterpene synthase
complex. For the functionally analogous plant 1,8-cineole synthase
(Sf-CinS1), only the apoenzyme structure is available. Furthermore,
superimposition of the bCinS and Sf-CinS1 reveals distinct active
site architectures. In Sf-CinS1, Asn338, which coordinates a water
molecule, was found to be crucial for the synthesis of 1,8-cineole.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref></sup> Mutation of Asn338 to Ile resulted in the formation
of sabinene as the major product but no &#x003b1;-terpineol and 1,8-cineole,
establishing the role of Asn338 in water capture. In bCinS, as mentioned
before, residues Trp58 and Asn305 coordinate the water molecule proposed
to be involved in the water attack. Though Asn305 in bCinS resides
in a different helix and region of the active site compared to Asn338
in Sf-CinS1, Asn305 might play a similar role to that proposed for
the plant enzyme (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acscatal.7b01924/suppl_file/cs7b01924_si_001.pdf">Figure S10</ext-link>). Analysis
using DALI<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref66">66</xref></sup> and PDBefold<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref67">67</xref></sup> servers showed many sesquiterpene synthases including pentalenene
synthase (PDB 1 ps1),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref32">32</xref></sup> germacradienol
synthase (PDB 5i1u),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref68">68</xref></sup> hedycaryol synthase (PDB 4mc3),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref69">69</xref></sup> geosmin synthase (PDB 5dz2),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref70">70</xref></sup> epi-isozizaene
synthase (PDB 4ltv),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref65">65</xref></sup> selinadiene synthase (40kz),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref58">58</xref></sup> and aristolochene synthase (PDB 4kwd)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref51">51</xref></sup> are very similar to bLinS and bCinS structures (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acscatal.7b01924/suppl_file/cs7b01924_si_001.pdf">Table S2</ext-link>).</p><fig id="fig9" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>bLinS and bCinS are related to bacterial
sesquiterpene synthases.
(A) Stereoview of a cartoon representation of a structural overlay
of bLinS (monomer B; in green), bCinS FGPP/FNPP (in blue) and aristolochene
synthase (ATAS) (PDB code 4KUX) in complex with a C15 substrate analogue (in magenta).
(B) Active site overlay of bCinS and ATAS, color coding as in panel
A. (C) Active site overlay of bLinS (monomer B) and ATAS, color coding
as in panel A.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="cs-2017-019242_0009" id="gr9" position="float"/></fig><p>Two sesquiterpene synthase
structures have been reported in complex
with substrate analogues: <italic>Aspergillus terreus</italic> aristocholene synthase (ATAS) with farnesyl thiolodiphosphate (FSPP;
PDB 4KUX) and
selinadiene synthase (SdS) with dihydrofarnesyl diphosphate (DHFPP;
PDB 4OKZ). A
comparison of these structures with bLinS and bCinS might allow pinpointing
of those active site differences that play a role in determining substrate
specificity (C<sub>10</sub> versus C<sub>15</sub>). Since the Mg<sup>2+</sup> and pyrophosphate binding regions are highly conserved,
most variations in the active site architecture are restricted to
hydrophobic cavity surrounding the substrate carbon chain. In bCinS,
two phenylalanines (Phe 77 and Phe 179) constrict the substrate-binding
site when compared to the ATAS-FSPP and SdS-DHFPP structures, and
they would clash with a putative FPP substrate (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref></xref>b). Phe179 resides in the kink region of
the helix G1/2 of bCinS, and is replaced by Gly174 in ATAS and Ala183
in SdS. The bCinS Phe77 resides in helix D and is homologous to Leu80
in ATAS/Leu78 in SdS, with the latter both adopting a conformation
that is pointing away from the active site. This suggests bCinS evolved
from a sesquiterpene synthase by restricting active site volume.</p><p>Interestingly, bLinS contains nonaromatic residues at positions
equivalent to bCinS Phe77 and Phe179 (Thr75 and Cys177 in bLinS),
and thus resembles ATAS and SdS (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref></xref>c). This provides a rationale for the fact
bLinS can accept both GPP and FPP as substrates but bCinS can only
convert GPP.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref></sup></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Conclusions</title><p>We
have shown that expression of <italic>Streptomyces clavuligerus</italic> linalool synthase and 1,8-cineole synthase in an <italic>E. coli</italic> geranyl diphosphate producing strain leads
to higher levels of production (linalool) or more enriched product
profiles (1,8-cineole) than previously reported. Crystal structures
of both <italic>S. clavuligerus</italic> monoterpene
synthases reveal the bacterial monoterpene synthases are more similar
to previously characterized sesquiterpene synthases. A comparison
with the sesquiterpene synthases allowed identification of key residues
that can be exploited for rational design and switching of activity
between the two classes. These results provide a basis for application
of the bacterial monoterpene synthases to generate diverse monoterpene
scaffolds and employ synthetic biology approaches for large-scale
monoterpenoid production.</p></sec></body><back><notes id="notes-1" notes-type="si"><title>Supporting Information Available</title><p>The Supporting Information
is available free of charge on the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org">ACS Publications website</ext-link> at DOI: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/acscatal.7b01924">10.1021/acscatal.7b01924</ext-link>.<list id="silist" list-type="simple"><list-item><p>Extended EPR results
and discussion, Scheme S1, Figures
S1&#x02013;S10, Tables S1&#x02013;S2 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acscatal.7b01924/suppl_file/cs7b01924_si_001.pdf">PDF</ext-link>)</p></list-item></list></p></notes><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sifile1"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="cs7b01924_si_001.pdf"><caption><p>cs7b01924_si_001.pdf</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><notes notes-type="COI-statement" id="notes-3"><p>The authors
declare the following competing financial interest(s): Patent pending
for the use of bLinS and bCinS in production of monoterpenes using
biocatalysis and synthetic biology methods.</p></notes><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We
thank Colin Levy, Manchester Protein Structure Facility
(MPSF) for help with X-ray data collection, Matthew J. Cliff for NMR
analysis of synthetic compounds and Derren J. Heyes for project management.
We thank Diamond Light Source for access to beamlines I04 and I04-1
(proposal number mx12788). This work was funded by the U.K. Biotechnology
and Biological Sciences Research Council (BBSRC; BB/M000354/1, BB/M017702/1
and BB/L027593/1:ERA-IB2 TERPENOSOME). D.L. is a Royal Society Wolfson
Merit Award holder. M.W.v.d.K. is a BBSRC David Phillips Fellow. N.S.S.
was a Royal Society Wolfson Merit Award holder and is an Engineering
and Physical Sciences Research Council (EPSRC; EP/J020192/1) Established
Career Fellow.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit1"><name><surname>Tholl</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<source>Adv. Biochem. Eng./Biotechnol.</source>
<year>2015</year>, <volume>148</volume>, <fpage>63</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>106</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/10_2014_295</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit2"><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>K. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Alonso-Gutierrez</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Keasling</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>T. S.</given-names></name>
<source>Adv. Biochem. Eng./Biotechnol.</source>
<year>2015</year>, <volume>148</volume>, <fpage>355</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>89</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/10_2014_288</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit3"><name><surname>Leferink</surname><given-names>N. G. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jervis</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zebec</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Toogood</surname><given-names>H. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Takano</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Scrutton</surname><given-names>N. S.</given-names></name>
<source>Chemistryselect</source>
<year>2016</year>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>1893</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1896</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/slct.201600563</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29756025</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit4"><name><surname>Peralta-Yahya</surname><given-names>P. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>del Cardayre</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Keasling</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>
<source>Nature</source>
<year>2012</year>, <volume>488</volume>, <fpage>320</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11478</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22895337</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit5"><name><surname>Jongedijk</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cankar</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Buchhaupt</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Schrader</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bouwmeester</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Beekwilder</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<source>Appl. Microbiol.
Biotechnol.</source>
<year>2016</year>, <volume>100</volume>, <fpage>2927</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-016-7337-7</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26915992</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit6"><name><surname>Zebec</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wilkes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jervis</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Scrutton</surname><given-names>N. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Takano</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Breitling</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<source>Curr. Opin. Chem. Biol.</source>
<year>2016</year>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>37</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>43</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cbpa.2016.06.002</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27315341</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit7"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ort</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>
<source>Plant Biotechnol J.</source>
<year>2015</year>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>137</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>46</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pbi.12343</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25626473</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit8"><name><surname>Formighieri</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Melis</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<source>Photosynth.
Res.</source>
<year>2016</year>, <volume>130</volume>, <fpage>123</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>135</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11120-016-0233-2</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26895437</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit9"><name><surname>Oldfield</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>F. Y.</given-names></name>
<source>Angew. Chem., Int. Ed.</source>
<year>2012</year>, <volume>51</volume>, <fpage>1124</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>37</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/anie.201103110</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit10"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Honzatko</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
<source>Nat. Prod. Rep.</source>
<year>2012</year>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>1153</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>75</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/c2np20059g</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22907771</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit11"><name><surname>Aaron</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Christianson</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>
<source>Pure Appl. Chem.</source>
<year>2010</year>, <volume>82</volume>, <fpage>1585</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1597</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1351/PAC-CON-09-09-37</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21562622</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit12"><name><surname>Srividya</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Croteau</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>B. M.</given-names></name>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.
U. S. A.</source>
<year>2015</year>, <volume>112</volume>, <fpage>3332</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1501203112</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25733883</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit13"><name><surname>Hyatt</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Croteau</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<source>Arch. Biochem. Biophys.</source>
<year>2005</year>, <volume>439</volume>, <fpage>222</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.abb.2005.05.017</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15978541</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit14"><name><surname>Whittington</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wise</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Urbansky</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Coates</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Croteau</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Christianson</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</source>
<year>2002</year>, <volume>99</volume>, <fpage>15375</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>80</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.232591099</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12432096</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit15"><name><surname>Hyatt</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Youn</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Santhamma</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Coates</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Croteau</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad.
Sci. U.
S. A.</source>
<year>2007</year>, <volume>104</volume>, <fpage>5360</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0700915104</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17372193</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit16"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Morehouse</surname><given-names>B. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Matos</surname><given-names>J. O.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Krauss</surname><given-names>I. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Oprian</surname><given-names>D. D.</given-names></name>
<source>Biochemistry</source>
<year>2017</year>, <volume>56</volume>, <fpage>1716</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1725</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.biochem.7b00144</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28272876</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit17"><name><surname>Morehouse</surname><given-names>B. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Matos</surname><given-names>J. O.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>S. N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Entova</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Oprian</surname><given-names>D. D.</given-names></name>
<source>Biochemistry</source>
<year>2017</year>, <volume>56</volume>, <fpage>1706</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1715</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.biochem.7b00143</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28272875</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit18"><name><surname>Kampranis</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ioannidis</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Purvis</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mahrez</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ninga</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Katerelos</surname><given-names>N. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Anssour</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dunwell</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Degenhardt</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Makris</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Goodenough</surname><given-names>P. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>C. B.</given-names></name>
<source>Plant Cell</source>
<year>2007</year>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>1994</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2005</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.106.047779</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17557809</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit19"><name><surname>Rudolph</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Parthier</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Egerer-Sieber</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Geiger</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>Y. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kreis</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Muller-Uri</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<source>Acta Crystallogr.,
Sect. F: Struct. Biol.
Commun.</source>
<year>2016</year>, <volume>72</volume>, <fpage>16</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S2053230X15023043</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26750479</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit20"><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kuzuyama</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Komatsu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shin-Ya</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Omura</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cane</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</source>
<year>2015</year>, <volume>112</volume>, <fpage>857</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>62</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1422108112</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25535391</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit21"><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Arima</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nagamitsu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Johmoto</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Uekusa</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Eguchi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shin-ya</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cane</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<source>J. Antibiot.</source>
<year>2015</year>, <volume>68</volume>, <fpage>385</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>94</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ja.2014.171</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25605043</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit22"><name><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ohnishi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<source>ChemBioChem</source>
<year>2011</year>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>1988</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cbic.201100330</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21726035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit23"><name><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ohnishi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<source>ChemBioChem</source>
<year>2011</year>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>2403</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cbic.201100501</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21910204</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit24"><name><surname>Dickschat</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>
<source>Nat. Prod. Rep.</source>
<year>2016</year>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>87</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>110</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C5NP00102A</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26563452</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit25"><name><surname>Koksal</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>W. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cane</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Christianson</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>
<source>Biochemistry</source>
<year>2012</year>, <volume>51</volume>, <fpage>3011</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi201827a</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22455514</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit26"><name><surname>Lapczynski</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Letizia</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Api</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
<source>Food Chem. Toxicol.</source>
<year>2008</year>, <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>S190</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2008.06.087</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19097259</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit27"><name><surname>Seol</surname><given-names>G. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K. Y.</given-names></name>
<source>Adv. Exp. Med. Biol.</source>
<year>2016</year>, <volume>929</volume>, <fpage>389</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>398</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-319-41342-6_18</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27771935</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit28"><name><surname>Karp</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Santhamma</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Assink</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Coates</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Croteau</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name>
<source>Arch. Biochem. Biophys.</source>
<year>2007</year>, <volume>468</volume>, <fpage>140</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.abb.2007.09.008</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17949678</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit29"><name><surname>Dixit</surname><given-names>V. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Laskovics</surname><given-names>F. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Noall</surname><given-names>W. I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Poulter</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name>
<source>J. Org. Chem.</source>
<year>1981</year>, <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>1967</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1969</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jo00322a060</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit30"><name><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lobley</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Prince</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
<source>Acta Crystallogr.,
Sect. D: Biol. Crystallogr.</source>
<year>2013</year>, <volume>69</volume>, <fpage>1260</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0907444913015308</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23793152</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit31"><name><surname>Kabsch</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<source>Acta Crystallogr.,
Sect. D: Biol. Crystallogr.</source>
<year>2010</year>, <volume>66</volume>, <fpage>125</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0907444909047337</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20124692</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit32"><name><surname>Lesburg</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cane</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Christianson</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>
<source>Science</source>
<year>1997</year>, <volume>277</volume>, <fpage>1820</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1824</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.277.5333.1820</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9295272</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit33"><name><surname>McCoy</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Grosse-Kunstleve</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Winn</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Storoni</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Read</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
<source>J. Appl. Crystallogr.</source>
<year>2007</year>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>658</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>674</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0021889807021206</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19461840</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit34"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Afonine</surname><given-names>P. V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bunkoczi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>V. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>I. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Echols</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Headd</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>L. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kapral</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Grosse-Kunstleve</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>McCoy</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Moriarty</surname><given-names>N. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Oeffner</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Read</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Terwilliger</surname><given-names>T. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zwart</surname><given-names>P. H.</given-names></name>
<source>Acta Crystallogr., Sect. D: Biol. Crystallogr.</source>
<year>2010</year>, <volume>66</volume>, <fpage>213</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0907444909052925</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20124702</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit35"><name><surname>Emsley</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lohkamp</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>W. G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cowtan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<source>Acta Crystallogr., Sect. D:
Biol. Crystallogr.</source>
<year>2010</year>, <volume>66</volume>, <fpage>486</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>501</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0907444910007493</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20383002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit36"><name><surname>Afonine</surname><given-names>P. V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Grosse-Kunstleve</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Echols</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Headd</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Moriarty</surname><given-names>N. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mustyakimov</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Terwilliger</surname><given-names>T. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Urzhumtsev</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zwart</surname><given-names>P. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name>
<source>Acta Crystallogr., Sect.
D: Biol. Crystallogr.</source>
<year>2012</year>, <volume>68</volume>, <fpage>352</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>67</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0907444912001308</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22505256</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit37"><name><surname>Joosten</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Murshudov</surname><given-names>G. N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Perrakis</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<source>IUCrJ</source>
<year>2014</year>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>213</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S2052252514009324</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit38"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>V. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Arendall</surname><given-names>W. B.</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name>; <name><surname>Headd</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Keedy</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Immormino</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kapral</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>L. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name>
<source>Acta Crystallogr., Sect. D: Biol. Crystallogr.</source>
<year>2010</year>, <volume>66</volume>, <fpage>12</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0907444909042073</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20057044</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit39"><name><surname>MacKerell</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bashford</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bellott</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dunbrack</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Evanseck</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ha</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Joseph-McCarthy</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kuchnir</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kuczera</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>F. T. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mattos</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Michnick</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ngo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>D. T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Prodhom</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Reiher</surname><given-names>W. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Roux</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Schlenkrich</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Stote</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Straub</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wiorkiewicz-Kuczera</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Karplus</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<source>J. Phys. Chem. B</source>
<year>1998</year>, <volume>102</volume>, <fpage>3586</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3616</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jp973084f</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24889800</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit40"><name><surname>Foloppe</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>MacKerell</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name>
<source>J. Comput. Chem.</source>
<year>2000</year>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>86</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>104</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1096-987X(20000130)21:2&#x0003c;86::AID-JCC2&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-G</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit41"><name><surname>Olsson</surname><given-names>M. H. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sondergaard</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rostkowski</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>
<source>J. Chem. Theory Comput.</source>
<year>2011</year>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>525</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>537</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ct100578z</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26596171</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit42"><name><surname>Sondergaard</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Olsson</surname><given-names>M. H. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rostkowski</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>
<source>J. Chem. Theory Comput.</source>
<year>2011</year>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>2284</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2295</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ct200133y</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26606496</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit43"><name><surname>Jorgensen</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chandrasekhar</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Madura</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Impey</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>
<source>J. Chem. Phys.</source>
<year>1983</year>, <volume>79</volume>, <fpage>926</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>935</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.445869</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit44"><name><surname>Humphrey</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dalke</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Schulten</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<source>J. Mol. Graphics</source>
<year>1996</year>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>33</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0263-7855(96)00018-5</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit45"><name><surname>van
der Kamp</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sirirak</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zurek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Allemann</surname><given-names>R. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mulholland</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>
<source>Biochemistry</source>
<year>2013</year>, <volume>52</volume>, <fpage>8094</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>105</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi400898k</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24106830</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit46"><name><surname>Major</surname><given-names>D. T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Freud</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Weitman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<source>Curr. Opin. Chem. Biol.</source>
<year>2014</year>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>25</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cbpa.2014.03.010</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24735749</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit47"><name><surname>O&#x02019;Brien</surname><given-names>T. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bertolani</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tantillo</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name>
<source>Chem. Sci.</source>
<year>2016</year>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>4009</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4015</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C6SC00635C</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30155043</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit48"><name><surname>Allner</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Villa</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<source>J. Chem. Theory Comput.</source>
<year>2012</year>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>1493</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1502</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ct3000734</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26596759</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit49"><name><surname>G&#x000f6;tz</surname><given-names>A. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Poole</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Le Grand</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name>
<source>J. Chem. Theory Comput.</source>
<year>2012</year>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>1542</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1555</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ct200909j</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22582031</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref50"><mixed-citation publication-type="computer-program" id="cit50"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Case</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Betz</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cerutti</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cheatham</surname><given-names>T. E.</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name>; <name><surname>Darden</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Duke</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Giese</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gohlke</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Goetz</surname><given-names>A. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Homeyer</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Izadi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Janowski</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kaus</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kovalenko</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>T. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>LeGrand</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Luchko</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Madej</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mermelstein</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Merz</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Monard</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>H. T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Omelyan</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Onufriev</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Roe</surname><given-names>D.
R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Roitberg</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sagui</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Simmerling</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Botello-Smith</surname><given-names>W. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Swails</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kollman</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Amber</source>; <publisher-name>University
of California</publisher-name>: <publisher-loc>San Francisco</publisher-loc>, <year>2016</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit51"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Al-lami</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Janvier</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>D&#x02019;Antonio</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Faraldos</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cane</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Allemann</surname><given-names>R. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Christianson</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>
<source>Biochemistry</source>
<year>2013</year>, <volume>52</volume>, <fpage>5441</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>53</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi400691v</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23905850</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit52"><name><surname>Aaron</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cane</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Christianson</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>
<source>Biochemistry</source>
<year>2010</year>, <volume>49</volume>, <fpage>1787</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1797</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi902088z</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20131801</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit53"><name><surname>Alonso-Gutierrez</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Batth</surname><given-names>T. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Keasling</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Petzold</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>T. S.</given-names></name>
<source>Metab. Eng.</source>
<year>2013</year>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>33</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ymben.2013.05.004</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23727191</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit54"><name><surname>Fujisaki</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nishino</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Katsuki</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<source>J. Biochem.</source>
<year>1986</year>, <volume>99</volume>, <fpage>1327</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>37</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.jbchem.a135600</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3519603</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit55"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>E. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S. W.</given-names></name>
<source>J. Biotechnol.</source>
<year>2014</year>, <volume>169</volume>, <fpage>42</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>50</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbiotec.2013.11.009</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24269531</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit56"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Xian</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<source>Bioengineered</source>
<year>2015</year>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>288</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>93</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/21655979.2015.1062188</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26091008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit57"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>E. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S. W.</given-names></name>
<source>Biotechnol. J.</source>
<year>2016</year>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>1291</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1297</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/biot.201600250</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27440491</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit58"><name><surname>Baer</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rabe</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Citron</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Klapschinski</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Groll</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dickschat</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>
<source>Angew. Chem., Int. Ed.</source>
<year>2014</year>, <volume>53</volume>, <fpage>7652</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/anie.201403648</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit59"><name><surname>Krissinel</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Henrick</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<source>J. Mol. Biol.</source>
<year>2007</year>, <volume>372</volume>, <fpage>774</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>97</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmb.2007.05.022</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17681537</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit60"><name><surname>Morrissey</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Horton</surname><given-names>T. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>DeRose</surname><given-names>V. J.</given-names></name>
<source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source>
<year>2000</year>, <volume>122</volume>, <fpage>3473</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3481</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja992989z</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit61"><name><surname>DeRose</surname><given-names>V. J.</given-names></name>
<source>Curr. Opin. Struct.
Biol.</source>
<year>2003</year>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>317</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0959-440X(03)00077-0</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12831882</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit62"><name><surname>Stich</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lahiri</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yeagle</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dicus</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Brynda</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gunn</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Aznar</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Derose</surname><given-names>V. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Britt</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name>
<source>Appl. Magn. Reson.</source>
<year>2007</year>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>321</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>341</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF03166263</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22190766</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit63"><name><surname>Rinkel</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rabe</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zur Horst</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dickschat</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>
<source>Beilstein J. Org.
Chem.</source>
<year>2016</year>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>2317</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2324</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3762/bjoc.12.225</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28144299</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit64"><name><surname>Wise</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Urbansky</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Helms</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Coates</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Croteau</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source>
<year>2002</year>, <volume>124</volume>, <fpage>8546</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja0265714</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12121093</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit65"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>W. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Himmelberger</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Litwin</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>G. G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cane</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Christianson</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>
<source>Biochemistry</source>
<year>2014</year>, <volume>53</volume>, <fpage>1155</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>68</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi401643u</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24517311</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit66"><name><surname>Holm</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rosenstrom</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<year>2010</year>, <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>W545</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>W549</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkq366</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20457744</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit67"><name><surname>Krissinel</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Henrick</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<source>Acta Crystallogr., Sect. D:
Biol. Crystallogr.</source>
<year>2004</year>, <volume>60</volume>, <fpage>2256</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>68</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0907444904026460</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15572779</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit68"><name><surname>Grundy</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Leoni</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Christianson</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Allemann</surname><given-names>R. K.</given-names></name>
<source>Biochemistry</source>
<year>2016</year>, <volume>55</volume>, <fpage>2112</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.biochem.6b00115</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26998816</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit69"><name><surname>Baer</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rabe</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Citron</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>de Oliveira Mann</surname><given-names>C. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kaufmann</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Groll</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dickschat</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>
<source>ChemBioChem</source>
<year>2014</year>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>213</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cbic.201300708</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24399794</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref70"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit70"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>G. G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lombardi</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pemberton</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Matsui</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Koksal</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>F. V. t.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Vedula</surname><given-names>L. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>W. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cane</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Christianson</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>
<source>Biochemistry</source>
<year>2015</year>, <volume>54</volume>, <fpage>7142</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.biochem.5b01143</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26598179</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>