<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Plant Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Plant Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-462X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5042961</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2016.01472</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Plant Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Meta-Analysis of the Core Aroma Components of Grape and Wine Aroma</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ilc</surname><given-names>Tina</given-names></name><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/329890/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Werck-Reichhart</surname><given-names>Dani&#x000e8;le</given-names></name><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/218087/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Navrot</surname><given-names>Nicolas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/86480/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><institution>Institut de Biologie Mol&#x000e9;culaire des Plantes, Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique, Universit&#x000e9; de Strasbourg</institution><country>Strasbourg, France</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: <italic>Angelos K. Kanellis, Aristotle University of Thessaloniki, Greece</italic></p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: <italic>Xiaoqiang Wang, The Samuel Roberts Noble Foundation, USA; Yorgos Kotseridis, Agricultural University Athens, Greece</italic></p></fn><corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: <italic>Nicolas Navrot, <email xlink:type="simple">navrot@unistra.fr</email></italic></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p>This article was submitted to Plant Metabolism and Chemodiversity, a section of the journal Frontiers in Plant Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>9</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>1472</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>06</day><month>7</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>9</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2016 Ilc, Werck-Reichhart and Navrot.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Ilc, Werck-Reichhart and Navrot</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) or licensor are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Wine aroma strongly influences wine quality, yet its composition and its evolution during the winemaking process are poorly understood. Volatile compounds that constitute wine aroma are traditionally divided into three classes according to their origin: grape, fermentation, and maturation aroma. We challenge this view with meta-analysis and review of grape and wine volatiles and their precursors from 82 profiling experiments. We compiled a list of 141 common grape and wine volatiles and quantitatively compared 43 of them. Our work offers insight into complex relationships between biosynthesis of aroma in grapes and the changes during the winemaking process. Monoterpenes are one of the largest and most researched wine aroma compounds. We show that their diversity in wines is mainly due to the oxidative metabolism of linalool in grapes. Furthermore, we demonstrate that most of the linalool produced in grapes is converted to these oxidized derivatives.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>volatiles</kwd><kwd>aroma</kwd><kwd>gas chromatography</kwd><kwd>profiling</kwd><kwd>wine</kwd><kwd>grapes</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001">Agence Nationale de la Recherche<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100001665</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn001">ANR-13-BSV6-0010</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn002">Seventh Framework Programme<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100004963</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn002">REA Grant Agreement 289217</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="5"/><table-count count="2"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="86"/><page-count count="15"/><word-count count="0"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>A crucial determinant of the wine quality is aroma, the composition of which is still not fully understood, due mainly to the interactions of the genetic factors with the environment. Yet this knowledge is necessary to ensure consistent production of high quality wines (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Pol&#x000e1;&#x00161;kov&#x000e1; et al., 2008</xref>). Wine aroma is a complex mixture of volatile organic compounds. These are small, non-polar molecules that readily enter the gas phase and reach our nasal cavity while we smell or drink a glass of wine. Different volatile organic compounds in wine span a large range of concentrations. While it is tempting to think that the more abundant compounds impact the aroma more than the trace compounds, it is not necessarily the case. Human nose can perceive some of the compounds at very low concentrations, whereas others remain undetected even at high levels. The strength of aroma of a particular compound is expressed as an odor detection threshold, which is the lowest concentration perceivable to the human smell. Compounds with low sensory thresholds are often responsible for the characteristic smell of a particular food (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Dunkel et al., 2014</xref>).</p><p>Wine aroma compounds differ in their origin and evolution during the winemaking process. Many authors have classified wine aroma compounds into three categories based on their origin: grape (or varietal) aroma, fermentation aroma and aging aroma, also called the wine bouquet (<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">Rapp and Mandery, 1986</xref>; <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Ebeler, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">Styger et al., 2011</xref>). However, these three classes are not so clear-cut: ultimately most of the aroma precursors (even the simple ones) originate from grapes and are in some way modified by the fermentation process or aging.</p><p>The grape aroma is synthesized in grape berries by a variety of enzymes, including terpene synthases, <italic>O</italic>-methyl transferases, carotenoid cleavage dioxygenases, cytochromes P450 and probably other not yet characterized enzymes. Genetic variation in aroma biosynthesis genes cause differences in aroma between grapevine varieties: an allelic variant of 1-deoxy-<sc>D</sc>-xylulose-5-phosphate synthase, a terpenoid biosynthetic gene, causes accumulation of terpenoids in Muscat and Gewurztraminer grapes. An abundance of terpenoids gives these wines a distinct floral aroma (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Battilana et al., 2009</xref>, <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Duch&#x000ea;ne et al., 2009</xref>). In another example, differential expression of an <italic>O</italic>-methyl transferase gene results in higher production of methoxypyrazines, compounds evoking the typical capsicum aroma in Sauvignon wines (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Guillaumie et al., 2013</xref>). The genetic factors underlying the aroma typicity of all other grapevine varieties&#x02014;in Europe alone over 2000 varieties have been described (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Lacombe et al., 2011</xref>)&#x02014;remain unexplored.</p><p>Grape berries store most of the volatiles they produce as glycosides (<xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">Strauss et al., 1988</xref>). Possible functions of glycosylation are sequestration, detoxification and decrease of volatility and reactivity (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Hjelmeland and Ebeler, 2014</xref>). Since glycosides are not volatile, they do not directly contribute to wine aroma. They do, however, affect the aroma indirectly: they form a precursor pool from which volatile aglycones can be released during yeast and malolactic fermentation, during vinification by addition of exogenous glycosidases, during wine aging owing to its low pH (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Maicas and Mateo, 2005</xref>) and, as demonstrated recently, by enzymatic hydrolysis in the mouth, catalyzed by the enzymes in the saliva (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Mayr et al., 2014</xref>). Aroma glycosides in grapes have either one or two sugar moieties attached to the aglycone (forming mono- or diglycosides, respectively). The first sugar moiety, directly attached to the aglycone, is in all cases glucose. The majority of glycosides (at least in the case of terpenoids) are present in the form of diglycosides, in which a second sugar&#x02014;arabinose, apiose or rhamnose&#x02014;is attached to the glucose (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Maicas and Mateo, 2005</xref>). The diglycosides cannot be hydrolyzed by a &#x003b2;-glucosidase, and require other glycosidase enzymes to release the volatile aglycone (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Gunata et al., 1988</xref>).</p><p>The winemaking process profoundly influences the wine aroma development. Processes contributing are the hydrolysis of glycosides present in the must and the production, particularly, of alcohols and esters, by the yeast (<italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>) itself. Different yeast strains can produce remarkably different aroma profiles (<xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">Romano et al., 2003</xref>). After alcoholic fermentation wines are sometimes subjected to malolactic fermentation by <italic>Oenococcus oeni</italic>, the principal role of which is to reduce tartness or acidity of wine by converting malic acid to lactic acid. These bacteria can also alter the composition of aroma by, for example, promoting deglycosylation (<xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">Ugliano and Moio, 2006</xref>).</p><p>The evolution of wine aroma continues after the fermentation process. In addition to above-mentioned acid hydrolysis of aroma glycosides during wine aging, low pH can cause other important chemical changes. <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">Williams et al. (1980b)</xref> postulated that some hydroxylated linalool derivatives undergo cyclisation or other rearrangements at low pH. In addition, during storage in oak barrels, compounds from the wood are extracted to the wine and influence its taste and aroma.</p><p>Standardized sample preparation (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Gunata et al., 1985</xref>; <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">Voirin et al., 1992</xref>) and analytic procedures are routinely performed for evaluation of grape and wine volatiles and their precursors. Grape juices or wines are extracted to a non-ionic solid phase, free volatiles are eluted by a non-polar solvent (pentane or a mixture of pentane and dichloromethane), and glycosylated volatiles are eluted by a more polar solvent (ethyl acetate or methanol). The free fraction can then be directly analyzed by gas chromatography. The bound fraction is enzymatically hydrolyzed before the analysis. Gas chromatography allows for simultaneous analysis of hundreds of volatiles with good resolution of structurally similar molecules. Furthermore, coupling to a mass spectrometer enables reliable identification of compounds by searching mass spectra databases even when analytical standards are not available.</p><p>Many research laboratories used this method to investigate how aroma is influenced by grape variety, grape ripening, environment and different winegrowing and winemaking techniques. While these studies have without doubt addressed some of these important questions, a comprehensive picture of wine aroma integrating these valuable data has not been painted yet. We collected, curated and analyzed these data to answer the following questions. What are the components of grape and wine aroma? At which concentrations are they present? To what extent are they glycosylated? We compared these parameters between grapes and wines. We then compared these data to the existing knowledge on the origin and evolution of aroma components with a particular focus on their biosynthesis. This meta-analysis adds to our understanding of wine aroma composition and development.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s1"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Data Collection</title><p>We collected published datasets on free and glycosylated grape and wine volatiles. We used search term &#x0201c;grape aroma profiling free glycosylated&#x0201d; on Google Scholar and reviewed citations of included publications. We reviewed 104 publications that reported profiling of grapes or wines. Foutry-five of them were excluded because they only contained information on free volatiles, and 8 because they only contained information on glycosylated volatiles. To ensure the compounds were annotated correctly, only publications that contained information of Kovats retention index were included. Further 31 publications were therefore excluded, which resulted in 19 selected publications (<bold>Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref></bold>). Publications or samples that described <italic>Vitis</italic> species other than <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> subsp. <italic>vinifera</italic> were excluded from all quantitative analysis, but used for validation of retention indices.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Publications included in the analysis.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample type</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of samples</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genotypes/Varieties</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">Yilmaztekin et al., 2015</xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wine</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Karaoglan</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">S&#x000e1;nchez-Palomo et al., 2015</xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wine</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Verdejo</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">Selli et al., 2006</xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wine</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Narince</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">Toci et al., 2012</xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wine</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negroamaro</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira et al., 2008</xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wine</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lourerio, Alvarinho</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Becatti et al., 2014</xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wine</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sangiovese</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">G&#x000f3;mez Garc&#x000ed;a-Carpintero et al., 2011a</xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wine</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bobal</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">G&#x000f3;mez Garc&#x000ed;a-Carpintero et al., 2011b</xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wine</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moravia Agria</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">G&#x000f3;mez Garc&#x000ed;a-Carpintero et al., 2012</xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wine</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moravia Dulce, Rojal, Tortosi</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Boido et al., 2003</xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grape</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tannat</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Ghaste et al., 2015</xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grape</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F3P30, IASMA ECO3, F3P63, Riesling, Gew&#x000fc;rztraminer, Moscato Rosa<sup>&#x02217;</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Bureau et al., 2000</xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grape</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Muscat of Frontignan</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Canosa et al., 2011</xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grape</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Menc&#x000ed;a, Espadeiro, Ca&#x000ed;&#x000f1;o Redondo, Pedral, Sous&#x000f3;n</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Fenoll et al., 2009</xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grape</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Muscat Hamburg</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Genisheva and Oliveira, 2009</xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grape</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alvarinho, Arinto, Avesso, Azal, Batoca, Lourerio, Trajadura</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">Ugliano and Moio, 2008</xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grape</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fiano</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">Vrhovsek et al., 2014</xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grape</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sauvignon Blanc, Chardonnay, Gew&#x000fc;rztraminer, Gr&#x000fc;ner Veltliner, Sangiovese</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Hell&#x000ed;n et al., 2010</xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grape</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Superior Seedless</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Lopez-Tammames et al., 1997</xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grape</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Albarinho, Listan, Treixadura, Greanche, Parellada, Tempranillo, Viura, Xarel&#x022c5;lo</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Baek and Cadwallader, 1999</xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grape</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Vitis rotundifolia</italic> (Muscadine)<sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib><italic><sup>&#x02217;</sup>Non-vinifera genotypes (Nero, Isabella, <italic>Vitis arizonica</italic> and <italic>Vitis cinerea</italic>) were excluded from the quantitative analysis. <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup>Excluded from the quantitative analysis.</italic></attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Data Curation</title><p>Molecule names and their Kovats retention indices were aggregated in one file and manually checked for duplicates (synonyms), which resulted in 385 unique molecules. They were assigned to one of the 16 classes of volatiles (aliphatic alcohol, ketone, aldehyde, ester, or acid, monoterpene, norisoprenoid, sulfur-containing, phenol, aromatic alcohol, ketone, aldehyde, ester, or acid, nitrogen-containing or other). Two hundred and forty-four unique molecules appeared in less than three publications and were excluded from further analysis because of insufficient information. Kovats retention indices of the remaining 141 compounds were compared and in the cases where standard deviation of the retention indices exceeded 50, outliers were excluded (annotation of a compound was considered incorrect in this particular publication and was excluded from the dataset).</p><p>We paid particular attention to geometric isomers of some compounds, which elute close to each other and have similar or identical mass spectra and are therefore often misannotated. Such pairs of compounds are: pyranic linalool oxides, furanic linalool oxides and 8-hydroxylinalools. In case of pyranic linalool oxides, the two isomers were incorrectly annotated in the first paper reporting their structure (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Felix et al., 1963</xref>). This error was identified and corrected later (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Kreis et al., 1996</xref>), but some authors continued to use the incorrect annotation. All the data were curated so that the first eluted furanoid linalool oxide was re-annotated as <italic>trans</italic> isomer, and the second one as <italic>cis</italic>. Similarly, the first eluted pyranoid linalool oxide was annotated as <italic>trans</italic> and the second one as <italic>cis</italic> (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Luan et al., 2006b</xref>). Retention indices of (<italic>Z</italic>) and (<italic>E</italic>)-8-hydroxylinalool were first reported in (<xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">Winterhalter et al., 1986</xref>) and the author claimed the NMR spectra were in agreement with previously published data. However, in a subsequent publication (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Chassagne et al., 1999</xref>), which is also cited in the widely used database of volatiles Pherobase<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn01">1</xref></sup>, the retention indices of the two compounds are inverted even if the author received standards from the author of (<xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">Winterhalter et al., 1986</xref>). Recent publication (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Hofer et al., 2014</xref>) confirms the correct elution order is (<italic>Z</italic>)-, followed by (<italic>E</italic>)-8-hydroxylinalool, as reported in the original publication (<xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">Winterhalter et al., 1986</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Statistical analysis was performed using the R software version 3.0.2 (<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">R Development Core Team, 2011</xref>). For quantitative analysis 43 molecules with more than 30 data points were selected from the pool of 141 validated compounds. Concentrations of these compounds in free and glycoside bound forms were then extracted from the 20 publications. If a compound was only detected in the free fraction, it was assigned a concentration of 0 in the glycosylated fraction, and vice versa. Labels &#x0201c;not detectable&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;not quantifiable&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;trace&#x0201d; were all converted to zero concentration. Concentrations of free and bound form of each molecule were then added to get the &#x0201c;total concentration&#x0201d;. &#x0201c;Fraction glycosylated&#x0201d; was calculated by dividing the concentration of glycosylated compound with the total concentration.</p><p>Concentration units were not the same in all studies. All concentrations in wines were reported in &#x003bc;g L<sup>-1</sup>, some concentrations in grapes were reported in &#x003bc;g L<sup>-1</sup> and some in &#x003bc;g kg<sup>-1</sup>. In addition, grape juice and wine have a different density, so the concentrations are not directly comparable, but since we compared them on a logarithmic scale we considered these differences negligible and did not adjust for them.</p><p>Log-transformed concentrations were compared using a two-sided <italic>t</italic>-test. Only molecules with 5 or more data points in each category (grape and wine) were included. Glycosylated fractions were compared using Mann-Whitney&#x02013;Wilcoxon <italic>u</italic> test. Correlations were calculated on total concentrations (free + glycosylated) for compounds with more than 40 complete observations. Linear models for linalool derivatives were calculated on log total molar concentrations (free + glycosylated) with non-zero values. Linalool derivatives with low R<sup>2</sup> value (&#x0003c;0.45) were excluded from the graph [hotrienol, (<italic>cis</italic>)-linalool oxide (pyranoid)]. Data, residuals normality and leverage were visually evaluated for each model.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec><title>Composition of Wine Aroma</title><p>Analysis of 19 publications describing grape or wine aroma revealed 385 different volatile organic compounds. More than half of them were only identified in one or two studies, and were eliminated from further analysis to account for the possibility of incorrect identification. Some of the eliminated compounds might be important varietal compounds, but this study focuses on the similarities, not the differences between the varieties. The remaining 141 validated volatile compounds (<bold>Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref></bold>) were assigned to one of the 12 classes based on their chemical structure and biosynthetic origin. Authors of most reviews make a clear distinction between grape and fermentation derived wine aroma (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Ebeler, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Dunlevy et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">Styger et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">Robinson et al., 2014</xref>) and therefore use a different classification of wine aroma components. Classes defined in this study are based on classifications from other authors, while trying to contain all the molecules and to minimize the overlap between classes. The most represented classes (with respect to the number of validated compounds) were aliphatic alcohols, aliphatic esters, monoterpenes and volatile phenols (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref></bold>).</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>List of grape and wine volatiles reported in at least three studies with mean retention indices.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compound</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RI</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compound</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RI</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compound</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RI</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Aliphatic alcohols</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methanol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">879</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-heptanol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1318</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<italic>E</italic>)-2-hexen-1-ol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1408</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1-propanol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1045</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4-methyl-1-pentanol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1319</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<italic>Z</italic>)-2-hexen-1-ol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1414</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-methyl-propanol (isobutanol)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1085</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<italic>Z</italic>)-2-penten-1-ol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1321</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1-octen-3-ol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1452</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1-butanol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1146</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-methyl-1-pentanol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1326</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1-heptanol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1460</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-methyl-1-butanol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1212</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1-hexanol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1357</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-ethyl-1-hexanol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1497</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-methyl-1-butanol (isoamyl alcohol)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1213</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<italic>E</italic>)-3-hexen-1-ol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1371</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,3-butanediol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1547</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1-pentanol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1249</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-ethoxy-1-propanol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1377</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1-octanol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1561</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-methyl-3-buten-1-ol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1252</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<italic>Z</italic>)-3-hexen-1-ol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1387</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Aliphatic ketones</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-hydroxy-2-butanone (acetoin)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1284</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Aliphatic aldehydes</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hexanal</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1095</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<italic>E</italic>)-2-hexenal</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1223</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Aliphatic esters</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethyl acetate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">836</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethyl lactate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1336</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diethyl succinate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1688</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isobutyl acetate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1012</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethyl octanoate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1437</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethyl methyl succinate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1743</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethyl butanoate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1055</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-hydroxy 2-methylpropyl butyrate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1461</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methyl 4-hydroxybutyrate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1783</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethyl 3-methylbutanoate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1070</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethyl 3-hydroxybutanoate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1509</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethyl 4-hydroxybutyrate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1822</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Butyl acetate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1070</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethyl lactate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1336</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethyl dodecanoate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1852</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isoamyl acetate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1134</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diethyl malonate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1597</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diethyl malate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2057</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethyl hexanoate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1218</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methyl decanoate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1629</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethyl succinate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2359</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hexyl acetate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1285</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethyl decanoate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1650</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethyl 4-hydroxybutyrate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1822</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Aliphatic acids</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acetic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1440</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pentanoic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1705</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Decanoic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2293</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Propanoic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1524</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hexanoic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1835</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dodecanoic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2447</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-methylpropanoic acid (isobutyric acid)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1579</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<italic>E</italic>)-2-hexenoic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1942</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tetradecanoic acid (myristic acid)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2669</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Butanoic acid (butyric acid)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1617</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Octanoic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2055</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isovaleric acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1659</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nonanoic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2142</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Monoterpenes</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limonene</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1202</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Citral/ (<italic>E</italic>)-geranial</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1743</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6-hydroxylinalool (diendiol II)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2152</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>trans</italic>-linalool oxide (F)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1447</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Citronellol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1764</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8-hydroxy-6,7-dihydrolinalool</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2217</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cis</italic>-linalool oxide (F)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1476</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cis</italic>-linalool oxide (P)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1766</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<italic>Z</italic>)-8-hydroxylinalool</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2274</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linalool</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1547</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nerol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1811</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<italic>E</italic>)-8-hydroxylinalool</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2304</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Terpinen-4-ol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1599</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geraniol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1846</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geranic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2317</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hotrienol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1624</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exo-2-hydroxy-1,8-cineole</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1851</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p</italic>-menth-1-ene-7,8-diol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2502</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">alpha-terpineol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1697</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7-hydroxylinalool (diendiol I)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1950</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>trans</italic>-linalool oxide (P)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1727</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7-hydroxy-6,7-dihydrolinalool</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1988</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Norisoprenoids</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4-oxo-isophorone</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1703</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,4-dihydro-3-oxo-actinidol II</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2420</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-hydroxy-7,8-dihydro-beta-ionol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2684</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2;-damascenone</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1804</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-hydroxy-&#x003b2;-damascone</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2553</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-hydroxy-7,8-dehydro-&#x003b2;-ionol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2732</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,4-dihydro-3-oxo-actinidol I</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2382</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dehydrovomifoliol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2554</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vomifoliol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3148</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,4-dihydro-3-oxo-actinidol III</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2412</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-oxo-alpha-ionol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2617</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sulfur-containing volatiles</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3(2H)-2-methyldihydro-thiophenone</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1505</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-methylthiopropanoic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1757</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,2-benzothiazole</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-(methylthio)-1-propanol (methionol)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1719</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Volatile phenols</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methyl salicylate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1779</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syringol (2,6-dimethoxyphenol)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2243</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethyl vanillate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2676</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Guaiacol (2-methoxyphenol)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1869</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isoeugenol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2302</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,4-dimethoxyphenol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2756</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phenol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1982</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methyl salicylate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1779</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zingerone</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2796</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4-ethylguaiacol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2055</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Guaiacol (2-methoxyphenol)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1869</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tyrosol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3008</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4-methyl phenol (p-cresol)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2087</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4-methoxyphenylethyl alcohol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2302</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methyl vanillyl eter</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3030</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-methyl phenol (m-cresol)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2119</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4-vinylphenol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2388</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,4,5-trimethoxyphenol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3032</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eugenol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2181</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<italic>E</italic>)-4-allylsyringol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2424</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4-methoxyphenylethyl alcohol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2302</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4-ethylphenol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2187</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vanillin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2550</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4-vinylphenol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2388</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p</italic>-vinylguaiacol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2200</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methyl vanillate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2568</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4-hydroxy-2-methyl acetophenone</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2212</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acetovanillone (Apocynin)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2654</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>Benzenoids</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benzaldehyde</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1519</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethyl benzene acetate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1782</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethyl cinnamate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2286</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phenylacetaldehyde</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1639</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-phenyl ethyl acetate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1809</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benzoic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2391</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acetophenone</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1667</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benzyl alcohol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1883</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benzylacetic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2502</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethylbenzaldehyde</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1728</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-phenylethanol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1913</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cinnamic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3045</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benzyl acetate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1735</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benzenepropanol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2037</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>Nitrogen-containing volatiles</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N</italic>-ethyl-benzamine</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1750</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N</italic>-(2-phenylethyl)-acetamide</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2563</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>Other volatiles</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gamma-butyrolactone</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1628</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Furaneol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2023</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,3-dihydrobenzofuran</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2377</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p><bold>Classes of grape and wine volatile compounds evaluated in this study. (A)</bold> Classes of volatiles with examples. <bold>(B)</bold> Number of different molecules from each class that were included in this study. <bold>(C)</bold> Euler diagram of wine volatiles included in this study and key food and wine odorants, identified in two other meta-analyses. Two other meta-analyses identified volatile compounds with the strongest impact on aroma of food (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Dunkel et al., 2014</xref>) and wine (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Francis and Newton, 2005</xref>). While the overlap between the three studies is sizeable, many key odorants are not detected in volatile profiling experiments. Each tile represents one volatile molecule and its color corresponds to the molecular class.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-07-01472-g001"/></fig><p>Not all volatiles contribute to the aroma equally. Their impact depends on their concentration, as well as aroma intensity. The latter is usually expressed as the odor detection threshold, which is the lowest concentration of a particular compound that can be detected by the human smell. In a recent meta-analysis, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Dunkel et al. (2014)</xref> compiled a list of food volatiles occurring at concentrations exceeding their odor detection threshold, and named them key food odorants. Somehow surprisingly, a total of only 220 key food odorants are responsible for the aroma of most of the foods and beverages we consume, and among those fewer than 40 contribute to aroma of an individual food item. Another meta-analysis identified 57 key wine odorants, which were identified as wine volatiles with concentrations above their odor detection threshold. All but 2 of these volatiles are also included among the 220 key food odorants. Only 60% (<italic>N</italic> = 35) of those key wine odorants overlap with our set of common wine volatiles, compiled from non-targeted profiling experiments (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref></bold>). We named that group &#x0201c;evident&#x0201d; key odorants. The other 40% (<italic>N</italic> = 22) of key wine odorants are overlooked in non-targeted volatile profiling experiments, presumably because of their low concentrations. We named that group of volatiles &#x0201c;hidden&#x0201d; key odorants. The two largest groups within the hidden key odorants are sulfur-containing volatiles and fatty acid lactones (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S1</xref>). Several sulfanyl (or mercapto) alcohols were identified as important varietal compounds in Sauvignon Blanc and many other varieties, but their low abundance requires the use of targeted analytical methods, such as stable isotope dilution analysis (SIDA) for their quantification (<xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">Roland et al., 2011</xref>) and were therefore not among the volatiles included in this study. Even among monoterpenes, one of the largest classes in our study, two odor-active molecules (<italic>cis</italic>-rose oxide and wine lactone) are not detected in non-targeted volatile profiling experiments. Conversely, the high-impact aliphatic alcohols, acids and esters, as well as phenols and benzenoids, are apparently present in sufficient concentrations to be easily detectable in profiling experiments. A last group of 15 common wine volatiles features on the list of key food odorants, but not the key wine odorants. We labeled those compounds &#x0201c;potential&#x0201d; key odorants (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S1</xref>). The progress in analytical chemistry will likely permit discovery of more key wine odorants in the future. Rotundone, the odorant conferring the peppery character to Shiraz wines, was only discovered recently (<xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">Wood et al., 2008</xref>) and was not included neither among the key food odorants nor the key wine odorants.</p><p>Although odor detection threshold is commonly used to describe an influence of a particular compound on aroma, this value needs to be used with caution for describing complex aroma mixtures, such as wines. Both synergistic and antagonistic effects can occur in odor perception. Sometimes a mixture of compounds can be perceived even if all components are at sub-threshold concentrations. Conversely, some compounds can mask the perception of other compounds, so they remain undetected at supra-threshold concentrations (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Dalton et al., 2000</xref>; <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Ishii et al., 2008</xref>). In addition, odor detection threshold is averaged across the population. Because of the variability in odor receptor genes in human population, each individual has a highly personalized odor perception (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Mainland et al., 2013</xref>). Finally, threshold values are not known for all the wine volatiles. For these reasons we decided to include all the volatiles, not just the key wine odorants, in our meta-analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>Origin and Evolution of Wine Aroma</title><p>During the winemaking process the aroma undergoes major changes, in particular deglycosylation of aroma compounds synthesized in grapes and biosynthesis of new compounds. To analyze these changes quantitatively we selected 43 compounds with sufficient number of available data points (&#x0003e;30) across the 82 volatile profiling datasets. For each compound we computed the total concentration (the sum of free and bound concentration) and percentage that is glycosylated (bound/total concentration), and tested for differences between these values in grapes and wines (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>). These differences in concentration and degree of glycosylation are largely characteristic of each class of molecules.</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p><bold>Comparison of the total concentration <bold>(left)</bold> and percentage of glycosylation <bold>(right)</bold> of selected grape and wine volatile organic compounds.</bold> &#x0201c;Total concentration&#x0201d; is the sum of &#x0201c;free&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;bound&#x0201d; concentration and &#x0201c;percentage glycosylated&#x0201d; is &#x0201c;bound concentration&#x0201d; divided by &#x0201c;total concentration.&#x0201d; Each point represents one grape or wine sample from one of the 19 publications included in the study. Non-detected compounds (concentration zero) were assigned a concentration 0.01 &#x003bc;g L<sup>-1</sup> to allow their representation on a logarithmic scale. Gray dots on the right indicate significant difference between grapes and wines and their size is proportional to the p-value of the statistical test. Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test was used on log-transformed concentrations and Wilcoxon rank sum test was used on glycosylated fraction.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-07-01472-g002"/></fig><sec><title>Aliphatic Alcohols</title><p>Aliphatic alcohols are a diverse group of compounds that can originate both from grapes and yeast fermentation. C6-alcohols are a common group of plant volatiles with six carbon atoms and have a characteristic &#x0201c;green&#x0201d; aroma, reminiscent of leaves and fresh cut grass. They are formed from the corresponding C6-aldehydes, also important aroma compounds, by alcohol dehydrogenase enzymes. C6-aldehydes are products of hydroxyperoxide lyase (CYP74) enzymes (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Matsui, 2006</xref>), which were recently characterized in grapevine (<xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et al., 2012</xref>). C6 alcohols can be consumed by the yeast during fermentation (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Mauricio et al., 1997</xref>), which may explain why concentration of (<italic>E</italic>)-2-hexen-1-ol is lower in wines compared to grapes.</p><p>High levels of short chain alcohols, also known as fusel alcohols, can negatively impact wine aroma (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Ebeler and Thorngate, 2009</xref>). They are formed by the yeast during fermentation from amino acid catabolism (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Mauricio et al., 1997</xref>). A typical example is isoamyl alcohol, the concentration of which is much higher in wines compared to grapes and is also the most abundant compound in this study (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>).</p><p>Aliphatic alcohols also contribute to the aroma as precursors of esters, which are discussed below.</p></sec><sec><title>Aliphatic Acids</title><p>The yeast produces aliphatic acids during fermentation (<xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">Styger et al., 2011</xref>) from primary metabolites: long aliphatic acids (C6 and above) are derived from fatty acids, short and branched aliphatic acids are derived from amino acids and acetic acid is derived from sugar. Aroma of volatile fatty acids is generally unpleasant, ranging from sweaty and cheesy to goaty and rancid. Although all aliphatic acids included in this study were detected in both grapes and wines, their concentration was significantly higher in wines (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>), confirming they are predominantly a fermentation product.</p><p>Longer aliphatic acids (C8 and C10) in grapes are glycosylated at least to some extent, which is unexpected because they lack a hydroxyl group to which the sugar moiety is usually attached. Instead, they are probably stored as glucose esters, a less common type of glycoconjugate, where sugar and aglycone are connected via an ester bond. Fatty acid glucose esters have been described in other plants (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Dembitsky, 2004</xref>), but their role as wine aroma precursors has not yet been extensively studied.</p><p>Aliphatic acids can be transformed to more pleasant smelling compounds, such as esters (described below) and lactones. Five fatty acid derived lactones (&#x003b3;-nonalactone, &#x003b3;-decalactone, &#x003b3;-dodecalactone, &#x003b3;-(<italic>Z</italic>)-6-dodecenolactone and (<italic>Z</italic>)-oak lactone, also known as whisky lactone), are among the &#x0201c;hidden&#x0201d; key wine odorants, presumably because of their low concentration in wines (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Francis and Newton, 2005</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Aliphatic Esters</title><p>Esters are a group of volatiles that contribute to fruity notes of wine and other fermented beverages. They are produced during fermentation from alcohol and acyl-CoA by yeast alcohol acyltransferase enzymes, which explains why their concentrations in grapes are negligible (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>).</p><p>The two major groups of esters in wine are ethyl esters and acetate esters. The concentration of ethyl esters of medium-chain fatty acids depends on the concentration of the fatty acid precursor (<xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">Saerens et al., 2008</xref>). Our data confirms this observation: concentrations of ethyl hexanoate and ethyl octanoate are strongly positively correlated to concentrations of their precursors, hexanoic and octanoic acids, respectively (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref></bold>). Similar relationship was recently found for C9 and, to a lesser extent, C12 ethyl esters (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Boss et al., 2015</xref>). While hexanoic acid is predominantly a fermentation product, non-negligible amounts are present in grapes as well. The biosynthesis of hexanoic acid in grapes could thus influence the concentration of a typical fermentation product, ethyl hexanoate, in wine.</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>FIGURE 3</label><caption><p><bold>Relationships between the concentrations of esters and their precursors in wines. (A)</bold> Concentration of ethyl hexanoate is correlated to concentration of hexanoic acid (<italic>R</italic> = 0.780, <italic>p</italic>-value &#x0003c; 0.001) and <bold>(B)</bold> concentration of ethyl butanoate is correlated to concentration of octanoic acid (<italic>R</italic> = 0.830, <italic>p</italic>-value &#x0003c; 0.001). Concentrations of isoamyl acetate <bold>(C)</bold> and hexyl acetate <bold>(D)</bold> are not correlated to the concentration of their alcohol precursor (&#x003b1; = 0.01).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-07-01472-g003"/></fig><p>Conversely, precursor concentration does not determine the concentration of acetate esters. The limiting factor in the production of acetate esters by <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> is expression of the alcohol acetyltransferase gene in yeast (<xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">Verstrepen et al., 2003</xref>). Indeed, isoamyl acetate and hexyl acetate do not correlate to the concentrations of their precursors (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref></bold>).</p></sec><sec><title>Monoterpenes</title><p>Monoterpenes are a large class of plant specialized metabolites. They are built from two isoprenoid units, which constitute a backbone of 10 carbon atoms. These compounds give many fruits, flowers, herbs, and spices their characteristic aroma. Most of the wine monoterpenes contribute toward floral and citrusy notes. For example, monoterpenols and their derivatives give the characteristic aroma to Muscat (<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">Rib&#x000e9;reau-Gayon et al., 1975</xref>) and Gewurztraminer (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Guth, 1997</xref>) wines. High monoterpenol concentration in these cultivars results from a mutation in an early terpenoid biosynthesis gene deoxy-<sc>D</sc>-xylulose synthase (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Battilana et al., 2009</xref>, <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Duch&#x000ea;ne et al., 2009</xref>). Our data show that monoterpenols span a large concentration range in grapes and wines (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>) which points to their role as varietal aroma compounds in some grapevine varieties. Unlike other classes of volatiles described here their concentrations in grapes and wines are similar, as expected for grape-derived compounds. Conversely, the glycosylated percentage of many terpene compounds is lower in wines compared to grapes, suggesting fermentation nonetheless affects the monoterpene content in wine by releasing volatile monoterpenes from their glycosylated precursors.</p><p>Monoterpenes are products of terpene synthase enzymes. The terpene synthase gene family has expanded in grapevine, which underlines the importance of terpenoids in this species (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Martin et al., 2010</xref>). More than half of the terpene synthase genes have been functionally characterized (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Martin et al., 2010</xref>) and were found to produce a large number of different mono- and sesquiterpene backbones <italic>in vitro</italic>. Interestingly, this variability is not reflected in the volatile profiles of grapes and wines in our selected studies.</p><p>Sesquiterpenes do not appear in our dataset of 141 validated volatiles. However, a labeling study revealed production of 14 sesquiterpenes in grape skins of two different varieties, suggesting the sesquiterpene metabolism in grapes is nonetheless active (<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">May et al., 2013</xref>). The concentrations of sesquiterpenes in grapes and wines are probably too low to be detected in non-targeted profiling experiments, but they do contribute to wine aroma of at least some varieties: rotundone, an oxygenated sesquiterpene, is responsible for the peppery aroma of Shiraz wines (<xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">Wood et al., 2008</xref>). Recent reports suggest higher concentrations of rotundone in Shiraz are due to mutations in one of the sesquiterpene synthase genes (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Drew et al., 2016</xref>) in this cultivar. These mutations change the activity of the enzyme and cause production of &#x003b1;-guaiene, which is subsequently oxidized by a cytochrome P450 enzyme CYP71BE5 (<xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">Takase et al., 2016</xref>).</p><p>Monoterpenes, on the other hand, are one of the largest molecular classes in our study, with 22 different molecules identified in grapes or wines (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref></bold>). Interestingly, this large chemical variability among wine monoterpenes does not result from the variability of different backbones synthesized by terpene synthases. Half of the validated monoterpenes in this study are derivatives of the same monoterpene: linalool. Seemingly the variability of monoterpenes in grapes arises from the enzymes that oxygenate linalool at different positions.</p><p>Elaborate oxidative linalool metabolism in grapevine was previously demonstrated by feeding experiments (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Luan et al., 2006a</xref>). All of the described linalool derivatives, with the exception of nerol oxide, 6,7-epoxylinalool and 6,7-dihydroxylinalool are also present on our list of validated volatiles. Common metabolic origin of monoterpenes, in particular linalool derivatives, is also apparent from the correlation matrix of grape and wine volatiles (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref></bold>). Linalool is positively correlated to all the monoterpenes included in the study, which supports its role as a central monoterpene metabolite in grapes. Enzymes catalyzing linalool oxidation in grapes have not yet been identified but, in other plants, enzymes from the cytochrome P450 superfamily were shown to oxidize monoterpenes (reviewed in <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Ilc et al., 2016</xref>), including linalool (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Ginglinger et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Hofer et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Boachon et al., 2015</xref>). Hydroxylated linalool derivatives were discovered in grapes in early 1980s (<xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">Williams et al., 1980a</xref>; <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">Strauss et al., 1988</xref>). These compounds have a very weak odor so they are unlikely to contribute to the wine aroma directly, but they may nonetheless contribute to the aroma indirectly. They were found to spontaneously transform to compounds with strong aroma in conditions mimicking wine maturation. In acidic conditions they undergo spontaneous elimination of water and rearrangement to either linear (hotrienol) or cyclic compounds (linalool oxides; <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">Williams et al., 1980b</xref>). Although low concentrations of hotrienol were also detected in grapes, its concentration in wines is significantly higher (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>), which supports the hypothesis of acid-catalyzed formation from 7-hydroxylinalool during winemaking and wine maturation. In addition, concentrations of 7-hydroxylinalool and hotrienol are strongly correlated (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref></bold>). We do not, however, find the same evidence for non-enzymatic formation of linalool oxides from 6,7-dihydroxylinalool or 6,7-epoxylinalool. Not only these two putative linalool oxide precursors were not detected in any of the experiments, but the concentrations of linalool oxides were also comparable in wines and grapes. In addition linalool oxides are glycosylated to a very high degree in grapes, which suggests they are formed in metabolically active grape berries, as demonstrated previously in the feeding study (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Luan et al., 2006a</xref>). Formation through acid-catalyzed cyclisation during wine maturation is therefore probably of lesser significance.</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>FIGURE 4</label><caption><p><bold>Correlation matrix of selected volatile compounds in wines and grapes.</bold> Total concentrations were log-transformed prior to calculation of correlation. Only the compounds with more than 40 data points were included in the calculation. Color (see color scale) and dot size are proportional to the correlation coefficient. Only coefficients with <italic>p</italic>-value &#x0003c; 0.001 are displayed. Nor., norisoprenoids; Benz., benzenoids.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-07-01472-g004"/></fig><p>From a single profiling experiment, it is difficult to estimate what proportion of the total linalool pool is transformed to oxygenated derivatives, mainly because not all derivatives are quantified in all the experiments. Strong correlation between concentrations of monoterpenes in the studies included in this meta-analysis (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref></bold>) allowed us to describe relationships between concentrations of linalool and its oxygenated derivatives with a set of linear models (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">S2</xref>). In the investigated concentration range (0.001&#x02013;10 &#x003bc;M) most of linalool is oxygenated (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref></bold>). At low concentrations virtually all linalool (97%) is oxygenated and the main linalool derivative is (<italic>E</italic>)-8-hydroxylinalool. At high concentrations, oxygenated derivatives represent 52% of the complete linalool pool, and the most abundant derivative is 7-hydroxylinalool. 6-hydroxylinalool and linalool oxides represent a minor part of the linalool derivatives. The total fraction of oxygenated linalool derivatives in the linalool pool is underestimated since not all linalool derivatives were included in the calculation.</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>FIGURE 5</label><caption><p><bold>Linalool derivatives in grapes and wines <bold>(A)</bold> and estimated flux of linalool to different oxygenated derivatives <bold>(B)</bold>.</bold> Relationship between log concentrations of each linalool derivative and linalool was described with a linear regression. These models were then used to estimate the concentration of each derivative in the function of linalool concentration. (<italic>cis</italic>)-linalool oxide (F) and hotrienol were excluded from the figure because of low <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> value (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">S2</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-07-01472-g005"/></fig><p>Monoterpenes in grapes are predominantly glycosylated, although variation between the samples is high (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>). Since only free compounds can impact the wine aroma, this variability could be important for varietal characteristics. Several monoterpenes are glycosylated to a lesser extent in wines as compared to grapes. This can be attributed to hydrolysis of glycosides by the yeast during fermentation, as well as acid hydrolysis during wine maturation.</p><p>In spite of the large number of monoterpenes included in this study, the list presented here is not exhaustive. The lowest limit of quantification in the analyzed set of profiling experiments is around 10<sup>-7</sup> &#x003bc;g L<sup>-1</sup> (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>) and concentrations of some monoterpenes, including key wine odorants rose oxide or wine lactone, are below this limit. Furthermore, another linalool derivative, (<italic>E</italic>)-8-carboxylinalool, has been detected in grapes and wines, but is not detectable by gas chromatography, hence the absence from the data collected here. This compound also indirectly influences wine aroma as a precursor to wine lactone.</p></sec><sec><title>Norisoprenoids</title><p>Norisoprenoids are a group of carotenoid-derived metabolites. Similarly to monoterpenes, their aroma is mostly described as floral or fruity, although some, for example 1,1,6-trimethyl-1,2-dihydronaphthalene (TDN) which is described as petrol or kerosene-like, can have a negative impact on aroma (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Marais et al., 1992</xref>).</p><p>Norisoprenoids are synthesized by carotenoid cleavage dioxygenases, enzymes that cleave carotenoid substrates at different in-chain positions, yielding products of different sizes. All the norisoprenoids in this study have 13 carbon atoms (C13-norisoprenoids), with the exception of 4-oxoisosporone (C9).</p><p>The most abundant carotenoids in grapes are &#x003b2;-carotenoid, lutein, violaxanthin and neoxanthin (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Baumes et al., 2002</xref>). Most of the norisoprenoids in this study are derived from neoxanthin (<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Mendes-Pinto, 2009</xref>). A carotenoid cleavage dioxygenase from grapevine was characterized (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Mathieu et al., 2005</xref>), but it was shown to cleave zeaxanthin, a minor grape carotenoid, whereas neoxanthin was not tested as a substrate.</p><p>The chemical diversity of norisoprenoids in grapes appears to originate from different non-enzymatic reactions, including photooxygenation, thermal degradation or acid hydrolysis (<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Mendes-Pinto, 2009</xref>). Although norisoprenoids are considered grape-derived metabolites, our data show higher concentrations of two norisoprenoids (3-hydroxy-&#x003b2;-damascone and 3-oxo-&#x003b1;-ionol) in wines as compared to the grapes (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>).</p></sec><sec><title>Volatile Phenols</title><p>Volatile phenols are a heterogeneous group of wine volatiles with respect to both their origin and impact on wine aroma. Many of them are common plant volatiles, derived from ferulic acid or related metabolites, and contribute to pleasant spicy aroma notes. Although enzymes catalyzing their biosynthesis have not yet been characterized in grapes, they have been studied in other plants. Examples include clove aroma eugenol, which is synthesized by an enzyme reducing coniferyl acetate in basil or petunia flowers (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Koeduka et al., 2006</xref>), or vanillin, synthesized from ferulic acid by a hydratase/lyase enzyme in vanilla pods (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Gallage et al., 2014</xref>). Most of volatile phenols are stored in grapes as glycosides, and can be hydrolyzed during winemaking. It is noteworthy that vanillin in wine can also originate from aging in oak barrels (<xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">Spillman et al., 1997</xref>).</p><p>Not all volatile phenols are associated with pleasant aroma: some of them, for example guaiacol, are described as smokey, ashy, or medicinal, and are considered off-flavors in wine. These compounds can originate from fermentation, contamination with spoilage yeast <italic>Brettanomyces</italic> (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Chatonnet et al., 1992</xref>) or smoke exposure of grapes, for example from nearby forest fires (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Hayasaka et al., 2010</xref>). Concentration of guaiacol is much higher in wines compared to grapes (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>), which confirms fermentation origin of this compound. Interestingly, some authors suggested that glycosylated precursors from grapes represent only a minor source of <italic>p</italic>-vinyl guaiacol in wine (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Chatonnet et al., 1993</xref>), but our data suggest this contribution can be substantial.</p></sec><sec><title>Benzenoids</title><p>Benzenoid compounds in wines are cinnamic acid derivatives with varying side chain lengths and oxidation states. Phenylethanol and phenylacetaldehyde have a weak floral aroma. The high odor detection threshold of phenylethanol is compensated by its high concentration. Although these volatiles can be produced by both plants (<xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">Tieman et al., 2006</xref>) and yeast (<xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">Vuralhan et al., 2005</xref>), their concentration in wines is generally much higher than in grapes, which suggests that contribution from yeast is larger (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>). An exception is phenylacetaldehyde, concentration of which is higher in grapes compared to wines and which is reduced by the yeast to yield 2-phenylethanol.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Meta-analysis is a powerful approach that allows to summarize and draw new conclusions from a collection of existing data. While most studies focus on the differences in volatile profiles between varieties or grapes subjected to different viticultural practices, we attempted to highlight the common characteristics of grape and wine volatile profiles. The inventory we compiled from 20 publications (<bold>Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref></bold>) should facilitate peak annotation of non-targeted profiling experiments, and help researchers compare their results to data from other experiments. Our analysis also serves as a reminder that while non-targeted profiling allows quantification a large number of different volatiles, it can easily miss some important odor-active compounds. A targeted approach is required for the detection of low-abundant volatiles, such as sulfur-containing volatiles or fatty acid derived lactones, which influence wine aroma because of their low odor detection threshold. In the future, new hidden key wine odorants, which have so far slipped under the radar of non-targeted analysis, will likely be discovered using more sensitive methods.</p><p>Quantitative analysis of wine and grape profiling data revealed large variations spanning several orders of magnitude in concentrations among different compounds and samples. We paid particular attention to variation between grape and wine samples to highlight the changes that occur in the volatile composition during the winemaking process. Although wine aroma compounds are traditionally divided into three classes, based on their origin&#x02014;grape-derived, fermentation-derived and aging-derived&#x02014;our analysis showed that concentrations of many compounds can be influenced by all three processes. They are connected to both grape and yeast metabolic networks and, in addition, undergo chemical transformations. For example, many grape-derived volatiles accumulate in berries essentially as glycosylated derivatives, which are subsequently hydrolyzed during the winemaking process. We furthermore showed that concentrations of some groups of compounds, such as monoterpenes, are tightly correlated, which is indicative of their common metabolic origin. Linalool, a typical aroma of floral-scented wines, has a particularly rich oxidative metabolism. We showed that most of the linalool in grapes is oxygenated to a variety of different compounds. Linalool oxygenases thus not only influence wine aroma by formation of new compounds, but also by depletion of linalool, one of the key wine odorants. Once more data will be available, similar relationships may transpire for other classes of compounds with so far poorly understood metabolism, such as norisoprenoids or phenolic compounds. Understanding metabolism of aroma compounds in grapes and during the fermentation could help wine industry anticipate the changes that occur during the winemaking process and their influence on wine quality.</p></sec><sec><title>Author Contributions</title><p>Investigation, TI; Formal Analysis, TI; Writing &#x02013; Original Draft, TI; Writing &#x02013; Review and Editing, NN and DW-R; Visualization, TI; Supervision, NN and DW-R; Project administration, DW-R; Funding Acquisition, DW-R.</p></sec><sec><title>Conflict of Interest Statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> The authors acknowledge the support of the Agence Nationale de la Recherche to the InteGrape project (ANR-13-BSV6-0010). The research leading to these results has received funding from the People Programme (Marie Curie Actions) of the European Union&#x02019;s 7th Framework Programme (FP7/2007-2013) to TI under REA Grant Agreement 289217.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><p>We thank Julien Denos for helpful discussions on data analysis. This publication reflects only the authors&#x02019; view and the European Union is not liable for any use that may be made of the information contained herein.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="fn01"><label>1</label><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pherobase.com/">http://www.pherobase.com/</ext-link></p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="supplementary material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://journal.frontiersin.org/article/10.3389/fpls.2016.01472">http://journal.frontiersin.org/article/10.3389/fpls.2016.01472</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1"><media xlink:href="Table_1.DOCX"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM2"><media xlink:href="Table_2.DOCX"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baek</surname><given-names>H. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cadwallader</surname><given-names>K. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Contribution of free and glycosidically bound volatile compounds to the aroma of muscadine grape juice.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Food Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>64</volume>
<fpage>441</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>444</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2621.1999.tb15059.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Battilana</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Costantini</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Emanuelli</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sevini</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Segala</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moser</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The 1-deoxy-d-xylulose 5-phosphate synthase gene co-localizes with a major QTL affecting monoterpene content in grapevine.</article-title>
<source><italic>Theor. Appl. Genet.</italic></source>
<volume>118</volume>
<fpage>653</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>669</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-008-0927-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19037624</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Battilana</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Emanuelli</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gambino</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gribaudo</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasperi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boss</surname><given-names>P. K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Functional effect of grapevine 1-deoxy-D-xylulose 5-phosphate synthase substitution K284N on Muscat flavour formation.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Exp. Bot.</italic></source>
<volume>62</volume>
<fpage>5497</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5508</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/err231</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21868399</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baumes</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wirth</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bureau</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunata</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Razungles</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Biogeneration of C13-norisoprenoid compounds: experiments supportive for an apo-carotenoid pathway in grapevines.</article-title>
<source><italic>Anal. Chim. Acta</italic></source>
<volume>458</volume>
<fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0003-2670(01)01589-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Becatti</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Genova</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranieri</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tonutti</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Postharvest treatments with ethylene on <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> (cv Sangiovese) grapes affect berry metabolism and wine composition.</article-title>
<source><italic>Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>159</volume>
<fpage>257</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>266</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2014.02.169</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24767053</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boachon</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Junker</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miesch</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bassard</surname><given-names>J.-E.</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000f6;fer</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Caillieaudeaux</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>CYP76C1 (Cytochrome P450)-mediated linalool metabolism and the formation of volatile and soluble linalool oxides in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flowers: a strategy for defense against floral antagonists.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell</italic></source>
<volume>27</volume>
<fpage>2972</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2990</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.15.00399</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26475865</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boido</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lloret</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Medina</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Far&#x000f1;ia</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrau</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Versini</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Aroma composition of <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> cv. Tannat: the typical red wine from Uruguay.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Agric. Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>51</volume>
<fpage>5408</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5413</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf030087i</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12926890</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boss</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeffery</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Potential grape-derived contributions to volatile ester concentrations in wine.</article-title>
<source><italic>Molecules</italic></source>
<volume>20</volume>
<fpage>7845</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7873</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules20057845</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25939071</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bureau</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Razungles</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumes</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>The aroma of Muscat of Frontignan grapes: effect of the light environment of vine or bunch on volatiles and glycoconjugates.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Sci. Food Agric.</italic></source>
<volume>80</volume>
<fpage>2012</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2020</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/1097-0010(200011)80:14&#x0003c;2012::AID-JSFA738&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-X</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Canosa</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Masa</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vilanova</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Study of the volatile and glycosidically bound compounds of minority <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> red cultivars from NW Spain.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Inst. Brew.</italic></source>
<volume>117</volume>
<fpage>462</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>471</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aca.2012.01.026</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chassagne</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boulanger</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crouzet</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Enzymatic hydrolysis of edible <italic>Passiflora fruit</italic> glycosides.</article-title>
<source><italic>Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>66</volume>
<fpage>281</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>288</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0308-8146(99)00044-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chatonnet</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubourdieu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boidron</surname><given-names>J. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavigne</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Synthesis of volatile phenols by <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> in wines.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Sci. Food Agric.</italic></source>
<volume>62</volume>
<fpage>191</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>202</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jsfa.2740620213</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chatonnet</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubourdie</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boidron</surname><given-names>J.-N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pons</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>The origin of ethylphenols in wines.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Sci. Food Agric.</italic></source>
<volume>60</volume>
<fpage>165</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>178</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jsfa.2740600205</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dalton</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Doolittle</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagata</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Breslin</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>The merging of the senses: integration of subthreshold taste and smell.</article-title>
<source><italic>Nat. Neurosci.</italic></source>
<volume>3</volume>
<fpage>431</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>432</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/74797</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10769380</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dembitsky</surname><given-names>V. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Chemistry and biodiversity of the biologically active natural glycosides.</article-title>
<source><italic>Chem. Biodivers.</italic></source>
<volume>1</volume>
<fpage>673</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>781</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cbdv.200490060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17191879</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drew</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>T. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sweetman</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000f8;ller</surname><given-names>B. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Simonsen</surname><given-names>H. T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Two key polymorphisms in a newly discovered allele of the <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> TPS24 gene are responsible for the production of the rotundone precursor &#x003b1;-guaiene.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Exp. Bot.</italic></source>
<volume>67</volume>
<fpage>799</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>808</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erv491</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26590310</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duch&#x000ea;ne</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Legras</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karst</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Merdinoglu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Claudel</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaegli</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Variation of linalool and geraniol content within two pairs of aromatic and non-aromatic grapevine clones.</article-title>
<source><italic>Aust. J. Grape Wine Res.</italic></source>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>120</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>130</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1755-0238.2008.00039.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dunkel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinhaus</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotthoff</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krautwurst</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schieberle</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Nature&#x02019;s chemical signatures in human olfaction: a foodborne perspective for future biotechnology.</article-title>
<source><italic>Angew. Chemie - Int. Ed. Engl</italic></source>. <volume>53</volume>
<fpage>7124</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7143</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/anie.201309508</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dunlevy</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalua</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keyzers</surname><given-names>R. R. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boss</surname><given-names>P. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>&#x0201c;The production of flavour and aroma compounds in grape berries,&#x0201d; in</article-title>
<source><italic>Grapevine Molecular Physiology and Biotechnology</italic></source>
<role>ed.</role>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Roubelakis-Angelakis</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>) <fpage>293</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>340</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-90-481-2305-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ebeler</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Analytical chemistry: unlocking the secrets of wine flavor.</article-title>
<source><italic>Food Rev. Int.</italic></source>
<volume>17</volume>
<fpage>45</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>64</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1081/FRI-100000517</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ebeler</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorngate</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Wine chemistry and flavor: looking into the crystal glass.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Agric. Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>57</volume>
<fpage>8098</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8108</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf9000555</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19719127</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Felix</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Melera</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seibl</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kovats</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1963</year>). <article-title>Zur kenntnis &#x000e4;therischer &#x000d6;le. 2. Mitteilung. Die Struktur der sogenannten &#x0201c;Linalooloxide&#x0201d;.</article-title>
<source><italic>Helv. Chim. Acta</italic></source>
<volume>46</volume>
<fpage>1513</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1536</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hlca.19630460507</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fenoll</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Manso</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Changes in the aromatic composition of the <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> grape Muscat Hamburg during ripening.</article-title>
<source><italic>Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>114</volume>
<fpage>420</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>428</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2008.09.060</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>I. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Newton</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Determining wine aroma from compositional data.</article-title>
<source><italic>Aust. J. Grape Wine Res.</italic></source>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>114</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>126</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1755-0238.2005.tb00283.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gallage</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>E. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kannangara</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Motawia</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>J&#x000f8;rgensen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Vanillin formation from ferulic acid in <italic>Vanilla planifolia</italic> is catalysed by a single enzyme.</article-title>
<source><italic>Nat. Commun.</italic></source>
<volume>5</volume>:<issue>4037</issue>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms5037</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Genisheva</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Monoterpenic characterization of white cultivars from Vinhos Verdes appellation of origin (North Portugal).</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Inst. Brew.</italic></source>
<volume>115</volume>
<fpage>308</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>317</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/j.2050-0416.2009.tb00386.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghaste</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Narduzzi</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vrhovsek</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shulaev</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattivi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Chemical composition of volatile aroma metabolites and their glycosylated precursors that can uniquely differentiate individual grape cultivars.</article-title>
<source><italic>Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>188</volume>
<fpage>309</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>319</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2015.04.056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26041197</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ginglinger</surname><given-names>J.-F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boachon</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000f6;fer</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paetz</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000f6;llner</surname><given-names>T. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miesch</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Gene coexpression analysis reveals complex metabolism of the monoterpene alcohol linalool in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flowers.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell</italic></source>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>4640</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4657</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.113.117382</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24285789</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>G&#x000f3;mez Garc&#x000ed;a-Carpintero</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez Palomo</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000f3;mez Gallego</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez Vinas</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Free and bound volatile compounds as markers of aromatic typicalness of Moravia Dulce, Rojal and Tortos&#x000ed; red wines.</article-title>
<source><italic>Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>131</volume>
<fpage>90</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>98</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2011.08.035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>G&#x000f3;mez Garc&#x000ed;a-Carpintero</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez Palomo</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez Vinas</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-Carpintero</surname><given-names>E. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Palomo</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Vi&#x000f1;as</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011a</year>). <article-title>Aroma characterization of red wines from cv. Bobal grape variety grown in La Mancha region.</article-title>
<source><italic>Food Res. Int.</italic></source>
<volume>44</volume>
<fpage>61</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2010.11.013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>G&#x000f3;mez Garc&#x000ed;a-Carpintero</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Palomo</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallego</surname><given-names>M. A. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Vi&#x000f1;as</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011b</year>). <article-title>Volatile and sensory characterization of red wines from cv. Moravia Agria minority grape variety cultivated in La Mancha region over five consecutive vintages.</article-title>
<source><italic>Food Res. Int.</italic></source>
<volume>44</volume>
<fpage>1549</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1560</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2011.04.022</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guillaumie</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ilg</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rety</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brette</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trossat-Magnin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Decroocq</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Genetic analysis of the biosynthesis of 2-Methoxy-3-Isobutylpyrazine, a major grape-derived aroma compound impacting wine quality.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>162</volume>
<fpage>604</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>615</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.113.218313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23606597</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gunata</surname><given-names>Y. Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayonove</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumes</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cordonnier</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>The aroma of grapes i. extraction and determination of free and glycosidical- ly bound fractions of some grape aroma components.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Chromatogr.</italic></source>
<volume>331</volume>
<fpage>83</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0021-9673(85)80009-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gunata</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bitteur</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brillouet</surname><given-names>J.-M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayonove</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cordonnier</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <article-title>Sequential enzymic hydrolysis of potentially aromatic glycosides from grape.</article-title>
<source><italic>Carbohydr. Res.</italic></source>
<volume>184</volume>
<fpage>139</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>149</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0008-6215(88)80012-0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guth</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Identification of character impact odorants of different white wine varieties.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Agric. Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>45</volume>
<fpage>3022</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3026</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf9608433</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayasaka</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldock</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardon</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herderich</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Glycosylation of smoke-derived volatile phenols in grapes as a consequence of grapevine exposure to bushfire smoke.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Agric. Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>58</volume>
<fpage>10989</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10998</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf103045t</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20923151</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hell&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Manso</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fenoll</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Evolution of aroma and phenolic compounds during ripening of &#x0201c;Superior Seedless&#x0201d; grapes.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Agric. Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>58</volume>
<fpage>6334</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6340</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf100448k</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20438135</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hjelmeland</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebeler</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Glycosidically bound volatile aroma compounds in grapes and wine: a review.</article-title>
<source><italic>Am. J. Enol. Vitic.</italic></source>
<volume>66</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5344/ajev.2014.14104</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hofer</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boachon</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Renault</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gavira</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miesch</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iglesias</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Dual function of the cytochrome P450 CYP76 family from <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> thaliana in the metabolism of monoterpenols and phenylurea herbicides.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>166</volume>
<fpage>1149</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1161</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.114.244814</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25082892</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ilc</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parage</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boachon</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Navrot</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Werck-Reichhart</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Monoterpenol oxidative metabolism: role in plant adaptation and potential applications.</article-title>
<source><italic>Front. Plant Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>7</volume>:<issue>509</issue>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2016.00509</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roudnitzky</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beno</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bensafi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hummel</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rouby</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Synergy and masking in odor mixtures: an electrophysiological study of Orthonasal vs. Retronasal perception.</article-title>
<source><italic>Chem. Senses</italic></source>
<volume>33</volume>
<fpage>553</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>561</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/chemse/bjn022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18502772</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koeduka</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fridman</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gang</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vass&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>B. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kish</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Eugenol and isoeugenol, characteristic aromatic constituents of spices, are biosynthesized via reduction of a coniferyl alcohol ester.</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</italic></source>
<volume>103</volume>
<fpage>10128</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10133</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0603732103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16782809</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kreis</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mosandl</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Elution order of the furanoid linalool oxides on common gas chromatographic phases and modified cyclodextrin phases.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Essent. Oil Res.</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>339</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>341</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10412905.1996.9700635</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lacombe</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Audeguin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boselli</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bucchetti</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabello</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chatelet</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Grapevine european catalogue: towards a comprehensive list.</article-title>
<source><italic>Vitis - J. Grapevine Res.</italic></source>
<volume>50</volume>
<fpage>65</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>68</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lopez-Tammames</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carro-Marino</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunata</surname><given-names>Y. Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sapis</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumes</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayonove</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Potential aroma in several varieties of spanish grapes.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Agric. Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>45</volume>
<fpage>1729</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1735</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf960572w</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luan</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mosandl</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Degenhardt</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gubesch</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>W&#x000fc;st</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006a</year>). <article-title>Metabolism of linalool and substrate analogs in grape berry mesocarp of <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> L. cv. Morio Muscat: demonstration of stereoselective oxygenation and glycosylation.</article-title>
<source><italic>Anal. Chim. Acta</italic></source>
<volume>563</volume>
<fpage>353</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>364</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aca.2006.01.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luan</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mosandl</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gubesch</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>W&#x000fc;st</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006b</year>). <article-title>Enantioselective analysis of monoterpenes in different grape varieties during berry ripening using stir bar sorptive extraction- and solid phase extraction-enantioselective-multidimensional gas chromatography-mass spectrometry.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Chromatogr. A</italic></source>
<volume>1112</volume>
<fpage>369</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>374</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chroma.2005.12.056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16405900</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maicas</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mateo</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Hydrolysis of terpenyl glycosides in grape juice and other fruit juices: a review.</article-title>
<source><italic>Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</italic></source>
<volume>67</volume>
<fpage>322</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>335</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-004-1806-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15635463</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mainland</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trimmer</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>L. L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>The missense of smell: functional variability in the human odorant receptor repertoire.</article-title>
<source><italic>Nat. Neurosci.</italic></source>
<volume>17</volume>
<fpage>114</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>120</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.3598</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24316890</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marais</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Wyk</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rapp</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Effect of storage time, temperature and region on the levels of 1,1,6-trimethyl-12-dihydronaphthalene and other volatiles, and on quality of Weisser Riesling wines.</article-title>
<source><italic>S. Afr. J. Enol. Vitic.</italic></source>
<volume>13</volume>
<fpage>33</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aubourg</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schouwey</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Daviet</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schalk</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toub</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Functional annotation, genome organization and phylogeny of the grapevine (<italic>Vitis vinifera</italic>) terpene synthase gene family based on genome assembly, FLcDNA cloning, and enzyme assays.</article-title>
<source><italic>BMC Plant Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>10</volume>:<issue>226</issue>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-10-226</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mathieu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Terrier</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Procureur</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bigey</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000fc;nata</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>A Carotenoid cleavage dioxygenase from <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> L.: functional characterization and expression during grape berry development in relation to C13-norisoprenoid accumulation.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Exp. Bot.</italic></source>
<volume>56</volume>
<fpage>2721</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2731</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/eri265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16131507</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsui</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Green leaf volatiles: hydroperoxide lyase pathway of oxylipin metabolism.</article-title>
<source><italic>Curr. Opin. Plant Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>274</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>280</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2006.03.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16595187</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mauricio</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zea</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortega</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Medina</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>The effects of grape must fermentation conditions on volatile alcohols and esters formed by <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Sci. Food Agric.</italic></source>
<volume>75</volume>
<fpage>155</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>160</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1097-0010(199710)75:2&#x0003c;155::AID-JSFA853&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-S</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>May</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>B. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>W&#x000fc;st</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Biosynthesis of sesquiterpenes in grape berry exocarp of <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> L.: evidence for a transport of farnesyl diphosphate precursors from plastids to the cytosol.</article-title>
<source><italic>Phytochemistry</italic></source>
<volume>95</volume>
<fpage>135</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>144</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2013.07.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23954075</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mayr</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldock</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardon</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>P. O.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Determination of the importance of in-mouth release of volatile phenol glycoconjugates to the flavor of smoke-tainted wines.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Agric. Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>62</volume>
<fpage>2327</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2336</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf405327s</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24617920</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mendes-Pinto</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Carotenoid breakdown products the&#x02014;norisoprenoids&#x02014;in wine aroma.</article-title>
<source><italic>Arch. Biochem. Biophys.</italic></source>
<volume>483</volume>
<fpage>236</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>245</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.abb.2009.01.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19320050</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumes</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maia</surname><given-names>M. O.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Volatile and glycosidically bound composition of Loureiro and Alvarinho wines.</article-title>
<source><italic>Food Sci. Technol. Int.</italic></source>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>341</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>353</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1082013208097442</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pol&#x000e1;&#x00161;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herszage</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebeler</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Wine flavor: chemistry in a glass.</article-title>
<source><italic>Chem. Soc. Rev.</italic></source>
<volume>37</volume>
<issue>2478</issue>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/b714455p</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>R Development Core Team</collab> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>R: a Language and Environment for Statistical Computing.</article-title>
<source><italic>R Found. Stat. Comput.</italic></source>
<volume>1</volume>:<issue>409</issue>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-540-74686-7</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rapp</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandery</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <article-title>Wine aroma.</article-title>
<source><italic>Experientia</italic></source>
<volume>42</volume>
<fpage>873</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>884</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01941764</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rib&#x000e9;reau-Gayon</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boidron</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Terrier</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1975</year>). <article-title>Aroma of Muscat grape varieties.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Agric. Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>23</volume>
<fpage>1042</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1047</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf60202a050</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boss</surname><given-names>P. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Solomon</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trengove</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heymann</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebeler</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Origins of grape and wine aroma. Part 1. Chemical components and viticultural impacts.</article-title>
<source><italic>Am. J. Enol. Vitic.</italic></source>
<volume>65</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5344/ajev.2013.12070</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roland</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Razungles</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavelier</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Varietal thiols in wine: discovery, analysis and applications.</article-title>
<source><italic>Chem. Rev.</italic></source>
<volume>111</volume>
<fpage>7355</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7376</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/cr100205b</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21780789</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Romano</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiore</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paraggio</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Caruso</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Capece</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Function of yeast species and strains in wine flavour.</article-title>
<source><italic>Int. J. Food Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>86</volume>
<fpage>169</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>180</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0168-1605(03)00290-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12892932</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saerens</surname><given-names>S. M. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Delvaux</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verstrepen</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Dijck</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thevelein</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Delvaux</surname><given-names>F. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Parameters affecting ethyl ester production by <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> during fermentation.</article-title>
<source><italic>Appl. Environ. Microbiol</italic></source>
<volume>74</volume>
<fpage>454</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>461</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17993562</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Palomo</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alonso-Villegas</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez Vi&#x000f1;as</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Characterisation of free and glycosidically bound aroma compounds of La Mancha Verdejo white wines.</article-title>
<source><italic>Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>173</volume>
<fpage>1195</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1202</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2014.10.148</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25466143</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Selli</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Canbas</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabaroglu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Erten</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lepoutre</surname><given-names>J.-P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunata</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Effect of skin contact on the free and bound aroma compounds of the white wine of <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> L. cv Narince.</article-title>
<source><italic>Food Control</italic></source>
<volume>17</volume>
<fpage>75</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>82</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2004.09.005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spillman</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollnitz</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liacopoulos</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Skouroumounis</surname><given-names>G. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sefton</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Accumulation of vanillin during barrel-aging of white, red, and model wines.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Agric. Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>45</volume>
<fpage>2584</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2589</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf970034z</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Massy-Westropp</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <article-title>Novel monoterpene disaccharide glycosides of <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> grapes and wines.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Agric. Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>36</volume>
<fpage>569</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>573</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0031-9422(82)83034-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B71"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Styger</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prior</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>F. F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Wine flavor and aroma.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Ind. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</italic></source>
<volume>38</volume>
<fpage>1145</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1159</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10295-011-1018-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21786136</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B72"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takase</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinmori</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinohara</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mochizuki</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Cytochrome P450 CYP71BE5 in grapevine (<italic>Vitis vinifera</italic>) catalyzes the formation of the spicy aroma compound (-)-rotundone.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Exp. Bot.</italic></source>
<volume>67</volume>
<fpage>787</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>798</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erv496</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26590863</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B73"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tieman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schauer</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernie</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klee</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Tomato aromatic amino acid decarboxylases participate in synthesis of the flavor volatiles 2-phenylethanol and 2-phenylacetaldehyde.</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</italic></source>
<volume>103</volume>
<fpage>8287</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8292</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0602469103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16698923</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B74"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toci</surname><given-names>A. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crupi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gambacorta</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dipalmo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Antonacci</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coletta</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Free and bound aroma compounds characterization by GC-MS of Negroamaro wine as affected by soil management.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Mass Spectrom.</italic></source>
<volume>47</volume>
<fpage>1104</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1112</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jms.3045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22972778</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B75"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ugliano</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moio</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>The influence of malolactic fermentation and <italic>Oenococcus oeni</italic> strain on glycosidic aroma precursors and related volatile compounds of red wine.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Sci. Food Agric.</italic></source>
<volume>86</volume>
<fpage>2468</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2476</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jsfa</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B76"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ugliano</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moio</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Free and hydrolytically released volatile compounds of <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> L. cv. Fiano grapes as odour-active constituents of Fiano wine.</article-title>
<source><italic>Anal. Chim. Acta</italic></source>
<volume>621</volume>
<fpage>79</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>85</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aca.2008.03.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18573373</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B77"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verstrepen</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Laere</surname><given-names>S. D. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanderhaegen</surname><given-names>B. M. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Derdelinckx</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dufour</surname><given-names>J.-P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pretorius</surname><given-names>I. S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Expression levels of the yeast alcohol acetyltransferase genes ATF1, Lg-ATF1 and ATF2 control the formation of a broad range of volatile esters.</article-title>
<source><italic>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>69</volume>
<fpage>5228</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5237</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.69.9.5228-5237.2003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12957907</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B78"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Voirin</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumes</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunata</surname><given-names>Z. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bitteur</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayonove</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tapiero</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Analytical methods for monoterpene glycosides in grape and wine. I. XAD-2 extraction and gas chromatographic-mass spectrometric determination of synthetic glycosides.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Chromatogr.</italic></source>
<volume>590</volume>
<fpage>313</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>328</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0021-9673(92)85395-A</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1560099</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B79"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vrhovsek</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lotti</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Masuero</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weingart</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattivi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Quantitative metabolic profiling of grape, apple and raspberry volatile compounds (VOCs) using a GC/MS/MS method.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Chromatogr. B</italic></source>
<volume>966</volume>
<fpage>132</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>139</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jchromb.2014.01.009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B80"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vuralhan</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luttik</surname><given-names>M. A. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tai</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boer</surname><given-names>V. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morais</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schipper</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Physiological characterization of the ARO10-dependent, broad-substrate-specificity 2-oxo acid decarboxylase activity of <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>71</volume>
<fpage>3276</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3284</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.71.6.3276-3284.2005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15933030</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B81"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980a</year>). <article-title>New linalool derivatives in Muscat of Alexandria grapes and wines.</article-title>
<source><italic>Phytochemistry</italic></source>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>1137</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1139</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0031-9422(80)83070-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B82"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Straws</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980b</year>). <article-title>Hydroxylated linalool derivatives as precursors of volatile monoterpenes of Muscat Grapes.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Agric. Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>28</volume>
<fpage>766</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>771</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf60230a037</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B83"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winterhalter</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Katzenberger</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schreier</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <article-title>6,7-Epoxylinalool and related oxygenated terpenoids from <italic>Carica papaya</italic> fruit.</article-title>
<source><italic>Phytochemistry</italic></source>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>1347</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1350</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0031-9422(00)81287-X</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B84"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siebert</surname><given-names>T. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Capone</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elsey</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollnitz</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>From wine to pepper: rotundone, an obscure sesquiterpene, is a potent spicy aroma compound.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Agric. Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>56</volume>
<fpage>3738</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3744</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf800183k</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18461961</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B85"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yilmaztekin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kocabey</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayaloglu</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Effect of maceration time on free and bound volatiles of red wines from cv. Karao&#x000f0;lan (<italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> L.) grapes grown in Arapgir, Turkey.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Food Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>80</volume>
<fpage>C556</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>C563</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1750-3841.12767</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25677953</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B86"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>B.-Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X.-Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y.-W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>C.-Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Q.-H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Isolation and characterization of two hydroperoxide lyase genes from grape berries.</article-title>
<source><italic>Mol. Biol. Rep.</italic></source>
<volume>39</volume>
<fpage>7443</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7455</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11033-012-1577-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22318551</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>