<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4364678</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25786135</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0119302</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-55844</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Biosynthesis of the Diterpenoid Lycosantalonol via Nerylneryl Diphosphate in <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>
</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Biosynthesis of the Diterpenoid Lycosantalonol in <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic></alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Matsuba</surname><given-names>Yuki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zi</surname><given-names>Jiachen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>A. Daniel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>Reuben J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pichersky</surname><given-names>Eran</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Molecular, Cellular and Developmental Biology, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Michigan, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff002">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Biochemistry, Biophysics &#x00026; Molecular Biology, Iowa State University, Ames, Iowa, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff003">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Department of Biochemistry, Michigan State University, East Lansing, Michigan, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Hamberger</surname><given-names>Bj&#x000f6;rn</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>University of Copenhagen, DENMARK</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: YM EP. Performed the experiments: YM. Analyzed the data: YM ADJ EP. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: JZ ADJ RJP. Wrote the paper: YM RJP EP.</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>lelx@umich.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>3</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e0119302</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>12</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>1</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2015 Matsuba et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Matsuba et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="pone.0119302.pdf"/><abstract><p>We recently reported that three genes involved in the biosynthesis of monoterpenes in trichomes, a <italic>cis</italic>-prenyltransferase named neryl diphosphate synthase 1 (<italic>NDPS1</italic>) and two terpene synthases (<italic>TPS19</italic> and <italic>TPS20</italic>), are present in close proximity to each other at the tip of chromosome 8 in the genome of the cultivated tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>). This terpene gene &#x0201c;cluster&#x0201d; also contains a second <italic>cis</italic>-prenyltransferase gene (<italic>CPT2</italic>), three other TPS genes, including <italic>TPS21</italic>, and the cytochrome P450-oxidoreductase gene <italic>CYP71BN1</italic>. <italic>CPT2</italic> encodes a neryneryl diphosphate synthase. Co-expression in <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> of <italic>CPT2</italic> and <italic>TPS21</italic> led to the formation of the diterpene lycosantalene, and co-expression in <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> of <italic>CPT2</italic>, <italic>TPS21</italic> and CYP71BN1 led to the formation of lycosantalonol, an oxidation product of lycosantalene. Here we show that maximal expression of all three genes occurs in the petiolule part of the leaf, but little expression of these genes occurs in the trichomes present on the petiolules. While lycosantalene or lycosantalonol cannot be detected in the petiolules of wild-type plants (or anywhere else in the plant), lycosantalene and lycosantalonol are detected in petiolules of transgenic tomato plants expressing <italic>CPT2</italic> under the control of the 35S CaMV promoter. These results suggest that lycosantalene and lycosantalonol are produced in the petiolules and perhaps in other tissues of wild-type plants, but that low rate of synthesis, controlled by the rate-limiting enzyme CPT2, results in product levels that are too low for detection under our current methodology. It is also possible that these compounds are further modified in the plant. The involvement of <italic>CPT2</italic>, <italic>TPS21</italic> and <italic>CYP71BN1</italic> in a diterpenoid biosynthetic pathway outside the trichomes, together with the involvement of other genes in the cluster in the synthesis of monoterpenes in trichomes, indicates that this cluster is further evolving into &#x0201c;sub-clusters&#x0201d; with unique biochemical, and likely physiological, roles.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This research was supported by grants from National Science Foundation to EP (IOS-1025636, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nsf.gov/">http://www.nsf.gov/</ext-link>) and National Institutes of Health to RJP (GM076324, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nih.gov/">http://www.nih.gov/</ext-link>). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="5"/><table-count count="2"/><page-count count="16"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001"><title>Introduction</title><p>The metabolic pathways that are shared by practically all plant species are generally termed primary metabolism, while new biochemical pathways that have evolved in various plant lineages in response to selection exerted by local biotic and abiotic factors have been dubbed &#x0201c;specialized&#x0201d; metabolism [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Terpenoids constitute a large class of plant metabolites, and while some terpenoids belong to primary metabolism, such as the sterols, carotenoids, and gibberellins, the majority of them have limited distribution in specific plant lineages and are thus part of specialized metabolism.</p><p>In particular, thousands of monoterpene, sesquiterpene and diterpene compounds have been identified in various plants serving diverse functions such as floral scents, defense compounds throughout the plants, and signal molecules [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. The diversity is achieved mostly by divergence in the terpene synthase (TPS) gene family among plant species. This family, which includes anywhere from a score to over a hundred genes in any given plant genome, encodes enzymes that use prenyldiphosphates as precursors to fashion a basic hydrocarbon backbone, which can then be further modified by hydroxylation, glycosylation, acylation, peroxidation, cleavage, and other reactions [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].</p><p>Most TPSs use <italic>trans</italic>-prenyl diphosphates as their precursor&#x02014;geranyl diphosphate (GPP) for monoterpene synthases, <italic>E</italic>,<italic>E</italic>-farnesyl diphosphate (<italic>ee</italic>FPP) for sesquiterpene synthases, and <italic>E</italic>,<italic>E</italic>,<italic>E</italic>-geranylgeranyl diphosphate (GGPP) for diterpene synthases. However, it was recently discovered that some TPSs of plants in the Solanaceae family use <italic>cis</italic>-prenyl diphosphates as substrates&#x02014;neryl diphosphate (NPP) for monoterpenes, <italic>Z</italic>,<italic>Z</italic>-farnesyl diphosphate (<italic>zz</italic>FPP) for sesquiterpene synthases, and neryneryl diphosphate (NNPP) for diterpene synthases [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Thus, a change in substrates also adds to the diversity of terpenes found in nature.</p><p>A detailed analysis of the TPS gene family in <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> (cultivated tomato) identified a cluster of genes on chromosome 8 (<xref rid="pone.0119302.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A</xref>, [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]) that include five TPS genes as well as two functional <italic>cis</italic>-prenyltransferases (= <italic>cis</italic>-prenyl diphosphate synthases) and one functional cytochrome P450 oxidoreductase gene, previously designated as <italic>CYP71D51</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] but renamed here as <italic>CYP71BN1</italic> according to the numbering assignment of the Cytochrome P450 homepage (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://drnelson.uthsc.edu/CytochromeP450.html">http://drnelson.uthsc.edu/CytochromeP450.html</ext-link>). Two of the TPS genes, <italic>TPS19</italic> and <italic>TPS20</italic>, were shown to encode monoterpene synthases that use NPP, the product of <italic>CPT1</italic> (= neryl diphosphate synthase 1, or <italic>NDPS1</italic>). <italic>TPS19</italic>, <italic>TPS20</italic> and <italic>NDPS1</italic> are highly expressed in trichomes, which synthesize and accumulate the resulting monoterpenes [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p><fig id="pone.0119302.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0119302.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>Lycosantalonol biosynthesis in <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) The terpene gene cluster on the tip of chromosome 8. (<bold>B</bold>) The biosynthetic pathway to lycosantanolol. AOX, alcohol oxidase; TPS, terpene synthase; CPT, <italic>cis</italic>-prenyl transferase; NDPS1, neryl diphosphate synthase 1; CYP, cytochrome P450; AAT, alcohol acyltransferase; DMAPP, dimethylallyl diphosphate; IPP, isopentenyl diphosphate; NNPP, nerylneryl diphosphate. Genes that are not functional because of deletions or insertions are shown with a &#x0201c;&#x003c8;&#x0201d; symbol.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0119302.g001"/></fig><p>However, the other TPS genes in this cluster were not specifically or even highly expressed in trichomes [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Two of these TPSs, <italic>TPS18</italic> and <italic>TPS41</italic>, were shown to be closely related to a pair of <italic>Nicotiana tobacum</italic> (tobacco) genes involved in the synthesis of the diterpene <italic>Z</italic>-abienol [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], although demonstration of enzymatic activity of the tomato proteins encoded by these genes is still lacking [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. The fifth TPS gene in this cluster, <italic>TPS21</italic>, was shown to encode a protein that in vitro uses NNPP to produce a previously unknown diterpene [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] that was subsequently structurally characterized and named lycosantalene [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. NNPP is the product of the second CPT gene, <italic>CPT2</italic>, that is present in the gene cluster on chromosome 8 (<xref rid="pone.0119302.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A</xref>). Furthermore, by co-expressing <italic>CPT2</italic>, <italic>TPS21</italic>, and <italic>CYP71BN1</italic> in a bacterial system we were able to show that the CYP71BN1 enzyme is able to catalyze two sequential oxidation reactions of lycosanatalene to produce first epoxy-lycosantalene and then lycosantalonol (<xref rid="pone.0119302.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1B</xref>, [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]).</p><p>To date, however, lycosanatalene and its oxidative derivatives have not been identified in any tomato tissue. Here we show that <italic>TPS21</italic>, <italic>CPT2</italic> and <italic>CYP71BN1</italic> are expressed at their highest levels in leaf petiolules, and that this part of the plant is likely to naturally produce compounds derived from NNPP.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec003"><title>Chemicals</title><p>DMAPP, IPP, and <italic>zz</italic>FPP were obtained from Echelon Biosciences. Radio-labeled <sup>14</sup>C&#x02013;IPP, 60.0 mCi/mmol (2.22 GBq/mmol), was obtained from Perkin Elmer. Solid-phase microextraction (SPME) fiber was obtained from Supelco. All other chemicals were obtained from Sigma, Promega, Invitrogen or Qiagen.</p></sec><sec id="sec004"><title>Tissue isolation and preparation of petiolules, petiolules without trichomes, and trichomes from petiolules for RNA extractrion and metabolite analysis</title><p>For analysis of terpenoids of whole petiolules, 20&#x02013;30 mg of petiolules of compound leaves from all developmental stages were grounded in a microtube and 100 &#x003bc;l of hexane were added into the tube and incubated for 10 min. Water was then added, the sample was vortexed and centrifuged, the hexane phase was analyzed by GC-MS. For analysis of terpenoids in trichomes, 20&#x02013;30 mg of intact petiolules were placed in a microtube and 100 &#x003bc;l of hexane were added into the tube and incubated for 10 min (the &#x0201c;dip&#x0201d; method), and then the hexane was removed and analyzed by GC-MS. To measure terpenoid content in the non-trichome portion of the petiolules, petiolules that were first dipped in hexane (to remove terpenoids from the trichomes) were placed into a fresh microtube, ground, and extracted with 100 &#x003bc;l of hexane, and the hexane extracts were analyzed by GC-MS.</p><p>For the qRT-PCR analysis, intact whole petiolules were ground in liquid nitrogen and total RNA was extracted. To obtain petiolules without trichomes and pure trichome preparations, intact petiolules were first placed in a microtube and frozen with liquid nitrogen. Vortexing the tube caused the trichomes to separate from the petiolule tissue. Using a tweezer, the petiolules without trichomes were removed and placed in a new tube, ground, and total RNA was extracted. The remaining trichomes were collected by centrifugation and used for total RNA extraction as well.</p></sec><sec id="sec005"><title>Gene expression analysis of <italic>CPT2</italic>, <italic>TPS21</italic> and <italic>CYP71BN1</italic> by qRT-PCR</title><p>After total RNA was isolated with the E.Z.N.A. Plant RNA MiniKit (Omega Bio-tek), it was treated with a DNA-free kit (Ambion) to remove genomic DNA contamination, and used for first-strand cDNA synthesis with a High Capacity cDNA reverse transcription kit and random primers (Applied Biosystems) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol. To quantify the mRNA abundance of <italic>CPT2</italic>, <italic>TPS21</italic> and <italic>CYP71BN1</italic> in each tissue in <italic>S</italic>. <italic>lycopersicum</italic>, quantitative RT-PCR was performed as previously described [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0119302.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. To compare absolute expression levels among the three genes, the standard curve method was used. Relative expression levels in different tissues were normalized to the expression levels of tomato elongation factor-1a (EF-1 a; GenBank: X14449). All primers used in this study are shown in <xref rid="pone.0119302.s006" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>. Three or four biological replicates (as indicated in the legends) were used for each point, and triplicates of each sample were done.</p></sec><sec id="sec006"><title>Transgenic plants</title><p>For the <italic>35S-CPT2</italic> construct, the open reading frame of the <italic>CPT2</italic> gene was amplified with KOD polymerase using pGEM-T Easy-<italic>CPT2</italic> plasmid as a template and ligated into pSAT4A vector [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] between SalI/BamHI restriction sites. The region including the double 35S CaMV promoter, enhancer, <italic>CPT2</italic> gene, and the terminator of pSAT4A-<italic>CPT2</italic> was digested with I-SceI restriction enzyme and ligated into the I-SceI site of the binary vector, pPZP-RCS2 [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. For the <italic>35S-CPT2</italic>-RNA interference (RNAi) construct, a 190 bp fragment of <italic>CPT2</italic> that corresponds to nucleotides 54 to 243 of the gene was amplified by PCR. The fragment was ligated in the sense and antisense orientations into pRNA69 [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] between the XhoI/KpnI and BamHI/XbaI restriction sites, respectively. The hairpin cassette was released by SpeI/SacI digestion and transferred to the pZP212 binary vector [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] between the XbaI/SacI restriction sites. All primers used are shown in <xref rid="pone.0119302.s006" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>. The binary vectors were introduced into <italic>S</italic>. <italic>lycopersicum</italic> cultivar MP1 by the University of Nebraska Plant Transformation Facility (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://biotech.unl.edu/plant-transformation">http://biotech.unl.edu/plant-transformation</ext-link>). All transgenic plants were grown at the growth room at the same condition as previously described [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] and the first generation of <italic>35S-CPT2</italic> and <italic>35S-CPT2</italic>-RNAi transgenic lines were used for the metabolic analyses. <italic>CPT2</italic> transcript levels of individual <italic>35S-CPT2</italic> and <italic>35S</italic>-<italic>CPT2</italic>-RNAi transgenic plants were analyzed by RT-PCR and qRT-PCR, using total RNA obtained from terminal leaflets and petiolules, respectively, with primers shown in <xref rid="pone.0119302.s006" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec007"><title>Terpenoids analysis by GC-MS</title><p>Terpenoids were collected by extraction with hexane from plant tissues or by SPME of ground plant samples placed in a 2 ml glass vial for 15 min at 42&#x000b0;C. To analyze the accumulation of terpenoid glucosides, glucosides were extracted with 80% methanol from ground tissue for 16 hours at 4&#x000b0;C. The extracts were filtered and solvent evaporated without heating in a SpeedVac concentrator (Savant). Compounds were dissolved in 50 mM citrate buffer pH 5.0, and &#x003b2;-glucosidase was added and the sample was incubated for 16 hours at 37&#x000b0;C, or dissolved in either 0.5 N HCl or 0.5 N NaOH and incubated for 1 hour at room temperature, and then neutralized with NaOH or HCl. Nonpolar compounds were extracted with hexane and the samples were analyzed by GC-MS. Samples were injected in split mode (2:1) into a Rxi-5Sil MS column (30-m length, 0.25-&#x003bc;m film thickness, and 0.25-mm ID; Restek) on a GC-2010 Plus coupled to a GCMS-QP2010 SE (Shimadzu) using 70 eV electron ionization. Injector temperature was 240&#x000b0;C, and interface temperature was 280&#x000b0;C. The following GC methods were used: After a 3-min isothermal hold at 150&#x000b0;C, the column temperature was increased by 3&#x000b0;C/min to 240&#x000b0;C. Lycosantalene, nerylnerol, lycosantalonol, and epoxy-lycosantalene obtained by engineering <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> cells and verified by NMR [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] were used as standards.</p></sec><sec id="sec008"><title>Terpenoids analysis by HPLC-MS</title><p>The 80% methanol extract of ground petiolules was analyzed using high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) (LC-20AD pump, CTO-20A column oven, and SIL-5000 autosampler, Shimadzu) using an ODS column (Ascentis Express C<sub>18</sub>, i.d. 2.1 x 100 mm, Supelco) coupled with time-of-flight (TOF)-MS (LCT Premier TOF-MS, Waters) with ES negative ion mode from <italic>m/z</italic> 50 to 1500 using three multiplexed collision-induced dissociation functions (Aperture 1 voltages were 10, 20, and 30 V) with 0.3 s per scan for each function. Metabolites were separated by linear gradient elution (0.3 ml/min) from 40 to 100% solvent B (100% methanol) in solvent A (0.15% formic acid in water) for 14 min. All data were analyzed with MassLynx V4.1 software (Waters).</p></sec><sec id="sec009"><title>Recombinant CPT2 characterization</title><p>Recombinant CPT2 protein was generated in <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> BL21 (DE3) that harbored the expression vector pEXP5-CT/TOPO (Invitrogen) containing <italic>CPT2</italic> cDNA with a deletion of the 153 nucleotide sequences corresponding to the 51 amino acids of the N-terminal putative transit peptide. <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> harboring <italic>CPT2</italic>-pEXP5-CT/TOPO were incubated in Luria-Bertani media at 30&#x000b0;C until they reach OD<sub>600</sub> = 0.8. The production of the CPT2 protein was then induced by adding 1 mM isopropyl-&#x003b2;-D-1-thiogalactopyranoside as a final concentration and incubating the culture for 18 hours at 16&#x000b0;C. The recombinant CPT2 protein was purified by HIS-Select HF Nickel Affinity Gel (Sigma) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol. Kinetic analysis was performed using <sup>14</sup>C-IPP as a substrate with 3.0 &#x003bc;g of purified recombinant enzyme in each reaction. The pH preference of the enzyme was determined by enzymatic assays with 0.5 &#x003bc;g purified enzyme using different pHs in buffers including 100 mM KCl, 7.5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 5% (v/v) glycerol, and 5 mM DTT. The reaction mixture, including 40 &#x003bc;M DMAPP and 40 &#x003bc;M <sup>14</sup>C-IPP with a total volume of 50 &#x003bc;l was incubated at 30&#x000b0;C for 15 min. The reaction was stopped and the phosphate groups were removed from the enzymatic products by adding 1 volume of 1 N HCl and incubating the samples at 37&#x000b0;C for 30 min. The hydrolyzed radio-labeled products were extracted with 150 &#x003bc;l of ethyl acetate, and the radio-labeled products were quantified in 100 &#x003bc;l of the extract by scintillation counting. Estimates of the <italic>K</italic>
<sub><italic>m</italic></sub> for <italic>zz</italic>FPP and IPP were performed over a range of substrate concentrations using a fixed concentration of the co-substrate as follow: 5&#x02013;80 &#x003bc;M <sup>14</sup>C-IPP at 150 &#x003bc;M <italic>zz</italic>FPP and 10&#x02013;80 &#x003bc;M <italic>zz</italic>FPP at 50 &#x003bc;M <sup>14</sup>C-IPP. All other conditions were same as previously described [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec010"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec011"><title>Optimal transcript levels of <italic>CPT2</italic>, <italic>TPS21</italic> and <italic>CYP71BN1</italic> are observed in leaf petiolules</title><p>Because we previously looked at organ-specific expression of <italic>CPT2</italic>, <italic>TPS21</italic> and <italic>CYP71BN1</italic> by measuring transcripts extracted from whole organs, it was possible that the overall low-level expression observed in these genes was masking high-level expression in small parts of a given organ or at different stages of development. We therefore examined transcript levels of these genes in sub-sections of the compound tomato leaf and in young vs. old organs of the plant (<xref rid="pone.0119302.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2A</xref>). There was some variation in the patterns of transcript levels among the three genes. <italic>TPS21</italic> transcripts were present in various parts in relatively similar levels, with the exception of fruits and roots, where the levels were quite low (<xref rid="pone.0119302.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2B</xref>). <italic>CYP71BN1</italic> transcript levels were highest in petiolules, the stem-like structure connecting the leaflet to the main petiole, and particularly in young petiolules, but also present in petioles, stems and flowers (<xref rid="pone.0119302.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2B</xref>). However, <italic>CPT2</italic> transcripts were present in young petiolules at levels that were at least 4-fold higher than in any other tissue examined (<xref rid="pone.0119302.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2B</xref>). The transcripts of all three genes were at their highest levels in young petiolules, compare with other tissues examined here. However, the relative transcript levels of the three genes were different. While the transcript levels of <italic>CPT2</italic> and <italic>TPS21</italic> were almost same, the transcript levels of <italic>CYP71BN1</italic> were approximately 10-fold higher than the levels of the other two genes (<xref rid="pone.0119302.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2B</xref>).</p><fig id="pone.0119302.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0119302.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title>qRT-PCR analyses of <italic>CPT2</italic>, <italic>TPS21</italic> and <italic>CYP71BN1</italic> transcripts in different tissues of <italic>S</italic>. <italic>lycopersicum</italic>.</title><p>Total RNA was isolated from various tomato tissues. Leaflets and petiolules were prepared from four different developmental compound leaf stages. Error bars represent SE. Values are from three biological and three technical replicates.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0119302.g002"/></fig><p>We also investigated whether <italic>CPT2</italic>, <italic>TPS21</italic> and <italic>CYP71BN1</italic> gene transcripts are present specifically in trichome. Relative levels of <italic>CPT2</italic>, <italic>TPS21</italic> and <italic>CYP71BN1</italic> transcript in petiolules from which trichomes have been removed (see <xref rid="sec002" ref-type="sec">M&#x00026;M</xref>) were 1.5-, 1.3- and 1.7-fold, respectively, higher compare with their levels in whole petiolules (including trichomes), indicating that transcripts of these three genes are present mostly in non-trichome cells in this organ (<xref rid="pone.0119302.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). Consistent with this conclusion, the relative transcript levels of the three genes in the trichomes of petiolules were respectively 22-, 21- and 40-fold lower compare with their levels in whole petiolules (<xref rid="pone.0119302.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>).</p><fig id="pone.0119302.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0119302.g003</object-id><label>Fig 3</label><caption><title>qRT-PCR analysis of <italic>CPT2</italic>, <italic>TPS21</italic>, <italic>CYP71BN1</italic> transcripts in petiolules.</title><p>RNA was isolated from whole petiolule, petiolules from which trichomes have been removed, and from the trichomes. Error bars represent SE. Values are from four biological replicates with three technical replicates of each.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0119302.g003"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec012"><title>Over-expressesing <italic>CPT2</italic> in petiolules results in detectable levels of lycosantalene and lycosantalonol</title><p>Since the maximal levels of transcripts for all three genes <italic>CPT2</italic>, <italic>TPS21</italic> and <italic>CYP71BN1</italic> occur in young petiolule, we searched for lycosantalonol or related compounds with the basic lycosantalene skeleton in this organ in wild-type plants. Petiolules were placed in a glass vial and ground with a glass stick. Volatiles were collected by SPME at 42&#x000b0;C for 15 min and analyzed by GC-MS. For non-volatile terpenoids analysis, compounds were extracted from the ground petiolules with hexane as a solvent and the extracts were analyzed by GC-MS. To investigate the accumulation of diterpenoid glucosides or diterpenoids that were modified by acylation, compounds were extracted from the ground petiolules with 80% methanol, and treated with either acid or base (final concentration 0.5 N HCl or 0.5 N NaOH, respectively), or dried first, then resuspended in buffer and incubated with almond recombinant &#x003b2;-glucosidase. After these treatments, compounds were extracted with hexane and analyzed by GC-MS. No peaks with the retention times of lycosantalene, epoxy-lycosantalene, or lycosantalonol were detected in the chromatograms of samples obtained by any of the methods described above (one such result is shown in <xref rid="pone.0119302.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4A</xref>). Furthermore, we did not detect any other peaks in which at least two of the ions of <italic>m/z</italic> 69, 81, 93, 95, 107, 109 and 121, which are prominent in the MS of lycosantalene and/or its derivatives, constituted a significant part of their mass spectra.</p><fig id="pone.0119302.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0119302.g004</object-id><label>Fig 4</label><caption><title>GC-MS analysis of diterpenes from hexane extracts of whole petiolules.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Non-transformed <italic>S</italic>. <italic>lycopersicum</italic>, (<bold>B</bold>&#x02013;<bold>D</bold>) three individual plants of <italic>S</italic>. <italic>lycopersicum</italic> transformed with the <italic>35S-</italic>CPT2 gene construct. Chromatograms of the selected ion of <italic>m/z</italic> 109 are shown here. (<bold>E</bold>) Four combined chromatographs of authentic standards. 1, nerylnerol; 2, lycosantalene: 3, epoxy-lycosantalene; 4, lycosantalonol. Mass Spectra for all peaks is shown in <xref rid="pone.0119302.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Fig.</xref> Whole petiolules were ground and extracted with hexane as described in Materials and Methods.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0119302.g004"/></fig><p>Since it was possible that such compounds were produced in the wild-type petiolules at such low levels as to be below the detection threshold of our methods, and that increasing the rate of synthesis of NNPP would lead to higher levels of synthesis of lycosantalene and its derivatives, we constructed transgenic tomato plants containing the <italic>CPT2</italic> gene under the control of the strong, non-specific 35S promoter. <italic>CPT2</italic> expression level of individual transgenic plants was determined by RT-PCR (<xref rid="pone.0119302.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Fig.</xref>). SPME analysis of transgenic leaflets of plants over-expressing <italic>CPT2</italic> detected lycosantalene in eight of the 13 individual transgenic plants tested. Three individual plants which had the highest lycosantalene levels were selected for further analyses. Petiolules were collected from these three individual transgenic tomato lines and diterpenoids were extracted with hexane and analyzed by GC-MS. Nerylnerol, lycosantalene and lycosantalonol were all detected in all three individual plants (<xref rid="pone.0119302.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4B-D</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0119302.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Fig.</xref>). To investigate the accumulation of diterpenoid glucosides or diterpenoids that were modified by acylation, compounds were extracted from ground petiolules and analyzed in the same way as described above for wild-type petiolules. However, no additional lycosantalene derivatives were found in the transgenic petiolules in any of these three lines.</p></sec><sec id="sec013"><title>Petiolules of <italic>CPT2</italic>-overexpressing lines produce neryneryl diphosphate-derived diterpenes in non-trichomes cells</title><p>Tomato trichomes have high levels of the monoterpene &#x003b2;-phellandrene and the sesquiterpene &#x003b2;-caryophyllene, which are present at much lower levels in other aerial cells [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. We analyzed hexane extracts of ground whole petiolules of transgenic plants overexpressing <italic>CPT2</italic> ground, hexane extracts of ground petiolules from which the terpenes in the trichomes had first been removed by dipping the sample in hexane, as well as terpenoid content of the hexane solution in which the petiolules were dipped in. We measured lycosantalene rather than lycosanatalonol since the former has a lower detection threshold. This analysis showed that petiolules without trichomes had higher ratios of lycosantalene to &#x003b2;-phellandrene and to &#x003b2;-caryophyllene than petiolules with trichomes (<xref rid="pone.0119302.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), indicating that a higher proportion of lycosantalene than &#x003b2;-phellandrene and &#x003b2;-caryophyllene is present in the non-trichome petiolule tissue. The observation that the ratios of lycosantalene to &#x003b2;-phellandrene and to &#x003b2;-caryophyllene were lower in trichomes than in whole petiolules (<xref rid="pone.0119302.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) is also consistent with this conclusion.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0119302.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0119302.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Ratios of lycosantalene levels to &#x003b2;-phellandrene and &#x003b2;-caryophyllene levels in petiolule with and without trichomes, and in trichomes of transgenic <italic>S</italic>. <italic>lycopersicum</italic> plants overexpressing <italic>CPT2</italic>.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0119302.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0119302.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tissue</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lycosantalene / &#x003b2;-phellandrene (%)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lycosantalene / &#x003b2;-caryophyllene (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Petiolules without trichomes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1 &#x000b1; 1.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.2 &#x000b1; 8.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Petiolules with trichomes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1 &#x000b1; 1.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.1 &#x000b1; 9.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Petiolule trichomes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 &#x000b1; 0.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.4 &#x000b1; 2.1</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t001fn001"><p>Terpenes were extracted with hexane and analyzed by GC-MA as described in Materials and Methods.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec014"><title>CPT2 shows high affinity for IPP</title><p>We showed previously that the preferred initial acceptor substrate of CPT2 is DMAPP [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Here we measured the <italic>K</italic>
<sub><italic>m</italic></sub> and <italic>k</italic>
<sub><italic>cat</italic></sub> values of CPT2 for the condensation of <italic>zz</italic>FPP and IPP, the last step in the three-step reaction of synthesizing NNPP from DMAPP and 3 molecules of IPP. CPT2 showed optimal activity at pH 8.0&#x02013;8.5, similar to what has been observed with other CPT enzymes (<xref rid="pone.0119302.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3 Fig.</xref>). The <italic>K</italic>
<sub><italic>m</italic></sub> value for IPP was determined to be 3.8 &#x000b1; 0.3 &#x003bc;M and for <italic>zz</italic>FPP 22.9 &#x000b1; 1.1 &#x003bc;M, values that are lower than those of SlCPT1 (NDPS1) for its substrates (<italic>K</italic>
<sub><italic>m</italic></sub> value for IPP: 152 &#x003bc;M, DMAPP: 177 &#x003bc;M, [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]) and ShCPT1 (zFPS, <italic>K</italic>
<sub><italic>m</italic></sub> for IPP: 16, 36 &#x003bc;M, DMAPP: 35, 210 &#x003bc;M, [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]) (<xref rid="pone.0119302.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The measured <italic>k</italic>
<sub><italic>cat</italic></sub> value with CPT was similar with both IPP and <italic>zz</italic>FPP substrates, at 2.6 x 10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> (s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>).</p><table-wrap id="pone.0119302.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0119302.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>NNPS activity of CPT2.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0119302.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0119302.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Substrate</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>K</italic>
<sub><italic>m</italic></sub> (&#x003bc;M)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>k</italic>
<sub><italic>cat</italic></sub> (s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>k</italic>
<sub><italic>cat</italic></sub> /<italic>Km</italic>, s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> mM<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IPP</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8 &#x000b1; 0.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2.6 &#x000b1; 0.2) x 10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68 &#x000b1; 0.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>zz</italic>FPP</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.9 &#x000b1; 1.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2.6 &#x000b1; 0.1) x 10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11 &#x000b1; 0.01</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec015"><title>No obvious morphological phenotypes are observed in <italic>35S-CPT2</italic> or <italic>35S-CPT2-RNAi</italic> tomato lines</title><p>Although we were able to detect lycosantalene and lycosantalonol in transgenic tomato plants overexpressing <italic>CPT2</italic> under the control of the 35S promoter, the gross morphology of the plants was similar to that of wild-type plants. We also examined the transgenic tomato plants expressing a <italic>35S-CPT2</italic> RNAi construct in which <italic>CPT2</italic> gene expression was reduced by up to 80% (<xref rid="pone.0119302.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4 Fig.</xref>), and these plants grew normally and showed no morphological differences from wild-type tomato plants at all developmental stages.</p></sec><sec id="sec016"><title>No differences in metabolic compounds are observed between both <italic>CPT2</italic> over-expressing and RNAi lines and wild-type plants</title><p>The volatile and non-volatile hydrophobic compound analyses of petiolules from three individual transgenic plants in which <italic>CPT2</italic> transcript levels were reduced by 80% were performed by GC-MS, and no differences were observed compared with wild-type petiolules.</p><p>Next, a detailed hydrophilic metabolic compounds analysis was performed by HPLC-MS. The hydrophilic compounds were extracted with 80% methanol from ground petiolules from each of five individual transgenic plants as well as from control wild-type plants. All 2,370 peaks observed on chromatograms of the five individual <italic>CPT2</italic> over-expression lines (#03, 07, 19, 24, and 26) and/or the five <italic>CPT2</italic> RNAi lines (#01, 04, 05, 12, and 18) were compared to the peaks of the wild-type plants by a global comparison software (MarkerLynx XS, MassLynx, Waters). However, no significant increases or decreases in levels of the peaks among these three groups were observed.</p></sec><sec id="sec017"><title>CYP71BN1 is most similar to germacrene A oxidases</title><p>Cytochrome P450 oxidoreductases belonging to the CYP71 clan are known to be involved in the biosynthesis of specialized metabolites such as isoprenoids, alkaloids, flavonoids and cyanogenic glucosides. Most mono-, sesqui- and diterpene-modifying P450s belong to this CYP71 clan [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Phylogenetic tree analysis showed that tomato CYP71BN1 was most similar to sesquiterpene oxidases, germacrene A oxidases (GAOs) from both Asteraecae and Barnadesioideae and amorpha-4, 11-diene oxidase (AMO) from Asteraecae (<xref rid="pone.0119302.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). GAOs and AMO each catalyze three consecutive oxidations of sesquiterpenes, germacrene A to yield germacrene A acid, in the case of GAO, and amorpha-4,11-dine to yield amorpha-4, 11-dine acid in the case of AMO [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Tomato CYP71BN1 catalyzes the two sequential oxidations of the diterpene, lycosantalene to yield lycosantalonol (<xref rid="pone.0119302.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>).</p><fig id="pone.0119302.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0119302.g005</object-id><label>Fig 5</label><caption><title>Phylogenetic tree of tomato CYP71BN1 and other functionally characterized terpene-modifying P450s.</title><p>Neighbor-joining phylogenetic tree analysis using amino acid sequences was performed by MEGA 5 [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Bootstrap values were performed with 1000 replications (values shown next to branches). LsGAO1, <italic>Lactuca sativa</italic> germacrene A oxidase (GAO) 1 (ADF32078.1); CiGAO2, <italic>Cichorium intybus</italic> (ADF43080.1); HaGAO4, <italic>Helianthus annuus</italic> (ADF43082.1); ScGAO3, <italic>Saussurea costus</italic> (ADF43081.1); AaAMO1, <italic>Artemisia annua</italic> amorpha-4, 11-diene monooxygenase (Q1PS23.1); BsGAO5, <italic>Barnadesia spinosa</italic> (ADF43083.1); HmHPO, <italic>Hyoscyamus muticus</italic> premnaspirodiene oxygenase (HPO) (A6YIH8.1); Nt-CYP71D20, <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic> 5-epiaristolochene dihydroxylase (Q94FM7.2); Ms-CYP71D18, <italic>Mentha spicata</italic> (-)-(4<italic>S</italic>)-limonene-6-hydroxylase (Q9XHE8.1); Mp-CYP71D13, <italic>Mentha x piperita</italic> (-)-(4<italic>S</italic>)-limonene-3-hydroxylase (Q9XHE7.1); Mp-CYP71D15, <italic>Mentha x piperita</italic> (-)-(4<italic>S</italic>)-limonene-3-hydroxylase (Q9XHE6.1); Zz-CYP71BA1, <italic>Zingiber zerumbet</italic> &#x003b1;-humulene oxidase (E3W9C4.1); AtKO, <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana ent</italic>-kaurene oxidase (KO) (NM_122491); OsKO2, <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> (BAF19823); OsKO4, <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> (BAF19823).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0119302.g005"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="sec018"><title>Discussions</title><sec id="sec019"><title>CPT2, TPS21 and CYP71BN1 catalyze the steps in the biosynthesis of lycosantalonol in petiolules</title><p>Gene expression analyses revealed that <italic>CPT2</italic>, <italic>TPS21</italic> and <italic>CYP71BN1</italic> co-express in the petiolule, but not in the trichomes of petiolule. While we did not detect any lycosantalene, lycosantalonol, or their derivatives in the petiolules or any other part of the wild-type plants, including leaflets, petioles and stems where these genes are also appreciably expressed although at lower levels than in petiolules (<xref rid="pone.0119302.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>), we did detect lycosantalene and lycosantalonol in the petiolules of transgenic tomato expressing <italic>CPT2</italic> under the control of the CaMV 35S promoter. This observation suggests that the amount of NNPP in this tissue limits the amount of the final product of the pathway. Since <italic>CPT2</italic> as well as <italic>TPS21</italic> and <italic>CYP71BN1</italic> are expressed at some level in petiolules, and more so than in any other tissues examined, it is likely that lycosantalene and lycosantalonol are also synthesized in petiolules of non-transgenic tomato plants, and perhaps in other tissues as well, but at levels too low to be detected with our analytical methods. A corollary hypothesis is that lycosantalene and lycosantalonol are intermediates of unknown final metabolite(s), and they only accumulate when the flux is increased artificially, as by overexpressing <italic>CPT2</italic>. Other groups have reported the accumulation of intermediates in transgenic plants but not in wild-type plants, in some cases without yet identifying the final products (for instance &#x003b2;-amyrin in rice [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]).</p><p>We had previously reported that the CPT2 protein is localized to the plastids [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. While the entire pathway to lycosantalonol may not necessarily need to occur in the same compartment&#x02014;examples of pathways for which enzymes are found in different compartments and where intermediates move from one compartment to another abound (for instance, sesqui- and diterpeniod [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], anthocyanins [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] and benzoxazinoid [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>])&#x02014;we note that the sequences of both <italic>TPS21</italic> and <italic>CYP71BN1</italic> are predicted by WoLFPSORT (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wolfpsort.org/">http://www.wolfpsort.org/</ext-link>) to encode an N-terminal transit peptide that would target the proteins to the plastid. Furthermore, the sequence of the transit peptide of TPS21 is similar to that of ShTPS45 (zFPS), a protein that was experimentally shown to localize to plastids [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p><p>The possible role of lycosantalonol or its derivatives in the petiolules is not yet known. While the expression of genes encoding some leaf terpenes has been shown to be induced by herbivory or fungal attack, our attempts to find conditions under which <italic>CPT2</italic> or <italic>TPS21</italic> are induced, for example by using alamethicin [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] have failed to identify such conditions. Since wild-type petiolules make at most low levels of lycosantalonol, this compounds or its derivatives are unlikely to be involved in direct defense.</p></sec><sec id="sec020"><title>Evolution of <italic>cis</italic>-prenyltransferases that produce short-chain prenyl diphosphates and terpene synthases that use all-<italic>cis</italic>-prenyldiphohsphates</title><p>The genomes of most plant species examined appear to have a small (&#x0003c;10 members) family of CPT genes. However, these genes are believed to be involved in the biosynthesis of polyprenols (&#x0003e;C<sub>35</sub>) [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Only in the genus <italic>Solanum</italic> (Solanaceae) have CPT genes been found that are involved in the synthesis of precursors of C<sub>10</sub>-C<sub>20</sub> terpenes [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0119302.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0119302.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0119302.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0119302.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0119302.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], although analysis of the recently released genome sequence of <italic>Nicotiana tomentosiformis</italic> and <italic>N</italic>. <italic>sylvestiris</italic> reveal close homologs of <italic>SlCPT6</italic>, which encodes a <italic>z</italic>FPS, but no close homologs of <italic>SlCPT2</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0119302.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). The limited distribution of CPTs for the synthesis of C<sub>10</sub>-C<sub>20</sub> prenyldiphosphates to Solanaceae, and in particular of CPT2 to the <italic>Solanum</italic> genus, suggests that such enzymes are evolutionary novelties and that the ability to synthesize lycosantalene and lycosantalonol is probably confined to <italic>Solanum</italic> or at most to Solanaceae.</p><p>In a previous study, we suggested that <italic>TPS21</italic> was created by a duplication of an ancestral gene likely to encode a diterpene, and whose other progeny is <italic>TPS18</italic>. A second duplication, in the <italic>TPS21</italic> gene lineage, gave rise to an ancestral <italic>TPS19</italic>/<italic>TPS20</italic> lineage (which then duplicated to <italic>TPS19</italic> and <italic>TPS20</italic>) [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Based on the position of <italic>TPS21</italic> in the phylogenetic tree and its activity with NNPP, we further hypothesized that the ability to use <italic>cis</italic>-prenyl diphosphates arose first in the ancestral <italic>TPS21</italic> lineage. Although CPT2 had been shown to be able to use NPP and <italic>zz</italic>FPP as substrates, its catalytic efficiency with these substrates is lower than with DMAPP as substrate [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. These data are consistent with CPT2 having a similar catalytic activity to that of the ancestral <italic>cis</italic>-prenyltransferase in the cluster, since it is not dependent on other <italic>cis</italic>-prenyl diphosphates for its substrate and therefore did not have to evolve only after the others had. We also note that the <italic>K</italic>
<sub><italic>m</italic></sub> value of CPT2 for IPP is lower than of other CPTs in the terpenoid gene cluster on chromosome 8.</p></sec><sec id="sec021"><title>Origin of CYP71BN1</title><p>Cytochrome P450 oxidoreductases are known to catalyze reactions including hydroxylation, peroxidation and epoxidation. These enzymes are categorized into clades based on their amino acid sequences [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Their catalytic mechanism has been well studied and individual family members have been shown to have slightly different helical structures that might be associated with different substrate binding. CYP71BN1 catalyzes the two-step oxidation of lycosantalene. The CYP71 enzymes most similar in primary sequence to CYP71BN1 are GAO and AMO, each of which catalyzes three sequential oxidations of a sesquiterpene to produce a sesquiterpene acid. CYP71s, including GAO and AMO, appear to have evolved from the CYP701 family, whose members include the enzyme that catalyzes the three-step oxidation of the diterpene <italic>ent</italic>-kaurene to form <italic>ent</italic>-kaurenoic acid, a precursor of the plant gibberellin hormones (<xref rid="pone.0119302.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>, [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]). This <italic>ent</italic>-kaurene oxidase (KO), which is found in all land plants, is the only primary metabolism enzyme in the CYP71 clan. Furthermore, both enzymatic products of GAO and AMO, germacrene A acid and amorpha-4,11-dine acid, respectively, are intermediates of the final metabolic products, which are sesquiterpene lactones (costunolide and artemisinin, respectively). These examples, and the observation that no lycosantalonol could be detected in wild-type tomato plants, suggest that lycosantalonol only serves as an intermediate and is further metabolized by other enzymes in tomato, although we have not yet identified such enzymes.</p></sec><sec id="sec022"><title>Evolution of the functional terpenoid gene cluster on chromosome 8 of tomato</title><p>Recently, multiple examples of &#x0201c;clusters&#x0201d; of genes that are involved in specifying enzymes for the same pathway of specialized metabolism have been identified in plants [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. We have recently reported that the three genes <italic>CPT2</italic>, <italic>TPS21</italic> and <italic>CYP71BN1</italic>, involved in the biosynthesis of the novel diterpenoid lycosantalonol, are located next to each other in a narrow region of 20 kb on chromosome 8 in <italic>S</italic>. <italic>lycopersicum</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. <italic>CPT1</italic> (<italic>NDPS1</italic>), <italic>TPS19</italic>, and <italic>TPS20</italic> (<italic>PHS</italic>), which are responsible for the biosynthesis of the trichome-specific monoterpene &#x003b2;-phellandrene, are located next to these three genes, as are two other TPS genes, <italic>TPS18</italic> and <italic>TPS41</italic>, that encode proteins whose biochemical activities have not yet been determined. A very similar gene cluster with the same gene order has also been found on chromosome 8 of the wild tomato species <italic>S</italic>. <italic>pimpinellifolium</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. However, in other species in <italic>Solanum</italic> that have been examined&#x02014;<italic>S</italic>. <italic>pennellii</italic>, <italic>S</italic>. <italic>habrohaites</italic>, and <italic>S</italic>. <italic>tuberosum</italic>&#x02014;<italic>CPT2</italic>, <italic>TPS21</italic>, and/or <italic>CYP71BN1</italic> contain small or large deletions that clearly render them inactive. Inactivation by deletions is often observed in genes that once encoded enzymes of specialized metabolism [<xref rid="pone.0119302.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Since plant specialized metabolites co-evolve with pathogens and herbivores or as adaptations to environmental stress, it is not surprising that pathways of specialized metabolites are inherently unstable and exhibit fast rates of evolution.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec023"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0119302.s001"><label>S1 Fig</label><caption><title>RT-PCR analysis to identify 35S-<italic>CPT2</italic> transgenic plants with higher levels of <italic>SlCPT2</italic> transcripts compared to non-transgenic plants.</title><p>Transgenic plants lines CPT2oe-03, 19 and 22 were further analyzed for their diterpenoid content by GC-MS. Lines CPT2oe-03, 07, 19, 24 and 26 were used for metabolic analysis by HPLC-MS.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0119302.s001.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0119302.s002"><label>S2 Fig</label><caption><title>Mass spectra of compounds corresponding to peaks in <xref rid="pone.0119302.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>.</title><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0119302.s002.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0119302.s003"><label>S3 Fig</label><caption><title>Determination of pH optimum of activity of purified recombinant CPT2.</title><p>Buffers used were 50 mM citrate buffer (pH 3.0&#x02013;5.5), 50 mM phosphate buffer (pH 6.0&#x02013;8.0) and 50 mM Tris-HCl buffer (pH 8.0&#x02013;9.5).</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0119302.s003.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0119302.s004"><label>S4 Fig</label><caption><title>Petiolule <italic>CPT2</italic> transcript levels in 16 transgenic plants expressing the 35S-CPT2-RNAi construct compared to wild-type <italic>CPT2</italic> transcript levels.</title><p>Total RNA was extracted from petiolule tissue. Lines CPT2i-01, 04, 05, 12 and 18, which had the lowest <italic>CPT2</italic> transcript levels, were used for metabolic analysis.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0119302.s004.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0119302.s005"><label>S5 Fig</label><caption><title>Neighbor-joining phylogenetic tree analysis of <italic>Solanum</italic> and <italic>Nicotiana</italic> CPTs.</title><p>The sizes of the polyisoprenoids of characterized enzymes are shown inside brackets. Nt, <italic>Nicotiana tomentosiformis</italic>; Ns, <italic>Nicotiana sylvestris</italic>.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0119302.s005.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0119302.s006"><label>S1 Table</label><caption><title>Synthetic oligonucleotides used in this study.</title><p>(PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0119302.s006.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Thomas Clemente and the University of Nebraska plant transformation facility for generating transgenic tomato plants.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0119302.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Pichersky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lewinsohn</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Convergent evolution in plant specialized metabolism</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Plant Biol</source>
<volume>62</volume>: <fpage>549</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>566</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-arplant-042110-103814</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21275647?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21275647</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Thulasiram</surname><given-names>HV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Erickson</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Poulter</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Chimeras of two isoprenoid synthases catalyze all four coupling reactions in isoprenoid biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>316</volume>: <fpage>73</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>76</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 17412950?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17412950</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Vickers</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gershenzon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lerdau</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Loreto</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A unified mechanism of action for volatile isoprenoids in plant abiotic stress</article-title>. <source>Nat Chem Biol</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>283</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>291</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nchembio.158</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19377454?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19377454</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Dudareva</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pichersky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Biochemical and molecular genetic aspects of floral scents</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>
<volume>122</volume>: <fpage>627</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>634</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 10712525?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10712525</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Gershenzon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dudareva</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The function of terpene natural products in the natural world</article-title>. <source>Nat Chem Biol</source>
<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>408</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>414</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 17576428?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17576428</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Dicke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>IT</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The evolutionary context for herbivore-induced plant volatiles: beyond the &#x02018;cry for help&#x02019;</article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>167</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>175</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2009.12.002</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20047849?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20047849</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tholl</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bohlmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pichersky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The family of terpene synthases in plants: A mid-size family of genes for specialized metabolism that is highly diversified throughout the kingdom</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>
<volume>66</volume>: <fpage>212</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>229</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2011.04520.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21443633?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21443633</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Schilmiller</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schauvinhold</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Charbonneau</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Monoterpenes in the glandular trichomes of tomato are synthesized from a neryl diphosphate precursor rather than geranyl diphosphate</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>106</volume>: <fpage>10865</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10870</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0904113106</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19487664?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19487664</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Sallaud</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rontein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Onillon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jab&#x000e8;s</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Duff&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Giacalone</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A novel pathway for sesquiterpene biosynthesis from <italic>Z</italic>, <italic>Z</italic>-farnesyl pyrophosphate in the wild tomato <italic>Solanum habrochaites</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>21</volume>: <fpage>301</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>317</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.107.057885</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19155349?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19155349</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Akhtar</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matsuba</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schauvinhold</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lees</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The tomato <italic>cis</italic>-prenyltransferase gene family</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>
<volume>73</volume>: <fpage>640</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>652</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.12063</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23134568?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23134568</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Matsuba</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>TTH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wiegert</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Falara</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gonzales-Vigil</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leong</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Evolution of a complex locus for terpene biosynthesis in <italic>solanum</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>2022</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2036</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.113.111013</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23757397?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23757397</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Zi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matsuba</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tantillo</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pichersky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Biosynthesis of lycosantalonol, a <italic>cis</italic>-prenyl derived diterpenoid</article-title>. <source>J Am Chem Soc</source>
<volume>136</volume>: <fpage>16951</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16953</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja508477e</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25406026?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25406026</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Sallaud</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Giacalone</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>T&#x000f6;pfer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goepfert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bakaher</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>R&#x000f6;sti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Characterization of two genes for the biosynthesis of the labdane diterpene <italic>Z</italic>-abienol in tobacco (<italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic>) glandular trichomes</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>
<volume>72</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2012.05068.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22672125?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22672125</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Tzfira</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lacroix</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vyas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leitner-Dagan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>pSAT vectors: a modular series of plasmids for autofluorescent protein tagging and expression of multiple genes in plants</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source>
<volume>57</volume>: <fpage>503</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>516</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 15821977?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15821977</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Goderis</surname><given-names>IJWM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>De Bolle</surname><given-names>MFC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fran&#x000e7;ois</surname><given-names>IEJA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wouters</surname><given-names>PFJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Broekaert</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cammue</surname><given-names>BPA</given-names></name>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>A set of modular plant transformation vectors allowing flexible insertion of up to six expression units</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source>
<volume>50</volume>: <fpage>17</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>27</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 12139006?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12139006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lough</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Emerson</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Forster</surname><given-names>RLS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>A surveillance system regulates selective entry of RNA into the shoot apex</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>1497</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1508</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 12119370?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12119370</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hajdukiewicz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Svab</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maliga</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>The small, versatile <italic>pPZP</italic> family of Agrobacterium binary vectors for plant transformation</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source>
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>989</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>994</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 7919218?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7919218</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gonzales-Vigil</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matsuba</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pichersky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Determination of residues responsible for substrate and product specificity of <italic>Solanum habrochaites</italic> short-chain <italic>cis</italic>-prenyltransferases</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>
<volume>164</volume>: <fpage>80</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.113.230466</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24254315?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24254315</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hamberger</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Plant P450s as versatile drivers for evolution of species-specific chemical diversity</article-title>. <source>Phil Trans R Soc B</source>
<volume>368</volume>: <fpage>20120426</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2012.0426</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23297350?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23297350</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>G&#x000f6;pfert</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ikezawa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Macnevin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kathiresan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Conrad</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Biochemical conservation and evolution of germacrene A oxidase in asteraceae</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>285</volume>: <fpage>16588</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16598</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M110.111757</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20351109?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20351109</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Teoh</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Polichuk</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Covello</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>
<italic>Artemisia annua L</italic>. (Asteraceae) trichome-specific cDNAs reveal CYP71AV1, a cytochrome P450 with a key role in the biosynthesis of the antimalarial sesquiterpene lactone artemisinin</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett</source>
<volume>580</volume>: <fpage>1411</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1416</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 16458889?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16458889</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ro</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paradise</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ouellet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ndungu</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Production of the antimalarial drug precursor artemisinic acid in engineered yeast</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>440</volume>: <fpage>940</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>943</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 16612385?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16612385</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Inagaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Etherington</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Geisler</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dokarry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Investigation of the potential for triterpene synthesis in rice through genome mining and metabolic engineering</article-title>. <source>New Phytologist</source>
<volume>191</volume>: <fpage>432</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>448</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2011.03712.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21501172?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21501172</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Dudareva</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Klempien</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Muhlemann</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Biosynthesis, function and metabolic engineering of plant volatile organic compounds</article-title>. <source>New Phytologist</source>
<volume>198</volume>: <fpage>16</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.12145</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23383981?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23383981</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nakayama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Achievements and perspectives in biochemistry concerning anthocyanin modification for blue flower coloration</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source>
<volume>56</volume>: <fpage>28</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 25015943?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25015943</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Frey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schullehner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dick</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fiesselmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gierl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Benzoxazinoid biosynthesis, a model for evolution of secondary metabolic pathways in plants</article-title>. <source>Phytochemistry</source>
<volume>70</volume>: <fpage>1645</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1651</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2009.05.012</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19577780?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19577780</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Falara</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alba</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kant</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schuurink</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pichersky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Geranyllinalool synthases in Solanaceae and other angiosperms constitute an ancient branch of diterpene synthases involved in the synthesis of defensive compounds</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>
<volume>166</volume>: <fpage>428</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>441</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.114.243246</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25052853?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25052853</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Swiezewska</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Danikiewicz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Polyisoprenoids: structure, biosynthesis and function</article-title>. <source>Progress in Lipid Research</source>
<volume>44</volume>: <fpage>235</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>258</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 16019076?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16019076</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Gonzales-Vigil</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hufnagel</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Last</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Evolution of TPS20&#x02010;related terpene synthases influences chemical diversity in the glandular trichomes of the wild tomato relative <italic>Solanum habrochaites</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>
<volume>71</volume>: <fpage>921</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>935</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2012.05040.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22563774?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22563774</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Werck-Reichhart</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A P450-centric view of plant evolution</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>
<volume>66</volume>: <fpage>194</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>211</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2011.04529.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21443632?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21443632</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>N&#x000fc;tzmann</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Osbourn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Gene clustering in plant specialized metabolism</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Biotechnol</source>
<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>91</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>99</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.copbio.2013.10.009</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24679264?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24679264</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Rad</surname><given-names>UV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huttl</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lottspeich</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gierl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Frey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Two glucosyltransferases are involved in detoxification of benzoxazinoids in maize</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>
<volume>28</volume>: <fpage>633</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>642</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 11851909?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11851909</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Frey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sicker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lindberg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meeley</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>A 2-oxoglutarate-dependent dioxygenase is integrated in DIMBOA-biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Phytochemistry</source>
<volume>62</volume>: <fpage>371</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>376</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 12620350?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12620350</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Jonczyk</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Osterrieder</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fiesselmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schullehner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haslbeck</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Elucidation of the final reactions of DIMBOAglucoside biosynthesis in maize: characterization of Bx6 and Bx7</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>
<volume>146</volume>: <fpage>1053</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1063</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.107.111237</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18192444?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18192444</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bakht</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leggett</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maxwell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Melton</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Osbourn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>A gene cluster for secondary metabolism in oat: implications for the evolution of metabolic diversity in plants</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>101</volume>: <fpage>8233</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8238</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 15148404?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15148404</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wilderman</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coates</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Identification of syn-pimara-7,15-diene synthase reveals functional clustering of terpene synthases involved in rice phytoalexin/allelochemical biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>
<volume>135</volume>: <fpage>2098</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2105</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 15299118?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15299118</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ishihara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Imaishi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Endo</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ohkawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Iwamura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Molecular characterization and chromosomal localization of cytochrome P450 genes involved in the biosynthesis of cyclic hydroxamic acids in hexaploid wheat</article-title>. <source>Mol Genet Genomics</source>
<volume>267</volume>: <fpage>210</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>217</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 11976964?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11976964</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ishihara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Imaishi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ohkawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Endo</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Iwamura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Rearrangement of the genes for the biosynthesis of benzoxazinones in the evolution of Triticeae species</article-title>. <source>Planta</source>
<volume>217</volume>: <fpage>776</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>782</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 12734755?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12734755</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Michelmore</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meyers</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Clusters of resistance genes in plants evolve by divergent selection and a birth-and-death process</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>1113</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1130</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 9847076?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9847076</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0119302.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>MEGA5: Molecular evolutionary genetics analysis using maximum likelihood, evolutionary distance, and maximum parsimony methods</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
<volume>28</volume>: <fpage>2731</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2739</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msr121</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21546353?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21546353</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>