<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?origin publisher?><?properties no_embargo?><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlm.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Planta</journal-id><journal-title>Planta</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0032-0935</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1432-2048</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2756395</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17924138</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">631</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00425-007-0631-y</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Herbivore-induced terpenoid emission in <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic>: concerted action of jasmonate, ethylene and calcium signaling</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arimura</surname><given-names>Gen-ichiro</given-names></name><address><phone>+49-3641-571213</phone><fax>+49-3641-571202</fax><email>garimura@ice.mpg.de</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garms</surname><given-names>Stefan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maffei</surname><given-names>Massimo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bossi</surname><given-names>Simone</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schulze</surname><given-names>Birgit</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leitner</surname><given-names>Margit</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mith&#x000f6;fer</surname><given-names>Axel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boland</surname><given-names>Wilhelm</given-names></name><address><email>boland@ice.mpg.de</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Bioorganic Chemistry, Max Planck Institute for Chemical Ecology, Hans-Kn&#x000f6;ll-Stra&#x000df;e 8, 07745 Jena, Germany </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Plant Biology and Centre of Excellence CEBIOVEM, University of Turin, Viale P.A. Mattioli 25, 10125 Turin, Italy </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>10</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>227</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>453</fpage><lpage>464</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>3</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>9</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Springer-Verlag 2007</copyright-statement></permissions><abstract xml:lang="EN"><p>Plant volatiles emitted by <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic> in response to feeding larvae of <italic>Spodoptera exigua</italic> are composed of a complex blend of terpenoids. The cDNAs of three terpene synthases (TPSs), which contribute to the blend of terpenoids, were cloned from <italic>M. truncatula</italic>. Their functional characterization proved MtTPS1 to be a &#x003b2;-caryophyllene synthase and MtTPS5 to be a multi-product sesquiterpene synthase. MtTPS3 encodes a bifunctional enzyme producing (<italic>E</italic>)-nerolidol and geranyllinalool (precursors of C<sub>11</sub> and C<sub>16</sub> homoterpenes) from different prenyl diphosphates serving as substrates. The addition of jasmonic acid (JA) induced expression of the TPS genes, but terpenoid emission was higher from plants treated with JA and the ethylene precursor 1-amino-cyclopropyl-1-carboxylic acid. Compared to infested wild-type <italic>M. truncatula</italic> plants, lower amounts of various sesquiterpenes and a C<sub>11</sub>&#x02013;homoterpene were released from an ethylene-insensitive mutant <italic>skl</italic>. This difference coincided with lower transcript levels of <italic>MtTPS5</italic> and of 1-deoxy-<sc>d</sc>-xylulose-5-phosphate synthase (<italic>MtDXS2</italic>) in the damaged <italic>skl</italic> leaves. Moreover, ethephon, an ethylene-releasing compound, modified the extent and mode of the herbivore-stimulated Ca<sup>2+</sup> variations in the cytoplasm that is necessary for both JA and terpene biosynthesis. Thus, ethylene contributes to the herbivory-induced terpenoid biosynthesis at least twice: by modulating both early signaling events such as cytoplasmic Ca<sup>2+</sup>-influx and the downstream JA-dependent biosynthesis of terpenoids.</p><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (doi:10.1007/s00425-007-0631-y) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Calcium</kwd><kwd>Ethylene</kwd><kwd>Jasmonic acid</kwd><kwd><italic>Medicago truncatula</italic></kwd><kwd>Terpenoid</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer-Verlag 2008</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p>Volatile terpenoids, the major products among the herbivore-induced plant volatiles (HIPVs) in the legume <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic>, include monoterpenes (C<sub>10</sub>), sesquiterpenes (C<sub>15</sub>), and tetranor-terpenoids (homoterpenes, C<sub>11</sub> or C<sub>16</sub>) (Leitner et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2005</xref>). The biosynthetic routes to terpenes are fed by either the mevalonate (MVA) pathway in the cytosol/endoplasmic reticulum or the 2-<italic>C</italic>-methyl-<sc>d</sc>-erythritol 4-phosphate (MEP) pathway in the plastids; both pathways generate the five-carbon compound isopentenyl diphosphate (IDP) and its isomer dimethylallyl diphosphate (DMADP). Cytosolic and plastidic prenyltransferases, respectively, synthesize farnesyl diphosphate (FDP) as a substrate for sesquiterpenes and geranyl diphosphate (GDP) and geranylgeranyl diphosphate (GGDP) as substrates for mono- and diterpenes (Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Concepci&#x000f3;n and Boronat <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2002</xref>; Eisenreich et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2004</xref>). Both pathways can cross-talk by exchanging intermediates (e.g., IDP or GDP) (Bick and Lange <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2003</xref>). Molecular diversity is further expanded by the terpene synthases (TPSs), which utilize the different prenyl diphosphates as substrates. The transcript levels of four genes for terpene synthases, TPSs 1&#x02013;4, are enhanced in <italic>M. truncatula</italic> leaves damaged by <italic>Spodoptera exigua</italic> (beet armyworm [BAW]) herbivory or treated with methyl jasmonate (Gomez et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2005</xref>). Terpenoid formation is generally assumed to be regulated on the transcript level of the TPS genes (Dudareva et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2003</xref>; McKay et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2003</xref>; Sharon-Asa et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2003</xref>; Arimura et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2004a</xref>), but the mode of regulation is often complex (L&#x000fc;cker et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2001</xref>; Aharoni et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2003</xref>; Arimura et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2004b</xref>; Aharoni et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2005</xref>) and needs to be studied individually with respect to the plant and the herbivore.</p><p>Till now, little has been known about early physiological events and the interaction between the signaling networks in plants that occur when herbivores feed. The interaction of various pathways in the networks is assumed to result in an integrated overall response that initiates the emission of a characteristic volatile pattern. Since the blends of HIPVs may vary with the attacking herbivore (De Moraes et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">1998</xref>; Ozawa et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2000</xref>; Leitner et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2005</xref>), various components and cross-talk between the involved signaling pathways are thought to be responsible for the characteristic terpenoid blend (Engelberth et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2001</xref>; Schmelz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2003b</xref>). Several oxylipin compounds (jasmonic acid (JA), its precursors, and related compounds) very likely act as master switches for herbivore-stimulated plant responses, activating distinct sets of defense genes leading to terpenoid formation (Arimura et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2004a</xref>; Ament et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2006</xref>). In addition, antagonistic or synergistic cross-reactions with other regulators, in particular involving ethylene and salicylic acid, seem to control and coordinate the formation of a characteristic blend of volatiles (Ozawa et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2000</xref>; Engelberth et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2001</xref>; Horiuchi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2001</xref>; Schmelz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2003b</xref>). Although ethylene is a well known modulator of processes of plant development and plant defense against biotic and abiotic stresses (Wang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2002</xref>), only little is known about how ethylene affects the composition of herbivore-induced volatiles (Kahl et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2000</xref>; Schmelz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2003a</xref>; Schmelz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2003b</xref>). Using the model plant <italic>M. truncatula</italic>, we compared the ethylene-insensitive mutant <italic>sickle</italic> (<italic>skl</italic>) with wild-type plants and showed that the ethylene signaling cascade modulates the intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup>-level and interacts with JA signaling to generate a specific blend of terpenoids in response to feeding BAW larvae. In addition, three cDNAs encoding new terpene synthases, <italic>MtTPS1</italic>, <italic>MtTPS3</italic>, and <italic>MtTPS5</italic>, were cloned from <italic>M. truncatula</italic> and heterologously expressed for biochemical characterization.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Plants and caterpillars</title><p>Plants of <italic>M. truncatula</italic>, wild-type cv. Jemalong (Pogue Agri Partners, Kenedy, TX, USA) and the ethylene-insensitive mutant <italic>skl</italic> (<italic>skl1&#x02013;1</italic>: isolated and backcrossed by the group of Dr. Douglas R. Cook, University of California, Davis) were grown in soil. Each plastic pot contained one or two plants and was kept in a growth chamber at 27&#x000b0;C (14&#x000a0;h light:10&#x000a0;h dark; relative humidity: 65%) for 6&#x02013;8&#x000a0;weeks. Plants without flowers were used for each treatment. <italic>Spodoptera exigua</italic> [beet armyworm (BAW)] larvae were reared on artificial diet in a plastic box (22&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1&#x000b0;C; 14&#x000a0;h light: 10&#x000a0;h dark) (Bergomaz and Boppr&#x000e9; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">1986</xref>). For BAW infestation, 5&#x02013;6 third-instar larvae were placed on shoots of <italic>M. truncatula</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Chemical treatment</title><p>A solution containing JA (1&#x000a0;mM, pH 5.8&#x02013;6.0), 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylic acid (ACC, 1&#x000a0;mM; Sigma-Aldrich, St Louis, MO, USA), and/or silver thiosulfate (STS, 1&#x000a0;mM; Sigma-Aldrich) in 20&#x000a0;ml of water was evenly sprayed onto intact plants growing in plastic pots. Lower concentrations of JA and ACC solutions (e.g. 0.3&#x000a0;mM each) had little effect on induced volatiles in <italic>M. truncatula</italic> plants. For ethephon treatment, ethephon (10&#x000a0;mM; Sigma-Aldrich) in 100 &#x003bc;l of 50&#x000a0;mM MES buffer, pH 6.0, was applied to leaves of an intact <italic>M. truncatula</italic> plant. For inhibition experiments, the petioles of detached plantlets of <italic>M. truncatula</italic> were placed in glass vials containing aqueous solutions of fosmidomycin (7&#x000a0;ml, 100 &#x003bc;M; Molecular Probes, Eugene, OR, USA), or lovastatin (7&#x000a0;ml, 100 &#x003bc;M; A.G. Scientific, San Diego, CA, USA). Incubation experiments with labelled precursors were carried out by placing the plantlets in water (7&#x000a0;ml, containing 1-deoxy-[5,5-<sup>2</sup>H<sub>2</sub>]-<sc>d</sc>-xylulose at 1&#x000a0;mg/ml). Controls were also placed in water. After pre-incubation with the labelled precursor or the inhibitors for 2&#x000a0;h, either JA&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;ACC (1&#x000a0;mM each) in 20&#x000a0;ml of water were sprayed evenly onto the plants or 5&#x02013;6 larvae were placed on the plants. For headspace analysis, the plants were transferred 2&#x000a0;h after JA&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;ACC treatment into a glass cabinet for volatile collection (see below). Each treatment started at 10:00. During treatments, temperatures were kept constant at 22&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1&#x000b0;C, and the photoperiod was 14&#x000a0;h light (6,000 lux): 10&#x000a0;h dark. The light period extended from 07:00 to 21:00.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Analysis of volatiles</title><p>For headspace analysis, a potted plant or a plantlet in a glass vial was enclosed with or without caterpillars in glass containers (2.5&#x000a0;l). The emitted volatiles were trapped onto charcoal traps (1.5&#x000a0;mg of charcoal, CLSA-Filter, Le Ruisseau de Montbrun, Daumazan sur Arize, France) while air circulated for 24 or 48&#x000a0;h. The collected volatiles were eluted with dichloromethane (2&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;20 &#x003bc;l) containing <italic>n</italic>-bromodecane (100&#x000a0;ng &#x003bc;l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) as an internal standard. Samples were analyzed on a ThermoQuest/Finnigan TRACE GC 2000 with a TRACE MS (Manchester, UK) equipped with an EC<sup>TM</sup>-5 capillary column (0.25&#x000a0;mm i.d.&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;15&#x000a0;m with 0.25-mm film, Alltech, Deerfield, IL, USA). Injection volume: 1 &#x003bc;l; split 1:100; 220&#x000b0;C. Ionization energy: 70&#x000a0;eV. Compounds were eluted under programmed conditions starting from 40&#x000b0;C (2-min hold) and ramped up at 10&#x000b0;C min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> to 200&#x000b0;C followed by 30&#x000b0;C min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> to 280&#x000b0;C, which was held for 1&#x000a0;min prior to cooling. Helium at a flow rate of 1.5&#x000a0;ml min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> served as a carrier gas. The headspace volatiles were identified by comparing their mass spectra and Kov&#x000e0;ts indices with authentic references on two columns of different polarity (Leitner et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2005</xref>). Absolute quantification of the volatiles was not possible due to the limited availability of authentic standards and partly overlapping peak areas of germacrene D  <bold>16</bold> and an unknown sesquiterpene <bold>17</bold>. Relative peak areas from integration of the reconstructed ion chromatogram were used without additional calibration.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Analysis of oxylipins</title><p>Leaves (0.5&#x000a0;g) were homogenized with an Ultra-Turrax<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> T25 Basic (Ika, Staufen, Germany) on ice for 5&#x000a0;min in methanol (8&#x000a0;ml) containing 0.03% BHT and 0.03&#x000a0;M pentafluorobenzyl hydroxylamine hydrochloride (PFBHA, Sigma-Aldrich) (Schulze et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2006</xref>). [<sup>2</sup>H<sub>2</sub>]-JA (150&#x000a0;ng) and [<sup>2</sup>H<sub>2</sub>]-12-oxophytodienoic acid (250&#x000a0;ng) were added as internal standards. The methanol extract was shaken for derivatisation at room temperature for 2&#x000a0;h, and 4.0&#x000a0;ml diluted HCl (pH&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3) were added. The methanol/water phase was carefully extracted with hexane (3&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10&#x000a0;ml), and after centrifugation, the hexane layers were collected and combined. The hexane fraction was passed through a Chromabond NH<sub>2</sub> cartridge (3&#x000a0;ml/500&#x000a0;mg, Macherey-Nagel, D&#x000fc;ren, Germany) preconditioned with methanol (5&#x000a0;ml) and hexane (5&#x000a0;ml), washed with the solvent mixture of 2-propanol/dichloromethane (2:1 v/v, 5&#x000a0;ml), and eluted with diethyl ether/formic acid (98:2, 10&#x000a0;ml). The solvents were evaporated under argon, and the remaining crude acids were esterified with an ethereal solution of diazomethane (1&#x000a0;ml) at room temperature for 5&#x000a0;min. After evaporation of the solvent, the sample was dissolved in 30 &#x003bc;l dichloromethane and analyzed by gas chromatography&#x02013;mass spectrometry (GC&#x02013;MS) as described (Schulze et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2006</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Cytoplasmic Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentration</title><p>A solution of Fluo-3 AM (acetoxy-methyl ester of Fluo-3, 5 &#x003bc;M, Fluka, Buchs, Switzerland), 0.5&#x000a0;mM calcium sulphate, and 2.5 &#x003bc;M DCMU [3-(3&#x02032;,4&#x02032;-dichlorphenyl)-1,1-dimethylurea] in 50&#x000a0;mM MES buffer, pH 6.0, was used for initial treatment of leaves of an intact <italic>M. truncatula</italic> plant as previously described (Maffei et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2004</xref>). A leaf was cut once by a razor blade in order to allow the dye to enter the tissues. One hour after treatment with Fluo-3 AM, the leaf was fixed on an Olympus FLUOview confocal laser scanning microscope stative without detaching it from the plant. The microscope was operated with a Krypton/Argon laser at 488 and 568&#x000a0;nm wavelengths: the first wavelength excited the Fluo-3 dye emitting green light, while the second excited mostly chloroplasts emitting a red fluorescence. Images generated by the FluoView software were analyzed using the NIH Image J software described earlier (Maffei et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2004</xref>). Aequorin-dependent luminescence was determined according to (Maffei et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2006</xref>).</p><p>For high resolution subcellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> localization, after treatment with Fluo-3 AM for 1&#x000a0;h, leaves were mounted on a Leica TCS SP2 multiband confocal laser-scanning microscope stative without separating the leaf from the plant. Scannings were recorded using the HCX PL APO 63x/1.20 W Corr/0.17CS objective. The microscope was operated with a Laser Ar (458&#x000a0;nm/5&#x000a0;mW; 476&#x000a0;nm/5&#x000a0;mW; 488&#x000a0;nm/20&#x000a0;mW; 514&#x000a0;nm/20&#x000a0;mW), a Laser HeNe 543&#x000a0;nm/1.2&#x000a0;mW, and a Laser HeNe 633&#x000a0;nm/10&#x000a0;mW.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Real-time PCR</title><p>Total RNA was isolated from leaf tissues using the Concert Plant RNA Reagent (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) following the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol. Total RNA was purified to eliminate genomic DNA using the Qiagen RNeasy Plant RNA kit and the RNase-Free DNase Set (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany). First-strand cDNA was synthesized using the SuperScript III Reverse Transcriptase (RT) (Invitrogen), oligo(dT)<sub>12&#x02013;18</sub> primer, and 2 &#x003bc;g of total RNA at 50&#x000b0;C for 50&#x000a0;min. Primers for real-time polymerase chain reaction (PCR) were designed using the Primer 3 Software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://frodo.wi.mit.edu/cgi-bin/primer3/primer3_www.cgi">http://frodo.wi.mit.edu/cgi-bin/primer3/primer3_www.cgi</ext-link>) for a length of the resulting PCR product of approximately 200&#x000a0;bp. Primers were designed using partial DNA sequences obtained from the TIGR <italic>M. truncatula</italic> expressed sequence tag (EST) database: (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.tigr.org/tigr-scripts/tgi/T_index.cgi?species=medicago">http://www.tigr.org/tigr-scripts/tgi/T_index.cgi?species=medicago</ext-link>) and GenBank. The real-time PCR was done on a Mx3000P Real-Time PCR System (Stratagene, La Jolla, CA, USA). The process was performed with 25 &#x003bc;l of reaction mixture containing 12.5 &#x003bc;l of 2&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;Brilliant SYBR Green QPCR Master Mix (Stratagene), cDNA (1 &#x003bc;l from 20 &#x003bc;l of each RT product pool), 100&#x000a0;nM primers, and 30&#x000a0;mM ROX as a passive reference dye. The following protocol was followed: initial polymerase activation: 10&#x000a0;min at 95&#x000b0;C; 40 cycles of 30 s at 95&#x000b0;C, 60&#x000a0;s at 55&#x000b0;C, and 30&#x000a0;s at 72&#x000b0;C. PCR conditions were determined by comparing threshold values in dilution series of the RT product, followed by non-RT template control and non-template control for each primer pair. Relative RNA levels were calibrated and normalized with the level of actin mRNA (EST annotation no. AA660796).</p><p>Primers used for real-time PCR are: actin, 5&#x02032;-TAC CCC ATT GAG CAC GGT AT-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-ATA CAT GGC AGG CAC ATT GA-3&#x02032;; <italic>MtDXS1</italic>, 5&#x02032;-AGC CGT TCA GAA CTG TTT GG-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-ATC AAG GGC CAT GAA CTG AG-3&#x02032;; <italic>MtDXS2</italic>, 5&#x02032;-ACA CCG GTG GTC ATC TTA GC-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-CAT CCC TTT TGG GAA AAC CT-3&#x02032;; <italic>MtHMGR1</italic>, 5&#x02032;-GCC GTA AAT GAT GGG AGA GA-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-GCC AGC TAA AAC AGC TCC AG-3&#x02032;; <italic>MtTPS1</italic>, 5&#x02032;-TGC TCC AAC CCC TAA TGC TA-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-CCT CGA AGG GTT TGT GAC AT-3&#x02032;; <italic>MtTPS2</italic>, 5&#x02032;-TGT CGC AAA AAC AGA TGA GC-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-ATC CTT GTT GCC TCA ACA CC-3&#x02032;; <italic>MtTPS3</italic>, 5&#x02032;-TGC AAT CAC AAA ATG CAA CA-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-GAT CTG GGA GAC ATG CCA TT-3&#x02032;; <italic>MtTPS5</italic>, 5&#x02032;-CCG ATG CCT TTT ATG ACT CG-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-TGT GCC ACT TGG ATT TTT CA-3&#x02032;. The EST annotation numbers are: actin, AA660796; <italic>MtHMGR1</italic>, TC102857. GenBank accession numbers are: <italic>MtDXS1</italic>, AJ430047; <italic>MtDXS2</italic>, AJ430048; <italic>MtTPS1</italic> AY763425; <italic>MtTPS2</italic>, AY766250; <italic>MtTPS3</italic>, AY766249; <italic>MtTPS5</italic>, DQ188184.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>cDNA cloning and TPS enzyme assay</title><p>Cloning 3&#x02032;-end of <italic>MtTPS5</italic> cDNAs was accomplished by rapid amplification of cDNA ends (RACE PCR) using total RNA and the First Choice RLM-RACE Kit (Ambion, Austin, TX, USA) following the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol. For functional identification, cDNAs were amplified by PCR using <italic>Pfu</italic> DNA Polymerase (Promega, Madison, WI, USA) with a set of primers for an open reading frame of <italic>MtTPS1</italic><italic>MtTPS3</italic>, or <italic>MtTPS5</italic>. The cDNA was subcloned into the pHis8&#x02013;3 expression vector (Jez et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2000</xref>). The recombinant vectors were transformed into <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> BL21-CodonPlus(DE3). The bacterial strain was grown to<italic> A</italic><sub>600</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.5 at 37&#x000b0;C in 5&#x000a0;ml of LB medium with kanamycin at 50 &#x003bc;g/ml. Cultures were induced with 1&#x000a0;mM isopropyl 1-thio-&#x003b2;-<sc>d</sc>-galactopyranoside (IPTG) and held overnight at 16&#x000b0;C while being shaken at 200&#x000a0;rpm. Cells were pelleted by centrifugation and resuspended in 1&#x000a0;ml TPS buffer (25&#x000a0;mM HEPES, pH&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;7.3, 12.5&#x000a0;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.25&#x000a0;mM MnCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.25&#x000a0;mM NaWO<sub>4</sub>, 0.125&#x000a0;mM NaF, 5&#x000a0;mM DTT, 10% glycerol). Resuspended cells were broken by sonication. Cell extracts were cleared by centrifugation and assayed for TPS activity with 50 &#x003bc;M GDP (Echelon Biosciences Incorporated, Salt Lake City, UT, USA), FDP (Echelon Biosciences Incorporated) or GGDP (Sigma-Aldrich). The assay mixture (1&#x000a0;ml) was covered with 1&#x000a0;ml of pentane to trap volatile products. After incubation at 30&#x000b0;C for 1&#x000a0;h, the pentane layer was transferred to a glass vial and concentrated to ~150 &#x003bc;l under a gentle stream of N<sub>2</sub>. Alternatively, the headspace of the assay mixture was analyzed using solid-phase microextraction (SPME, Supelco Inc., Bellefonte, PA, USA). Extracts of <italic>E. coli</italic> transformed with expression vectors without the TPS gene were used as controls following the above procedure. The enzymatic products were analyzed by GC&#x02013;MS and identified by comparing their mass spectra and Kov&#x000e0;ts indices with authentic references as described above.</p><p>Stereochemistry of (<italic>E</italic>)-nerolidol was analyzed by a Hewlett-Packard 5980 gas chromatograph coupled to a Hewlett-Packard 5917A quadrupole type mass selective detector (70 eV; scan range: 45&#x02013;400&#x000a0;amu) equipped with a capillary column coated with heptakis-(2,6-di-<italic>O</italic>-methyl-3-<italic>O</italic>-pentyl)-<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-cyclodextrin (0.25&#x000a0;mm&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;25&#x000a0;m, 0.25 &#x003bc;m film, Macherey Nagel, D&#x000fc;ren, Germany). Samples (1 &#x003bc;l) were injected splitless at 230&#x000b0;C with a column flow of 1&#x000a0;ml min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (He). Elution was programmed from 50 to 160&#x000b0;C (10&#x000a0;min) at 2.3&#x000b0;C min<sup>&#x02212;1&#x000a0;</sup>and then to 210&#x000b0;C at 15&#x000b0;C min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (2&#x000a0;min). The elution order of (3<italic>S</italic>)-(<italic>E</italic>)-nerolidol and (3<italic>R</italic>)-(<italic>E</italic>)-nerolidol was determined with a racemic and a chiral reference according to (Degenhardt and Gershenzon <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2000</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>HIPV biosynthesis in <italic>M. truncatula</italic> WT and the ethylene-insensitive mutant <italic>skl</italic></title><p>The plant hormone ethylene is generally involved in processes of plant development and plant defense against biotic and abiotic stresses (Wang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2002</xref>). In genetic studies using <italic>M. truncatula</italic>, the ethylene-insensitive mutant <italic>skl</italic> displayed a supernodulation phenotype (Penmetsa and Cook <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">1997</xref>; Oldroyd et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2001</xref>), demonstrating that ethylene is an essential element in the interaction between root and rhizobia. We used <italic>skl</italic> to study whether and how ethylene is involved in the signaling cascades leading to characteristic blends of HIPVs. To obtain sufficient amounts of HIPV from herbivore-damaged plants, volatiles were continuously collected for 48&#x000a0;h after exposure to BAW feeding (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a). Wild-type (WT) plants exposed to BAW larvae released a blend of volatiles comprising fatty acid-derived compounds, sesquiterpenes, and two homoterpenes. On the other hand, BAW-damaged <italic>skl</italic> plants released significantly lower amounts of certain sesquiterpenes (&#x003b1;-copaene, germacrene D along with an unidentified sesquiterpene (I), &#x003b1;-muurolene, (<italic>E</italic>)-nerolidol, and &#x003b2;-himachalol), and a homoterpene ((<italic>E</italic>)-4,8-dimethyl-1,3,7-nonatriene, DMNT). The monoterpene limonene was constitutively released only from <italic>skl</italic> plants but not from WT; after BAW damage, the emission of limonene increased (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a, compound 3).
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p> Volatile profiles and mRNA levels in wild-type (WT) and in <italic>skl</italic> plants. <bold>a </bold>Volatiles emitted from WT and from <italic>skl</italic> plants damaged by beet armyworms (BAW); (+) with larvae, (&#x02212;) without larvae for 48&#x000a0;h. Emission is presented as relative peak area (g shoot tissue)<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> collected over a 48-h period + SE (<italic>n&#x000a0;</italic>=&#x000a0;4). Means followed by small letters for each set of volatiles that are significantly different according to Scheffe&#x02019;s test (<italic>P&#x000a0;</italic>&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05).<italic> 1</italic> 1-octene-3-ol,<italic> 2</italic> (<italic>Z</italic>)-3-hexenyl acetate,<italic> 3</italic> limonene,<italic> 4</italic><italic>n</italic>-nonanal,<italic> 5</italic> DMNT,<italic> 6</italic><italic>n</italic>-decanal,<italic> 7</italic> (+)-cyclosativene,<italic> 8</italic> &#x003b1;-ylangene,<italic> 9</italic> &#x003b1;-copaene,<italic> 10</italic> &#x003b2;-caryophyllene,<italic> 12</italic> &#x003b1;-himalachene,<italic> 14</italic><italic>allo</italic>-aromadendrene,<italic> 15</italic> &#x003b3;-muurolene,<italic> 16</italic> germacrene D,<italic> 17</italic> unidentified sesquiterpene (I),<italic> 18</italic> &#x003b1;-muurolene,<italic> 20</italic> (<italic>E</italic>)-nerolidol,<italic> 21</italic> TMTT,<italic> 22</italic> &#x003b2;-himachalol. Relative peak areas from integration of the reconstructed ion chromatogram were used without additional calibration. Peak areas of germacrene D and unidentified sesquiterpene (16&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;17) were determined as the sum due to insufficient separation. <bold>b </bold>Relative mRNA levels for genes involved in terpenoid biosynthesis in BAW-infested leaves. Data represent the mean + SE (<italic>n&#x000a0;</italic>=&#x000a0;4). *<italic>P&#x000a0;</italic>&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05 (ANOVA).<italic> DXS</italic> DXP synthase,<italic> HMGR</italic> HMG-CoA reductase,<italic> TPS</italic> terpene synthase</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="425_2007_631_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p>Next, we investigated transcript levels of genes of early and late steps in terpenoid biosynthesis in BAW-damaged WT and <italic>skl</italic> by quantitative RT-PCR analysis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b). The transcript levels of putative terpene synthases <italic>MtTPS2</italic> and <italic>MtTPS3</italic> (Gomez et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2005</xref>) were induced at similar levels in WT and <italic>skl</italic> plants throughout the entire period of BAW damage, whereas the transcript levels of <italic>MtTPS1</italic> (Gomez et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2005</xref>) and the gene encoding 1-deoxy-<sc>d</sc>-xylulose-5-phosphate (DXP) synthase (<italic>MtDXS2</italic>) involved in the MEP pathway (Walter et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2002</xref>) were initially lower in <italic>skl</italic> plants after exposure to BAW feeding (2&#x000a0;h, <italic>P&#x000a0;</italic>=&#x000a0;0.08 and <italic>P&#x000a0;</italic>&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05, respectively, ANOVA). A putative sesqui-TPS gene (<italic>MtTPS5</italic>) mined from the TIGR <italic>M. truncatula</italic> EST database was only up-regulated in WT plants after 24&#x000a0;h. Unlike <italic>MtDXS2</italic>, the transcript levels of <italic>MtDXS1</italic> and 3-hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl-CoA reductase (<italic>MtHMGR1</italic>), two other genes of early terpenoid biosynthesis, were identical in both BAW-damaged WT and <italic>skl</italic> plants.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Product spectrum of MtTPSs</title><p>MtTPS1 and MtTPS3 had been predicted to represent sesqui-TPS and mono-/di-TPS, due to both their sequence homology to TPSs from other plants and their localization in cytosol and plastids, respectively (Gomez et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2005</xref>). Protein extracts from transformed bacterial cultures [<italic>E. coli</italic> strain BL21-CodonPlus(DE3)] containing and expressing the full-length coding region of either <italic>MtTPS1</italic> or <italic>MtTPS3</italic>, were assayed with FDP as substrate. The products of MtTPS1 were identified as &#x003b2;-caryophyllene (92% of total product) and &#x003b1;-humulene (8% of total product, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a). Although MtTPS3 has previously been predicted to represent a mono-/di-TPS (Gomez et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2005</xref>), the recombinant MtTPS3 generated (<italic>E</italic>)-nerolidol as a single product when supplied with FDP as substrate (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a). A control extract prepared from the BL21-CodonPlus(DE3) strain transformed with a plasmid without the TPS cDNA insert did not produce significant amount of (<italic>E</italic>)-nerolidol (0.6% residual production). The MtTPS3 product was identified as pure (3<italic>S</italic>)-(<italic>E</italic>)-nerolidol by GC on a chiral <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-cyclodextrin column (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b).
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold> Sesquiterpenes formed by the assay of the recombinant MtTPS enzymes with FDP as substrate. An assay of the extract prepared from the BL21-CodonPlus(DE3) strain transformed with a plasmid without the TPS cDNA insert serves as control. <bold>b </bold>Stereochemistry of (<italic>E</italic>)-nerolidol was identified by comparing the retention time with that of authentic standards of (3<italic>R</italic>)-(<italic>E</italic>)-nerolidol and (3<italic>S</italic>)-(<italic>E</italic>)-nerolidol using GC&#x02013;MS. Also shown is the sesquiterpene product formed by recombinant MtTPS3 enzyme in&#x000a0;vitro</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="425_2007_631_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p>In order to ensure the functional involvement of MtTPS5 in the HIPV biosynthesis, we determined a full-length cDNA sequence for the <italic>MtTPS5</italic> from <italic>M. truncatula</italic> (GenBank accession no. DQ188184). The deduced protein sequence of MtTPS5 encodes a predicted protein of 553 amino acids that shares 55% identity and 74% similarity with MtTPS1 and 49% identity and 70% similarity with poplar (<italic>Populus trichocarpa&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;deltoides</italic>) germacrene D synthase (AY438099). A functional assay with FDP as substrate resulted in the production of 11 sesquiterpene hydrocarbons: &#x003b1;-cubebene, &#x003b1;-copaene, &#x003b2;-cubebene, &#x003b2;-caryophyllene, &#x003b2;-copaene, &#x003b1;-humulene, <italic>allo</italic>-aromadendrene, &#x003b3;-muurolene, germacrene D, &#x003b1;-muurolene, &#x003b4;-cadinene, and four sesquiterpene alcohols, e.g., (-)-cubebol (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a). All compounds&#x02014;except two sesquiterpene alcohols&#x02014;were unambiguously identified by their Kov&#x000e1;ts indices and mass fragmentation patterns using combined GC&#x02013;MS and authentic standards. Interestingly, the alcohols were not detected in the profile of plant volatiles (see Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a). With GDP as substrate the recombinant MtTPSs yielded traces of monoterpenes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a). For example, recombinant MtTPS1 and MtTPS5 synthesized the monoterpenes myrcene, limonene, &#x003b2;-ocimene, terpinolene, &#x003b1;-terpineol, and three unidentified monoterpenes at about 5% of the rate of sesquiterpene products. MtTPS3 produced linalool at 5% of the rate of (<italic>E</italic>)-nerolidol. Using GGDP both TPS failed to produce diterpenoids (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b). In contrast, the recombinant MtTPS3 generated the diterpene geranyllinalool when supplied with GGDP (ca. 65% of the rate of (<italic>E</italic>)-nerolidol). The oxidative degradation of (<italic>E</italic>)-nerolidol and geranyllinalool generates the homoterpenes DMNT and (<italic>E</italic>,<italic>E</italic>)-4,8,12-trimethyltrideca-1,3,7,11-tetraene (TMTT) (Donath and Boland <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">1994</xref>), both of which have been found in the blend of HIPVs from BAW-damaged WT and <italic>skl</italic> plants (see Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a).
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Mono- and diterpenes formed by the assay of the recombinant MtTPS enzymes with GDP (<bold>a</bold>) and GGDP (<bold>b</bold>) as substrates, respectively. The GDP- and GGDP-derived products trapped by SPME and pentene, respectively, are illustrated. Assays of the extract prepared from the BL21-CodonPlus(DE3) strain transformed with a plasmid without the TPS cDNA insert serve as control</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="425_2007_631_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Synergistic effects of jasmonic acid and ACC on terpenoid biosynthesis</title><p>The endogenous levels of JA in WT and <italic>skl</italic> plants increased and reached a maximum 24&#x000a0;h after being exposed to feeding BAW larvae, but the differences between the two plants were not significant (Fig.&#x000a0;S1 of electronic supplementary material). However, the composition of terpenoids depends on the concerted action of various signals, among which JA and ethylene are very likely important factors controlling TPS gene expression. To study the synergistic interaction between JA and ethylene signaling in WT leaf terpenoid biosynthesis, solutions of JA, ACC (precursor of ethylene), or JA&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;ACC were applied. Compared with the control, after 2&#x000a0;h JA induced <italic>MtDXS2</italic>, <italic>MtTPS1</italic>, and <italic>MtTPS3</italic> transcripts, but after 24&#x000a0;h only <italic>MtTPS1</italic> and <italic>MtTPS3</italic> remained induced (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Treatment with ACC alone did not result in gene induction. Unlike the individual application of JA or ACC, their combined addition (JA&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;ACC) resulted in a significant increase of the transcript level of <italic>MtDXS2</italic> after 2&#x000a0;h and of <italic>MtTPS5</italic> after 24&#x000a0;h. The mRNA levels of <italic>MtHMGR1</italic> and <italic>MtDXS1</italic> were never significantly enhanced (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Effect of exogenous application of JA and ACC on relative mRNA levels for genes involved in the biosynthesis of terpenoids in WT leaves. Treatments: JA (J), the ethylene precursor ACC (A), or both (+) for 2 and 24&#x000a0;h (mean + SE, <italic>n&#x000a0;</italic>=&#x000a0;3&#x02013;4). Means followed by small letters for each set of volatiles that are significantly different according to Scheffe&#x02019;s test (<italic>P&#x000a0;</italic>&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05)</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="425_2007_631_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p><p>Since after 2&#x000a0;h the emission of volatiles was not detectable, the effect of JA, ACC and JA&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;ACC was investigated with volatiles that were continuously collected for 24&#x000a0;h after spraying the solution on WT <italic>M. truncatula</italic> plants (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). &#x003b2;-Caryophyllene, the product of MtTPS1, was induced by JA and JA&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;ACC, whereas (<italic>E</italic>)-nerolidol and, to a greater extent, its degradation product DMNT resulting from MtTPS3 activity were induced by JA (DMNT) and by JA&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;ACC (DMNT and (<italic>E</italic>)-nerolidol). The products of MtTPS5 were found mainly after stimulation by JA&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;ACC. The stimulatory effect of ethylene on the JA-linked terpenoid biosynthesis was also demonstrated by adding STS, a known inhibitor of ethylene perception (Veen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">1983</xref>). Application of JA&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;ACC&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;STS to WT plants reduced the emission of JA&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;ACC-induced DMNT and other sesquiterpenes.
<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Effect of exogenous application of JA and ACC: volatiles released from WT plants treated with water (control), JA, ACC, JA&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;ACC, or JA&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;ACC&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;STS for 24&#x000a0;h. Emission is presented as relative peak area (g shoot tissue)<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> collected over a 24-h period + SE (<italic>n&#x000a0;</italic>=&#x000a0;4&#x02212;5). Relative peak areas from integration of the reconstructed ion chromatogram were used without additional calibration. Peak areas of germacrene D and unidentified sesquiterpene (16&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;17) were determined as the sum due to insufficient separation. Means followed by small letters for each set of volatiles are significantly different according to Scheffe&#x02019;s test (<italic>P&#x000a0;</italic>&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05).<italic> 2</italic> (<italic>Z</italic>)-3-hexenyl acetate,<italic> 3</italic> limonene,<italic> 4</italic><italic>n</italic>-nonanal,<italic> 5</italic> DMNT,<italic> 6</italic><italic>n</italic>-decanal,<italic> 7</italic> (+)-cyclosativene,<italic> 8</italic> &#x003b1;-ylangene,<italic> 9</italic> &#x003b1;-copaene,<italic> 10</italic> &#x003b2;-caryophyllene,<italic> 11</italic> &#x003b2;-copaene,<italic> 12</italic> &#x003b1;-himalachene,<italic> 13</italic> &#x003b1;-humulene,<italic> 14</italic><italic>allo</italic>-aromadendrene,<italic> 15</italic> &#x003b3;-muurolene,<italic> 16</italic> germacrene D,<italic> 17</italic> unidentified sesquiterpene (I),<italic> 18</italic> &#x003b1;-muurolene,<italic> 19</italic> &#x003b4;-cadinene<italic>, 20</italic> (<italic>E</italic>)-nerolidol,<italic> 22</italic> &#x003b2;-himachalol</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="425_2007_631_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Pathway allocation of sesquiterpene biosynthesis in BAW-treated plants</title><p>In addition to the cytosolic MEV pathway, the plastidial MEP pathway, represented by the strongly responding <italic>MtDXS2</italic>, should be the main source for herbivore-induced sesquiterpene biosynthesis. Therefore, we analyzed the contribution of the MEP pathway to sesquiterpene biosynthesis by administering 1-deoxy-[5,5-<sup>2</sup>H<sub>2</sub>]-<sc>d</sc>-xylulose ([<sup>2</sup>H<sub>2</sub>]-DOX (Meyer et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2004</xref>)) to WT <italic>M. truncatula</italic> followed by induction with JA&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;ACC (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a). The emitted sesquiterpenes &#x003b1;-copaene, &#x003b2;-caryophyllene, and (<italic>E</italic>)-nerolidol displayed a degree of labelling between 65 and 79%, demonstrating that the MEP pathway contributed substantially to their biosynthesis. On average, the degree of deuterium labelling was between 65 and 80% for all sesquiterpenes; only the degree of labelling of DMNT was lower (40% of the total, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a). In addition, the relative contribution of the two pathways to the sesqui- and homoterpene biosyntheses was further tested by treating the plantlets with specific inhibitors (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>b). The MEP pathway was blocked by the application of fosmidomycin, a specific inhibitor of the DXP-reductoisomerase (Kuzuyama et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">1998</xref>), and the MVA pathway was selectively inhibited by lovastatin, an inhibitor of HMGR (Bach and Lichtenthaler <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">1982</xref>). As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>b, both pathways contribute to sesquiterpene biosynthesis, since both inhibitors suppressed the formation of the sesquiterpenes to a characteristic extent.
<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;6</label><caption><p>Pathway allocation in terpenoid biosynthesis in JA&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;ACC induced <italic>M. truncatula</italic>.<bold> a</bold> Degree of labelling of terpenoids emitted from JA&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;ACC-induced plants pre-treated with [<sup>2</sup>H<sub>2</sub>]-DOX. <bold>b </bold>Volatiles from JA&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;ACC-induced plants after pre-treatment with lovastatin (L), fosmidomycin (F), or water (C). Emission is presented as relative peak area (g shoot tissue)<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> collected over a 24-h period + SE (<italic>n&#x000a0;</italic>=&#x000a0;3&#x02212;4). Relative peak areas from integration of the reconstructed ion chromatogram were used without additional calibration. Means followed by small letters for each set of volatiles are significantly different according to Scheffe&#x02019;s test (<italic>P&#x000a0;</italic>&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05)</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="425_2007_631_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Impact of ethylene on Ca<sup>2+ </sup>signaling</title><p>Besides JA and ethylene, other factors might be involved in controlling terpenoid biosynthesis. In Lima bean, the first event after leaf feeding is an influx of Ca<sup>2+</sup> in the damaged area (Maffei et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2004</xref>). Moreover, applying the Ca<sup>2+</sup>-chelator BAPTA to Lima bean leaves has been shown to suppress the herbivore-induced transcript of defense-related genes involved in sesquiterpene biosynthesis (Arimura et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2000</xref>). Therefore, we next studied the impact of JA and ethylene on the level of Ca<sup>2+</sup> in <italic>M. truncatula</italic> WT and <italic>skl</italic> leaves after damage with BAW. The membrane-permeable Fluo-3 AM [Ca<sup>2+</sup>-sensitive fluorescent probe] was applied to leaf tissue of <italic>M. truncatula</italic>, and showed cytoplasmic subcellular localization (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>a). While the treatment of WT leaves with JA showed no visible effect on intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> variation (Fig. S2 of electronic supplementary material). On the other hand, ethephon, a releasing source of ethylene (Edelmann et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2002</xref>), had a strong impact on the Ca<sup>2+</sup> levels of WT plants as shown by the Ca<sup>2+</sup>-selective dye Fluo-3 AM. When leaves of WT and <italic>skl</italic> plants were treated after BAW damage with ethephon (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>b) only the WT leaves showed a significant reduction of cytoplasmic Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentrations ([Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>cyt</sub>) which continued to decrease over 20&#x000a0;min. Despite a small initial decrease, the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>cyt</sub> of <italic>skl</italic> was not affected. In line with these observations, pre-treatment with ethephon abolished the rapid increase of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>cyt</sub> in the WT leaf after BAW damage (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>c). Conversely, the <italic>skl</italic> leaves, which do not respond to ethylene, showed an immediate increase of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>cyt</sub> in the damaged area.
<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;7</label><caption><p>Effect of ethylene on cytoplasmic Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentrations. <bold>a </bold>A WT leaf was treated with Fluo-3 AM for 1&#x000a0;h and damaged with a BAW larva. The confocal laser scanning microscope analysis showed false-colour subcellular localization of the dyes, proving that the dyes are loaded mainly into the cytoplasm. The<italic> green fluorescence</italic> refers to the binding of Fluo-3 AM with Ca<sup>2+</sup>, whereas the chloroplasts are evidenced by a<italic> bright red</italic> colour caused by chlorophyll fluorescence. <bold>b </bold>The dye-loaded WT or <italic>skl</italic> leaf was damaged by a BAW larva. After 10&#x000a0;min, the leaf was treated with the ethephon solution (10&#x000a0;mM) or buffer (Control), indicated by a<italic> blue arrow</italic>. <bold>c </bold>Alternatively, the dye-loaded WT or <italic>skl</italic> leaf was pre-treated with ethephon (10&#x000a0;mM) for 20&#x000a0;min and exposed to a BAW larva for 10&#x000a0;min. Demonstrated false-colour images show differences between cellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentrations in WT and <italic>skl</italic> leaves 10&#x000a0;min after ethephon treatment. Data represent the ratio of Fluo-3 AM fluorescence &#x000b1; standard deviation (SD) (<italic>n&#x000a0;</italic>=&#x000a0;4)</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="425_2007_631_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p><p>Altogether, these findings suggest that ethylene can modulate the extent and mode of Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx resulting from herbivore attack, either directly or through feedback from ethylene effects on downstream events.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Involvement of Ca<sup>2+</sup> signaling in the BAW-induced terpenoid formation</title><p>In order to investigate the possible role of Ca<sup>2+</sup> signaling on JA and terpenoid biosynthesis, WT plants were treated with the Ca<sup>2+</sup>-chelator (BAPTA) prior to BAW treatment (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>). JA (but not 12-oxophytodienoic acid [OPDA], Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>a) levels as well as the levels of DMNT, &#x003b1;-copaene, and &#x003b2;-caryophyllene (<italic>P&#x000a0;</italic>&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05; ANOVA) were reduced (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>b). These terpenoids represent the final products of MtTPS1, MtTPS3, and MtTPS5 proteins, the genes of which were either or both regulated by JA and JA&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;ACC (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).
<fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;8</label><caption><p>Biosynthesis of oxylipins (<bold>a</bold>) and volatiles (<bold>b</bold>) in WT leaves after treatment with BAPTA or water (control). Leaves to be used for oxylipin analysis were harvested 6&#x000a0;h after BAW exposure (mean + SE, <italic>n&#x000a0;</italic>=&#x000a0;4). Volatiles emitted from the infested plants were collected for 48&#x000a0;h starting with BAW damage. Emission is presented as relative peak area (g shoot tissue)<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> collected over a 48-h period + SE (<italic>n&#x000a0;</italic>=&#x000a0;4). *<italic>P&#x000a0;</italic>&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05, **<italic>P&#x000a0;</italic>&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01 (ANOVA). Peak areas from integration of the reconstructed ion chromatogram were used without additional calibration</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="425_2007_631_Fig8_HTML" id="MO8"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec17" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>The composition of the induced volatile blends depends on plastic phenotypic responses which can be modulated by the interplay of several biosynthetic pathways and levels of signaling molecules (Arimura et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2005</xref>). In order to dissect the complexity of plastic responses, we used the ethylene-insensitive <italic>skl</italic> mutant of <italic>M. truncatula</italic> in combination with defined chemical treatments and BAW exposure. Within the BAW- or treatment (JA&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;ACC)-induced blends of volatiles, sesqui and homoterpenoids were the most abundant (see Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a). To identify the genes responsible for terpenoid biosynthesis, we cloned three MtTPS genes, based on sequence similarities with other angiosperm <italic>TPS</italic> genes, namely <italic>MtTPS1</italic>, <italic>MtTPS3</italic>, and <italic>MtTPS5.</italic> Heterologous protein expression and biochemical analysis of the enzymatic product identified MtTPS1 as a &#x003b2;-caryophyllene synthase, MtTPS3 as a nerolidol/geranyl linalool synthase, and MtTPS5 as a multiproduct sesquiterpene synthase. Multi-product TPSs significantly contribute to the plasticity of blends and are increasingly found in plants, especially in context with herbivory, as shown previously for other plants (K&#x000f6;llner et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2004</xref>; Tholl et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2005</xref>). In addition to olefinic sequiterpenes, the heterologously expressed MtTPS5 protein produced a number of hydroxylated products which were not detected in the gas phase of <italic>M. truncatula</italic> plants (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a). Whether these compounds are subsequently modified <italic>in planta</italic> remains to be clarified.</p><p>Conventional pathway allocation suggests that the sesquiterpene precursors, IDP and DMADP, are mainly provided by the cytosolic MVA pathway. However, evidence is emerging that the plastidial MEP pathway may also significantly contribute to cytosolic sesquiterpene biosynthesis by allowing IDP to be shuttled between the different compartments (Piel et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">1998</xref>; Bick and Lange <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2003</xref>; Bartram et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2006</xref>). Here we demonstrate this for <italic>M. truncatula</italic> by the administration of labelled [<sup>2</sup>H<sub>2</sub>]-DOX and pathway-specific inhibitors. These results indicate that the MEP pathway, as well as the cytosolic MEV pathway, plays a dominant role by providing terpenoid precursors.</p><p>Compared to WT plants, the <italic>skl</italic> mutant produced lower amounts of sequiterpenes and DMNT when challenged with feeding insects, suggesting a possible role for ethylene as a modulator of BAW-induced terpenoid biosynthesis. In fact, ethylene and JA synergistically induce the biosynthesis of certain sesquiterpenes [e.g., &#x003b1;-copaene, (<italic>E</italic>)-nerolidol, and germacrene D along with unidentified sesquiterpenes (I)]. The production of these sesquiterpenes coincides with enhanced transcript levels of <italic>MtDXS2</italic> and <italic>MtTPS5</italic>. In contrast, <italic>MtTPS1</italic> and <italic>MtTPS3</italic> transcripts were only induced by JA treatment.</p><p>Feeding BAW raised the expression level of <italic>MtTPS3</italic> in WT and <italic>skl</italic> plants in the same way, but levels of (<italic>E</italic>)-nerolidol and DMNT formation were higher in WT plants, suggesting that ethylene might have a post-transcriptional impact on the MtTPS3 protein. Another interesting aspect is that MtTPS3 has been claimed to be a plastidial-targeted protein (Gomez et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2005</xref>), which is also consistent with its ability to produce the diterpene geranyllinalool from GGDP (see Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b). The subcellular localization of (<italic>E</italic>)-nerolidol formation and subsequent DMNT-production remains unsolved.</p><p>Ethylene has been recently shown to enhance sesquiterpenes and suppress monoterpenes in <italic>Zea mays</italic> (Ruther and Kleier <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2005</xref>). In this case, the presence of ethylene enhanced the hexenol-induced production of volatiles (linked to increased internal JA levels) by a factor of 5&#x02013;6 with respect to the sesquiterpenes, but suppressed the constitutively emitted monoterpene linalool (Ruther and Kleier <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2005</xref>). In <italic>M. truncatula</italic> the simultaneous application of JA&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;ACC also significantly enhanced production of sesquiterpenes. The suppressing effect of ethylene on monoterpene biosynthesis in WT plants becomes obvious from the volatile profile of the <italic>skl</italic> mutant: it lacks ethylene perception and as a consequence, constitutively emits limonene. The mode of monoterpene suppression by ethylene in WT <italic>M. truncatula</italic> is still unknown and will require the identification of the limonene synthase and of specific elements that control plastidial monoterpene biosynthesis. It is interesting to note that the sesquiterpene synthases MtTPS1 and MtTPS5 represent multiproduct enzymes that could also synthesize monoterpenes, including limonene. However, since BAW attack enhanced the transcript levels of <italic>MtTPS1</italic> and <italic>MtTPS5</italic> in WT leaves that lacked limonene emission, these enzymes could not be responsible for the production of limonene. The lack of any plastidial transit peptide at the N-terminus of MtTPS1 and MtTPS5 supports their prediction as cytosolic proteins involved in sesquiterpenoid biosynthesis.</p><p>WT and <italic>skl</italic> plants showed different resting levels of cytosolic [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>cyt</sub>; but after BAW feeding, both plants increased at the same rate (see Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>b). Both pre- and post-treatment with ethephon reduced the BAW-triggered [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>cyt</sub> increase in WT leaves, but had no effect on <italic>skl</italic> plants. In order to test whether or not this effect is general, we treated the transgenic aequorin-expressing soybean cell culture (Mith&#x000f6;fer et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">1999</xref>) with ethephon and insect regurgitate containing active eliciting compounds. In this artificial system, ethephon abolished the regurgitate-elicited and transient increase of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>cyt</sub> (Fig. S3 of electronic supplementary material). Accordingly, either ethephon or the released ethylene have a direct effect on Ca<sup>2+</sup> homeostasis. Depriving plants of extracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> by BAPTA reduces the formation of JA (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>a) and the release of terpenoids (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>b). The level of OPDA is not affected. However, the <italic>skl</italic> plants only slightly modify the level of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>cyt</sub> and never completely remove external Ca<sup>2+</sup>. These facts may explain why the level of JA production after feeding BAW is not significantly different between WT and <italic>skl</italic> plants (see Fig. S1 of electronic supplementary material).</p><p>Although the simultaneous application of JA&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;ACC strongly stimulates volatile emissions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>), this effect may be partly due to the action of ACC, but not of ethylene. ACC, which was found to occur as a conjugate with JA, might act as an additional factor controlling gene expression, similar to the conjugates of JA and isoleucine (Krumm et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">1995</xref>; Staswick and Tiryaki <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2004</xref>). This assumption is supported by the observation that the combined treatment with JA&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;ACC&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;STS does not fully compensate for the effect of JA&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;ACC (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>).</p><p>In conclusion, our results demonstrate that either the phytohormone ethylene or its precursor (ACC) affects the different levels of BAW-induced terpenoid blends by modulating early signaling events such as the cytoplasmic Ca<sup>2+</sup>-influx and later the JA-dependent biosynthesis of terpenoids.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><supplementary-material id="N0x1e39a00N0x2dbd3b8" content-type="local-data"><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.
</p><media xlink:href="425_2007_631_MOESM1_ESM.tif" id="MOESM1" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p>Fig. S1 The JA levels in WT and skl leaves damaged by feeding BAW. Data represent the mean&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;SE (<italic>n</italic>=4) (TIF 54 kb)</p></caption></media><media xlink:href="425_2007_631_MOESM2_ESM.tif" id="MOESM2" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p>Fig. S2 Effect of JA on cytoplasmic Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentrations [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>cyt</sub>. A WT leaf was dam-aged by a BAW larva. After 10 min, the leaf was treated with the JA solution (1 mM) for up to 30 min. Demonstrated false-colour images show no difference between [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>cyt</sub> before and after JA treatment. The quantitative data are given at the bottom (black line). In the graph, blue lines indicate the ratio of Fluo-3 AM fluorescence when each leaf was treated with JA (1 mM) for 20 min and exposed to a BAW larva for up to 30 min (TIF 152 kb)</p></caption></media><media xlink:href="425_2007_631_MOESM3_ESM.tif" id="MOESM3" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p>Fig. S3 Cytosolic Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentration ([Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>cyt</sub>) changes in soybean cell suspension culture, which expresses the Ca<sup>2+</sup>-sensing aequorin system, treated with oral secretions from a BAW larva with (red) or without (black) ethephon (10 mM) for 10 min. Cells treated with water served as controls (blue). Each experiment was performed three times, with similar results each time (TIF 59 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Dr. Giles E. Oldroyd (John Innes Centre) for <italic>skl</italic> seeds; Dr. Maritta Kunert and Ms. Anja David for volatile analysis. (-)-Cubebol was generously provided by Dr. Alois F&#x000fc;rstner (Max Planck Institute for Kohlenforschung). This work was supported by the Japanese Society for the Promotion of Science (to G.A.) and the Centre of Excellence CEBIOVEM of the University of Turin (to M.M.).</p></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aharoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Giri</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Deuerlein</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Griepink</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kogel</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Verstappen</surname><given-names>FWA</given-names></name><name><surname>Verhoeven</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jongsma</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwab</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouwmeester</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Terpenoid metabolism in wild-type and transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2003</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>2866</fpage><lpage>2884</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.016253</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Aharoni A, Giri AP, Deuerlein S, Griepink F, de Kogel WJ, Verstappen FWA, Verhoeven HA, Jongsma MA, Schwab W, Bouwmeester HJ (2003) Terpenoid metabolism in wild-type and transgenic Arabidopsis plants. Plant Cell 15:2866&#x02013;2884 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14630967</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aharoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jongsma</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouwmeester</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Volatile science? Metabolic engineering of terpenoids in plants</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci</source><year>2005</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>594</fpage><lpage>602</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2005.10.005</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Aharoni A, Jongsma MA, Bouwmeester HJ (2005) Volatile science? Metabolic engineering of terpenoids in plants. Trends Plant Sci 10:594&#x02013;602 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16290212</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ament</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Schie</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouwmeester</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Haring</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuurink</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction of a leaf specific geranylgeranyl pyrophosphate synthase and emission of (<italic>E</italic>,<italic>E</italic>)-4,8,12-trimethyltrideca-1,3,7,11-tetraene in tomato are dependent on both jasmonic acid and salicylic acid signaling pathways</article-title><source>Planta</source><year>2006</year><volume>224</volume><fpage>1197</fpage><lpage>1208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00425-006-0301-5</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Ament K, Van Schie CC, Bouwmeester HJ, Haring MA, Schuurink RC (2006) Induction of a leaf specific geranylgeranyl pyrophosphate synthase and emission of (E,E)-4,8,12-trimethyltrideca-1,3,7,11-tetraene in tomato are dependent on both jasmonic acid and salicylic acid signaling pathways. Planta 224:1197&#x02013;1208 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16786318</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arimura</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozawa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimoda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishioka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Boland</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Takabayashi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Herbivory-induced volatiles elicit defence genes in lima bean leaves</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2000</year><volume>406</volume><fpage>512</fpage><lpage>515</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35020072</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Arimura G, Ozawa R, Shimoda T, Nishioka T, Boland W, Takabayashi J (2000) Herbivory-induced volatiles elicit defence genes in lima bean leaves. Nature 406:512&#x02013;515 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10952311</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arimura</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>DPW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohlmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Forest tent caterpillars (<italic>Malacosoma disstria</italic>) induce local and systemic diurnal emissions of terpenoid volatiles in hybrid poplar (<italic>Populus trichocarpa&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;deltoides</italic>): cDNA cloning, functional characterization, and patterns of gene expression of (-)-germacrene D synthase, <italic>PtdTPS1</italic></article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2004</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>603</fpage><lpage>616</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2003.01987.x</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Arimura G, Huber DPW, Bohlmann J (2004a) Forest tent caterpillars (Malacosoma disstria) induce local and systemic diurnal emissions of terpenoid volatiles in hybrid poplar (Populus trichocarpa&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;deltoides): cDNA cloning, functional characterization, and patterns of gene expression of (-)-germacrene D synthase, PtdTPS1. Plant J 37:603&#x02013;616 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14756770</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arimura</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozawa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kugimiya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Takabayashi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohlmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Herbivore-induced defense response in a model legume. Two-spotted spider mites induce emission of (<italic>E</italic>)-&#x003b2;-ocimene and transcript accumulation of (<italic>E</italic>)-&#x003b2;-ocimene synthase in <italic>Lotus japonicus</italic></article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>1976</fpage><lpage>1983</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.104.042929</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Arimura G, Ozawa R, Kugimiya S, Takabayashi J, Bohlmann J (2004b) Herbivore-induced defense response in a model legume. Two-spotted spider mites induce emission of (E)-&#x003b2;-ocimene and transcript accumulation of (E)-&#x003b2;-ocimene synthase in Lotus japonicus. Plant Physiol 135:1976&#x02013;1983 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15310830</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arimura</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kost</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Boland</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Herbivore-induced, indirect plant defences</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>2005</year><volume>1734</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>111</lpage></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Arimura G, Kost C, Boland W (2005) Herbivore-induced, indirect plant defences. Biochim Biophys Acta 1734:91&#x02013;111 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15904867</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bach</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lichtenthaler</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mevinolin: a highly specific inhibitor of microsomal 3-hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl-coenzyme A reductase of radish plants</article-title><source>Z Naturforsch [C]</source><year>1982</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>46</fpage><lpage>50</lpage></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Bach TJ, Lichtenthaler HK (1982) Mevinolin: a highly specific inhibitor of microsomal 3-hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl-coenzyme A reductase of radish plants. Z Naturforsch [C] 37:46&#x02013;50 </citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bartram</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jux</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gleixner</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Boland</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dynamic pathway allocation in early terpenoid biosynthesis of stress-induced lima bean leaves</article-title><source>Phytochemistry</source><year>2006</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>1661</fpage><lpage>1672</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2006.02.004</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Bartram S, Jux A, Gleixner G, Boland W (2006) Dynamic pathway allocation in early terpenoid biosynthesis of stress-induced lima bean leaves. Phytochemistry 67:1661&#x02013;1672 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16580034</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bergomaz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Boppr&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A simple instant diet for rearing Arctiidae and other moths</article-title><source>J Lepidopt Soc</source><year>1986</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>137</lpage></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Bergomaz R, Boppr&#x000e9; M (1986) A simple instant diet for rearing Arctiidae and other moths. J Lepidopt Soc 40:131&#x02013;137 </citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bick</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolic cross talk between cytosolic and plastidial pathways of isoprenoid biosynthesis: unidirectional transport of intermediates across the chloroplast envelope membrane</article-title><source>Arch Biochem Biophys</source><year>2003</year><volume>415</volume><fpage>146</fpage><lpage>154</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0003-9861(03)00233-9</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Bick JA, Lange M (2003) Metabolic cross talk between cytosolic and plastidial pathways of isoprenoid biosynthesis: unidirectional transport of intermediates across the chloroplast envelope membrane. Arch Biochem Biophys 415:146&#x02013;154 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12831836</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moraes</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Par&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Alborn</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><name><surname>Tumlinson</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Herbivore-infested plants selectively attract parasitoids</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1998</year><volume>393</volume><fpage>1907</fpage><lpage>1922</lpage></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">De Moraes CM, Lewis WJ, Par&#x000e9; PW, Alborn HT, Tumlinson JH (1998) Herbivore-infested plants selectively attract parasitoids. Nature 393:1907&#x02013;1922 </citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Degenhardt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gershenzon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Demonstration and characterization of (<italic>E</italic>)-nerolidol synthase from maize: a herbivore-inducible terpene synthase participating in (3<italic>E</italic>)-4,8-dimethyl-1,3,7-nonatriene biosynthesis</article-title><source>Planta</source><year>2000</year><volume>210</volume><fpage>815</fpage><lpage>822</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004250050684</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Degenhardt J, Gershenzon J (2000) Demonstration and characterization of (E)-nerolidol synthase from maize: a herbivore-inducible terpene synthase participating in (3E)-4,8-dimethyl-1,3,7-nonatriene biosynthesis. Planta 210:815&#x02013;822 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10805454</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donath</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Boland</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biosynthesis of acyclic homoterpenes in higher plants parallels steroid hormone metabolism</article-title><source>J Plant Physiol</source><year>1994</year><volume>143</volume><fpage>473</fpage><lpage>478</lpage></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Donath J, Boland W (1994) Biosynthesis of acyclic homoterpenes in higher plants parallels steroid hormone metabolism. J Plant Physiol 143:473&#x02013;478 </citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dudareva</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kish</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolosova</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorenstein</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>F&#x000e4;ldt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohlmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>(<italic>E</italic>)-&#x003b2;-Ocimene and myrcene synthase genes of floral scent biosynthesis in snapdragon: function and expression of three terpene synthase genes of a new terpene synthase subfamily</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2003</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1227</fpage><lpage>1241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.011015</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Dudareva N, Martin D, Kish CM, Kolosova N, Gorenstein N, F&#x000e4;ldt J, Miller B, Bohlmann J (2003) (E)-&#x003b2;-Ocimene and myrcene synthase genes of floral scent biosynthesis in snapdragon: function and expression of three terpene synthase genes of a new terpene synthase subfamily. Plant Cell 15:1227&#x02013;1241 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12724546</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edelmann</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gudi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000fc;hnemann</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The gravitropic setpoint angle of dark-grown rye seedlings and the role of ethylene</article-title><source>J Exp Bot</source><year>2002</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>1627</fpage><lpage>1634</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erf007</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Edelmann HG, Gudi G, K&#x000fc;hnemann F (2002) The gravitropic setpoint angle of dark-grown rye seedlings and the role of ethylene. J Exp Bot 53:1627&#x02013;1634 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12096101</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eisenreich</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Bacher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Arigoni</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohdich</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biosynthesis of isoprenoids via the non-mevalonate pathway</article-title><source>Cell Mol Life Sci</source><year>2004</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>1401</fpage><lpage>1426</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00018-004-3381-z</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Eisenreich W, Bacher A, Arigoni D, Rohdich F (2004) Biosynthesis of isoprenoids via the non-mevalonate pathway. Cell Mol Life Sci 61:1401&#x02013;1426 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15197467</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Engelberth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x000fc;ler</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bachmann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Rechtenbach</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Boland</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ion channel-forming alamethicin is a potent elicitor of volatile biosynthesis and tendril coiling. Cross talk between jasmonate and salicylate signaling in lima bean</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>377</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.125.1.369</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Engelberth J, Koch T, Sch&#x000fc;ler G, Bachmann N, Rechtenbach J, Boland W (2001) Ion channel-forming alamethicin is a potent elicitor of volatile biosynthesis and tendril coiling. Cross talk between jasmonate and salicylate signaling in lima bean. Plant Physiol 125:369&#x02013;377 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11154344</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bede</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Alborn</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><name><surname>Tumlinson</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Korth</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lepidopteran herbivory and oral factors induce transcripts encoding novel terpene synthases in <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic></article-title><source>Arch Insect Biochem Physiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>114</fpage><lpage>127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/arch.20037</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Gomez SK, Cox MM, Bede JC, Inoue K, Alborn HT, Tumlinson JH, Korth KL (2005) Lepidopteran herbivory and oral factors induce transcripts encoding novel terpene synthases in Medicago truncatula. Arch Insect Biochem Physiol 58:114&#x02013;127 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15660362</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horiuchi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Arimura</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozawa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimoda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takabayashi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishioka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exogenous ACC enhances volatiles production mediated by jasmonic acid in lima bean leaves</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><year>2001</year><volume>509</volume><fpage>332</fpage><lpage>336</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0014-5793(01)03194-5</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Horiuchi J, Arimura G, Ozawa R, Shimoda T, Takabayashi J, Nishioka T (2001) Exogenous ACC enhances volatiles production mediated by jasmonic acid in lima bean leaves. FEBS Lett 509:332&#x02013;336 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11741612</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrer</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Noel</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dissection of malonyl-coenzyme A decarboxylation from polyketide formation in the reaction mechanism of a plant polyketide synthase</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2000</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>890</fpage><lpage>902</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi991489f</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Jez JM, Ferrer JL, Bowman ME, Dixon RA, Noel JP (2000) Dissection of malonyl-coenzyme A decarboxylation from polyketide formation in the reaction mechanism of a plant polyketide synthase. Biochemistry 39:890&#x02013;902 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10653632</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kahl</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Siemens</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Aerts</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000e4;bler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000fc;hnemann</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Preston</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>IT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Herbivore-induced ethylene suppresses a direct defense but not a putative indirect defense against an adapted herbivore</article-title><source>Planta</source><year>2000</year><volume>210</volume><fpage>336</fpage><lpage>342</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/PL00008142</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Kahl J, Siemens DH, Aerts RJ, G&#x000e4;bler R, K&#x000fc;hnemann F, Preston CA, Baldwin IT (2000) Herbivore-induced ethylene suppresses a direct defense but not a putative indirect defense against an adapted herbivore. Planta 210:336&#x02013;342 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10664141</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>K&#x000f6;llner</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnee</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gershenzon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Degenhardt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The variability of sesquiterpenes emitted from two <italic>Zea mays</italic> cultivars is controlled by allelic variation of two terpene synthase genes encoding stereoselective multiple product enzymes</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2004</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1115</fpage><lpage>1131</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.019877</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">K&#x000f6;llner TG, Schnee C, Gershenzon J, Degenhardt J (2004) The variability of sesquiterpenes emitted from two Zea mays cultivars is controlled by allelic variation of two terpene synthase genes encoding stereoselective multiple product enzymes. Plant Cell 16:1115&#x02013;1131 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15075399</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krumm</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bandemer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Boland</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction of volatile biosynthesis in the Lima bean (<italic>Phaseolus lunatus</italic>) by leucine- and isoleucine conjugates of 1-oxo- and 1-hydroxyindan-4-carboxylic acid: evidence for amino acid conjugates of jasmonic acid intermediates in the octadecanoid signalling pathway</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><year>1995</year><volume>377</volume><fpage>523</fpage><lpage>529</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0014-5793(95)01398-9</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Krumm T, Bandemer K, Boland W (1995) Induction of volatile biosynthesis in the Lima bean (Phaseolus lunatus) by leucine- and isoleucine conjugates of 1-oxo- and 1-hydroxyindan-4-carboxylic acid: evidence for amino acid conjugates of jasmonic acid intermediates in the octadecanoid signalling pathway. FEBS Lett 377:523&#x02013;529 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8549790</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuzuyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Seto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fosmidomycin, a specific inhibitor of 1-deoxy-D-xylulose 5-phosphate reductoisomerase in the nonmevalonate pathway for terpenoid biosynthesis</article-title><source>Tetrahedron Lett</source><year>1998</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>7913</fpage><lpage>7916</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0040-4039(98)01755-9</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Kuzuyama T, Shimizu T, Takahashi S, Seto H (1998) Fosmidomycin, a specific inhibitor of 1-deoxy-D-xylulose 5-phosphate reductoisomerase in the nonmevalonate pathway for terpenoid biosynthesis. Tetrahedron Lett 39:7913&#x02013;7916 </citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leitner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Boland</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Mith&#x000f6;fer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Direct and indirect defences induced by piercing-sucking and chewing herbivores in <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic></article-title><source>New Phytol</source><year>2005</year><volume>167</volume><fpage>597</fpage><lpage>606</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2005.01426.x</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Leitner M, Boland W, Mith&#x000f6;fer A (2005) Direct and indirect defences induced by piercing-sucking and chewing herbivores in Medicago truncatula. New Phytol 167:597&#x02013;606 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15998409</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000fc;cker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouwmeester</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwab</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Blaas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Plas</surname><given-names>LHW</given-names></name><name><surname>Verhoeven</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of <italic>Clarkia</italic><italic>S</italic>-linalool synthase in transgenic petunia plants results in the accumulation of <italic>S</italic>-linalyl-&#x003b2;-D-glucopyranoside</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2001</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>315</fpage><lpage>324</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313x.2001.01097.x</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">L&#x000fc;cker J, Bouwmeester HJ, Schwab W, Blaas J, van der Plas LHW, Verhoeven HA (2001) Expression of ClarkiaS-linalool synthase in transgenic petunia plants results in the accumulation of S-linalyl-&#x003b2;-D-glucopyranoside. Plant J 27:315&#x02013;324 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11532177</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maffei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bossi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Spiteller</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mith&#x000f6;fer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Boland</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of feeding <italic>Spodoptera littoralis</italic> on lima bean leaves. I. Membrane potentials, intracellular calcium variations, oral secretions, and regurgitate components</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>134</volume><fpage>1752</fpage><lpage>1762</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.103.034165</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Maffei M, Bossi S, Spiteller D, Mith&#x000f6;fer A, Boland W (2004) Effects of feeding Spodoptera littoralis on lima bean leaves. I. Membrane potentials, intracellular calcium variations, oral secretions, and regurgitate components. Plant Physiol 134:1752&#x02013;1762 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15051862</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maffei</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Mith&#x000f6;fer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Arimura</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Uchtenhagen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bossi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertea</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cucuzza</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Novero</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Volpe</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Quadro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Boland</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of feeding <italic>Spodoptera littoralis</italic> on Lima Bean Leaves. III. Membrane depolarization and involvement of hydrogen peroxide</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>1022</fpage><lpage>1035</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.105.071993</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Maffei ME, Mith&#x000f6;fer A, Arimura G, Uchtenhagen H, Bossi S, Bertea CM, Cucuzza LS, Novero M, Volpe V, Quadro S, Boland W (2006) Effects of feeding Spodoptera littoralis on Lima Bean Leaves. III. Membrane depolarization and involvement of hydrogen peroxide. Plant Physiol 140:1022&#x02013;1035 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16443697</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McKay</surname><given-names>SAB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Godard</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SX</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohlmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Plant</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insect attack and wounding induce traumatic resin duct development and gene expression of (-)-pinene synthase in Sitka spruce</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>368</fpage><lpage>378</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.103.022723</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">McKay SAB, Hunter WL, Godard KA, Wang SX, Martin DM, Bohlmann J, Plant AL (2003) Insect attack and wounding induce traumatic resin duct development and gene expression of (-)-pinene synthase in Sitka spruce. Plant Physiol 133:368&#x02013;378 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12970502</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoeffler</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Grosdemange-Billiard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohmer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Practical synthesis of 1-deoxy-D-xylulose and 1-deoxy-D-xylulose 5-phosphate allowing deuterium labelling</article-title><source>Tetrahedron</source><year>2004</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>12153</fpage><lpage>12162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tet.2004.10.016</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Meyer O, Hoeffler JF, Grosdemange-Billiard C, Rohmer M (2004) Practical synthesis of 1-deoxy-D-xylulose and 1-deoxy-D-xylulose 5-phosphate allowing deuterium labelling. Tetrahedron 60:12153&#x02013;12162 </citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mith&#x000f6;fer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhagwat</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Boller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Neuhaus-Url</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transgenic aequorin monitors cytosolic calcium transients in soybean cells challenged with &#x003b2;-glucan or chitin elicitors</article-title><source>Planta</source><year>1999</year><volume>207</volume><fpage>566</fpage><lpage>574</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004250050519</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Mith&#x000f6;fer A, Ebel J, Bhagwat AA, Boller T, Neuhaus-Url G (1999) Transgenic aequorin monitors cytosolic calcium transients in soybean cells challenged with &#x003b2;-glucan or chitin elicitors. Planta 207:566&#x02013;574 </citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oldroyd</surname><given-names>GED</given-names></name><name><surname>Engstrom</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethylene inhibits the Nod factor signal transduction pathway of <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic></article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2001</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1835</fpage><lpage>1849</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.13.8.1835</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Oldroyd GED, Engstrom EM, Long SR (2001) Ethylene inhibits the Nod factor signal transduction pathway of Medicago truncatula. Plant Cell 13:1835&#x02013;1849 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11487696</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ozawa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Arimura</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Takabayashi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimoda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishioka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Involvement of jasmonate- and salicylate-related signaling pathways for the production of specific herbivore-induced volatiles in plants</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>391</fpage><lpage>398</lpage></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Ozawa R, Arimura G, Takabayashi J, Shimoda T, Nishioka T (2000) Involvement of jasmonate- and salicylate-related signaling pathways for the production of specific herbivore-induced volatiles in plants. Plant Cell Physiol 41:391&#x02013;398 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10845451</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Penmetsa</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A legume ethylene-insensitive mutant hyperinfected by its rhizobial symbiont</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1997</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>527</fpage><lpage>530</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.275.5299.527</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Penmetsa RV, Cook DR (1997) A legume ethylene-insensitive mutant hyperinfected by its rhizobial symbiont. Science 275:527&#x02013;530 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8999796</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Piel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Donath</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bandemer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Boland</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mevalonate-independent biosynthesis of terpenoid volatiles in plants: induced and constitutive emission of volatiles</article-title><source>Angew Chem Int Ed</source><year>1998</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>2478</fpage><lpage>2481</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1521-3773(19981002)37:18&#x0003c;2478::AID-ANIE2478&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-Q</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Piel J, Donath J, Bandemer K, Boland W (1998) Mevalonate-independent biosynthesis of terpenoid volatiles in plants: induced and constitutive emission of volatiles. Angew Chem Int Ed 37:2478&#x02013;2481 </citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Concepci&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Boronat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Elucidation of the methylerythritol phosphate pathway for isoprenoid biosynthesis in bacteria and plastids. A metabolic milestone achieved through genomics</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>1079</fpage><lpage>1089</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.007138</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Concepci&#x000f3;n M, Boronat A (2002) Elucidation of the methylerythritol phosphate pathway for isoprenoid biosynthesis in bacteria and plastids. A metabolic milestone achieved through genomics. Plant Physiol 130:1079&#x02013;1089 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12427975</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruther</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kleier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant-plant signaling: ethylene synergizes volatile emission in <italic>Zea mays</italic> induced by exposure to (<italic>Z</italic>)-3-hexen-1-ol</article-title><source>J Chem Ecol</source><year>2005</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>2217</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10886-005-6413-8</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Ruther J, Kleier S (2005) Plant-plant signaling: ethylene synergizes volatile emission in Zea mays induced by exposure to (Z)-3-hexen-1-ol. J Chem Ecol 31:2217&#x02013;22 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16132223</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharon-Asa</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Shalit</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Frydman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bar</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Or</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavi</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewinsohn</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Eyal</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Citrus fruit flavor and aroma biosynthesis: isolation, functional characterization, and developmental regulation of <italic>Cstps1</italic>, a key gene in the production of the sesquiterpene aroma compound valencene</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2003</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>664</fpage><lpage>674</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313X.2003.01910.x</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Sharon-Asa L, Shalit M, Frydman A, Bar E, Holland D, Or E, Lavi U, Lewinsohn E, Eyal Y (2003) Citrus fruit flavor and aroma biosynthesis: isolation, functional characterization, and developmental regulation of Cstps1, a key gene in the production of the sesquiterpene aroma compound valencene. Plant J 36:664&#x02013;674 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14617067</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmelz</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Alborn</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelberth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tumlinson</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitrogen deficiency increases volicitin-induced volatile emission, jasmonic acid accumulation, and ethylene sensitivity in maize</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>295</fpage><lpage>306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.103.024174</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Schmelz EA, Alborn HT, Engelberth J, Tumlinson JH (2003a) Nitrogen deficiency increases volicitin-induced volatile emission, jasmonic acid accumulation, and ethylene sensitivity in maize. Plant Physiol 133:295&#x02013;306 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12970495</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmelz</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Alborn</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><name><surname>Tumlinson</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synergistic interactions between volicitin, jasmonic acid and ethylene mediate insect-induced volatile emission in <italic>Zea mays</italic></article-title><source>Physiol Plant</source><year>2003</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>412</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1034/j.1399-3054.2003.00054.x</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Schmelz EA, Alborn HT, Tumlinson JH (2003b) Synergistic interactions between volicitin, jasmonic acid and ethylene mediate insect-induced volatile emission in Zea mays. Physiol Plant 117:403&#x02013;412 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12654041</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schulze</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lauchli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonwa</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Boland</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Profiling of structurally labile oxylipins in plants by in situ derivatization with pentafluorobenzyl hydroxylamine</article-title><source>Anal Biochem</source><year>2006</year><volume>348</volume><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>283</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ab.2005.10.021</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Schulze B, Lauchli R, Sonwa MM, Schmidt A, Boland W (2006) Profiling of structurally labile oxylipins in plants by in situ derivatization with pentafluorobenzyl hydroxylamine. Anal Biochem 348:269&#x02013;283 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16307716</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Staswick</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiryaki</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The oxylipin signal jasmonic acid is activated by an enzyme that conjugates it to isoleucine in<italic> Arabidopsis</italic></article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2004</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>2117</fpage><lpage>2127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.104.023549</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Staswick PE, Tiryaki I (2004) The oxylipin signal jasmonic acid is activated by an enzyme that conjugates it to isoleucine in Arabidopsis. Plant Cell 16:2117&#x02013;2127 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15258265</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tholl</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Petri</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gershenzon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pichersky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Two sesquiterpene synthases are responsible for the complex mixture of sesquiterpenes emitted from <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flowers</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2005</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>757</fpage><lpage>771</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2005.02417.x</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Tholl D, Chen F, Petri J, Gershenzon J, Pichersky E (2005) Two sesquiterpene synthases are responsible for the complex mixture of sesquiterpenes emitted from Arabidopsis flowers. Plant J 42:757&#x02013;771 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15918888</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Veen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Silver thiosulfate: an experimental tool in plant science</article-title><source>Sci Hortic</source><year>1983</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>224</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0304-4238(83)90001-8</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Veen H (1983) Silver thiosulfate: an experimental tool in plant science. Sci Hortic 20:211&#x02013;224 </citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hans</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Strack</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Two distantly related genes encoding 1-deoxy-D-xylulose 5-phosphate synthases: differential regulation in shoots and apocarotenoid-accumulating mycorrhizal roots</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2002</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313X.2002.01352.x</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Walter MH, Hans J, Strack D (2002) Two distantly related genes encoding 1-deoxy-D-xylulose 5-phosphate synthases: differential regulation in shoots and apocarotenoid-accumulating mycorrhizal roots. Plant J 31:243&#x02013;54 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12164805</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>KLC</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethylene biosynthesis and signaling networks</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2002</year><volume>14</volume><issue>Suppl</issue><fpage>S131</fpage><lpage>S151</lpage></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Wang KLC, Li H, Ecker JR (2002) Ethylene biosynthesis and signaling networks. Plant Cell 14(Suppl):S131&#x02013;S151 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12045274</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>ACC</term><def><p>1-Aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BAPTA</term><def><p>1,2-Bis-(2- aminophenoxy)ethane-<italic>N</italic>,<italic>N</italic>,<italic>N</italic>&#x02032;,<italic>N</italic>&#x02032;-tetra acetic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BAW</term><def><p>Beet armyworm</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DMADP</term><def><p>Dimethylallyl diphosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DMNT</term><def><p>(<italic>E</italic>)-4,8-Dimethyl-1,3,7-nonatriene</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>[<sup>2</sup>H<sub>2</sub>]-DOX</term><def><p>1-Deoxy-[5,5-<sup>2</sup>H<sub>2</sub>]-<sc>d</sc>-xylulose</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DXP</term><def><p>1-Deoxy-<sc>d</sc>-xylulose-5-phosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DXS</term><def><p>DXP synthase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FDP</term><def><p>Farnesyl diphosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GDP</term><def><p>Geranyl diphosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GGDP</term><def><p>Geranylgeranyl diphosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HIPV</term><def><p>Herbivore-induced plant volatile</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HMGR</term><def><p>3-Hydroxy-3-methyl-glutaryl CoA reductase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IDP</term><def><p>Isopentenyl diphosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>JA</term><def><p>Jasmonic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MEP</term><def><p>2-<italic>C</italic>-methyl-<sc>d</sc>-erythritol 4-phosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MVA</term><def><p>Mevalonic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OPDA</term><def><p>12-Oxophytodienoic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SPME</term><def><p>Solid-phase microextraction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>STS</term><def><p>Silver thiosulfate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TMTT</term><def><p>(<italic>E</italic>,<italic>E</italic>)-4,8,12-Trimethyltrideca-1,3,7,11-tetraene</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TPS</term><def><p>Terpene synthase</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Electronic supplementary material</bold></p><p>The online version of this article (doi:10.1007/s00425-007-0631-y) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>