<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName nlm2jats3.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Plant Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Plant Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-462X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8475955</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2021.708697</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Plant Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Genome-Wide Identification and Functional Characterization of the Trans-Isopentenyl Diphosphate Synthases Gene Family in <italic>Cinnamomum camphora</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Zerui</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1312246/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Chunzhu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1337272/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>Ting</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Linhuan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Shanshan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Yuying</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1047570/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>An</surname><given-names>Wenli</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Xiasheng</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Song</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c002" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>School of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Guangzhou University of Chinese Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Guangzhou</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>National Engineering Research Center for Healthcare Devices, Institute of Medicine and Health, Guangdong Academy of Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Guangzhou</addr-line>, <country>China,</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>National Engineering Research Center for Modernization of Traditional Chinese Medicine, Guangzhou University of Chinese Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Guangzhou</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn id="fn1" fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Jian Li, Beijing Technology and Business University, China</p></fn><fn id="fn2" fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Raimund Nagel, University of Leipzig, Germany; Wajid Waheed Bhat, Michigan State University, United States; Jinhua Zuo, Beijing Vegetable Research Center, China</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Xiasheng Zheng, <email>xszheng@gzucm.edu.cn</email></corresp><corresp id="c002">Song Huang, <email>huangnn421@163.com</email></corresp><fn id="fn3" fn-type="other"><p>This article was submitted to Plant Metabolism and Chemodiversity, a section of the journal Frontiers in Plant Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>9</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>708697</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>5</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>7</month><year>2021</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2021 Yang, Xie, Zhan, Li, Liu, Huang, An, Zheng and Huang.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Yang, Xie, Zhan, Li, Liu, Huang, An, Zheng and Huang</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Trans-isopentenyl diphosphate synthases (TIDSs) genes are known to be important determinants for terpene diversity and the accumulation of terpenoids. The essential oil of <italic>Cinnamomum camphora</italic>, which is rich in monoterpenes, sesquiterpenes, and other aromatic compounds, has a wide range of pharmacological activities and has therefore attracted considerable interest. However, the <italic>TIDS</italic> gene family, and its relationship to the camphor tree (<italic>C. camphora</italic> L. Presl.), has not yet been characterized. In this study, we identified 10 <italic>TIDS</italic> genes in the genome of the <italic>C. camphora</italic> borneol chemotype that were unevenly distributed on chromosomes. Synteny analysis revealed that the <italic>TIDS</italic> gene family in this species likely expanded through segmental duplication events. Furthermore, cis-element analyses demonstrated that <italic>C. camphora</italic> TIDS (CcTIDS) genes can respond to multiple abiotic stresses. Finally, functional characterization of eight putative short-chain TIDS proteins revealed that CcTIDS3 and CcTIDS9 exhibit farnesyl diphosphate synthase (FPPS) activity, while CcTIDS1 and CcTIDS2 encode geranylgeranyl diphosphate synthases (GGPPS). Although, CcTIDS8 and CcTIDS10 were found to be catalytically inactive alone, they were able to bind to each other to form a heterodimeric functional geranyl diphosphate synthase (GPPS) <italic>in vitro</italic>, and this interaction was confirmed using a yeast two-hybrid assay. Furthermore, transcriptome analysis revealed that the <italic>CcTIDS3</italic>, <italic>CcTIDS8</italic>, <italic>CcTIDS9</italic>, and <italic>CcTIDS10</italic> genes were found to be more active in <italic>C. camphora</italic> roots as compared to stems and leaves, which were verified by quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR). These novel results provide a foundation for further exploration of the role of the <italic>TIDS</italic> gene family in camphor trees, and also provide a potential mechanism by which the production of camphor tree essential oil could be increased for pharmacological purposes through metabolic engineering.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>genome-wide identification</kwd><kwd><italic>Cinnamomum camphora</italic></kwd><kwd>trans-isopentenyl diphosphate synthases</kwd><kwd>functional characterization</kwd><kwd>gene family</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn1"><institution-wrap><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China
</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100001809</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id award-type="contract" rid="cn1">81903741</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="9"/><table-count count="2"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="74"/><page-count count="16"/><word-count count="9230"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p><italic>Cinnamomum camphora</italic> is a subtropical evergreen tree species that has been widely cultivated in southern China for over 1,500years (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2020b</xref>). Studies have shown that essential oil extracted from the leaves of the camphor tree, which is rich in monoterpenes, sesquiterpenes, and other aromatic compounds, has a wide range of pharmacological activities, including antibacterial, antioxidant, and insecticidal properties (<xref rid="ref72" ref-type="bibr">Yu et al., 2019</xref>).</p><p><italic>Cinnamomum camphora</italic> subspecies can be grouped into five chemotypes according to the dominant component in their essential oils, which were extracted from their leaves: linalool, D-borneol, camphor, cineole, or nerolidol (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">Guo et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2018</xref>). These terpenoids have important industrial and pharmaceutical applications. For example, D-borneol is a well-established traditional Chinese medicine that is used to treat cardiovascular diseases, including stroke, coronary heart disease, and angina pectoris (<xref rid="ref67" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2020</xref>). D-Borneol has been documented in various versions of the Chinese Pharmacopoeia (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">Liang et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr">Ren et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">Chai et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="ref67" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2020</xref>), and it is in high demand as a key ingredient in many traditional Chinese herbal formulas. This compound can also be used to relieve pain resulting from wounds, injuries, burns, and cuts (<xref rid="ref67" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2020</xref>). However, despite the high medicinal value of volatile terpenoids, limited plant resources, and low extraction efficiency limit the amounts of the essential oils from <italic>C. camphora</italic> that can be obtained for research or practical applications (<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">Ma et al., 2021</xref>).</p><p>An increasing body of research has demonstrated that metabolic engineering consists of optimizing the genetic and regulatory mechanisms that govern cellular processes, and this is an effective method that can be used to increase the production of active natural products in microorganisms and plants (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Choi et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">Li and Mutanda, 2019</xref>). Identifying the genes that govern production and accumulation of the essential oil in <italic>C. camphora</italic> could therefore enable the implementation of this approach to increase the essential oil yield, which would assist in meeting high demand.</p><p>Terpenoids are the largest category of plant specialized metabolites. More than 55,000 of these compounds have thus far been described, and are grouped into hemi- (C5), mono- (C10), sesqui- (C15), di- (C20), sester- (C25), tri- (C30), tetra- (C40), and poly- (C50) terpenoids according to the number of carbon atoms they contain (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">Dudareva et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">Pichersky et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="ref59" ref-type="bibr">Ueoka et al., 2020</xref>). Despite diverse functions and structures, all terpenoids contain two universal C5 units: isopentenyl diphosphate (IPP) and its allylic isomer dimethylallyl diphosphate (DMAPP). The mevalonic acid (MVA) pathway gives rise to IPP, and <italic>via</italic> enzymatic isomerization, to DMAPP, whereas the methylerythritol phosphate (MEP) pathway directly produces both IPP and DMAPP. IPP and DMAPP can be condensed (head to tail) by prenyltransferase (PTS) or isoprenyl diphosphate synthase (IDS), resulting in a series of prenyl diphosphates with various chain lengths. These linear precursors are then catalyzed by terpene synthase (TPS) and other modifying enzymes to form a variety of different terpenoids (<xref rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr">Tholl and Lee, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Athanasakoglou and Grypioti, 2019</xref>; <xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">Johnson et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">Johnson and Bhat, 2019</xref>; <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Adal and Mahmoud, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">Hivert et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">Miller and Bhat, 2020</xref>).</p><p>Isoprenyl diphosphate synthase is located at the branch point of the terpenoid biosynthetic pathway, and plays a vital role in the formation of diverse terpenoid structures (<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">Jia and Chen, 2016</xref>). Differences in terpenoid synthase gene expression and the supply of precursors determine the terpenoid composition produced by plants (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Dudareva et al., 2000</xref>; <xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">Johnson et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">Johnson and Bhat, 2019</xref>; <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Adal and Mahmoud, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">Miller and Bhat, 2020</xref>). Both trans- and cis- isomers of the products of IDS exist (<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">Liang et al., 2002</xref>). Trans-IDS (TIDS) enzymes synthesize isoprenyl diphosphates (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">Barja and Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Concepci&#x000f3;n, 2020</xref>) and are classified as short-chain (SC-TIDS, C10&#x02013;20), medium-chain (MC-TIDS, C25&#x02013;35), or long-chain (LC-TIDS, C40&#x02013;50), depending on the length of the isoprenyl diphosphates that they produce (<xref rid="ref63" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2019</xref>). Cis-IDSs (CIDSs) were initially predicted to synthesize long-chain isoprenyl diphosphates (&#x0003e;C50) for dolichol and polyprenol production (<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">Jia and Chen, 2016</xref>). Although, TIDSs and CIDSs have similarities in substrate preference and reaction products, they utilize different catalytic mechanisms and may be readily distinguished from one another by their primary amino acid (AA) sequences (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">Akhtar et al., 2013</xref>).</p><p>Short-chain-trans-isopentenyl diphosphate synthase includes homodimeric or heterodimeric geranyl diphosphate synthase (GPPS), farnesyl diphosphate synthase (FPPS), and geranylgeranyl diphosphate synthase (GGPPS; <xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">Jia and Chen, 2016</xref>), and their products provide the precursors for monoterpenes, sesquiterpenes, and diterpenes, respectively. Geranylfarnesyl diphosphate synthase (GFPPS) and polyprenyl diphosphate synthase (PPPS) are MC-TIDSs, whereas solanesyl diphosphate synthase (SPPS) is classified as an LC-TIDS (<xref rid="ref60" ref-type="bibr">Vandermoten et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">Nagel et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="ref61" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">Kopcsayov&#x000e1; and Vranov&#x000e1;, 2019</xref>).</p><p>Phylogenetic analysis has revealed that plant <italic>TIDS</italic> genes can be documented into five subfamilies according to sequence identity: <italic>TIDS-a</italic>, <italic>-b</italic>, <italic>-c</italic>, and <italic>-e</italic> including the genes encoding FPPS, SPPS, PPPS, and small subunits (SSUs) of GPPS, respectively (<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">Jia and Chen, 2016</xref>). The <italic>TIDS-d</italic> subfamily is more complex, and it includes genes encoding GGPPS, GFPPS, and PPPS that share a high sequence identity of at least 40%, with some shared identities of 55% or greater (<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">Jia and Chen, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">Cui et al., 2019</xref>). Identification of entire <italic>TIDS</italic> gene families in plant species is required to determine their functions and to understand their combined effect on the specific profile of terpenoids produced.</p><p>Thus far, this level of <italic>TIDS</italic> gene family characterization has only been achieved in the model plant <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">Kopcsayov&#x000e1; and Vranov&#x000e1;, 2019</xref>), in which 16 <italic>TIDS</italic> genes were identified, and in the tomato plant <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> (<xref rid="ref73" ref-type="bibr">Zhou and Pichersky, 2020</xref>), in which 10 were characterized. Studies characterizing these <italic>TIDS</italic> genes have revealed that while most of the synthase types they encode are homodimeric, GPPS may exist as either a homodimer or a heterodimer containing a small subunit (SSU) and a large subunit (LSU), or both (<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">Rai et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Adal and Mahmoud, 2020</xref>). The SSU can be further separated into two types (I and II), which are generally inactive alone. The LSU may be either inactive alone or possess GGPPS activity, while its heterodimer is an active GPPS (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Burke et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">Rai et al., 2013</xref>).</p><p>Given that isoprenyl diphosphate biosynthesis is a crucial determinant for the formation of downstream terpenoid type and their yield, in-depth studies on TIDSs in the camphor tree would be instrumental in optimizing the production of these medicinally valuable products. Here, for the first time, we conducted a genome-wide analysis in the borneol chemotype of <italic>C. camphora</italic> to identify and characterize TIDS genes and the proteins they encode.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec3"><title>Plant Materials</title><p>Borneol chemotype <italic>C. camphora</italic> plants were purchased from Ji&#x02019;an Yu Feng Natural Species Co., Ltd. (Ji&#x02019;an, China), and grown in an artificial climate box (Shanghai Yiheng Instrument Co., Ltd., Shanghai, China) at 25&#x000b0;C with a 12h light and then 12h dark photoperiod. We verified the origin of these plants through DNA barcodes.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Genome-Wide Identification of TIDS Genes in <italic>C. camphora</italic></title><p>We downloaded TIDS protein sequences of <italic>A. thaliana</italic> and <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> from The Arabidopsis Information Resource (TAIR)<xref rid="fn0001" ref-type="fn"><sup>1</sup></xref> and the Sol Genomics Network (<xref rid="ref65" ref-type="bibr">Wijfjes and Smit, 2019</xref>).<xref rid="fn0002" ref-type="fn"><sup>2</sup></xref> We then used the Protein Basic Logical Alignment Search Tool (BLASTP, United States National Library of Medicine)<xref rid="fn0003" ref-type="fn"><sup>3</sup></xref> to compare these sequences with the <italic>C. camphora</italic> database (unpublished), using previously established thresholds for <italic>e</italic>-value (&#x02264;1e<sup>&#x02212;5</sup>) and identity (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">Cui et al., 2019</xref>). Any genes identified were then used as queries for a second round of BLASTP searches to ensure no putative <italic>CcTIDS</italic> genes were missed. We also conducted a Hidden Markov Model (HMM) search for sequence homologs using the HMMER 3.0 program and the polyprenyl synthase domain PF00348 as a bait, and previously established <italic>e</italic>-value and identity thresholds (<xref rid="ref66" ref-type="bibr">Wong et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">Cui et al., 2019</xref>).</p><p>The BLASTP and HMM search results were then integrated to identify candidate TIDS genes. Their sequences were then submitted to the online Pfam database and NCBI conserved domains database (CDD) in order to verify the presence of the polyprenyl synthase domain (<xref rid="ref74" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et al., 2020</xref>). The physicochemical parameters of each CcTIDS, including molecular weight and isoelectric point, were calculated using the ExPASy online tool (<xref rid="ref74" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et al., 2020</xref>).<xref rid="fn0004" ref-type="fn"><sup>4</sup></xref> The MEME online tool<xref rid="fn0005" ref-type="fn"><sup>5</sup></xref> was used to discover conserved domains in the amino acid sequence of each CcTIDS (<xref rid="ref74" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et al., 2020</xref>). Finally, we used the chloroP (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">Emanuelsson et al., 1999</xref>),<xref rid="fn0006" ref-type="fn"><sup>6</sup></xref> TargetP (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">Emanuelsson et al., 2000</xref>),<xref rid="fn0007" ref-type="fn"><sup>7</sup></xref> Wolfpsort (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">Horton et al., 2007</xref>),<xref rid="fn0008" ref-type="fn"><sup>8</sup></xref> and Plant-mPloc (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">Chou and Shen, 2010</xref>)<xref rid="fn0009" ref-type="fn"><sup>9</sup></xref> tools to predict the subcellular localization of each CcTIDS.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Phylogenetic Relationship, Exon-Intron Structure, Chromosomal Localization, and Cis-Acting Element Analysis</title><p>A maximum likelihood (ML) evolutionary tree was constructed using the identified <italic>C. camphora</italic> TIDS amino acid sequences and those of 10 other plant species (<italic>A. thaliana</italic>: <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">Arabidopsis Genome Initiative, 2000</xref>; <italic>Oryza sativa</italic>: <xref rid="ref71" ref-type="bibr">Yu et al., 2002</xref>; <italic>Physcomitrella patens</italic>: <xref rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr">Rensing et al., 2008</xref>; <italic>Selaginella moellendorffii</italic>: <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Banks et al., 2011</xref>; <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic>: <xref rid="ref58" ref-type="bibr">Tomato Genome Consortium, 2012</xref>; <italic>Amborella trichopoda</italic>: <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">Amborella Genome Project, 2013</xref>; <italic>Picea abies</italic>: <xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">Nystedt et al., 2013</xref>; <italic>Zea mays</italic>: <xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">Jiao et al., 2017</xref>; and <italic>Cinnamomum micranthum</italic>: <xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">Chaw et al., 2019</xref>) and the Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis (MEGA) tool (version 7.0; <xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">Kumar et al., 2016</xref>) with the best models of JTT+G. Bootstrap value, which indicates the reliability of each branch node, was set at 1,000 replicates. The resulting tree was visualized using EvolView v3 (<xref rid="ref56" ref-type="bibr">Subramanian et al., 2019</xref>).</p><p>Exons and introns for each TIDS were identified using the gene transfer format (GTF) file from the <italic>C. camphora</italic> genome, which contains information regarding gene structure, and visualized using TBtools (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2020a</xref>). Finally, in order to identify cis-regulatory elements, TBtools was used to extract the 2,000bp upstream sequence for each TIDS gene identified in the <italic>C. camphora</italic> genome (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2020a</xref>). We then compared these sequences with the PlantCARE database of plant cis-acting regulatory elements (<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">Lescot et al., 2002</xref>). Circos graphs showing the chromosomal localization and results of the synteny analysis of the CcTIDS sequences were drawn using TBtools (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2020a</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>RNA Extraction, cDNA Synthesis, and Gene Cloning</title><p>Total RNA was extracted from the root, stem, and leaf of <italic>C. camphora</italic> using the Plant Pure Plant RNA Kit (Aidlab, Beijing, China). cDNA was synthesized from 1&#x003bc;g of high-quality total RNA (OD 260/280=1.8&#x02013;2.2, OD 260/230&#x02265;2.0, RIN&#x02265;6.5, and 28S:18S&#x02265;1.0) using the TransScript One-Step gDNA Removal and cDNA Synthesis SuperMix kit (TransGen Biotech, Beijing, China) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions (<xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">Su et al., 2019</xref>).</p><p>The primers use to amplify eight putative SC-TIDSs were designed using the Primer Premier 5 program (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S4</xref>). Amplification by PCR was conducted using the 2&#x000d7;TransStart FastPfu PCR SuperMix (TransGen Biotech, Beijing, China) and cDNA as the template. Purified PCR products were then cloned into the pEASY-blunt vector using previously described methods (<xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">Su et al., 2019</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec7"><title>Quantitative Real-Time PCR Analysis</title><p>Quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR) was performed using the TransStar Tip Green qPCR SuperMix (TransGen Biotech, Beijing, China) and the CFX96 Touch Deep Well platform (Bio-Rad, United States; <xref rid="ref67" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2020</xref>). We used a previously described reaction system composition and qRT-PCR procedure (<xref rid="ref67" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2020</xref>). Primers are listed in <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S4</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec8"><title>Subcellular Localization of CcTIDS Proteins</title><p>Full-length putative SC-TIDS gene sequences without stop codons were each fused with enhanced green fluorescent protein (EGFP) and ligated into the pAN580 vector (using the primers described in <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S4</xref>). The recombinant vectors were then transformed into <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> protoplasts using polyethylene glycol (PEG; <xref rid="ref73" ref-type="bibr">Zhou and Pichersky, 2020</xref>). Protoplast isolation and recombinant vector transformation were performed with protocols described in previous studies (<xref rid="ref70" ref-type="bibr">Yoo et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="ref64" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2018</xref>). EGFP fluorescent signals were observed using a Zeiss laser scanning microscope (LSM) 800 (Zeiss, Germany) as previously described (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">Beck et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">Su et al., 2019</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec9"><title>Recombinant Expression and Enzymatic Assays</title><p>Truncated or full length versions of the eight putative SC-TIDSs were ligated into the pET32a [polyhistidine (6x His) tag, Wego, Guanghzou, China] or pMAL-C5X (MBP tag, Wego, Guanghzou, China) expression vectors using the pEASY-Basic Seamless Cloning and Assembly Kit (TransGen Biotech) following the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions (<xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">Su et al., 2019</xref>), using the primers listed in <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S4</xref>. Constructs were verified using Sanger sequencing. Upon sequence confirmation, recombinant plasmids were transferred into the expression strain <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> Rossetta (DE3; Huayueyang, Beijing, China). Heterologous protein expression in this strain and the purification of the fusion protein were conducted according to previously established methods (<xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">Su et al., 2019</xref>).</p><p>In order to establish the function of each SC-TIDS, a 200-&#x003bc;l <italic>in vitro</italic> enzymatic activity reaction containing 25mmol/L MOPSO buffer with pH of 7.0, 10mmol/L magnesium chloride, 10% glycerin, 20&#x02013;50&#x003bc;g protein, and substrates (150&#x003bc;mol/L IPP+40&#x003bc;mol/L DMAPP or GPP or FPP, Sigma-Aldrich, United States), was conducted. Each mixture was first incubated at 30&#x000b0;C for 6h, and then, 200&#x003bc;l of 200mmol/L Tris&#x02013;HCl (pH 9.5), containing 2units of bovine intestine alkaline phosphatase (18unitsmg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; Sigma-Aldrich) and 2units of potato apyrase (25.2unitsmg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; Sigma-Aldrich) were added (<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">Rai et al., 2013</xref>). An overnight hydrolysis reaction was carried out at 30&#x000b0;C. Ethyl acetate was then used to extract the enzymatic reaction buffer in 2&#x000d7;400&#x003bc;l extractions (<xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">Su et al., 2019</xref>). The ethyl acetate extracts were concentrated to 100&#x003bc;l under N<sub>2</sub>, and these concentrated extracts were then used for gas chromatography&#x02013;mass spectrometry (GC&#x02013;MS) analysis using previously described methods (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Athanasakoglou and Grypioti, 2019</xref>; <xref rid="ref67" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2020</xref>). The GPPS large and small subunits from <italic>Catharanthus roseus</italic> were also analyzed as a positive control (<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">Rai et al., 2013</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec10"><title>Yeast 2-Hybrid Assay</title><p>The interactions between the CcGPPS small and large subunits were verified by the following experiments: the truncated versions of these subunits were amplified from the cDNA of <italic>C. camphora</italic>, followed by fusing to the activation domain of the pGADT7 vector or the binding domain of the pGBKT7 vector. Recombinant vectors were co-transformed into <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> AH109 yeast and sequentially cultivated on the synthetic dropout (SD) medium SD/-Trp/-Leu. The interaction between the two proteins was tested on SD/-Trp/-Leu/-His/-Ade medium supplemented with 150mM 3-amino-1,24-triazole (3-AT).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec11"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec12"><title>Genome-Wide Identification of TIDS Genes in <italic>C. camphora</italic></title><p>Based on the HMM scan and BLASTP search results, 10 full-length, protein-coding TIDS-like gene sequences were identified in <italic>C. camphora</italic>, which we numbered <italic>CcPTPS1&#x02013;10</italic> according to their locations on the chromosomes. These genes included eight putative SC-TIDS (two FPPSs, <italic>CcTIDS3</italic> and <italic>CcTIDS9</italic>; two GPPSs, <italic>CcTIDS4</italic> and <italic>CcTIDS5</italic>; three GGPPSs, <italic>CcTIDS1</italic>, <italic>CcTIDS2</italic>, and <italic>CcTIDS8</italic>; and one GPPS small subunit, <italic>CcTIDS10</italic>) and two putative LC-TIDS (SPPS, and <italic>CcTIDS6</italic> and <italic>CcTIDS7</italic>), which were distributed along six of the 12 chromosomes (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). In addition, genome synteny analysis showed that three segmental duplications and no tandem duplication events likely occurred, suggesting that segmental duplication might be one of the reasons for TIDS gene family expansion (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Circos graph showing the chromosomal locations and duplicated gene pairs of trans-isopentenyl diphosphate synthases (<italic>CcTIDS</italic>) genes in the <italic>C. camphora</italic> genome. The blue segments represent the 12 chromosomes present in this species. Duplicated genes are indicated as red lines between each gene pair.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="fpls-12-708697-g001" position="float"/></fig><p>The proteins encoded by the <italic>CcTIDS</italic> genes were found to have a minimum size of 298 AA and a maximum size of 428 AA. All of the CcTIDS proteins had an isoelectric point (pI) &#x0003c;7, indicating that these proteins are rich in acidic AAs. Specific information for all CcTIDS proteins is shown in <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Nomenclature and physicochemical characteristics of TIDS genes identified in <italic>C. camphora</italic>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Gene ID</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Rename</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Chromosomal position</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Putative function</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Number of amino acids/AA</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Theoretical pI</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Molecular weight/KD</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><italic>In silico</italic> subcellular localization prediction</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Conserved motif</th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chloroP</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TargetP</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wolfpsort</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plant-mPloc</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">evm.model.LG01.0506</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CcTIDS1</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LG01</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGPPS</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">383</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.98</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.34</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FARM/SARM/CXXXC</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">evm.model.LG01.2465</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CcTIDS2</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LG01</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGPPS</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">387</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.33</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.7</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FARM/SARM/CXXXC</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">evm.model.LG04.0985</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CcTIDS3</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LG04</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FPPS</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">350</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.25</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.41</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cytoplasm</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mitochondrion.</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FARM/SARM</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">evm.model.LG04.2634</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CcTIDS4</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LG04</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPPS</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">421</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.67</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.45</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mitochondrion</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FARM/SARM</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">evm.model.LG05.1976</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CcTIDS5</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LG05</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPPS</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">428</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.09</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.04</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mitochondrion</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mitochondrion</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FARM/SARM</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">evm.model.LG06.0936</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CcTIDS6</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LG06</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPPS</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">415</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.42</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.3</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FARM/SARM</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">evm.model.LG08.1085</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CcTIDS7</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LG08</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPPS</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">401</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.50</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.68</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mitochondrion</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FARM/SARM</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">evm.model.LG11.0380</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CcTIDS8</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LG11</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGPPS</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">383</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.78</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.39</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FARM/SARM/CXXXC</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">evm.model.LG11.1115</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CcTIDS9</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LG11</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FPPS</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">364</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.18</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.45</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mitochondrion</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FARM/SARM</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">evm.model.LG11.1288</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CcTIDS10</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LG11</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPPS.SSU</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">298</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.24</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.13</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CXXXC\CXXXC</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec13"><title>Phylogenetic Relationships Within the <italic>C. camphora</italic> TIDS Gene Family</title><p>A total of 100 <italic>TIDS</italic>-like genes were identified in 10 other plant species (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Tables S1</xref> and <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2</xref>). It can be concluded from the number of TIDS genes contained in each species that as the complexity of the species increases, the greater amount TIDS it contains (<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">Coman et al., 2014</xref>). In addition, fewer <italic>CcTIDS</italic> genes were found in <italic>C. camphora</italic> than those in <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, <italic>Populus trichocarpa</italic>, <italic>O. sativa</italic>, and <italic>Z. mays</italic>, but equal to those in <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> and the stout camphor tree <italic>C. micranthum</italic>.</p><p>A ML evolutionary tree was built to determine the phylogenetic relationships between the <italic>C. camphora TIDS</italic> family and those found in the other plants (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). None of the genes apart from those in <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> and <italic>A. thaliana</italic> has yet been functionally characterized. In order to better distinguish the functional attributes of the <italic>TIDS</italic> genes on each branch, we added several well-characterized TIDS genes when constructing the phylogenetic tree (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S3</xref>). The <italic>TIDS</italic> genes in the resulting tree clustered into recently described catalytically distinct subfamilies (<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">Jia and Chen, 2016</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>A phylogenetic tree constructed using putative or characterized <italic>TIDS</italic> genes from 11 sequenced land plant genomes and a neighbor joining approach. GPPS, geranyl diphosphate synthase; FPPS, farnesyl diphosphate synthase; GGPPS, geranylgeranyl diphosphate synthase; LSU, large subunit; SSUI/II, small subunit I/II; GFPPS, geranylfarnesyl diphosphate synthase; PPPS, polyprenyl diphosphate synthase; and SPPS, solanesyl diphosphate synthase.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="fpls-12-708697-g002" position="float"/></fig><p>According to enzymatic activity and the relevance of genetic evolution, the subfamily encoding TIDS-e proteins was subdivided into two clades, which contained genes encoding GPPS small subunits I and II. Among them, only one single GPPS small subunit-encoding <italic>C. camphora</italic> gene, <italic>CcTIDS10</italic>, was placed (within the small subunit I clade), indicating that the genome of <italic>C. camphora</italic> only contained GPPS small subunit genes from this class. <italic>CcTIDS6</italic> and <italic>CcTIDS7</italic> were clustered closely with the genes encoding the TIDS-b subfamily of proteins, indicating that these two genes may function as SPPS enzymes.</p><p><italic>CcTIDS1</italic>, <italic>CcTIDS2</italic>, and <italic>CcTIDS8</italic> were found to belong to the TIDS-d subfamily, and therefore, may encode GGPPS, GFPPS, or PPPS enzymes. <italic>CcTIDS3</italic> and <italic>CcTIDS9</italic> were clustered with genes encoding TIDS-a proteins, indicating that they may encode FPPS enzymes. Although, the TIDS-c subfamily is known to contain mostly PPPS (<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">Jia and Chen, 2016</xref>), genes encoding functionally characterized GPPS enzymes were included in this clade according to our analysis. Two <italic>CcTIDSs</italic>, <italic>CcTIDS4</italic>, and <italic>CcTTPS5</italic>, were clustered within this subfamily and were more closely related with the known GPPS-encoding genes, indicating that they may possess GPPS activity as well (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec14"><title>Conserved Motifs, Exon-Intron Structure, and Multiple Gene Alignment Analysis of <italic>CcTIDS</italic> in the Camphor Tree</title><p>The evolution of gene families may be accompanied by changes in gene structure, which may provide additional information from which the diversification of gene functions can be inferred (<xref rid="ref68" ref-type="bibr">Ye et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">Cui et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2020</xref>). For this reason, we further analyzed the organization of the exons and introns of <italic>CcTIDS</italic> genes and compared them with those from <italic>A. thaliana</italic> and <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic>. Our results showed that the <italic>TIDS</italic> genes within the same subgroup mostly exhibited similar arrangements of exons and introns. For instance, <italic>CcTIDS6</italic> and <italic>CcTIDS7</italic>, which were assigned to the TIDS-b-encoding subfamily, possessed six introns each. <italic>CcTIDS1</italic>, <italic>CcTIDS2</italic>, and <italic>CcTIDS8</italic> were all found to contain no introns, indicating that they do not encode GFPPS, which are known to contain two introns, although, they were closely clustered with known GFPPS genes, and belong to the same subfamily (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). However, it remains unclear whether these genes encode GPPS large subunits or GGPPS proteins.</p><p>Our analysis on conserved TIDS motifs showed that TIDS belonging to the same subfamily exhibited a similar motif composition and arrangement (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figures 3A</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">D</xref>). Catalytically important conserved motifs were recognized in every identified TIDS sequence after multiple sequence alignment of CcTIDS, <italic>A. thaliana</italic> TIDS (AtTIDS), and <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> TIDS (SlTIDS). Two common aspartate-rich motifs, the first and second aspartate-rich motif (FARM and SARM, respectively), are known binding sites for DMAPP (<xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">Su et al., 2019</xref>), and these were present in sequences of all the TIDS sequences except for those of CcTIDS10, AtGPPS small subunit II, and SlGPPS small subunit I.</p><fig position="float" id="fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Tran-prenyltransferase protein subfamily analysis based on phylogenetic relationships. <bold>(A)</bold> Intron-exon structures, <bold>(B)</bold> conserved motifs, <bold>(C)</bold> analysis of <italic>C. camphora</italic> (Cc)TIDS, <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (At)TIDS, and <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> (Sl)TIDS. <bold>(D)</bold> Legend depicting the protein sequence of the corresponding motif. GPPS, geranyl diphosphate synthase; FPPS, farnesyl diphosphate synthase; GGPPS, geranylgeranyl diphosphate synthase; LSU, large subunit; SSUI/II, small subunit I/II; GFPPS, geranylfarnesyl diphosphate synthase; PPPS, polyprenyl diphosphate synthase; and SPPS, solanesyl diphosphate synthase.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="fpls-12-708697-g003" position="float"/></fig><p>In addition, two conserved cysteine-rich (CxxxC) motifs were found in CcTIDS10, AtGPPS small subunit II, and SlGPPS small subunit I, and one each in CcTIDS1, CcTIDS2, and CcTIDS8. These CxxxC motifs play important roles in the interaction between the two subunits of the plant heterodimer GPPS. Our data suggest that CcTIDS10 is most likely a GPPS small subunit that forms a heterodimer with CcTIDS1, CcTIDS2, or CcTPS8 as a GPPS large subunit (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec15"><title>Cis-Element Analysis of the TIDS Genes in <italic>C. camphora</italic></title><p>We analyzed cis-elements in the promoter of the <italic>CcTIDS</italic> genes to better understand their potential regulation and function. In total, 343 cis-acting elements were identified, and they were grouped into three categories, which were responsible for plant growth and development, phytohormone responsiveness, and stress responsiveness, according to previous research (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">Abdullah et al., 2018</xref>). Of these, nine belong to the plant growth and development category, of which AAGAA motifs (involved in the endosperm) and AS-1 elements (involved in shoot expression) accounted for the highest proportion (19.05%).</p><p>The greatest proportion of cis-acting regulatory elements related to phytohormone response were myelocytomatosis (MYC) elements that are associated with methyl jasmonate (MeJA), accounting for 50%. All <italic>CcTIDS</italic> genes contained at least five MYC cis-acting elements, suggesting that <italic>CcTIDS</italic> gene expression might be moderated by MeJA. Nearly half of all the cis-acting elements were associated with stress responsiveness (167/343), of which the most common three cis-acting elements were the STRE motif related to stress (19%), G-box (14%), and box 4 (9%), which are associated with responsiveness to light (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>). These results suggest that <italic>CcTIDS</italic> gene expression may be induced or suppressed by MeJA, and these genes may play roles in plant responses to a variety of abiotic stressors.</p><fig position="float" id="fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>(A)</bold> The number of cis-acting elements in each <italic>C. camphora (Cc)TIDS</italic> gene, indicated by the intensity of the red color and numbers in the grid. <bold>(B)</bold> Histograms indicating the number of cis-acting elements in each <italic>CcTIDS</italic> gene with functions in plant growth and development, phytohormone responsiveness, or stress responsiveness. <bold>(C)</bold> Pie charts showing the ratio of different cis-acting elements in each structural category.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="fpls-12-708697-g004" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec16"><title>Expression Patterns of <italic>CcTIDS</italic> Genes in Different <italic>C. camphora</italic> Tissues</title><p>Our sequence alignment, evolution, and gene structure analyses all indicated that the <italic>CcTIDS6</italic> and <italic>CcTIDS7</italic> genes most likely encode SPPS enzymes. Hence, only the eight putative SC-TIDS-encoding genes were included in further analyses of expression patterns and subcellular localization, and an enzymatic assay.</p><p>To identify potential roles for <italic>CcTIDS</italic> genes in different tissues of <italic>C. camphora</italic>, we established a transcriptome database based on RNA sequencing of the leaves, roots, and stems (Accession number: PRJNA747104). qRT-PCR was used to verify these transcriptome data. We found that the expression profiles of <italic>CcTIDS</italic> genes were tissue-specific (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>). For example, <italic>CcTIDS1</italic> and <italic>CcTIDS2</italic> were upregulated in the leaf tissue compared with the root and stem, whereas the expression level of <italic>CcTIDS3</italic>, <italic>9</italic>, <italic>8</italic>, and <italic>10</italic> were upregulated in the root compared with the other tissues. This may indicate that there are functional differences in <italic>CcTIDS</italic> according to the different <italic>C. camphora</italic> organs from which the tissue was derived.</p><fig position="float" id="fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Differential expression of <italic>C. camphora (Cc)TIDS</italic> genes in different tissues by transcriptome and quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR). <bold>(A)</bold> FPKM value of the RNA sequencing data for each gene in leaf, root, and stem tissues. <bold>(B&#x02013;I)</bold> Relative expression of each gene in the different plant tissues as calculated by qRT-PCR, with red and blue representing high and low expression levels, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="fpls-12-708697-g005" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec17"><title>Subcellular Localization of Putative SC-TIDS Proteins</title><p>Subcellular localization predictions using four different online software programs revealed that CcTIDS1, 2, 8, and 10 are likely to be located in plastids. However, the results for CcTIDS3, 4, 5, and 9 were inconsistent (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). In order to obtain exact subcellular location information for each candidate CcTIDS, we analyzed expression patterns using fluorescence microscopy (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>). Consistent with all prediction programs, the GFP signals for CcTIDS1, 2, 8, and 10 were localized mainly within chloroplasts. Fluorescently tagged CcTIDS3 and CcTIDS9 proteins were both localized in the cytoplasm, while fluorescent signals for CcTIDS4 and CcTIDS5 recombinant proteins indicated that they may be located within mitochondria.</p><fig position="float" id="fig6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Subcellular localization of eight putative <italic>C. camphora</italic> trans-prenyltransferase (CcTIDS) enzymes in <italic>A. thaliana</italic> protoplasts. eGFP, green fluorescent protein fluorescence image; chlorophyll, chlorophyll autofluorescence image; bright-field, transmission image; merged, all channels (eGFP, chlorophyll, and bright-field) combined.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="fpls-12-708697-g006" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec18"><title>Heterologous Expression and <italic>in vitro</italic> Functional Characterization of the SC-TIDS Proteins</title><p><italic>In vitro</italic> enzymatic assays were conducted using recombinant proteins extracted and purified from <italic>E. coli</italic> expression strains. The large subunit of CrGPPS was found to catalyze IPP and DMAPP to form geranyl diphosphate (GPP) and geranylgeranyl diphosphate (GGPP), whereas the small subunit of CrGPPS was found to be inactive alone. However, when both subunits were co-incubated, they catalyzed the formation of GPP (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S2</xref>). This is accordance with the results reported in previous research, indicating that the method is valid for the verification of SC-TIDS <italic>in vitro</italic> enzymatic activity (<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">Rai et al., 2013</xref>).</p><p>To characterize the two putative CcGPPS proteins (CcTIDS4 and 5), full-length and truncated versions of CcGPPSs were both analyzed. However, full-length recombinant CcGPPS protein was found to be completely insoluble. Therefore, soluble protein that was purified from the truncated version of each CcGPPS was used in the <italic>in vitro</italic> enzymatic activity assays. Unexpectedly, no catalytic products were detected for the truncated versions of both CcTIDS4 and CcTIDS5 under the conditions used here (<xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Functionally characterized enzymes in this study.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genes</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Full-length ORF/bp</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variants studied</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Accepted substrates</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Products</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rename</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CcTIDS1</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,149</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ala62-end</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DMAPP+IPP</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGPP</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CcGGPPS1</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CcTIDS2</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,161</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asp65-end</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DMAPP+IPP</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGPP</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CcGGPPS2</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">CcTIDS3</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">1,050</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Full length</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DMAPP+IPP</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FPP</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">CcFPPS1</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPP+IPP</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FPP</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">CcTIDS4</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,263</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Full length</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No activity</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,263</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M101-end</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No activity</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">CcTIDS5</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,284</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Full length</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No activity</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,284</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M108-end</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No activity</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CcTIDS8</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,149</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lys56-end</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No activity</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CcGPPS.LSU</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">CcTIDS9</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">1,092</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Full length</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DMAPP+IPP</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FPP</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">CcFPPS2</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPP+IPP</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FPP</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CcTIDS10</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">894</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asn65-end</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No activity</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CcGPPS.SSU</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CcTIDS8&#x00026;CcTIDS10</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,149&#x00026;894</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lys56-end&#x00026;Asn65-end</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DMAPP+IPP</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPP</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Two full-length putative CcFPPS proteins (CcTIDS 3 and 9) lacking a transit peptide were generated. As expected, both recombinant proteins exhibited FPPS activity, producing FPP as the unique product, indicating that these two TIDS proteins are FPP synthases. Therefore, we reclassified these two TIDS proteins as CcFPPS1 and CcFPPS2 (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Gas chromatography&#x02013;mass spectrometry (GC&#x02013;MS) profile showing <italic>in vitro</italic> reaction products of <italic>C. camphora</italic> trans-prenyltransferases CcTIDS3 and CcTIDS9, where different prenyldiphosphates were used as substrates. Expression and purification of <bold>(A)</bold> CcTIDS3 and <bold>(B)</bold> CcTIDS9 recombinant protein from <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> Rosetta (DE3) harboring pET32a(+)&#x02013;CcTIDS3/CcTIDS9, where lane 1 shows the total protein after induction, 2 shows the soluble protein, and 3&#x02013;6 shows the purified CcTIDS3 or CcTIDS9 recombinant protein from the first to the fourth collected tube. The GC&#x02013;MS chromatogram of the reaction products generated by <bold>(C)</bold> CcTIDS3 and <bold>(D)</bold> CcTIDS9 and the acid hydrolysis products of farnesol (FOH) standards. <bold>(E)</bold> Mass spectra of farnesol standard (shown in red) and products in the NIST14/Wiley275 library (blue). GPP, geranyl diphosphate; DMAPP, dimethylallyl diphosphate; and IPP, isopentenyl diphosphate.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="fpls-12-708697-g007" position="float"/></fig><p>It was predicted that three putative CcGGPPS proteins (CcTIDS1, 2, and 8) and one putative CcGPPS small subunit (CcTIDS10) contained a transit peptide. Therefore, truncated versions of these four proteins were fused to His or MBP tags, resulting in the formation of soluble protein. The activity of these four soluble proteins was detected in all substrate combinations. As a result, CcTIDS1 and 2 emitted a prominent chromatographic signal corresponding to geranylgeraniol (C20), demonstrating that CcTIDS1 and 2 function individually as <italic>bona fide</italic> GGPPS enzymes. Hence, these two proteins were renamed CcGGPPS1 and CcGGPPS2 (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figures 8A</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">F</xref>). In contrast, CcTIDS8 and 10 did not exhibit any chromatographic peak signal for farnesol (C15), geraniol (C10), or geranylgeraniol (C20), suggesting that these proteins are inactive alone (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8G</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig8"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Gas chromatography&#x02013;mass spectrometry profile showing <italic>in vitro</italic> reaction products of <italic>C. camphora</italic> trans-prenyltransferases CcTIDS1, CcTIDS2, CcTIDS8, and CcTIDS9, where different prenyldiphosphates were used as substrates. Expression and purification of <bold>(A)</bold> CcTIDS1, <bold>(B)</bold> CcTIDS2, <bold>(C)</bold> CcTIDS8, and <bold>(D)</bold> CcTIDS10 recombinant protein from <italic>E. coli</italic> Rosetta (DE3) harboring pET32a(+)&#x02013;CcTIDS1/CcTIDS10 or pMAL-C5x&#x02013;CcTIDS2/CcTIDS8, where lane 1 shows the total protein after induction, 2 shows the soluble protein, 3&#x02013;6 show the purified CcTIDS1 or CcTIDS2, CcTIDS8, or CcTIDS10 recombinant protein from the first to the fourth collected tube. The GC&#x02013;MS chromatogram of the reaction products generated by <bold>(E)</bold> CcTIDS8 and CcTIDS10, <bold>(F)</bold> CcTIDS1, and <bold>(G)</bold> CcPTS2 and the acid hydrolysis products of geraniol (GOH) and gerylgeraniol (GGOH) standards. <bold>(H)</bold> Mass spectra of GOH standard (red) and products in the NIST14/Wiley275 library (blue). <bold>(I)</bold> Mass spectra of the GGOH standard (red) and products in the NIST14/Wiley275 library (blue). <bold>(J)</bold> Confirmation of the interaction between CcTIDS8 and CcTIDS10 using a yeast two-hybrid system, where blue color indicates an interaction. Yeast cells harboring both constructs were spotted on synthetic dropout (SD) medium lacking Ade, His, Leu, and Trp (SD/&#x02212;4) to test for protein interactions. AD: pGADT7; BD: pGBDT7; AD-T: pGADT7::T; BD-53: pGBKT7-53. Cells co-transformed with pGADT7::T and pGBKT7-53 were included as a positive control, and pGADT7 and pGBDT7 as a vector control.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="fpls-12-708697-g008" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec19"><title>CcTIDS8 Interacts With CcTIDS10 to Generate GPP</title><p>Because CcTIDS10 was identified as the only CcGPPS small subunit, we determined whether this protein was able to interact with CcGGPPS1/2 or CcTIDS8 to form active heterodimers. Intriguingly, when CcTIDS10 was co-incubated with CcTIDS8, but not CcGGPPS1 or 2, GPP was detected as a sole product (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figures 8G</xref>-<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">I</xref>).</p><p>A yeast two-hybrid system (Y2H) was used to confirm the interaction of CcTIDS10 with CcTIDS8. As expected, CcTIDS10 was able to interact with CcTIDS8 and itself (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8J</xref>). These results, along with the co-localization of CcTIDS10 and CcTIDS8 in the plastid, confirmed that the inactive CcTIDS10 and CcTIDS8 interact to form heteromeric functional GPPS, generating GPP as the sole product. Thus, CcTIDS10 was designated as CcGPPS.small subunit (SSU), whereas CcTIDS8 was renamed as CcGPPS.large subunit (LSU).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussions" id="sec20"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this study, we reported the characterization of the <italic>C. camphora</italic> TIDS gene family for the first time. Of the 10 identified <italic>TIDS</italic> genes, three (<italic>CcGGPPS1</italic>, <italic>CcGGPPS2</italic>, and <italic>CcGPPS.LSU</italic>) were clustered within the subfamily encoding TIDS-d enzymes, while one single gene, <italic>CcTIDS10</italic>, was closely related to the subfamily encoding TIDS-e enzymes. Apart from those in gymnosperms, TIDS proteins within the TIDS-d and TIDS-e subfamily have been classified as GGPPS paralogs in previous studies. As a result, many GGPPS homologs were predicted from the plant genomes (<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">Coman et al., 2014</xref>).</p><p>The expansion of the GGPPS family in <italic>A. thaliana</italic> occurred at distinct evolutionary time points through different duplication mechanisms, including whole gene, tandem, and segmental genome duplications (<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">Coman et al., 2014</xref>). The evolution of this <italic>A. thaliana</italic> GGPPS family likely involved neofunctionalization (with the duplicated gene developing a function that was not present in the ancestral gene), subfunctionalization (in which the duplicated and ancestral genes retain different parts of the original function of the ancestral gene), and pseudogenization (loss of function; <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">Coman et al., 2014</xref>). Based on our fragment duplication and functional differentiation results for <italic>CcGGPPS1</italic>, <italic>CcGGPPS2</italic>, and <italic>CcGPPS.LSU</italic>, and the phylogenetic tree we constructed, these three genes may have been derived from the same ancestor, having undergone neo- or subfunctionalization.</p><p>Thus far, homodimeric GPPS has been functionally characterized in only a few plant species (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Burke et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">Hsiao et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr">Schmidt and Gershenzon, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">Gutensohn et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">Rai et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Adal and Mahmoud, 2020</xref>). We found that the <italic>C. camphora</italic> genome contained two putative homodimeric <italic>GPPS</italic> genes (<italic>CcTIDS4</italic> and <italic>CcTIDS5</italic>). Our evolutionary analysis suggested that these two genes were related to those encoding the functionally characterized homodimeric GPPS from <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, and subcellular localization experiments indicated that the two proteins encoded by these genes might localize to the mitochondria, consistent with earlier reports on <italic>C. roseus</italic> (<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">Rai et al., 2013</xref>). However, there was no observable GPPS activity associated with the proteins <italic>in vitro</italic>.</p><p>Instead, CcGPPS.SSU (CcTIDS10) and CcGPPS.LSU (CcTIDS8), both identified in our study, were found to interact with one another to form a heterodimeric CcGPPS that produced GPP from IPP and DMAPP substrates <italic>in vitro</italic>. These proteins were found to be inactive alone. This is consistent with previous reports in both <italic>Mentha</italic>&#x000d7;<italic>piperita</italic> subunits (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Burke et al., 2004</xref>), both <italic>Lavendula</italic>&#x000d7;<italic>intermedia</italic> subunits (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Adal and Mahmoud, 2020</xref>), and <italic>A. thaliana</italic> GPPS.SSU2 (<xref rid="ref62" ref-type="bibr">Wang and Dixon, 2009</xref>).</p><p>CcGPPS.SSU and CcGPPS.LSU were primarily expressed in roots compared with stems and leaves. Furthermore, both CcGPPS.SSU and CcGPPS.LSU were found to reside in plastids, which are the known site of monoterpene biosynthesis (<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">Magnard et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="ref69" ref-type="bibr">Yin et al., 2017</xref>). These results suggest that heteromeric CcGPPS likely participates in the biosynthesis of GPP in <italic>C. camphora</italic>.</p><p>Interestingly, all <italic>CcTIDS</italic> genes had orthologs of greater than 90% identity with the <italic>C. micranthum</italic> genome, with the sole exception of <italic>CcGPPS.SSU</italic> (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S3</xref>). <italic>Cinnamomum micranthum</italic>, known as the stout camphor tree, is the sister species of <italic>C. camphora</italic>. The genome of <italic>C. micranthum</italic> with a contig N<sub>50</sub> of 0.9Mb has been published. However, contig N<sub>50</sub> of the genome of <italic>C. camphora</italic> is 23.89Mb (data not shown), indicating that the assembly quality of the <italic>C. camphora</italic> genome is significantly better than that of the <italic>C. micranthum</italic> genome. This lower quality may explain why the GPPS.SSU gene is missing from the <italic>C. micranthum</italic> genome.</p><p>In addition, although, CcTIDS4 and CcTIDS5 did not possess GPPS activity in our study, they may perform different functions. For example, At2g34630 from <italic>A. thaliana</italic> was initially classified as a homodimeric GPPS (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">Bouvier et al., 2000</xref>), but further study indicated that <italic>At2g34630</italic> silencing did not affect the production of monoterpenes, and At2g34630 was subsequently identified as a PPPS (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Hsieh et al., 2011</xref>). Therefore, the functions of CcTIDS4 and 5 should be investigated in future studies.</p><p>In conclusion, this is the first comprehensive and systematic genome-wide analysis of TIDS gene families in <italic>C. camphora</italic>. In total, 10 TIDS genes in the borneol chemotype of <italic>C. camphora</italic> were identified. These genes likely expanded through segmental duplication events, and expression was found to respond to multiple abiotic stressors <italic>via</italic> cis-acting elements in the promoter region. Eight putative SC-TIDS were identified, six of which were catalytically active, including a heteromeric GPPS (composed of CcGPPS.SSU and CcGPPS.LSU), two CcFPPS (CcTIDS3 and 9), and two CcGGPPS (CcTIDS1 and 2), which catalyzed the biosynthesis of GPP, FPP, and GGPP, respectively (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Figure 9</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig9"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>Overview of the terpenoid biosynthesis pathway in <italic>C. camphora</italic>. AACT, acetoacetyl-coenzyme A thiolase; HMGS, 3-hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl coenzyme A synthase; HMGR, 3-hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl coenzyme A reductase; MVK, mevalonate kinase; PMK, 5-phospho mevalonate kinase; MVD, mevalonate diphosphate decarboxylase; IDI, isopentenyl diphosphate isomerase; FPPS, farnesyl diphosphate synthase; DXS,1-deoxy-D-xylulose-5-phosphate synthase; DXR,1-deoxy-D-xylulose-5-phosphate reductoisomerase; MCT, 2-C-methyl-D-erythritol-4-(cytidyl-5-diphosphate) transferase; CMK, 4-(cytidine50-diphospho)-2-C-methyl-D-erythritol kinase; MDS, 2-C-methyl-D-erythritol 2,4-cyclodiphosphate synthase; HDS,1-hydroxy-2-methyl-2-(E)-butenyl-4-diphosphate synthase; and HDR, 1-hydroxy-2-methyl-2-(E)-butenyl-4-diphosphate reductase.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="fpls-12-708697-g009" position="float"/></fig><p>Finally, <italic>CcTIDS3</italic>, <italic>8</italic>, <italic>9</italic>, and <italic>10</italic> were more active in roots compared with stems and leaves, which were confirmed by both transcriptome analysis and qRT-PCR experiments. These novel insights provide the basis for further investigation of the TIDS family in <italic>C. camphora</italic>, and a good foundation from which to develop a metabolic engineering approach to increase production of pharmacologically valuable essential oils from the camphor tree.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec21"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/<xref rid="sec24" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Material</xref>, further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding authors.</p></sec><sec id="sec22"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>ZY conceived, designed, and performed the experiments, analyzed the data, prepared the figures and tables, and authored and reviewed drafts of the paper. CX and LL conceived, designed, and performed the experiments, analyzed the data, and authored and reviewed drafts of the paper. SL, YH, and WA conceived, designed, and performed the experiments, and authored and reviewed drafts of the paper. SH and XZ conceived and designed the experiments, analyzed the data, prepared the figures and tables, and authored and reviewed drafts of the paper. All authors contributed to the article and approved the submitted version.</p></sec><sec sec-type="funding-information" id="sec41"><title>Funding</title><p>This research was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (grant number: 81903741).</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="sec40"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn id="fn0001"><p>
<sup>1</sup>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.arabidopsis.org/index.jsp" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.arabidopsis.org/index.jsp</ext-link>
</p></fn><fn id="fn0002"><p>
<sup>2</sup>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://solgenomics.net/organism/Solanum_lycopersicum/genome/" ext-link-type="uri">https://solgenomics.net/organism/Solanum_lycopersicum/genome/</ext-link>
</p></fn><fn id="fn0003"><p>
<sup>3</sup>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi" ext-link-type="uri">https://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi</ext-link>
</p></fn><fn id="fn0004"><p>
<sup>4</sup>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://web.expasy.org/protparam" ext-link-type="uri">https://web.expasy.org/protparam</ext-link>
</p></fn><fn id="fn0005"><p>
<sup>5</sup>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://meme-suite.org/meme/tools/meme" ext-link-type="uri">https://meme-suite.org/meme/tools/meme</ext-link>
</p></fn><fn id="fn0006"><p>
<sup>6</sup>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/ChloroP/" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/ChloroP/</ext-link>
</p></fn><fn id="fn0007"><p>
<sup>7</sup>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/TargetP/" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/TargetP/</ext-link>
</p></fn><fn id="fn0008"><p>
<sup>8</sup>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://wolfpsort.hgc.jp/" ext-link-type="uri">https://wolfpsort.hgc.jp/</ext-link>
</p></fn><fn id="fn0009"><p>
<sup>9</sup>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.csbio.sjtu.edu.cn/bioinf/plant-multi/" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.csbio.sjtu.edu.cn/bioinf/plant-multi/</ext-link>
</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec24"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpls.2021.708697/full#supplementary-material" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpls.2021.708697/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material id="SM1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abdullah</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Manzoor</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Zinc finger-homeodomain transcriptional factors (ZHDs) in upland cotton (<italic>Gossypium hirsutum</italic>): genome-wide identification and expression analysis in fiber development</article-title>. <source>Front. Genet.</source><volume>9</volume>:<fpage>357</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fgene.2018.00357</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 30356782?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30356782</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adal</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahmoud</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Short-chain isoprenyl diphosphate synthases of lavender (Lavandula)</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>102</volume>, <fpage>517</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>535</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-020-00962-8</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 31927660?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31927660</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akhtar</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuba</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schauvinhold</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lees</surname><given-names>H. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>The tomato cis-prenyltransferase gene family</article-title>. <source>Plant J.</source><volume>73</volume>, <fpage>640</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>652</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.12063</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 23134568?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23134568</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll1">Amborella Genome Project</collab></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>The Amborella genome and the evolution of flowering plants</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>342</volume>:<fpage>1241089</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1241089</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 24357323?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24357323</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll2">Arabidopsis Genome Initiative</collab></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Analysis of the genome sequence of the flowering plant <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>408</volume>, <fpage>796</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>815</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35048692</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 11130711?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11130711</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Athanasakoglou</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grypioti</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Isoprenoid biosynthesis in the diatom Haslea ostrearia</article-title>. <source>New Phytol.</source>
<volume>222</volume>, <fpage>230</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>243</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.15586</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30394540</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishiyama</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasebe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gribskov</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>dePamphilis</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The Selaginella genome identifies genetic changes associated with the evolution of vascular plants</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>332</volume>, <fpage>960</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>963</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1203810</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21551031</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barja</surname><given-names>M. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Concepci&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>A simple in vitro assay to measure the activity of geranylgeranyl diphosphate synthase and other short-chain prenyltransferases</article-title>. <source>Methods Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>2083</volume>, <fpage>27</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-4939-9952-1_2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31745910</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herren</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruiz-Sola</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Concepci&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruissem</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Characterization of the GGPP synthase gene family in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Mol. Biol.</source><volume>82</volume>, <fpage>393</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>416</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-013-0070-z</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 23729351?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23729351</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bouvier</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suire</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>d&#x02019;Harlingue</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Backhaus</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Camara</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Molecular cloning of geranyl diphosphate synthase and compartmentation of monoterpene synthesis in plant cells</article-title>. <source>Plant J.</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>241</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>252</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313x.2000.00875.x</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 11069698?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11069698</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klettke</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Croteau</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Heteromeric geranyl diphosphate synthase from mint: construction of a functional fusion protein and inhibition by bisphosphonate substrate analogs</article-title>. <source>Arch. Biochem. Biophys.</source>
<volume>422</volume>, <fpage>52</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.abb.2003.12.003</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 14725857?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14725857</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Protective effects of angong niuhuang pill on early atherosclerosis in apoE(&#x02212;/&#x02212;) mice by reducing the inflammatory response</article-title>. <source>Evid. Based Complement. Alternat. Med.</source><volume>2019</volume>:<fpage>9747212</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2019/9747212</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 31236126?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31236126</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaw</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>C. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Stout camphor tree genome fills gaps in understanding of flowering plant genome evolution</article-title>. <source>Nat. Plants</source><volume>5</volume>, <fpage>63</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41477-018-0337-0</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 30626928?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30626928</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>H. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2020a</year>). <article-title>TBtools: an integrative toolkit developed for interactive analyses of big biological data</article-title>. <source>Mol. Plant</source><volume>13</volume>, <fpage>1194</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1202</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molp.2020.06.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32585190</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Heteromeric geranyl(geranyl) diphosphate synthase is involved in monoterpene biosynthesis in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flowers</article-title>. <source>Mol. Plant</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>1434</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1437</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molp.2015.05.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25958235</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2020b</year>). <article-title>Metabolomics analysis to evaluate the antibacterial activity of the essential oil from the leaves of <italic>Cinnamomum camphora</italic> (Linn.) Presl</article-title>. <source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>253</volume>:<fpage>112652</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2020.112652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32035880</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z. X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Q. Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Borneol for regulating the permeability of the blood-brain barrier in experimental ischemic stroke: preclinical evidence and possible mechanism</article-title>. <source>Oxidative Med. Cell. Longev.</source><volume>2019</volume>:<fpage>2936737</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2019/2936737</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 30863478?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30863478</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Transcriptome analysis and identification of genes related to terpenoid biosynthesis in <italic>Cinnamomum camphora</italic></article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source><volume>19</volume>:<fpage>550</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-018-4941-1</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 30041601?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30041601</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>K. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>W. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S. Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Systems metabolic engineering strategies: integrating systems and synthetic biology with metabolic engineering</article-title>. <source>Trends Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>37</volume>, <fpage>817</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>837</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tibtech.2019.01.003</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 30737009?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30737009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>H. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Plant-mPLoc: a top-down strategy to augment the power for predicting plant protein subcellular localization</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>e11335</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0011335</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 20596258?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20596258</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Altenhoff</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zoller</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruissem</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vranov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Distinct evolutionary strategies in the GGPPS family from plants</article-title>. <source>Front. Plant Sci.</source>
<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>230</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2014.00230</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 24904625?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24904625</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Genome-wide identification, expression profiles and regulatory network of MAPK cascade gene family in barley</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>
<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>750</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-019-6144-9</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 31623562?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31623562</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dudareva</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murfitt</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorenstein</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolosova</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kish</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Developmental regulation of methyl benzoate biosynthesis and emission in snapdragon flowers</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source><volume>12</volume>, <fpage>949</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>961</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.12.6.949</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 10852939?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10852939</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dudareva</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pichersky</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gershenzon</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Biochemistry of plant volatiles</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol.</source>
<volume>135</volume>, <fpage>1893</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1902</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.104.049981</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15326281</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Emanuelsson</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunak</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>von Heijne</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Predicting subcellular localization of proteins based on their N-terminal amino acid sequence</article-title>. <source>J. Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>300</volume>, <fpage>1005</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1016</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/jmbi.2000.3903</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 10891285?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10891285</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Emanuelsson</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>von Heijne</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>ChloroP, a neural network-based method for predicting chloroplast transit peptides and their cleavage sites</article-title>. <source>Protein Sci.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>978</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>984</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1110/ps.8.5.978</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 10338008?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10338008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Molecular differentiation of five <italic>Cinnamomum camphora</italic> chemotypes using desorption atmospheric pressure chemical ionization mass spectrometry of raw leaves</article-title>. <source>Sci. Rep.</source><volume>7</volume>:<fpage>46579</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep46579</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 28425482?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28425482</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gutensohn</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Orlova</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>T. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidovich-Rikanati</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferruzzi</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sitrit</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Cytosolic monoterpene biosynthesis is supported by plastid-generated geranyl diphosphate substrate in transgenic tomato fruits</article-title>. <source>Plant J.</source><volume>75</volume>, <fpage>351</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>363</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.12212</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 23607888?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23607888</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hivert</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidovich-Rikanati</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bar</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sitrit</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaffer</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudareva</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Prenyltransferases catalyzing geranyldiphosphate formation in tomato fruit</article-title>. <source>Plant Sci.</source><volume>296</volume>:<fpage>110504</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plantsci.2020.110504</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 32540020?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32540020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horton</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Obayashi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams-Collier</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>WoLF PSORT: protein localization predictor</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>35</volume>, <fpage>W585</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>W587</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm259</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 17517783?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17517783</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hsiao</surname><given-names>Y. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeng</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>W. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chuang</surname><given-names>Y. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>T. S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>A novel homodimeric geranyl diphosphate synthase from the orchid <italic>Phalaenopsis bellina</italic> lacking a DD(X)2-4D motif</article-title>. <source>Plant J.</source><volume>55</volume>, <fpage>719</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>733</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2008.03547.x</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 18466308?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18466308</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>F. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>T. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>T. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Structure and mechanism of an <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> medium/long-chain-length prenyl pyrophosphate synthase</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol.</source>
<volume>155</volume>, <fpage>1079</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1090</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.110.168799</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 21220764?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21220764</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Clinical therapeutic effects of aspirin in combination with fufang danshen diwan, a traditional chinese medicine formula, on coronary heart disease: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Cell. Physiol. Biochem.</source>
<volume>39</volume>, <fpage>1955</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1963</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000447892</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 27771711?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27771711</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Catalytic functions of the isoprenyl diphosphate synthase superfamily in plants: a growing repertoire</article-title>. <source>Mol. Plant</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>189</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>191</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molp.2015.12.020</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 26751961?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26751961</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peluso</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stitzer</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Improved maize reference genome with single-molecule technologies</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>546</volume>, <fpage>524</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>527</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature22971</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 28605751?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28605751</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhat</surname><given-names>W. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Promiscuous terpene synthases from <italic>Prunella vulgaris</italic> highlight the importance of substrate and compartment switching in terpene synthase evolution</article-title>. <source>New Phytol.</source>
<volume>223</volume>, <fpage>323</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>335</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.15778</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 30843212?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30843212</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhat</surname><given-names>W. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bibik</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turmo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamberger</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Evolutionary Mint Genomics</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>A database-driven approach identifies additional diterpene synthase activities in the mint family (Lamiaceae)</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><volume>294</volume>, <fpage>1349</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1362</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.RA118.006025</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 30498089?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30498089</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kopcsayov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vranov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Functional gene network of prenyltransferases in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Molecules</source>
<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>4556</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules24244556</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 31842481?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31842481</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>MEGA7: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis version 7.0 for bigger datasets</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source>
<volume>33</volume>, <fpage>1870</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1874</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msw054</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 27004904?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27004904</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lescot</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x000e9;hais</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thijs</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchal</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreau</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van de Peer</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>PlantCARE, a database of plant cis-acting regulatory elements and a portal to tools for in silico analysis of promoter sequences</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>30</volume>, <fpage>325</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>327</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/30.1.325</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 11752327?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11752327</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>W. U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Identification and characterization of the CONSTANS-like gene family and its expression profiling under light treatment in <italic>Populus</italic></article-title>. <source>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</source><volume>161</volume>, <fpage>999</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1010</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2020.06.056</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 32531358?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32531358</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mutanda</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Chloroplastic metabolic engineering coupled with isoprenoid pool enhancement for committed taxanes biosynthesis in <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic></article-title>. <source>Nat. Commun.</source>
<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>4850</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-019-12879-y</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 31649252?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31649252</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>P. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>T. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Structure, mechanism and function of prenyltransferases</article-title>. <source>Eur. J. Biochem.</source>
<volume>269</volume>, <fpage>3339</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3354</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1432-1033.2002.03014.x</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 12135472?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12135472</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S. Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Suppression of MIF-induced neuronal apoptosis may underlie the therapeutic effects of effective components of Fufang Danshen in the treatment of Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source>Acta Pharmacol. Sin.</source>
<volume>39</volume>, <fpage>1421</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1438</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/aps.2017.210</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 29770796?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29770796</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2021</year>). <article-title>Molecular cloning and functional identification of a high-efficiency (+)-borneol dehydrogenase from <italic>Cinnamomum camphora</italic> (L.) Presl</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol. Biochem.</source><volume>158</volume>, <fpage>363</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>371</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plaphy.2020.11.023</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 33243711?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33243711</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Magnard</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roccia</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Caissard</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vergne</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hecquet</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Plant volatiles. Biosynthesis of monoterpene scent compounds in roses</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>349</volume>, <fpage>81</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>83</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aab0696</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 26138978?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26138978</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>G. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhat</surname><given-names>W. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>The biosynthesis of the anti-microbial diterpenoid leubethanol in <italic>Leucophyllum frutescens</italic> proceeds via an all-cis prenyl intermediate</article-title>. <source>Plant J.</source>
<volume>104</volume>, <fpage>693</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>705</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.14957</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 32777127?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32777127</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagel</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernholz</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vranov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ko&#x00161;uth</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergau</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ludwig</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2015</year>). <article-title><italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> isoprenyl diphosphate synthases produce the C25 intermediate geranylfarnesyl diphosphate</article-title>. <source>Plant J.</source><volume>84</volume>, <fpage>847</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>859</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.13064</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 26505977?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26505977</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nystedt</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Street</surname><given-names>N. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wetterbom</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zuccolo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scofield</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>The Norway spruce genome sequence and conifer genome evolution</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>497</volume>, <fpage>579</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>584</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature12211</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 23698360?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23698360</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pichersky</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Noel</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudareva</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Biosynthesis of plant volatiles: nature's diversity and ingenuity</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>311</volume>, <fpage>808</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>811</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1118510</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 16469917?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16469917</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rai</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smita</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shanker</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagegowda</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Heteromeric and homomeric geranyl diphosphate synthases from <italic>Catharanthus roseus</italic> and their role in monoterpene indole alkaloid biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Mol. Plant</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>1531</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1549</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/mp/sst058</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 23543438?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23543438</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Efficacy of suxiao jiuxin pill on coronary heart disease: a meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials</article-title>. <source>Evid. Based Complement. Alternat. Med.</source>
<volume>2018</volume>:<fpage>9745804</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2018/9745804</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 29770157?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29770157</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rensing</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmer</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Terry</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salamov</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The Physcomitrella genome reveals evolutionary insights into the conquest of land by plants</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>319</volume>, <fpage>64</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>69</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1150646</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 18079367?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18079367</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gershenzon</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Cloning and characterization of two different types of geranyl diphosphate synthases from Norway spruce (Picea abies)</article-title>. <source>Phytochemistry</source>
<volume>69</volume>, <fpage>49</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>57</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2007.06.022</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 17673268?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17673268</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Analysis of the role of geranylgeranyl diphosphate synthase 8 from Tripterygium wilfordii in diterpenoids biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Plant Sci.</source><volume>285</volume>, <fpage>184</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>192</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plantsci.2019.05.013</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 31203883?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31203883</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Subramanian</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lercher</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W.-H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Evolview v3: a webserver for visualization, annotation, and management of phylogenetic trees</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<volume>47</volume>, <fpage>W270</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>W275</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkz357</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 31114888?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31114888</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tholl</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Terpene specialized metabolism in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Arabidopsis Book</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e0143</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1199/tab.0143</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 22303268?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22303268</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll3">Tomato Genome Consortium</collab></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>The tomato genome sequence provides insights into fleshy fruit evolution</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>485</volume>, <fpage>635</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>641</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11119</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 22660326?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22660326</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ueoka</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyawaki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichino</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tatsumi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>A cytosol-localized geranyl diphosphate synthase from <italic>Lithospermum erythrorhizon</italic> and its molecular evolution</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol.</source><volume>182</volume>, <fpage>1933</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1945</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.19.00999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31974127</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vandermoten</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haubruge</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cusson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>New insights into short-chain prenyltransferases: structural features, evolutionary history and potential for selective inhibition</article-title>. <source>Cell. Mol. Life Sci.</source>
<volume>66</volume>, <fpage>3685</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3695</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00018-009-0100-9</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 19633972?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19633972</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Structural analyses of short-chain prenyltransferases identify an evolutionarily conserved GFPPS clade in brassicaceae plants</article-title>. <source>Mol. Plant</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>195</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>204</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molp.2015.10.010</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 26537048?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26537048</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Heterodimeric geranyl(geranyl)diphosphate synthase from hop (<italic>Humulus lupulus</italic>) and the evolution of monoterpene biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</source>
<volume>106</volume>, <fpage>9914</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9919</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0904069106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19482937</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H. X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Molecular cloning and functional characterization of multiple geranylgeranyl pyrophosphate synthases (ApGGPPS) from <italic>Andrographis paniculata</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Rep.</source><volume>38</volume>, <fpage>117</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>128</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00299-018-2353-y</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 30448883?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30448883</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>An integrative volatile terpenoid profiling and transcriptomics analysis for gene mining and functional characterization of AvBPPS and AvPS involved in the monoterpenoid biosynthesis in amomum villosum</article-title>. <source>Front. Plant Sci.</source><volume>9</volume>:<fpage>846</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2018.00846</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 29973947?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29973947</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wijfjes</surname><given-names>R. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smit</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Hecaton: reliably detecting copy number variation in plant genomes using short read sequencing data</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>
<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>818</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-019-6153-8</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 31699036?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31699036</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>W. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yap</surname><given-names>C. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisenhaber</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisenhaber</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>dissectHMMER: a HMMER-based score dissection framework that statistically evaluates fold-critical sequence segments for domain fold similarity</article-title>. <source>Biol. Direct</source>
<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>39</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13062-015-0068-3</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 26228544?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26228544</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>An</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Mining of candidate genes involved in the biosynthesis of dextrorotatory borneol in <italic>Cinnamomum burmannii</italic> by transcriptomic analysis on three chemotypes</article-title>. <source>PeerJ</source><volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e9311</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.9311</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 32566406?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32566406</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tie</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>The MAPKKK gene family in cassava: genome-wide identification and expression analysis against drought stress</article-title>. <source>Sci. Rep.</source><volume>7</volume>:<fpage>14939</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-13988-8</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 29097722?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29097722</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>W. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>I. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>N. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Co-expression of peppermint geranyl diphosphate synthase small subunit enhances monoterpene production in transgenic tobacco plants</article-title>. <source>New Phytol.</source>
<volume>213</volume>, <fpage>1133</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1144</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.14280</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 28079933?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28079933</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref70"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>Y. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Arabidopsis mesophyll protoplasts: a versatile cell system for transient gene expression analysis</article-title>. <source>Nat. Protoc.</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>1565</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1572</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2007.199</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 17585298?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17585298</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref71"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>G. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>A draft sequence of the rice genome (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L. ssp. indica)</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>296</volume>, <fpage>79</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>92</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1068037</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 11935017?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11935017</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref72"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Extraction of <italic>Cinnamomum camphora</italic> chvar. Borneol essential oil using neutral cellulase assisted-steam distillation: optimization of extraction, and analysis of chemical constituents</article-title>. <source>Ind. Crop. Prod.</source><volume>141</volume>:<fpage>111794</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2019.111794</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref73"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pichersky</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>The complete functional characterisation of the terpene synthase family in tomato</article-title>. <source>New Phytol.</source>
<volume>226</volume>, <fpage>1341</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1360</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.16431</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 31943222?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31943222</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref74"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>D.-N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.-L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Identification of the bHLH gene family in <italic>Dracaena cambodiana</italic> reveals candidate genes involved in flavonoid biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Ind. Crop. Prod.</source><volume>150</volume>:<fpage>112407</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2020.112407</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>