<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Hortic Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Hortic Res</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Horticulture Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2052-7276</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6246602</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30479779</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">108</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41438-018-0108-0</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The chromosome-level quality genome provides insights into the evolution of the biosynthesis genes for aroma compounds of <italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Xiulian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>Yuanzheng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Haiyan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Wenjie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Gongwei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Tingting</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Junhao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Min S.</given-names></name><address><email>minsungpark@grandomics.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Fei</given-names></name><address><email>frank@fafu.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Lianggui</given-names></name><address><email>wlg@njfu.com.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.410625.4</institution-id><institution>Co-Innovation Center for Sustainable Forestry in Southern China, </institution><institution>Nanjing Forestry University, </institution></institution-wrap>Nanjing, China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.410625.4</institution-id><institution>College of Landscape Architecture, </institution><institution>Nanjing Forestry University, </institution></institution-wrap>Nanjing, China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1760 2876</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.256111.0</institution-id><institution>State Key Laboratory of Ecological Pest Control for Fujian and Taiwan Crops, </institution><institution>Fujian Agriculture and Forestry University, </institution></institution-wrap>Fuzhou, China </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Nextomics Bioscience Institute, Wuhan, China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>20</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>72</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>12</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Sweet osmanthus (<italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic>) is a very popular ornamental tree species throughout Southeast Asia and USA particularly for its extremely fragrant aroma. We constructed a chromosome-level reference genome of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>fragrans</italic> to assist in studies of the evolution, genetic diversity, and molecular mechanism of aroma development. A total of over 118&#x02009;Gb of polished reads was produced from HiSeq (45.1&#x02009;Gb) and PacBio Sequel (73.35&#x02009;Gb), giving 100&#x000d7; depth coverage for long reads. The combination of Illumina-short reads, PacBio-long reads, and Hi-C data produced the final chromosome quality genome of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>fragrans</italic> with a genome size of 727&#x02009;Mb and a heterozygosity of 1.45 %. The genome was annotated using de novo and homology comparison and further refined with transcriptome data. The genome of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>fragrans</italic> was predicted to have&#x02009;45,542 genes, of which 95.68&#x000a0;% were functionally annotated. Genome annotation found 49.35&#x000a0;% as the repetitive sequences, with long terminal repeats (LTR) being the richest (28.94&#x000a0;%). Genome evolution analysis indicated the evidence of whole-genome duplication 15 million years ago, which contributed to the current content of 45,242 genes. Metabolic analysis revealed that linalool, a monoterpene is the main aroma compound. Based on the genome and transcriptome, we further demonstrated the direct connection between terpene synthases (TPSs) and the rich aromatic molecules in <italic>O</italic>. <italic>fragrans</italic>. We identified three new flower-specific <italic>TPS</italic> genes, of which the expression coincided with the production of linalool. Our results suggest that the high number of <italic>TPS</italic> genes and the flower tissue- and stage-specific <italic>TPS</italic> genes expressions might drive the strong unique aroma production of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>fragrans</italic>.</p></abstract><abstract id="Abs2" abstract-type="LongSummary"><title>Genome sequences: Discovering a sweet secret</title><p id="Par211">A high-quality genome sequence for sweet olive, <italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic>, has revealed which genes make the ornamental tree&#x02019;s blossoms so fragrant. Lianggui Wang at Nanjing Forestry University in China and coworkers used cutting-edge approaches to produce a high-resolution picture of sweet olive&#x02019;s genome. Analysis of the full sequence revealed that sweet olive has a large number of genes, more than 45,000. Further investigation showed that the entire genome had been duplicated, or accidentally copied, several million years ago. Thanks to the duplication, sweet olive has extra copies of the genes that produce its scent compound, resulting in its very strong scent. These results are only the beginning. Having this first sequence makes sequencing other varieties of sweet olive much easier, and future comparisons between genomes will help to pinpoint genes that control many other traits.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Genome duplication</kwd><kwd>Genome assembly algorithms</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100001809</institution-id><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China (National Science Foundation of China)</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>31601785</award-id><award-id>31870695</award-id><award-id>31601785</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Xiulian</given-names></name><name><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>Yuanzheng</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Haiyan</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>the Project of Key Research and Development Plan (Modern Agriculture) in Jiangsu (BE2017375), the Selection and Breeding of Excellent Tree Species and Effective Cultivation Techniques (CX(16)1005), the Project of Osmanthus National Germplasm Bank, the Top-notch Academic Programs Project of Jiangsu Higher Education Institutions.</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Sweet osmanthus (Dicotyledons, Lamiales, Oleaceae, <italic>Osmanthus</italic>) is one of the most popular, evergreen ornamental tree species in China due to its unique sweet aroma<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. More than 160 cultivars of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>fragrans</italic> have been classified based on phenotypes such as the leaf shape, flower color, aroma, season and frequency of flower blooming<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. The association between phenotypes and genotypes of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>fragrans</italic> has been examined through aroma compounds<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>, essential oils<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>, and taxonomy using various molecular markers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. Transcriptome studies have determined the genes that might be responsible for the emission of flower scent in <italic>O. fragrans</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. Gene expression has also been modulated at different flowering stages of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>fragrans</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Differential gene expression studies have identified genes in the mediated isopentenol production (MEP) pathway, as well as the terpenoid- and carotenoid-synthesis pathways. Transcriptomics studies allowed researchers to make connections between the major flower aroma compounds, and differentially expressed genes and encoded proteins. The flower aroma compounds, (<italic>R</italic>)- and (<italic>S</italic>)-linanool are produced by a terpene synthase(s) (TPS)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. Another key flower aroma compound, <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-ionone, is produced through the oxidative cleavage of <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-carotene by carotenoid cleavage enzymes (CCD)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. Transcriptome studies have shown that TPS(s) and CCD(s) are differentially expressed at different flowering stages in <italic>O. fragrans</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. Additionally, we and others have recently reported a set of transcription factors (TFs) associated with the expression of color and the emission of fragrance in <italic>O. fragrans</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. All of these gene expression studies provide valuable insights on how flower blooming and aroma production are interlinked<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. However, a genome sequence is largely needed to reveal the full genetic background of aroma production in sweet osmanthus and the evolution of aroma in the family Oleaceae.</p><p id="Par3">In this study, we generated a reference genome for <italic>O. fragrans</italic> to provide a solid foundation for our future understanding of the genome structure and evolution of the Oleaceae family. Furthermore, we conducted a detailed analysis of the aroma compounds, tissue and flowering time-specific differential gene expression to investigate the molecular mechanisms of sweet fragrance development in <italic>O. fragrans</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Sequencing summary</title><p id="Par4">We generated 100-fold PacBio single-molecule long reads (a total of 73.4&#x02009;Gb with an N50 length of 13.0&#x02009;kb), 77-fold <italic>k</italic>-mer depth Illumina paired-end short reads (45.1&#x02009;Gb) and Hi-C data that produced 23 unambiguous chromosome scaffolds for a high-quality assembly. For stepwise assembly, we first performed an initial PacBio-only assembly, resulting in an assembly size of 733.5&#x02009;Mb and a contig N50 of 1.59&#x02009;Mb, and the assembled genome had a highly complete BUSCOs (96.1 %) (Supplemental Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). Then, the initial contigs were subsequently polished with PacBio long reads and Illumina short reads. As the final step, Hi-C data were used to polish the scaffolds generated by the PacBio and Illumina reads.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Determination of genome size and heterozygosity</title><p id="Par5">The <italic>k</italic>-mer method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup> and KmerFreqAR<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup> were used to determine the genome size of <italic>O. fragrans</italic> using the quality-filtered reads of Illumina data. The genome size was estimated based on the formula: Genome size&#x02009;=&#x02009;Modified <italic>k</italic>-mer number/average <italic>k</italic>-mer depth, where modified <italic>k</italic>-mer&#x02009;=&#x02009;Total <italic>k</italic>-mer number&#x02212;error <italic>k</italic>-mer number and the average <italic>k</italic>-mer depth obtained from the main peak of <italic>k</italic>-mer distribution curve (Supplemental Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). To determine the heterozygosity, <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> genome data were used to simulate Illumina PE reads, which was carried out by using pIRS software<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. Then, a fitting KmerFreqAR<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup> was developed using the <italic>k</italic>-mer distribution curve of <italic>O. fragrans</italic>. When the two <italic>k</italic>-mer curves were consistent, the heterozygosity of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> was considered the reference for the heterozygosity of <italic>O. fragrans</italic>. The final analysis produced ~1.45% heterozygosity of the <italic>O. fragrans</italic> genome.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Genome assembly and quality assessment</title><p id="Par6">The integrated work-flow of genome assembly is shown (Supplemental Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>). The full PacBio long reads were converted to fasta format. Then, all subreads of genome data were assembled using Falcon v0.3.0<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup> with specific parameters (length-cutoff pr&#x02009;=&#x02009;8&#x02009;kb; length-cutoff pr&#x02009;=&#x02009;9&#x02009;kb). We used Arrow (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com">https://github.com</ext-link>) to polish the draft genome (G1) to obtain the corrected genome (G2). Then, G2 was polished again by Pilon<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>, which mapped the next-generation sequencing data to G2 with bwa to obtain the twice-corrected genome (G3). The <italic>O. fragrans</italic> genome had high heterozygosity, which led to a G3 size larger than the estimation. To acquire the nonredundant genome, heterozygous and redundant sequences were removed from the corrected genome using Redundans<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup> with the following parameters: heterozygosity&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0145 and Sequencing Depth&#x02009;=&#x02009;86. The nonredundant genome (G4) was ~741&#x02009;Mb, with a contig N50 size of 1.595&#x02009;Mb (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Finally, BUSCO v3.0 analysis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup> was performed to assess G4 using the embryophyta_odb10 database with default parameters.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Quality assessment statistics of the assembled genome of <italic>O. fragrans</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Stat type</th><th>Contig length</th><th>Contig number</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>N50</td><td>1,595,720</td><td>145</td></tr><tr><td>Longest</td><td>8,253,028</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td>740,635,307</td><td>774</td></tr><tr><td>Length&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;5&#x02009;kb</td><td>740,625,951</td><td>765</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par7">The clustering of contig by hierarchical clustering of the Hi-C data was performed. Through a comparative analysis, the only pair of reads around the DpnII digestion site was determined. Hi-C linkage was used as a criterion to measure the degree of tightness of the association between different contigs by standardizing the digestion sites of DpnII on the genome sketch. Agglomerative hierarchical clustering and LACHESIS produced chromosome assembly maps with a karyotype of 2<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;46 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). As a result, the total number of contigs of the <italic>O. fragrans</italic> genome map was 5327, and the total length was 740,635,307&#x02009;bp. The combined length of Hi-C contigs was 740,404,543&#x02009;bp, accounted for 99.97&#x000a0;% of the total length of the final assembled genome, indicating the high quality of Hi-C data (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Hi-C map of the O. fragrans genome showing genome-wide all-by-all interactions.</title><p>The map shows a high resolution of individual chromosomes that are scaffolded and assembled independently</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41438_2018_108_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e725"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Summary statistics demonstrating the high quality of the Hi-C map of <italic>O. fragrans</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Sample</th><th>
<italic>O. fragrans</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Draft contig total number</td><td>5327</td></tr><tr><td>Draft contig total length</td><td>740,635,307</td></tr><tr><td>Final contig number</td><td>5305</td></tr><tr><td>Final contig total length</td><td>740,404,543</td></tr><tr><td>Contig coverage on full genome (%)</td><td>99.97</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Annotation of repeat sequences</title><p id="Par8">The genome of <italic>O. fragrans</italic> had simply, moderately, and highly repetitive sequences. MIcroSAtellite was used to identify the repeat sequences in the genome of <italic>O. fragrans</italic> (MISA, RRID: SCR 010765). A total of 409,691 SSRs was obtained, including 305,868 mono-, 70,587 di-, 25,544 tri-, 3934 tetra-, 2081 penta-, and 1991 hexa-nucleotide repeats, respectively (Supplemental Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>). The tandem repeats finder (TRF, v4.07b)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup> identified over 400,000 tandem repeats, accounting for 0.076&#x000a0;% of the <italic>O</italic>. <italic>fragrans</italic> genome.</p><p id="Par9">We used homology-based and de novo approaches to identify transposable elements. RepeatMasker<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup> was used to search against the Repbase (v. 22.11)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup> and Mips-REdat libraries<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>. Then, we used RepeatMasker v4.0.6 to search the de novo repeat library that we built using RepeatModeler v1.0.11 (RepeatModeler, RRID: SCR 015027). Finally, TEs were confirmed by searching the TE protein database using a RepeatProteinMask and WU-BLASTX. The repetitive sequence was 49.35&#x000a0;%, of which LTR accounted for 28.49&#x000a0;% of the assembled genome of <italic>O. fragrans</italic> (Supplemental Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Annotation of noncoding RNA (ncRNA)</title><p id="Par10">We identified rRNA, miRNA, and snRNA genes in the <italic>O</italic>. <italic>fragrans</italic> genome by searching the Rfam database (release 13.0)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>, using BLASTN<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup> (<italic>E</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;1e&#x02212;5). Software tRNAscan-SE (v1.3.1)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup> and RNAmmer v1.2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup> were used to predict tRNAs and rRNAs, resulting in an <italic>O</italic>. <italic>frangrans</italic> genome with 525 miRNAs, 847 tRNAs, 49 rRNAs, and 2058 snRNAs (Supplemental Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Gene prediction</title><p id="Par11">The protein-coding genes were identified using homology-based and de novo predictions-based approaches. The <italic>O. fragrans</italic> genome was mapped against the published sequences of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, <italic>Olea europaea</italic>, <italic>Sesamum indicum</italic>, <italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic>, and <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic>. To accurately identify spliced alignments, we used GeneWise v2.2.0<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup> to filter all initially aligned coding sequences. For de novo prediction, the data from NGS and the full-length transcriptomes were analyzed with hisat2-2.1.0 and PASApipeline-2.0.2 to predict the complete gene set. We randomly selected 1000 genes to train the model parameters for Augustus v3.3<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>, GeneID v1.4.4<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>, GlimmerHMM<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>, and SNAP<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. The final consensus gene set was generatedusing EVidenceModeler (EVM) v1.1.1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>, which combined the genes predicted by the de novo and homology searches<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup> The assembled genome had 45,542 genes with an average transcript length of 4065&#x02009;bp, an average CDS length of 1142&#x02009;bp, and a number of exons per gene of 5 (Supplemental Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref>).</p><p id="Par12">The functional validity of the predicted genes was further evaluated by searching the UniProt (release 2017_10), KEGG (release 84.0), and InterPro (5.21-60.0) databases using Blastall44, KAAS,49, and InterProScan50. As a result, we were able to assign potential functions to 43,573 protein-coding genes out of the total of 45,542 genes in the <italic>O</italic>. <italic>fragrans</italic> genome (95.68&#x000a0;%) (Supplemental Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">7</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Genome evolution</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>Gene family analysis</title><p id="Par13">Although morphological investigation and a number of genes have placed <italic>O</italic>. <italic>fragrans</italic> in the Oleaceae family, there is still no whole genome-scale phylogenomic analysis of the evolutionary position of <italic>O. fragrans</italic>. Here, we compared the <italic>O. fragrans</italic> genome with the genome sequences of 11 other plants (<italic>A. thaliana, Fraxinus excelsior, Glycine max, O. europaea, Oryza sativa, Petunia axillaris, Petunia inflata, Prunus mume, Rosa chinensis, Solanum lycopersicum</italic>, and <italic>V</italic>. <italic>vinifera)</italic>. We applied the OrthoMCL (v2.0.9) pipeline<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup> (BLASTP <italic>E</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;1e&#x02212;5) to identify the potential orthologous gene families between the genomes of these plants. Gene family clustering identified 17,513 gene families consisting of 38,808 genes in <italic>O</italic>. <italic>fragrans</italic>, of which, 1086 gene families were unique to <italic>O</italic>. <italic>fragrans</italic>. <italic>O</italic>. <italic>europaea</italic>, and <italic>F</italic>. <italic>excelsior</italic> had the biggest number of shared gene families among these plants (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Species tree and evolution of gene numbers.</title><p><bold>a</bold> The phylogenetic tree showing the close relationship between sweet osmanthus and the wild olive (<italic>O</italic>. <italic>europaea</italic>). <bold>b</bold> The number of genes in various plant species, showing the high gene number of <italic>O. fragrans</italic> compared to a model (<italic>A</italic>. <italic>thaliana</italic>) and other tree species. The number of multiple copy paralogs is high in <italic>O. fragrans</italic></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41438_2018_108_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e1042"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Synteny analysis</title><p id="Par14">We used the protein sequences of <italic>O. fragrans</italic> that were aligned against each other with Blastp (<italic>E</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;1e&#x02212;5) to achieve the conserved paralogs, Then, MCScanX (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://chibba.pgml.uga.edu/mcscab2">http://chibba.pgml.uga.edu/mcscab2</ext-link>) was used to find the collinearity block in the genome. Using the Circos tool (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.circos.ca">http://www.circos.ca</ext-link>), we mapped and gene density, GC content, Gypsy density, and Copia density, as well as the average expression value of genes expressed in flowers on individual chromosomes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>High-quality assembly of twenty-three chromosomes.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Gene density, <bold>b</bold> GC content, <bold>c</bold> Gypsy density, <bold>d</bold> Copia density, and <bold>e</bold> average expression values of genes specifically expressed in flowers (from outside to inside)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41438_2018_108_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e1092"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Whole-genome duplication (WGD)</title><p id="Par15">To determine the source of the high number of genes (&#x0003e;45,000) in <italic>O. fragrans</italic>, the WGD events were analyzed by taking advantage of the high-quality genome of <italic>O. fragrans</italic>. We applied four-fold synonymous third-codon transversion (4DTv) and synonymous substitution rate (Ks) estimation to detect the WGD events. First, respective paralogous of <italic>O. fragrans</italic>, <italic>G. max</italic>, <italic>O</italic>. <italic>europaea</italic>, <italic>V</italic>. <italic>vinifera</italic>, and <italic>A</italic>. <italic>thaliana</italic> were identified with OrthoMCL. Then, the protein sequences of these plants were aligned against each other with Blastp (<italic>E</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;1e&#x02212;5) to achieve the conserved paralogs of each plant. Finally, the WGD events of each plant were evaluated based on their 4DTv (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>) or Ks (data not shown) distribution. The WGD analysis suggestted that <italic>O</italic>. <italic>fragrans</italic>, <italic>G</italic>. <italic>max</italic> and <italic>O</italic>. <italic>europaea</italic> experienced WGD events within less than 15 MYA, but <italic>V</italic>. <italic>vinifer</italic> and <italic>A</italic>. <italic>thaliana</italic> have not experienced WGD events recently (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>). We also compared the number of duplicated genes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b</xref>), the chromosome-level duplications (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4c</xref>), and the number of a functional homologs of glycotransferase and bHLH-Myc transcription factor genes between <italic>O</italic>. <italic>fragrans</italic> and <italic>V</italic>. <italic>vinifera</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4d</xref>), further validating the WGD events.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>Evidences for whole-genome duplication events in O. fragrans.</title><p><bold>a</bold> 4DTV; <bold>b</bold> the most abundant genes (red bar: duplicated genes, green: non-duplicated, 0: tandem-duplicated or small-scale-duplicated genes; 0&#x02013;12, number of duplicated copies) in a four-fold relationship when comparing <italic>O. fragrans</italic> and grapes. <bold>c</bold> A colinear relationship at the chromosome level. <bold>d</bold> Four-fold expansion of the functional homologs of glycosyltransferase and bHLH-MYC genes in grape (GSVIVT) and <italic>O. frgrans</italic> (evm.model.Contig). The data suggest that <italic>O. fragrans</italic> experienced two WGD events</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41438_2018_108_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e1224"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Determination of volatile aroma compounds</title><p id="Par17">To make a direct connection between the biosynthetic genes and flower fragrance development, we determined the volatile aroma compounds. Headspace-SPME combined with GC-MS analysis identified over 40 volatile compounds, including linalool, dihydrojasmone lactone (2(3H)-furanone, 5-hexyldihydro-), 1-cyclohexene-1-propanol, 2,6,6-tetramethyl-, and <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-ocimen as the major components. Linalool was present in the highest amount at the early flowering stage (S1) and decreased afterwards (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Identity and quantity of volatile aroma compounds in the various flowering stages of <italic>O. fragrans</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Fragrance_molecules</th><th>S1(A)</th><th><italic>P</italic>-value(A&#x00026;B)</th><th>S2(B)</th><th><italic>P</italic>-value(B&#x00026;C)</th><th>S3(C)</th><th><italic>P</italic>-value(A&#x00026;C)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Linalool</td><td>6.67&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.63</td><td>0.001</td><td>2.91&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2</td><td>0.007</td><td>0.22&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.15</td><td>0.000</td></tr><tr><td>2(3&#x02009;H)-Furanone, 5-hexyldihydro-</td><td>2.58&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.62</td><td>0.000</td><td>1.29&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.28</td><td>0.000</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>0.000</td></tr><tr><td>1-Cyclohexene-1-propanol, &#x000e0;,2,6,6-tetramethyl-</td><td>2.29&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.63</td><td>0.000</td><td>0.01&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td>0.975</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>0.000</td></tr><tr><td>&#x003b2;-Ocimene</td><td>1.28&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.42</td><td>0.002</td><td>0.68&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.26</td><td>0.001</td><td>0.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02</td><td>0.000</td></tr><tr><td>2-Furanmethanol, 5-ethenyltetrahydro-&#x003b1;,&#x003b1;,5-trimethyl-, cis-</td><td>1.25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.58</td><td>0.213</td><td>0.82&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.21</td><td>0.010</td><td>1.79&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.77</td><td>0.123</td></tr><tr><td>trans-Linalool oxide (furanoid)</td><td>1.18&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.57</td><td>0.296</td><td>0.78&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.25</td><td>0.001</td><td>2.34&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.91</td><td>0.007</td></tr><tr><td>(3&#x02009;R,6&#x02009;S)-2,2,6-Trimethyl-6-vinyltetrahydro-2H-pyran-3-ol</td><td>0.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.26</td><td>0.050</td><td>0.41&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.11</td><td>0.003</td><td>0.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.29</td><td>0.162</td></tr><tr><td>&#x003b1;-Ionone</td><td>0.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.18</td><td>0.000</td><td>0.18&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1</td><td>0.448</td><td>0.13&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04</td><td>0.000</td></tr><tr><td>2-Butanone, 4-(2,2-dimethyl-6-methylenecyclohexyl)-</td><td>0.37&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.13</td><td>0.000</td><td>0.01&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0</td><td>1.000</td><td>0.01&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0</td><td>0.000</td></tr><tr><td>(3&#x02009;R,6&#x02009;R)-2,2,6-Trimethyl-6-vinyltetrahydro-2H-pyran-3-ol</td><td>0.35&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.13</td><td>0.038</td><td>0.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.05</td><td>0.000</td><td>0.51&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.15</td><td>0.033</td></tr><tr><td>2H-Pyran-3(4&#x02009;H)-one, 6-ethenyldihydro-2,2,6-trimethyl-</td><td>0.33&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.11</td><td>0.276</td><td>0.22&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.06</td><td>0.052</td><td>0.43&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.28</td><td>0.342</td></tr><tr><td>Butanoic acid, 3-hexenyl ester, (E)-</td><td>0.14&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.05</td><td>0.284</td><td>0.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.07</td><td>0.891</td><td>0.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.06</td><td>0.346</td></tr><tr><td>2,4,6-Octatriene, 2,6-dimethyl-, (E,E)-</td><td>0.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03</td><td>0.055</td><td>0.06&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02</td><td>0.253</td><td>0.08&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04</td><td>0.387</td></tr><tr><td>Methyl salicylate</td><td>0.08&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.08</td><td>0.881</td><td>0.07&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.06</td><td>0.046</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>0.034</td></tr><tr><td>NA1</td><td>0.08&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03</td><td>0.016</td><td>0.05&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02</td><td>0.002</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>0.000</td></tr><tr><td>3-Buten-2-one, 4-(2,6,6-trimethyl-1-cyclohexen-1-yl)-</td><td>0.06&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02</td><td>0.000</td><td>1.18&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.58</td><td>0.892</td><td>1.15&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.28</td><td>0.000</td></tr><tr><td>NA3</td><td>0.06&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td>0.002</td><td>0.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02</td><td>0.000</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>0.000</td></tr><tr><td>3-Hexen-1-ol, acetate, (Z)-</td><td>0.05&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03</td><td>0.899</td><td>0.04&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04</td><td>0.003</td><td>0.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.31</td><td>0.004</td></tr><tr><td>cis-3-Hexenyl isovalerate</td><td>0.05&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02</td><td>0.224</td><td>0.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02</td><td>0.030</td><td>0.06&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02</td><td>0.278</td></tr><tr><td>trans-&#x003b2;-Ocimene</td><td>0.05&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td>0.002</td><td>0.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td>0.000</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>0.000</td></tr><tr><td>Methyl isovalerate</td><td>0.04&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03</td><td>0.376</td><td>0.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td>0.898</td><td>0.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02</td><td>0.314</td></tr><tr><td>(E)-4,8-Dimethylnona-1,3,7-triene</td><td>0.04&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02</td><td>0.046</td><td>0.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0</td><td>0.011</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>0.000</td></tr><tr><td>Hexanoic acid, methyl ester</td><td>0.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02</td><td>1.000</td><td>0.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td>0.011</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>0.011</td></tr><tr><td>cis-3-Hexenyl-&#x003b1;-methylbutyrate</td><td>0.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td>0.091</td><td>0.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td>0.091</td><td>0.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td>1.000</td></tr><tr><td>3-Buten-2-ol, 4-(2,6,6-trimethyl-2-cyclohexen-1-yl)-, (3E)-</td><td>0.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td>0.000</td><td>0.01&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td>0.119</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>0.000</td></tr><tr><td>Octanoic acid, methyl ester</td><td>0.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td>0.121</td><td>0.01&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0</td><td>0.592</td><td>0.01&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td>0.045</td></tr><tr><td>Tridecane</td><td>0.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td>0.015</td><td>0.01&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0</td><td>0.291</td><td>0.01&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td>0.121</td></tr><tr><td>trans-&#x003b2;-Ionone</td><td>0.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td>0.015</td><td>0.01&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0</td><td>0.000</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>0.000</td></tr><tr><td>Megastigma-4,6(Z),8(E)-triene</td><td>0.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td>0.000</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>1.000</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>0.000</td></tr><tr><td>2-Butanone, 4-(2,6,6-trimethyl-1-cyclohexen-1-yl)-</td><td>0.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td>0.010</td><td>0.28&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.13</td><td>0.001</td><td>0.67&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.23</td><td>0.000</td></tr><tr><td>(3E,7E)-4,8,12-Trimethyltrideca-1,3,7,11-tetraene</td><td>0.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0</td><td>0.173</td><td>0.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td>0.000</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>0.000</td></tr><tr><td>Hexadecane</td><td>0.01&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td>0.072</td><td>0.01&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0</td><td>0.000</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>0.000</td></tr><tr><td>Butanoic acid, methyl ester</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>0.000</td><td>0.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td>0.000</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>1.000</td></tr><tr><td>1-Butanol, 2-methyl-, acetate</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>1.000</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>0.000</td><td>0.06&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03</td><td>0.000</td></tr><tr><td>NA2</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>1.000</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>0.000</td><td>0.01&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td>0.000</td></tr><tr><td>Dodecane</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>1.000</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>0.000</td><td>0.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td>0.000</td></tr><tr><td>NA4</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>1.000</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>0.000</td><td>0.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td>0.000</td></tr><tr><td>2H-Pyran-3-ol, 6-ethenyltetrahydro-2,2,6-trimethyl-, acetate, trans-</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>1.000</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>0.000</td><td>0.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td>0.000</td></tr><tr><td>1-Cyclohexene-1-ethanol, 2,6,6-trimethyl-</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>0.000</td><td>0.01&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0</td><td>0.000</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>1.000</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Expression analysis</title><p id="Par18">We also produced comprehensive transcriptome dataset using both HiSeq and the Iso-Seq pipeline. We focused our further analysis on identifying the specific genes responsible for floral development and the biosynthesis of volatile aroma compounds in <italic>O. fragrans</italic>. The members of MADs transcription factors that control plant development were highly expressed in all tissues tested. Among them, AG, AP3/PI, AP1, and SEP were predominantly expressed in the early flower stage (S1), whereas, the expression level of the <italic>ANR1</italic> gene family was highly specific to the root tissue (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5b</xref>). Interestingly, the numbers of ABCE genes were higher than that of <italic>Fraxinus chinensis</italic>, a close relative of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>fragrans</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref>).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><title>MADS-box gene family in O. fragrans.</title><p><bold>a</bold> The evolution tree and expression values of the MADSs box genes, <bold>b</bold> Heatmap showing the tissue- and flowering stage- specific expressions of the members of ABCE genes</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41438_2018_108_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e2186"/></fig></p><p id="Par19">The major component of the volatile compounds in the floral scent of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>fragrans</italic>, linalool (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>), is known to be synthesized by terpenoid synthetases (TPS). Therefore, we compared the expression profiles of <italic>TPS</italic> genes and identified over 40 genes that contain the functional motifs of TPS. Differential gene expression (DGE) analysis identified 7 <italic>TPS</italic> genes that are highly expressed in flowers, compared to roots, leaves, and stems (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>).<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><title>The top 7 secondary metabolites produced by the osmanthus flower measured by GC-MS.</title><p>Note that the top molecule is linalool, a monoterpene, which was produced most in the S1 stage of the flower, and then decreased its amount in the flower. S1, S2, and S3 stand for the early, middle, and late stages, respectively</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41438_2018_108_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e2218"/></fig><fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><title>TPS (terpene synthase) gene family in O. fragrans.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Heatmap showing the tissue- and flowering stage-specific expression of the members of TPS genes, <bold>b</bold> TPS gene subfamily members. Yellow: S1 early flowering stage-specific Red: S3, late flowering stage-specific</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41438_2018_108_Fig7_HTML" id="d29e2234"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par20">Sweet osmanthus is one of the most beloved ornamental tree species in China and other parts of the world and has been cultivated for over two-thousand years in China due to its attractive traits of beautiful colors, unique aromas, a long flowering season, and medicinal efficacy. However, there is a limited number of studies that have investigated the genetic basis of the phenotypic diversity of sweet osmanthus. Recently, a set of genetic markers was identified<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>, and an effort to construct a genetic linkage map was reported<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. Additionally, several transcriptomics studies identified a large number of genes that are differentially expressed in some of the cultivars with attractive traits<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. While these studies indirectly associate the diverse phenotypes with the genotypes of sweet osmanthus, there is no genome information that can directly link the specific genes to particular traits. Thus, we have sequenced, assembled and annotated the genome of sweet osmanthus. Furthermore, combining HiSeq- and IsoSeq-based transcriptome analyses, we gained deep insight into the genes that control aroma compounds synthesis in the flowers of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>fragrans</italic>.</p><sec id="Sec16"><title>The high-quality reference genome provides deep insights to the evolution of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>fragrans</italic></title><p id="Par21">Currently, there are still no comprehensive analyses combining genomic, transcriptomic, and metabolic approaches to reveal the unique aroma of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>fragrans</italic>. Despite advances in second-generation sequencing, it is still very challenging to construct a high-quality plant genome due to the high complexity, large size, and high percentage of repeats and polyploidy. Therefore, we combined the second-generation short read to achieve high accuracy, the third-generation long reads for de novo assembly, and Hi-C to scaffold contigs into a chromosome-scale assembly. To guarantee a high-quality genome annotation, we combined <italic>de novo</italic>, homology-based, and experimental evidence obtained from the extensive transcriptomics data, including the full-length transcripts. We constructed a reference-quality genome that produced an unambiguous chromosome-scale assembly (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;23) and functionally annotated 43,573 genes out of the complete set of 45,542 genes of <italic>O. fragrans</italic> (95.68 %).</p><p id="Par22">The number of genes, 45,542, is high and is more than the genes present in some of the plants that are related to <italic>O. fragrans</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). This can be attributed to the repeated gene duplications which led to expansion of the gene families. The <italic>O. fragrans</italic> genome has higher number of multicopy genes compared to other plant species (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Furthermore, <italic>O</italic>. <italic>fragrans</italic> appears to have obtained and retained a large number of genes through the whole genome duplications (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). The majority of plant species have experienced genome duplications in their evolutionary past<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>. The high gene number of <italic>O. fragrans</italic> might be a result of complex interactions among various factors such as the rate of evolution, number of duplication events, level of gene retention, expansion of gene family and selection pressure. The recent (~15 MYA) WGD and high retention might explain the large gene number. The number of genes involved in secondary metabolism is particularly high in <italic>O. fragrans</italic> (unpublished observation), and these genes might have been retained and/or expanded after the whole-genome duplications. This result may reflect the continuous interaction between <italic>O. fragrans</italic> and environmental factors, which imposes a constant pressure for adaptation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par23">The calculated level of heterozygosity (1.45&#x000a0;%) is high in <italic>O. fragrans</italic> var ruixiangui. Considering that <italic>O. fragrans</italic> has been selectively bred for desirable traits for over 2000 years in China, 160 cultivars with diverse phenotypes have been selected. The high heterozygosity (1.45&#x000a0;%) in <italic>O. fragrans</italic> var ruixiangui might support an extensive breeding among cultivars throughout its history, although it is challenging to accurately determine the origin of the observed heterozygosity in the cultivar. Furthermore, as an androdioecious species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup>, the coexistence of selfing and crossing poses an additional challenge to trace the origin of the high heterozygosity. Recently, the first genetic map of <italic>O. fragrans</italic> was created using the SLAF-seq method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup> to provide a framework for understanding the genome organization. This linkage map has helped us assemble the reference genome and can help to investigate the origin of the high heterozygosity and history of hybridization among the cultivars of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>fragrans</italic>.</p><p id="Par24">The new genome can also be used as a reference for the whole genome resequencing of sweet osmanthus cultivars. Resequencing these whole genomes of various cultivars provides highly useful information on the potential drivers for the phenotype diversity, evolution, and population structure of a given species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>. Our preliminary genome sequencing of 30 different cultivars of <italic>O. fragrans</italic> identified a large number of single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNP), copy number variation (CNV), insertion sdeletion (InDel), structural variations (SV) and other mutation sites (unpublished results). Using the above mutation loci as new molecular genetic markers, researchers can study the history of cultivation, population dynamics and genetic diversity.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>The whole-genome duplication and the tandem duplication of the biosynthetic genes is likely the cause for the strong sweet aroma of <italic>O. fragrans</italic></title><p id="Par25">Among <italic>TPS</italic>-family genes, the <italic>TPS-b</italic> and <italic>g</italic> subfamilies are known to synthesize monoterpenes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>. Linalool, the major aroma compound identified in our study, is produced by the monoterpene synthesis pathway in <italic>O. fragrans</italic>. Using the high-quality genome and deep transcriptome information, we found a significant expansion of TPS as a whole, and of subfamilies b and g specifically, compared with the grape (<italic>V</italic>. <italic>vinifera</italic>), which did not have whole genome duplication (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). In addition to TPS1, 2, 3, and 4, which have been previously functionally validated, we identified seven additional <italic>TPS</italic> genes that are specifically expressed in flower stages S1 and S3. Three <italic>TPS</italic> genes appear to be new genes that are flower specific, indicating that the production of fragrance is controlled by a complex network involving multiple <italic>TPS</italic> genes functioning in time- and flower-specific manners. Our results suggest that the unique aromas of <italic>O. fragrans</italic> are some of the outcomes of the interrelationship between genome evolution, transcriptional regulation, and metabolic control. Our current work lays a solid foundation for further studies on the comparative genomics, molecular and biochemical mechanisms of aroma development in <italic>O</italic>. <italic>fragrans</italic>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec18" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par26">We constructed a high-quality reference genome of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>fragrans</italic> by combining Illumina, PacBio and Hi-C platforms. The genome of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>fragrans</italic> var. rixianggui is ~740&#x02009;Mb and has a high heterozygosity of 1.45&#x000a0;%. A large number of genes (45,542) was predicted by the gene models built with de novo, homology-based, and experimental data obtained from extensive transcription results. Our deep genome analysis indicates evidence of whole-genome duplication at ~15 MYA. Our new genome information should help the research community study the genome structure, genetic basis of genetic diversity, and regulation of the flowering process and scent development in <italic>O. fragrans</italic> and other related plant species.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec20"><title>Genome sequencing</title><p id="Par27">For genome sequencing, leaf samples were collected from a male tree (<italic>O</italic>. <italic>fragrans</italic> var. rixianggui) on the campus of Nanjing Forestry University, Nanjing, China, and were processed for genomic DNA isolation and library construction. Rixianggui (Semperfloren) is a unique cultivar because it has a strong aroma and blooms continuously, except in hot summer months, while other cultivars, for example, Thunbergii, Latifolius, and Aurantiaeus, bloom only in autumn. Genomic DNA was extracted using the CTAB method, size fractionated with BluePipin (Sage Science, Inc, MA, USA), used for library construction following the PacBio SMRT library construction protocol, and sequenced on the PacBio Sequel platform (Pacific Biosciences, CA, USA). For Illumina library construction, the extracted DNA was fragmented and size-fractionated using g-tube and BluePipin, then subjected to paired-end library construction and sequenced on the HiSeq X ten platform (Illumina Inc, CA, USA).</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Hi-C sequencing</title><p id="Par28">To ensure the quality of the Hi-C library, leaf samples were initially examined forintegrity of the nuclei by DAPI staining. Once confirmed for high quality nuclei, the samples were processed following the Hi-C procedure<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup>. The Hi-C library was sequenced on the Illumina HiSeq X ten platform (Illumina, CA, USA), generating 740 million Hi-C read pairs, which were submitted to the Lachesis Hi-C scaffolding pipeline<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>. Hi-C libraries produce different molecular types, including invalid pairs of self-circles, dangling-ends, and dumped-pairs. According to the different molecular types that lead to the alignment of paired reads on the genome in different directions, the unique alignment of reads on the genome needs to be statistically analyzed. Once recognized as an effective interaction, the final data only retained effective interactions. According to the above rules, the position of the DpnII digestion site in the reference genome was used, because it can also provide useful information on the structural organization of individual chromosomes.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Transcriptome sequencing</title><p id="Par29">To obtain information that can assist in the empirical annotation of genes, full-length transcriptome sequencing was performed. The samples from flowers at three different blooming stages (S1: beginning, S2: middle, S3: late; Suppl. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>), leaves, stems, and roots were collected from the same tree described above and processed for library construction. The total RNAs were extracted according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions of TRNzol Universal Reagent (Cat# DP424, TIANGEN Biotech Co. Ltd, Beijing, China). The quality and quantity of the RNA samples were evaluated using a NanoDrop&#x02122; One UV-Vis spectrophotometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific, USA), a Qubit&#x000ae; 3.0 Fluorometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific, USA) and an Agilent Bioanalyzer 2100 (Agilent Technologies, USA). All RNA samples with integrity values close to 10 were used for cDNA library construction and sequencing. The cDNA library was prepared using the TruSeq Sample Preparation (Illumina Inc, CA, USA) and IsoSeq Library Construction kits (Pacific Biosciences, CA, USA), and paired-end sequencing with 150&#x02009;bp was conducted on a HiSeq X ten platform (Illumina Inc, CA, USA).</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Aroma compound analysis</title><p id="Par30">Fresh flowers at three different stages (S1: beginning, S2: middle, S3: lat), defined by the size of the flower (Supplemental Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>), were picked from the same tree at the time of sample collection for the transcriptome studies described above. Sampling was replicated five times, and the samples were quickly put into polyethylene bags impermeable to gases, kept frozen and stored at &#x02212;20 &#x000b0;C. Headspace solid phase microextraction (SPME) combined with gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS) was used to determine the identity and quantity of the aroma volatiles. Flowers (0.3&#x02009;g) were placed in a 4&#x02009;mL solid-phase microextraction vial (Supelco Inc, USA), 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of 1000&#x000d7; diluted ethyl caprate (Macklin Inc, China) was added, and vials were capped with a 65&#x02009;&#x000b5;m DB-5 ms extraction head (Supelco Inc, USA). Then, the vial was incubated for 40&#x02009;min in a water bath at 45&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C to volatilize the aroma compounds and release them into the headspace. After the adsorption period, the fiber head was removed and introduced into the heated injector port of the GC for desorption at 250&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 3&#x02009;min. The desorbed volatile compounds from DB-5 ms were analyzed on a Trace DSQ GC-MS (Thermo-Fisher Scientific, USA), equipped with a 30&#x02009;m x 0.25&#x02009;mm&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;0.25&#x02009;mm TR-5 ms capillary column (Supelco Inc, USA). The oven temperature was programmed at 60&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 2&#x02009;min, increasing at 5&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C/min to 150&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, then increasing at 10&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C/min to reach 250&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, followed by maintaining the temperature of the transfer line at 250&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. Helium was taken as the carrier gas at a linear velocity of 1.0&#x02009;mL/min. Mass detector conditions on MS were: source temperature: 250&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C and the electronic impact (EI) mode at 70&#x02009;eV, with a speed of 4 scans/s over the mass range m/z 33-450&#x02009;amu in a 1&#x02009;s cycle. Volatile compounds were first auto-matched by mass spectra using the NIST98 database through ChemStation (Agilent, USA). A series of <italic>n</italic>-alkanes (C7-C30) (Sigma St. Louis, MO) was injected into the GC-MS set to obtain the linear retention indices of the volatile compounds, and they were analyzed under the same conditions. The data were also compared with published linear retention indices (NIST Chemistry WebBook, SRD 69). The normalization of peak-areas was used to calculate the quantities of the volatile aroma compounds.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec24"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41438_2018_108_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>new Supplemental</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p>These authors contributed equally to this work and should be considered co-first authors: Xiulian Yang, Yuanzheng Yue</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Change history</bold></p><p>4/19/2019</p><p>Since the publication of this article, the authors have noticed that the NCBI accession number is missing from article.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p><bold>Supplementary Information</bold> accompanies this paper at (10.1038/s41438-018-0108-0).</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported by research grants provided by the National Natural Science Foundation (31870695 and 31601785), the Project of Key Research and Development Plan (Modern Agriculture) in Jiangsu (BE2017375), the Selection and Breeding of Excellent Tree Species and Effective Cultivation Techniques (CX(16)1005), the Project of Osmanthus National Germplasm Bank, and the Top-notch Academic Programs Project of Jiangsu Higher Education Institutions.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p id="Par31">L.W. and Y.Y. designed and coordinated the whole project. X.Y., L.W., Y.Y., and F.C. together lead and performed the whole project. J.C., F.C., T.S., H.L., and W.D. performed the analyses of genome evolution, gene family analyses, and metabolic analyses, M.S.P., J.C., F.C., Y.Y., and G.C. participated in manuscript writing and revision. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec></ack><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>QB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The culture of sweet osmanthus in China</article-title><source>J. Henan Univ. Nat. Sci.</source><year>2003</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>136</fpage><lpage>139</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zang</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>QB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigation on natural resources of <italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic> Lour. at Zhou luo cun in Hunan</article-title><source>Acta Hortic. Sin.</source><year>2005</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>926</fpage><lpage>929</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zang</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>QB</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The studying history and the application to International Cultivar Registration Authority of sweet osmanthus (<italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic> Lour.)</article-title><source>J. Plant Resour. Environ.</source><year>2003</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>53</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>GX</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Application of HS-SPME and GC-MS to characterization of volatile compounds emitted from Osmanthus flowers</article-title><source>Ann. Chim.</source><year>2004</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>921</fpage><lpage>927</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/adic.200490114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15689028</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xin</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterization of volatile compounds in flowers from four groups of sweet osmanthus (<italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic>) cultivars</article-title><source>Can. J. Plant Sci.</source><year>2013</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>923</fpage><lpage>931</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4141/cjps2012-333</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>&#x00026; W, C.Y. Analysis of aroma-active compounds in three sweet osmanthus (<italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic>) cultivars by gas-chromatography olfactometry and GC-mass spectrometry</article-title><source>J. Zhejiang. Univ. Sci. B</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>638</fpage><lpage>648</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1631/jzus.B1400058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25001223</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Essential oil composition of <italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic> varieties by GC-MS and heuristic evolving latent projections</article-title><source>Chromatographia</source><year>2009</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>1163</fpage><lpage>1169</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1365/s10337-009-1255-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Variations in the components of <italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic> Lour. Essential oil at different stages of flowering</article-title><source>Food Chem.</source><year>2009</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2008.09.044</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition comparison of the essential oil from four groups of <italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic> Lour. flowers</article-title><source>J. Essent. Oil Plants</source><year>2012</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>832</fpage><lpage>838</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/0972060X.2012.10644128</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Water-soluble essential oil components of fresh flowers of <italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic> lour</article-title><source>J. Essent. Oil Res.</source><year>2016</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10412905.2015.1114532</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The RAPD analysis of 17 <italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic> cultivars in Henan province</article-title><source>Acta Hortic. Sin.</source><year>2004</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>685</fpage><lpage>687</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of genetic diversity and relationships among <italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic> cultivars using AFLP markers</article-title><source>Electron. J. Biotechnol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>3</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic diversity and population genetic structure of wild sweet osmanthus revealed by microsatellite markers</article-title><source>Acta Hortic. Sin.</source><year>2014</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>1427</fpage><lpage>1435</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and characterization of microsatellite markers for <italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic> (Oleaceae) using 454 sequencing technology</article-title><source>Genet. Mol. Res.</source><year>2015</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>17154</fpage><lpage>17158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4238/2015.December.16.15</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26681062</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>cDNA-AFLP analysis on 2 Osmanthus fragrans cultivars with different flower color and molecular characteristics of MYB1gene</article-title><source>Trees</source><year>2015</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>931</fpage><lpage>940</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00468-015-1175-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">He, Y. X., Yuan, W. J., Dong, M. F., Han, Y. J. &#x00026; Shang, F. D. The first genetic map in sweet osmanthus (Osmanthus fragrans Lour.) using specific locus amplified fragment sequencing. <italic>Front. Plant Sci.</italic><bold>8</bold>, 1621 (2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XS</given-names></name><name><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNA-Seq analysis and comparison of the enzymes involved in ionone synthesis of three cultivars of Osmanthus</article-title><source>J. Asian Nat. Prod. Res.</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptomic analysis of the candidate genes related to aroma formation in <italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic></article-title><source>Molecules</source><year>2018</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1604</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules23071604</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cloning and expression analysis of MEP pathway enzyme-encoding genes in <italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic></article-title><source>Genes</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>78</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/genes7100078</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Emission and accumulation of monoterpene and the key terpene synthase (TPS) associated with monoterpene biosynthesis in <italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic> Lour</article-title><source>Front. Plant Sci.</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1232</fpage><?supplied-pmid 26793212?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26793212</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baldermann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Functional characterization of a carotenoid cleavage dioxygenase 1 and its relation to the carotenoid accumulation and volatile emission during the floral development of <italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic> Lour</article-title><source>J. Exp. Bot.</source><year>2010</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>2967</fpage><lpage>2977</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erq123</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20478967</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baldermann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleischmann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biosynthesis of <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>- and <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-ionone, prominent scent compounds, in flowers of <italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic></article-title><source>Acta Biochim. Pol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18388/abp.2012_2176</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22428136</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>LX</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>cDNA cloning of the phytoene synthase (PSY) and expression analysis of PSY and carotenoid cleavage dioxygenase genes in <italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic></article-title><source>Biologia</source><year>2013</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>258</fpage><lpage>263</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2478/s11756-013-0002-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Differential expression of carotenoid-related genes determines diversified carotenoid coloration in flower petal of <italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic></article-title><source>Tree. Genet. Genom.</source><year>2014</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>329</fpage><lpage>338</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11295-013-0687-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YG</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptomic analysis and carotenogenic gene expression related to petal coloration in <italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic> &#x02018;Yanhong Gui&#x02019;</article-title><source>Trees</source><year>2016</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>1207</fpage><lpage>1223</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00468-016-1359-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptome sequencing and analysis of sweet osmanthus (<italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic> Lour.)</article-title><source>Genes. Genom.</source><year>2014</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>777</fpage><lpage>788</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13258-014-0212-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterization of <italic>OfWRKY3</italic>, a transcription factor that positively regulates the carotenoid cleavage dioxygenase gene <italic>OfCCD</italic>4 in <italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic></article-title><source>Plant Mol. Biol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>485</fpage><lpage>496</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-016-0483-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27106478</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Analysis of the main active ingredients and bioactivities of essential oil from <italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic> Var. thunbergii using a complex network approach</article-title><source>BMC Syst. Biol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>144</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12918-017-0523-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29282071</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guillaume</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Carl</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A fast, lock-free approach for efficient parallel counting of occurrences of K-Mers</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2011</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>764</fpage><lpage>770</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21217122</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>SOAPdenovo2: an empirically improved memory-efficient short-read de novo assembler</article-title><source>Gigascience</source><year>2012</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>18</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2047-217X-1-18</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>pIRS: Profile-based Illumina pair-end reads simulator</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2012</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1533</fpage><lpage>1535</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts187</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22508794</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Phased diploid genome assembly with single-molecule real-time sequencing</article-title><source>Nat. Methods</source><year>2016</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1050</fpage><lpage>1054</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.4035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27749838</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Abeel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shea</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Priest</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Abouelliel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakthikumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuomo</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Wortman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Earl</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pilon: an integrated tool for comprehensive microbial variant detection and genome assembly improvement</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e112963</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0112963</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25409509</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pryszcz</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabald&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Redundans: an assembly pipeline for highly heterozygous genomes</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2016</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>e113</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkw294</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27131372</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sim&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Waterhouse</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ioannidis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kriventseva</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name><surname>Zdobnov</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BUSCO: assessing genome assembly and annotation completeness with Single-Copy Orthologs</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2015</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>3210</fpage><lpage>3212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv351</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26059717</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stanke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinkamp</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Waack</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgenstern</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AUGUSTUS: a web server for gene finding in eukaryotes</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>W309</fpage><lpage>W312</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkh379</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15215400</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Using RepeatMasker to identify repetitive elements in genomic sequences</article-title><source>Curr. Protoc. Bioinforma.</source><year>2004</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>10</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohany</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Repbase Update, a database of repetitive elements in eukaryotic genomes</article-title><source>Mob. DNA</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>11</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13100-015-0041-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26045719</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nussbaumer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MIPS PlantsDB: a database framework for comparative plant genome research</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2013</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>D1144</fpage><lpage>D1151</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gks1153</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23203886</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalvari</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rfam 13.0: shifting to a genome-centric resource for non-coding RNA families</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2017</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>D335</fpage><lpage>D342</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkx1038</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Camacho</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>BLAST+: architecture and tapplications</article-title><source>BMC Bioinforma.</source><year>2009</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>421</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-10-421</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>tRNAscan-SE: a program for improved detection of transfer RNA genes in genomic sequence</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>1997</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>955</fpage><lpage>964</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/25.5.955</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9023104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lagesen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x000f8;dland</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Staerfeldt</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Rognes</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNAmmer: consistent and rapid annotation of ribosomal RNA genes</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2007</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>3100</fpage><lpage>3108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm160</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17452365</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Birney</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Durbin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Using GeneWise in the Drosophila annotation experiment</article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><year>2000</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>547</fpage><lpage>548</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.10.4.547</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10779496</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blanco</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Parra</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Guig&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Using geneid to identify genes</article-title><source>Curr. Protoc. Bioinforma.</source><year>2007</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>28</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Majoros</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Pertea</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TigrScan and GlimmerHMM: two open source ab initio eukaryotic gene-finders</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2004</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>2878</fpage><lpage>2879</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bth315</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15145805</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bromberg</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Rost</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SNAP: predict effect of non-synonymous polymorphisms on function</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2007</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>3823</fpage><lpage>3835</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm238</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17526529</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Automated eukaryotic gene structure annotation using EVidenceModeler and the program to assemble spliced alignments</article-title><source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>R7</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2008-9-1-r7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18190707</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moriya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Okuda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshizawa</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanehisa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>KAAS: an automatic genome annotation and pathway reconstruction server</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2007</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>W182</fpage><lpage>W185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm321</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17526522</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quevillon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>InterProScan: protein domains identifier</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>116</fpage><lpage>120</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gki442</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Bodt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Maere</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Van de Peer</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome duplication and the origin of angiosperms</article-title><source>Trends Ecol. Evol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>591</fpage><lpage>597</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tree.2005.07.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16701441</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoeckert</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>OrthoMCL: identification of ortholog groups for eukaryotic genomes</article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><year>2003</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>2178</fpage><lpage>2189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.1224503</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12952885</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ciu</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Widespread genome duplications throughout the history of flowering plants</article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><year>2006</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>738</fpage><lpage>749</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.4825606</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16702410</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Casneuf</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>De Bodt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Raes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Maere</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Van de Peer</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nonrandom divergence of gene expression following gene and genome duplications in the flowering plants Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title><source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>R13</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2006-7-2-r13</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16507168</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The differentiation and development of pistils of hermaphrodites and pistillodes of males in androdioecious Osmanthus fragrans L. and implications for the evolution to androdioecy</article-title><source>Plant Syst. Evol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>300</volume><fpage>843</fpage><lpage>849</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00606-013-0923-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High-throughput genotyping by whole-genome resequencing</article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><year>2009</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1068</fpage><lpage>1076</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.089516.108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19420380</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tholl</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Terpene synthases and the regulation, diversity and biological roles of terpene metabolism</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Plant. Biol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>297</fpage><lpage>304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2006.03.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16600670</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Dekker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High-throughput genome scaffolding from in vivo DNA interaction frequency</article-title><source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>1143</fpage><lpage>1147</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.2768</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24270850</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marie-Nelly</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High-quality genome (re) assembly using chromosomal contact data</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>5695</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms6695</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25517223</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jibran</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chromosome-scale scaffolding of the black raspberry (Rubus occidentalis L.) genome based on chromatin interaction data</article-title><source>Hortic. Res.</source><year>2018</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>18008</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41438-017-0013-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>