<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Hortic Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Hortic Res</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Horticulture Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2662-6810</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2052-7276</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8087695</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33931633</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">542</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41438-021-00542-x</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Genetic basis of high aroma and stress tolerance in the oolong tea cultivar genome</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Pengjie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Jiaxin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Shan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Shuai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>Chuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Wenling</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Shuilian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Hongli</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Yucheng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Mengya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Xuejin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Yun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Yuqiong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Jiangfan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Xingtan</given-names></name><address><email>zhangxingtan@caas.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2955-2813</contrib-id><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Naixing</given-names></name><address><email>ynxtea@126.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.256111.0</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1760 2876</institution-id><institution>College of Horticulture, </institution><institution>Fujian Agriculture and Forestry University/Key Laboratory of Tea Science in Universities of Fujian Province, </institution></institution-wrap>350002 Fuzhou, China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.410727.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0526 1937</institution-id><institution>Shenzhen Branch, Guangdong Laboratory for Lingnan Modern Agriculture, Genome Analysis Laboratory of the Ministry of Agriculture, Agricultural Genomics Institute at Shenzhen, </institution><institution>Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>518120 Shenzhen, China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.256111.0</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1760 2876</institution-id><institution>Center for Genomics and Biotechnology, Fujian Provincial Key Laboratory of Haixia Applied Plant Systems Biology, Key Laboratory of Genetics, </institution><institution>Fujian Agriculture and Forestry University, </institution></institution-wrap>350002 Fuzhou, China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>1</day><month>5</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>1</day><month>5</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>107</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>5</day><month>2</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>2</month><year>2021</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2021</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Tea plants (<italic>Camellia sinensis</italic>) are commercially cultivated in &#x0003e;60 countries, and their fresh leaves are processed into tea, which is the most widely consumed beverage in the world. Although several chromosome-level tea plant genomes have been published, they collapsed the two haplotypes and ignored a large number of allelic variations that may underlie important biological functions in this species. Here, we present a phased chromosome-scale assembly for an elite oolong tea cultivar, &#x0201c;Huangdan&#x0201d;, that is well known for its high levels of aroma. Based on the two sets of haplotype genome data, we identified numerous genetic variations and a substantial proportion of allelic imbalance related to important traits, including aroma- and stress-related alleles. Comparative genomics revealed extensive structural variations as well as expansion of some gene families, such as terpene synthases (TPSs), that likely contribute to the high-aroma characteristics of the backbone parent, underlying the molecular basis for the biosynthesis of aroma-related chemicals in oolong tea. Our results uncovered the genetic basis of special features of this oolong tea cultivar, providing fundamental genomic resources to study evolution and domestication for the economically important tea crop.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Genomics</kwd><kwd>Plant genetics</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>the Fujian Province &#x0201c;2011 Collaborative Innovation Center&#x0201d;, the Chinese Oolong Tea Industry Innovation Center special project (J2015-75)</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>the Scientific Research Foundation of Graduate School of Fujian Agriculture and Forestry University (324-1122yb060), and the Scientific Research Foundation of Horticulture College of Fujian Agriculture and Forestry University (2018B02).</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>the Earmarked Fund for China Agriculture Research System (CARS-19)</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>the National Natural Science Foundation of China (31701874)</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2021</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">The development of high-throughput sequencing has vigorously promoted research progress in plant genomics and genetics, especially single-molecule long-read sequencing and high-throughput chromatin conformation capture (Hi-C) technology, which have allowed complete plant genome sequencing and assembly at a low cost<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. Diploid or polyploid genomes consist of two or more homologous chromosome sets. Notably, most plant reference genome assemblies are collapsed homologous copies of each chromosome. Although such assembled genomes are convenient for comparison and inference, they ignore allelic variants that may have potential biological functions and affect the quality of heterozygous plant genomes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. Unzipping haplotypes into two or more sequence sets has become a new trend in genome assembly that is conducive to research on plant heterosis and evolution and provides a solid foundation for accurate and reliable genome editing. ALLHiC is a new algorithm for constructing allele-aware, chromosome-scale assemblies based on Hi-C data<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>, and it has been successfully applied to the genome assembly of several plant species, including an autotetraploid<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup> and an autooctoploid<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup> sugarcane genome, an autotetraploid cultivated alfalfa genome<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>, an allotetraploid rapeseed genome<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>, and two Ficus genomes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. ALLHiC is sensitive to the quality of input assembly and becomes powerless when the proportion of chimeric contigs and collapsed regions increases. However, high-precision sequencing technology and advanced assembly algorithms will help ALLHiC cross this barrier. Therefore, ALLHiC is a powerful tool for genome research on heterozygous diploid and polyploid plants.</p><p id="Par3">The tea plant <italic>Camellia sinensis</italic> L. O. Kuntze is a perennial evergreen woody plant that is commercially cultivated in &#x0003e;60 countries and accounts for &#x0003e;5 million tons of leaves picked each year<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. At present, &#x0003e;2 billion cups of tea are consumed worldwide every day. These teas are mainly manufactured by processing fresh tea leaves and are rich in characteristic secondary compounds, including theanine, caffeine, catechins, and volatiles, which are beneficial to human health<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. The United Nations General Assembly (UNGA) designated May 21 as &#x0201c;International Tea Day&#x0201d; to praise the high value of tea to the global society, economy, and culture, especially its significant role in rural poverty reduction and development in developing countries. However, compared with the tremendous contribution of tea to the global economic industry, fundamental biological research on tea plants and breeding efficiency are still lagging<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">Tea plants are an ideal model for investigating the molecular regulation mechanism of secondary metabolites<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. The rich collection of secondary metabolites endow tea with a distinctive taste, aroma and color and are involved in the responses to various environmental stresses<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>; thus, these metabolites are attracting increasing research attention. Great advances in tea genomics have effectively facilitated researchers&#x02019; understanding of tea quality and adaptability. The genomic sequences of two major tea plant varieties, namely, <italic>Camellia sinensis</italic> vars. <italic>sinensis</italic> (CSS)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup> and <italic>assamica</italic> (CSA)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup> have been resolved, especially those of three CSS cultivars (cultivars Shuchazao<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>, Biyun<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>, and Longjin 43<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>) whose high-precision chromosome-level genomic sequences have been obtained. In addition, the high-quality genome of an ancient tea tree has been published<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. However, these genomic assemblies have collapsed haplotypes and ignore the large number of allelic variations that exist in the highly heterozygous tea genome.</p><p id="Par5">In general, tea plants exhibit self-incompatibility<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>, which leads to high levels of heterozygosity and allelic variation in their genomes. The allelic variations between two haplotypes within a single genome may play a crucial role in phenotypic variation, heterosis, and evolution<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. Several studies support the key point that hybrid rice exhibits heterosis owing to alleles with high transcriptional activity and dominant expression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. In this study, we generated a chromosome-scale reference genome of CSS Huangdan (HD, 2<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2<italic>x</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;30) by PacBio HiFi (high-fidelity) sequencing and Hi-C technology. A phased genome with two fully represented haplotypes was also generated to facilitate the mining of allelic variation and allele-specific expression (ASE). HD is an elite tea cultivar originating from Anxi County, Fujian Province, China. Commercially, HD is suitable for processing into oolong, green, and black teas and was approved by the Chinese Crop Variety Approval Committee in 1985 (No. GS13008-1985). HD is not only a standard reference species for breeding oolong tea cultivars but also a high-aroma backbone parent that has been used to breed a series of excellent hybrid offspring<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>, including CSS Jinguanyin (JGY, No. GS2002017), CSS Huangguanyin (HGY, No. GS2002015), and CSS Jinmudan (JMD, No. GS2010024). Our research will enhance the understanding of genetic variation and heterosis of tea plants and lay the foundation for precise gene editing and molecular breeding in the future.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Genome assembly and annotation</title><p id="Par6">A total of 54.90&#x02009;Gb (~18.67-fold) of high-fidelity (HiFi) PacBio reads were sequenced on the PacBio Sequel II platform. In addition, chromosomal-level genome assembly was achieved using 327.80&#x02009;Gb (~111.50-fold) of Illumina short reads generated from two high-throughput conformation capture (Hi-C) libraries (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). To overcome the assembly problem caused by the high level of heterozygosity (2.79&#x02013;3.40%) of the tea plant genome, we generated nonredundant genome sequences using Hifiasm<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup> and Purge_Dups<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>, yielding a contig-level assembly with a total size of 2.94&#x02009;Gb. The assembled genome size was consistent with the genome size estimated using flow cytometry (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>). Compared with early published tea plant genomes, the contig N50 of the HD genome was 2.61&#x02009;Mb, which is ~4.3-fold, ~38.1-fold, and ~127.7-fold that of chromosome-level CSS-Shuchazao (SCZ-Chr)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>, scaffold-level CSS-Shuchazao (SCZ-Sca)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>, and CSA-Yunkang 10 (YK 10)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>, respectively (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). BUSCO<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup> analysis showed that the HD contig set contained 95.0% complete core orthologous genes in plants (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>). Subsequently, we anchored the nonredundant contig set onto 15 pseudochromosomes based on Hi-C contacts, representing a high-quality chromosome-scale monoploid genome assembly (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The length of the pseudochromosomes ranges from 140&#x02009;Mb (Chr11) to 247&#x02009;Mb (Chr1) (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>). The interaction signals were enriched in chromosomes, and the intensity of interaction along the diagonal was relatively smooth, showing well-organized contig orderings (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). Assembly assessment through long-terminal repeat (LTR) annotation showed that the LTR Assembly Index (LAI) score<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup> of the HD monoploid assembly was 16.6 (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref>), indicating that more LTRs were recovered in our assembly than in other published tea genomes (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Comparison of contig assemblies among tea plant genomes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>HD</th><th>SCZ-Chr</th><th>SCZ-Sca</th><th>YK 10</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Contig assembly size (Gb)</td><td>2.94</td><td>2.94</td><td>2.89</td><td>2.57</td></tr><tr><td>Max length (Mb)</td><td>20.56</td><td>2.89</td><td>0.54</td><td>0.26</td></tr><tr><td>Contig N50 (kb)</td><td>2610.56</td><td>600.46</td><td>67.07</td><td>19.96</td></tr><tr><td>Complete BUSCO ratio (%)</td><td>95.0%</td><td>90.6%</td><td>93.1%</td><td>90.2%</td></tr><tr><td>Raw LAI</td><td>13.75</td><td>12.35</td><td>1.93</td><td>2.32</td></tr><tr><td>LAI</td><td>16.16</td><td>14.19</td><td>3.89</td><td>5.17</td></tr><tr><td>GC content (%)</td><td>38.82</td><td>38.25</td><td>37.84</td><td>42.31</td></tr><tr><td>No. of genes</td><td>43,779</td><td>50,525</td><td>33,932</td><td>36,951</td></tr><tr><td>Average gene length (bp)</td><td>5452</td><td>4906</td><td>6821</td><td>3290</td></tr><tr><td>Average CDS length (bp)</td><td>1092</td><td>1086</td><td>1345</td><td>990</td></tr><tr><td>Average exon length (bp)</td><td>342</td><td>245</td><td>238</td><td>237</td></tr><tr><td>Average exon number per gene</td><td>4.4</td><td>5.1</td><td>5.7</td><td>4.8</td></tr><tr><td>Exon GC content (%)</td><td>43.26</td><td>43.83</td><td>44.50</td><td>44.55</td></tr><tr><td>Average intron length (bp)</td><td>1223</td><td>973</td><td>1298</td><td>640</td></tr><tr><td>Intron GC content (%)</td><td>34.57</td><td>35.38</td><td>33.94</td><td>33.50</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Genomic features of the HD genome along 15 pseudochromosomes.</title><p>The tracks from outermost to innermost indicate <bold>a</bold> pseudochromosomes of the monoploid genome, <bold>b</bold> gene density, <bold>c</bold> transposable element (TE) density, <bold>d</bold> single-nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) density, and <bold>e</bold> insertion-deletion (InDel) density</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41438_2021_542_Fig1_HTML" id="d32e866"/></fig><fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Assembly and LTR features of HD genome.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Chromatin interaction at 500-Kb resolution in the HD genome. <bold>b</bold> Syntenic analysis of HD monoploid genome assembly and HD-phased haplotypes. <bold>c</bold> Assessment of assembly quality with LAI value, where the <italic>y</italic>-axis represents LAI. <bold>d</bold> Distribution of LTR insertion time in HD and three published tea plant genomes. Dashed lines represent the mean insertion time in each genome</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41438_2021_542_Fig2_HTML" id="d32e891"/></fig></p><p id="Par7">Although high heterozygosity presents difficulties in resolving the tea plant genome, it stores abundant genetic resources that the monoploid genome cannot decipher. The recent emergence of HiFi reads and the Hifiasm algorithm help us to overcome the difficulties of phasing highly heterozygous genomes. On this basis, the ALLHiC algorithm<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref> aids in constructing a haplotype-resolved chromosome-level assembly by separating homologous chromosomes according to the strength of interaction signals. We finally divided the HD genome into two haplotypes (A and B) with the assistance of the monoploid reference assembly. The two haplotypes comprised a total of 30 pseudochromosomes with a total length of 5.88&#x02009;GB (2.92&#x02009;Gb for HA and 2.95&#x02009;Gb for HB). To assess the quality of the two haplotypes, we first compared them with the aforementioned HD monoploid reference assembly, showing good collinearity (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>). BUSCO analysis showed that 89.9% and 92.5% conserved single-copy genes were recalled from haplotype A and haplotype B, respectively, and a total of 95.1% were complete BUSCO genes (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Phased chromosome-scale assembly and annotation</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>Haplotype A</th><th>Haplotype B</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Length of chromosomes (Gb)</td><td>2.92</td><td>2.95</td></tr><tr><td>BUSCO completeness of assembly (%)</td><td>89.9</td><td>92.5</td></tr><tr><td>Number of genes</td><td>44,105</td><td>44,409</td></tr><tr><td>Number of genes with &#x0003e;2 alleles</td><td/><td>7211</td></tr><tr><td>Number of genes with 2 alleles</td><td/><td>19,723</td></tr><tr><td>Number of genes with 1 allele</td><td/><td>1066</td></tr><tr><td>Total number of genes with alleles</td><td/><td>26,000</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par8">Combining information such as orthologous proteins, de novo prediction and expression evidence, we annotated 43,779 protein-coding genes through the MAKER pipeline<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>, of which 98.20% (42,981/43,779) of the genes were supported by transcript evidence, and 49.85% (21,826/43,779) and 41.44% (22,139/43,779) genes could be functionally annotated by the GO and KEGG databases, respectively. The average length of the protein-encoding genes was 5452&#x02009;bp. In addition, the average length of introns was 1223&#x02009;bp with 35.85% GC content, and the average length of exons was 342&#x02009;bp with 43.26% GC content (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). We further used TEclass<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>, a transposable element (TE) automatic classification tool, to enhance the repeatMasker annotation result. Finally, 70.75% of the HD genome was annotated as repetitive sequences (2.08/2.94&#x02009;Gb) (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref>), and LTR retrotransposons (LTR-RTs) belonged to the largest class of TEs, accounting for 48.64% of the genomes (1.43/2.94&#x02009;Gb). Meanwhile, 24,741 intact LTR-RTs were identified in the HD genome using LTR_retriever<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup> (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5</xref>). Similar to the SCZ-Chr genome<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>, the HD genome showed more abundant LTR-RTs than two previously published draft genomes assembled based on Illumina short reads<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>, indicating that long-read sequencing technology provided a better solution for TE annotation in the highly repetitive genome. We also observed a significant enrichment of LTR-RT insertion events in the HD and SCZ-Chr genomes (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2d</xref>), dating a recent LTR burst back to 0.6 mya in the tea plant.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Alleles associated with stress tolerance and aroma-related components</title><p id="Par9">Comparison between the two haplotypes revealed a high level of synteny (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a</xref>). However, a large number of haplotypic variations were detected, including 23.57 million SNPs, 1.14 million insertions, and 1.13 million deletions (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">7</xref>). The genetic variants were widespread and evenly distributed across the 15 pseudochromosomes (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b</xref>). The phased chromosome-scale genome assembly allows us to separate alleles from 59.38% (26,000/43,779) protein-coding genes with at least one base substitution. These alleles showed an average similarity of 92.6% and Ka/Ks ratio of 0.61 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3c</xref>), suggesting relatively rapid evolution. Functional annotation revealed that the genes under positive selection (Ka/Ks&#x0003e;1) were enriched in multiple biological processes, such as the response to reactive oxygen species (ROS) and the metabolism of multiple terpenoids (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>), indicating their important roles in responses to stress and likely association with aroma-related volatile organic compounds (VOCs). RNA-seq reads from five different tissues, including buds, roots, stems, young leaves, and mature leaves, were also mapped against the allelic genes from HA and HB. We evaluated and clustered the correlation between the expression of 26,000 allelic genes in five tissues and found that the expression of these alleles in the same tissue was highly correlated and clustered together (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>Allelic variations and expression between two HD haplotypes.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Synteny block between allele gene pairs. <bold>b</bold> Genetic variations between the two haplotypes. <bold>c</bold> Distribution of ka/ks between allele gene pairs. <bold>d</bold> Correlation analysis and clustering of the expression of alleles in five tissues, including roots (R), stems (S), buds (B), young leaves (YL), and mature leaves (ML)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41438_2021_542_Fig3_HTML" id="d32e1069"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Extensive structural variations affected aroma-related genes</title><p id="Par10">Structural variants (SVs) represent genomic rearrangements greater than 50&#x02009;bp, which are an important basis for crop improvement and domestication traits<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. However, SVs have not yet been investigated in tea plants by comparing high-quality genomes. Here, we identified 45,304, 44,358, and 26,754 SVs by comparing HD to the three published SCZ-Chr<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>, LJ43<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup> and DASZ<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> genomes (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> and Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>). A similar level of SV was observed in the three genomes, ranging from 294.08 (9.77%) to 380.32 (12.63%) Mb. The SVs were not evenly distributed across the 15 chromosomes. For instance, chromosome 1 has a high SV frequency and the longest total length, and chromosome 12 has the lowest SV frequency (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>). These SVs affected 14,347, 13,119, and 15,222 protein-coding genes in SCZ-Chr, LJ43 and DASZ, respectively, suggesting that the SVs had a large effect on gene function. Among these genes, 3559 were shared (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b</xref>). These genes were involved in a variety of metabolic pathways in our KEGG analysis (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>), including zeatin biosynthesis, starch and sucrose metabolism, amino acid biosynthesis, carotenoid biosynthesis, glycosphingolipid biosynthesis, and diterpenoid biosynthesis, indicating the metabolic differentiation of tea germplasm resources. While HD is suitable for high-aroma oolong tea, SCZ and LJ43 are famous for processing into green tea. We analyzed the SV annotation genes of HD vs. SCZ-chr and HD vs. LJ43 and found that these genes were annotated in many aroma-related pathways (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4c</xref> and Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>), which indicated that SVs may affect the high-aroma characteristics of HD. We also observed that many terpenoids, which are important components of the aroma of oolong tea, exhibited structural variations in their synthetase genes (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4c</xref>), including (<italic>E</italic>)-nerolidol synthase (NES) and &#x003b1;-farnesene synthase (AFS), which can be used as SV resources for high-aroma tea breeding.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>SV statistics of the HD genome vs. three tea plant genomes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>HD vs. SCZ</th><th>HD vs. LJ43</th><th>HD vs. DASZ</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>No. of InDels (50&#x02013;500&#x02009;bp)</td><td>8174</td><td>8351</td><td>3718</td></tr><tr><td>No. of InDels (500&#x02013;10,000&#x02009;bp)</td><td>4539</td><td>5132</td><td>2023</td></tr><tr><td>No. of InDels (10,000&#x02013;50,000&#x02009;bp)</td><td>456</td><td>400</td><td>246</td></tr><tr><td>No. of InDels (50,000&#x02013;100,000&#x02009;bp)</td><td>21</td><td>19</td><td>9</td></tr><tr><td>No. of tandem expansion/contraction</td><td>5209</td><td>4998</td><td>3653</td></tr><tr><td>No. of repeat expansion/contraction</td><td>26,905</td><td>25,458</td><td>17,105</td></tr><tr><td>Size of InDels (Mb)</td><td>24.21</td><td>24.17</td><td>11.64</td></tr><tr><td>Size of tandem expansion/contraction (Mb)</td><td>75.76</td><td>41.46</td><td>46.79</td></tr><tr><td>Size of repeat expansion/contraction (Mb)</td><td>280.36</td><td>254.62</td><td>235.65</td></tr><tr><td>Total SV number</td><td>45,304</td><td>44,358</td><td>26,754</td></tr><tr><td>Total SV size (Mb)</td><td>380.32</td><td>320.25</td><td>294.08</td></tr><tr><td>Gene count</td><td>14,347</td><td>13,119</td><td>15,222</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>Analysis of SVs and related genes.</title><p><bold>a</bold> SV frequency plot of HD and three other tea plant genomes on 15 chromosomes. HD: Huangdan, SCZ: Suchazao<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>, LJ43: Longjing 43<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>, DASZ: An ancient tea tree<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. <bold>b</bold> Venn plot of three sets of SV-annotated genes. <bold>c</bold> Top 20 KEGG pathways of SV-annotated genes between the HD and SCZ genomes. Pathways related to aroma are marked with blue boxes, and SV-related terpene synthases (TPSs) and their corresponding terpenoids are highlighted</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41438_2021_542_Fig4_HTML" id="d32e1332"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Expansion of the terpene synthase (TPS) family contributes to the high-aroma characteristics of HD</title><p id="Par11">As a famous high-aroma backbone parent, HD has been used to breed a series of high-quality offspring. Compared with ordinary tea cultivars, the molecular mechanism of high-aroma formation is worthy of in-depth exploration. Our previous research<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup> showed that the most important aroma components of HD leaves are monoterpenoids and sesquiterpenoids, such as linalool and its oxides, geraniol, nerolidol, and &#x003b1;-farnesene, which are the quality basis for HD that is suitable for processing oolong tea. TPS is an important enzyme that can catalyze the production of a variety of terpenoids, which are essential for the tea aroma from the substrate. Compared with coffee and cacao, the newly released CSS-Suchazao (SCZ) genome showed that the amplification of <italic>TPS</italic> genes was driven by recent tandem replication events<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. Here, we identified 93 <italic>HDTPS</italic> genes in the HD genome (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">8</xref>). This number is greater than the number identified in the SCZ genome (72 <italic>SCZTPSs</italic>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>, suggesting that <italic>TPS</italic> genes have expanded considerably in the HD genome. Obviously, compared to <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, kiwifruit, and coffee (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>), the <italic>TPSs</italic> expanded with tandem duplication were specific to tea plants. <italic>HDTPSs</italic> were widely distributed on 14 chromosomes (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">8</xref>); however, they showed a similar clustered pattern and high collinearity across six chromosomes compared with <italic>SCZTPSs</italic> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Notably, 30 <italic>HDTPSs</italic> were enriched on chromosome 13, and this number was substantially higher than that in the SCZ genome.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><title>Comparison of TPS genes between HD and SCZ.</title><p><bold>a</bold> The TPS genes of HD were mainly distributed on six chromosomes. <bold>b</bold> The TPS genes of SCZ were mainly distributed on six chromosomes. <bold>c</bold> Collinearity analysis of HD and SCZ, in which the purple line indicates the collinearity of TPS genes</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41438_2021_542_Fig5_HTML" id="d32e1409"/></fig></p><p id="Par12">To compare the transcription abundance of <italic>TPS</italic> genes in HD and SCZ tissues, we mapped the transcriptome data of the five tissues (root, stem, apical bud, young leaf, and mature leaf) to their respective genomes using the same methods aforementioned. Phylogenetic analysis divided <italic>HDTPSs</italic> into four groups (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). TPS-b contained the most genes (55, 59.14%), followed by TPS-a (22, 23.66%). Classification of other plants showed that TPS-a is mainly composed of sesquiterpene synthases, TPS-b and TPS-g are mainly monoterpene synthases, and TPS-c/e/f include diterpene synthases<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. Our results showed that 27 <italic>HDTPSs</italic> were highly expressed in at least one tissue (TPM&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;10), whereas 12 were expressed in SCZ (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">8</xref>). The apical buds and young leaves of tea plants are the major economically important tissues used for processing tea beverages. We further analyzed the expression of <italic>TPS</italic> genes in buds and young leaves and discovered that 18 <italic>TPSs</italic> were highly expressed in HD (TPM&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;10) and 10 in SCZ. We also compared four homologous <italic>TPS</italic> genes, including linalool and (<italic>E</italic>)-nerolidol synthases (LIS/NES, HD.07G0009650, HD.07G0009680, CSS0000049.1, and CSS0000223.1)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>, (<italic>E</italic>)-NES (HD.07G0023490 and CSS0012706.1)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>, &#x003b1;-farnesene synthase (AFS, HD.07G0023580, HD.07G0023600, HD.07G0023610, and CSS0043927.1)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>, and ocimene synthase 2 (OCS2, HD.08G0016410 and CSS0025755.1)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>, that have been identified in vitro or in vivo (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). Among them, the expression levels of the LIS/NES homologous transcripts of HD and SCZ were similar, whereas the expression level of <italic>SCZOCS2</italic> in buds and leaves was higher than that of <italic>HDOCS2</italic>. However, the TPM values of the apical buds and young leaves of one <italic>HDAFS</italic> were 6-fold and 80-fold greater than in SCZ, respectively. The expression of NES of HD in young leaves was nearly 3-fold that of SCZ. In addition, we tested the aroma components of the leaves of HD and SCZ in October. The changes in the marked terpenoids were consistent at the genetic level, except for (<italic>E</italic>)-nerolidol, which may be due to the season and the unprocessed state of the tissues (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5</xref>). These results indicate that the widespread and specifically high expression of <italic>TPS</italic> genes in HD tissues may be an important factor affecting their high-aroma characteristics.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><title>Phylogenetic and tissue expression analysis of TPS genes from HD and SCZ.</title><p>The legends are shown on the left. The TPM values of five tissues (root, stem, apical bud, young leaf, and mature leaf) from HD and SCZ were normalized. Four homologous TPS genes, including linalool and (<italic>E</italic>)-nerolidol synthase (LIS/NES)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>, (<italic>E</italic>)-nerolidol synthase (NES)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>, &#x003b1;-farnesene synthase (AFS)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>, and ocimene synthase 2 (OCS2)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>, that have been identified in vitro or in vivo are marked</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41438_2021_542_Fig6_HTML" id="d32e1519"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Identification and comparison of C-repeat binding factors (CBFs)</title><p id="Par13">C-repeat binding factors (CBFs) are the core regulators in response to cold stress in plants; they can be rapidly induced by cold and accompany the C-repeat/dehydration response motif (CRT/DRE) in the promoter region of the target cold-response (COR) genes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. The CBFs of tea plant were initially identified in the previous draft genome and were found to be rapidly induced by cold stress and to regulate target genes in multiple pathways<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. We are interested in the number of CBF regulatory factors in tea plants, and the recently published chromosome-level genomes of tea plants provide convenience for our identification and comparison. We identified six CBFs in the four tea plant genomes, two more than in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, which was consistent with previous experimental verification<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. The CBFs of tea plant and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> clustered into different clades, indicating species conservation (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7a</xref>). However, the CBF clades from the four tea germplasms were different, which may be related to the different degrees of cold resistance of various tea plant resources. <italic>Arabidopsis AtCBF1-3</italic> is recognized as an important cascade core that regulates cold acclimation. They are arranged in tandem on chromosome 4 to regulate target genes in response to cold stress through binding G/ACCGAC motifs (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7b</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. Interestingly, we observed that the six CBFs in the HD genome were arranged tandemly on chromosomes 1 and 6 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7c</xref>), which may play an important role in the regulation of cold response in tea plants. Tea plants are believed to originate from southwestern China, and the recently sequenced ancient tea plant (DASZ) genome<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> from Yunnan Province allows us to compare the evolution and variation of the conserved domain of CBFs. By comparing the AP2 DNA-binding domain and two flanking signature sequences of CBFs among HD, DASZ, and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, we observed that the overall CBF protein sequences were highly conserved, and the similarity reached 89.77% (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7d</xref>). Among them, CBFs from tea plants and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> showed some amino acid differences at multiple positions. Compared with the ancient tea tree, one of the CBF genes (HD.06G0016290) from the elite tea cultivar HD showed amino acid mutations at 8 positions, which may affect its cold response and DNA-binding function. In summary, these results provide genomic evidence for CBF-mediated resistance to cold stress in tea plants.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><title>Comparison of C-repeat binding factors (CBFs).</title><p><bold>a</bold> Phylogenetic tree analysis of CBFs from four tea resources and <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>. HD: Huangdan, SCZ: Suchazao<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>, LJ43: Longjing 43<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>, DASZ: An ancient tea tree<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. <bold>b</bold> Three <italic>AtCBFs</italic> arranged in tandem on chromosome 4 in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. The binding sites of <italic>AtCBF1</italic> and <italic>AtCBF2</italic> verified by DNA affinity purification sequencing (DAP-seq) are presented in the form of sequence logos<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. <bold>c</bold> Six CBFs arranged in tandem on chromosomes 1 and 6 in the HD genome. <bold>d</bold> Multisequence alignment of the conserved binding domains of CBFs from HD, DASZ, and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. The sequence logo reflects the conservation of the amino acid at each position. The yellow box represents the AP2 DNA-binding domain; the purple overlines indicate two signature sequences; the small red box represents the amino acid mutation of CBFs of HD compared to DASZ</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41438_2021_542_Fig7_HTML" id="d32e1640"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par14">Oolong tea is one of six major types of tea production and is known for its high levels of aroma<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. Our study decoded the fully phased genome of an elite oolong tea cultivar, HD. Analysis of the genome revealed extensive genetic variations compared with other published tea genomes and frequent allelic imbalances associated with or likely contributing to high-aroma characteristics and stress tolerance. In addition, we observed a tandem evolution pattern of CBF genes, indicating their potential roles in the stress tolerance.</p><p id="Par15">Aroma plays a vital role in the quality of tea, and in addition to the tea manufacturing process, tea cultivars are the basis for the formation of tea aroma. HD is always well known for its high-aroma characteristics. Our team has participated in the breeding project with HD and CSS Tieguanyin as the backbone parents and has cultivated a series of high-aroma and high-quality offspring, including CSS Jinguanyin (JGY, No. GS2002017), CSS Huangguanyin (HGY, No. GS2002015), and CSS Jinmudan (JMD, No. GS2010024), which are certified by the Chinese Crop Variety Approval Committee as one of the most important pedigrees in Chinese tea breeding<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Our previous study showed that sesquiterpenes and monoterpenes are the core aroma components of HD and its progeny<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. Terpenoids are an important component of tea aroma due to their pleasant aroma and low odor threshold<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. Comparative genomics of HD and two green tea cultivars revealed extensive structural variations in TPS genes, which may affect the high-aroma characteristics of oolong tea cultivars. The number of TPS genes in SCZ (72) is notably higher than that in coffee (53), cacao (36), and kiwifruit (34)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. Our results showed that HD has 21 more TPS genes than SCZ, and they are mainly clustered on six chromosomes, especially chromosome 13, which may enhance the synthesis of terpenoids in HD. Remarkably, compared to SCZ, the TPS genes in HD were more widely and highly expressed in buds and leaves, which are economically important tissues. As a recent study has revealed, the increase in TPS members, the formation of clusters, the differentiation of catalytic functions, and differences in in gene expression regulation may all affect the production and concentration of terpenes in plants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>. Although the number of TPS genes in tea plants has expanded to varying degrees, the function of most TPS genes is still unknown<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>, except for several TPSs that have been shown to be involved in the formation of linalool<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>, (<italic>E</italic>)-nerolidol<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>, (<italic>E</italic>)-&#x003b2;-ocimene<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>, and &#x003b1;-farnesene<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. Oolong tea has more pleasant or distinctive aroma qualities than green tea<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>, possibly due to higher levels of (<italic>E</italic>)-nerolidol and &#x003b1;-farnesene<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>. This is likely attributable to the significantly upregulated expression of two TPS genes (NES and AFS). Overall, our results suggest that the expansion and specifically high expression of TPS family genes are the molecular basis of HD&#x02019;s high-aroma characteristics.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>Tea plant materials and sequencing</title><p id="Par16">Fresh leaves of an individual CSS cultivar HD planted in the tea plantation of Fujian Agriculture and Forestry University (Fuzhou, China; 26&#x000b0;08&#x02032;19&#x02033; N, 119&#x000b0;24&#x02032;06&#x02033; E) were collected for genome sequencing. The high-quality genomic DNA of HD samples was extracted using a DNeasy Plant Mini Kit (Qiagen, USA) and sent to Annoroad (Ningbo, China) to construct 10&#x02013;25&#x02009;kb SMRTbellTM libraries and sequenced using the PacBio Sequel II platform. The tender leaves of HD were also plucked and sent to Annoroad for Hi-C library construction and sequencing through an Illumina HiSeq Nova-seq system. In addition, five HD tissues, including tender roots, young stems, apical buds, tender leaves, and mature leaves, were collected, and the total RNA was extracted by an RNAprep Pure Plant kit (TIANGEN, Beijing, China). A total of 3&#x02009;&#x003bc;g RNA was used for each sample to generate a transcriptome library and sequenced using the Illumina platform.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Genome assembly</title><p id="Par17">We analyzed the genome size of the sequenced individuals by flow cytometry (BD FACSCalibur, BD Bioscience, USA) using tomato and maize as internal controls<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>. The CSS HD genome was assembled by incorporating sequencing data from PacBio circular consensus sequencing technology<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup> and the Hi-C method. First, HiFi reads were assembled with Hifiasm with the default parameters. We assembled two levels of chromosome-scale genomes, including a monoploid genome and an allele-defined haplotype-resolved assembly. Briefly, for monoploid assembly, although Purge_dups was contained in Hifiasm, we checked the read depth and filtered the primary contigs of the initial Hifiasm assembly by Purge_dups (v1.25) with the default parameters and evaluated the results by the Benchmarking Universal Single-Copy Orthologs (BUSCO) completeness<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup> and duplication score. Hi-C reads were assessed by the HiC-Pro (v2.11.4) program<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup> and were uniquely mapped to contig assemblies. Meanwhile, Juicer tools (v1.11.08)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup> and 3D-DNA pipelines (v180114)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup> were used to detect and correct misassembled contigs. To distribute contigs into the appropriate groups, we aligned the set of Hi-C corrected contigs against the &#x0201c;Shuchazao&#x0201d; chromosome-scale assembly using RaGOO (v1.1). Finally, the ALLHiC optimize algorithm (v0.9.13) was used to adjust the order and orientation of contigs in each group. We merged the haplotig sequence and alternative assembly to redo Purge_dups (v1.25) with the cutoff parameter &#x0201c;2 6 10 12 20 70&#x0201d;. The purged primary contigs and alternative contigs were merged and regarded as a draft contig assembly for the monoploid genome. The resulting contigs were subjected to haplotype phasing using the ALLHiC algorithm with default parameters, and the monoploid genome sequences were selected as a reference to identify allelic contigs. Chromosome-level haplotype A and haplotype B of CSS HD were fully resolved and released. In addition, we calculated the heterozygosity through GenomeScope2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup> with 33 k-mers. Chromosome localization and collinearity analysis of genes were visualized in TBtools<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Repetitive sequences and gene annotation</title><p id="Par18">We first ran RepeatModeler (v1.08), which can automatically execute RECON<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup> and RepeatScout<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>, to construct a de novo repeat library of the HD genome. RepeatMasker (v4.07) was utilized to identify and cluster repetitive sequences, and Teclass (v2.1.3)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup> was used to further classify unknown repetitive sequences. The TRF package (v4.09)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup> with modified parameters (&#x0201c;trf 1 1 2 80 5 200 2000&#x0201d;) from previous research<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup> was used to find tandem repeats.</p><p id="Par19">We ran two rounds of the MAKER pipeline<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>, which can integrate predictions based on orthologous proteins, ab initio calculations and transcriptome data to better annotate protein-coding genes. We first assembled transcriptome data through de novo assembly and genome-guided assembly by Trinity (v2.20)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup>. Then, the assembled transcripts were subjected to calculation and proper filtering of FPKM expression values with the same standards as in previous research<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. The filtered data were imported into the PASA program (v2.1.0)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup> and compared with the UniProt plant protein database for evaluation. Finally, the remaining transcripts were further trained<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. The evidence was integrated by the MAKER pipeline and used to generate a preliminary set of HD-encoding genes. The predicted gene models with low AED scores were selected for retraining using GENEMARK<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup>, SNAP (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/KorfLab/SNAP">https://github.com/KorfLab/SNAP</ext-link>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup>, and AUGUSTUS (v3.3.1)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref></sup> in the second round of MAKER running. Additionally, the transcriptome data were mapped to the genome via HISAT2 (v2.10) and reassembled via StringTie (v1.3.4)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup>. The assembled data were imported into the MAKER pipeline together with the homologous proteins of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, rice, grape, tomato, <italic>Morus notablis</italic>, and papaya. After filtering putative transposon-derived gene models, a set of HD protein-coding genes was generated. Then, the selected protein-coding gene set was functionally annotated with high-confidence orthologs in the eggNOG database<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Allele gene and genetic variation identification</title><p id="Par20">Initially, we annotated the HD A/B subgenome with the MAKER pipeline described above. The identification of alleles was based on the methods of sugarcane genome research. We first produced a table of alleles with two columns (including HA and HB). Two main approaches, including the synteny-based approach and the GMAP-based approach<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref></sup>, were used to generate the backbone of the allelic table. Initially, we used JCVI (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/tanghaibao/jcvi">https://github.com/tanghaibao/jcvi</ext-link>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref></sup>, the Python version of MCSCAN, to scan synteny blocks between two sets of genes. The cscore&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.99 parameter enabled us to obtain 1 vs. 1 comparison genes between two sets of haplotypes, while genes from the same synteny block were considered alleles to be classified. Subsequently, the gene models excluded from the synteny block were aligned to the monoploid assembly with GMAP (version 2013-10-28). If gene pairs share more than half of the reference genome coordinates, they can exist as alleles. The unfiltered alleles were compared in pairs using the mafft (v7.471) L-Ins-I model to enable accurate alignment between gene pairs. By comparing the alignment results, we were able to calculate the similarity between alleles. Only gene pairs with high similarity (&#x0003e;0.7) were considered to form a pair of alleles, while a pair of identical genes was considered to be the same allele. In the other case, there were multiple genes (&#x0003e;2) aligned to the same location using GMAP. We sorted these genes according to their similarity, removed the gene pairs with low similarity, and added the filtered genes as paralogs of alleles to the allele table.</p><p id="Par21">To explore the genetic difference and evolutionary relationship between two sets of haplotypes, we identified SNPs and InDels between them. SNP identification was performed by the Nucmer utility<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref></sup> with parameter settings consistent with the generation of pseudohaplotypes. The InDels between two subgenomes were found by Assemblytics (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://assemblytics.com/">http://assemblytics.com/</ext-link>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref></sup> with the default parameters. The analysis of structural variants (SVs) among tea plant genomes was also carried out by Nucmer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref></sup> and Assemblytics<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Analysis of allele expression</title><p id="Par22">A pipeline built into Trinity software<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup>, including bowtie, RNA-Seq by Expectation Maximization (RSEM) and edgeR, was used to analyze the difference in the expression of each pair of alleles in the allele table. In detail, for RNA-seq sequencing reads in five tissues, bud, root, stem, young leaf and mature leaf, we used trim-galore to remove their adaptations before mapping. Subsequently, reads were mapped to allelic transcripts, and the parameters &#x0201c;--all --best --strata -- M 300 --k 1&#x0201d; were used to obtain the optimal results. Then, RSEM was used to calculate the allele transcripts per kilobase of exon model per million mapped reads (TPM) values, and edegR was used to quantitatively evaluate the allelic differences of expression level.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Analysis of volatile compounds (VOCs)</title><p id="Par23">We collected the leaves of HD and SCZ in October, and the samples were ground to a powder in liquid nitrogen. One gram of the powder was transferred to a 20&#x02009;ml headspace vial. The vials were sealed using crimp-top caps with TFE-silicone headspace septa. At the time of SPME analysis, each vial was placed at 60&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 10&#x02009;min, and then a 65&#x02009;&#x000b5;m divinylbenzene/carboxene/polydimethylsilioxane fiber (Supelco, Bellefonte, PA, USA) was exposed to the headspace of the sample for 20&#x02009;min at 60&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. VOCs were detected by MetWare (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.metware.cn/">http://www.metware.cn/</ext-link>) based on the Agilent 7890B-7000D platform. Desorption of the VOCs from the fiber coating was carried out in the injection port of the GC apparatus at 250&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 5&#x02009;min in splitless mode. The identification and quantification of VOCs was carried out with a 30&#x02009;m&#x02009;x&#x02009;0.25&#x02009;mm&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;1.0&#x02009;&#x000b5;m DB-5MS (5% phenyl-polymethylsiloxane) capillary column. Helium was used as the carrier gas at a linear velocity of 1.0&#x02009;ml/min. The oven temperature was programmed from 40&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (5&#x02009;min), increased at 6&#x02009;&#x000b0;C/min to 280&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, and held for 5&#x02009;min. Mass spectra were recorded in electron impact (EI) ionization mode at 70&#x02009;eV. The quadrupole mass detector, ion source and transfer line temperatures were set at 150, 230, and 280&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, respectively. Mass spectra were scanned in the range <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> 30&#x02013;350&#x02009;amu at 1&#x02009;s intervals. Volatile compounds were identified by comparing the mass spectra with the data system library (MWGC) and linear retention index.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><sec id="Sec16"><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41438_2021_542_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Figure S1-S5</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="41438_2021_542_MOESM2_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Table S1-S8</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p>These authors contributed equally: Pengjie Wang, Jiaxin Yu</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41438-021-00542-x.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This research was funded by the Fujian Province &#x0201c;2011 Collaborative Innovation Center&#x0201d;, the Chinese Oolong Tea Industry Innovation Center special project (J2015-75), the National Natural Science Foundation of China (31701874), the Major Special Project of Scientific and Technological Innovation on Anxi Tea (AX2021001), the Earmarked Fund for the China Agriculture Research System (CARS-19), the Scientific Research Foundation of the Graduate School of Fujian Agriculture and Forestry University (324-1122yb060), and the Scientific Research Foundation of Horticulture College of Fujian Agriculture and Forestry University (2018B02).</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>N.Y., X.Z., and P.W. conceived and designed the research. P.W. and X.Z. collected the samples. P.W., J.Y., X.Z., S.C., S.J., C.Y., W.W., S.G., H.C., Y.Z., M.G., and X.C. performed the genome assembly and data analysis. P.W. and J.Y. wrote the manuscript. N.Y., X.Z., S.J., Y.S., Y.G., J.Y., and C.Y. revised the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All data are publicly available in the BIG Data Center (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bigd.big.ac.cn/">https://bigd.big.ac.cn/</ext-link>) under project number PRJCA003382. The raw genome and transcriptome sequencing data are publicly available under sub-number CRA003208. The assembly and annotation of the HD diploid genome are available under sub-number GWHAZTZ00000000. The assembly and annotation of the HD haplotype genome are available under sub-number GWHBAUV00000000.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p id="Par24">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The sequenced angiosperm genomes and genome databases</article-title><source>Front. Plant Sci.</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>418</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2018.00418</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29706973?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29706973</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XT</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>RX</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unzipping haplotypes in diploid and polyploid genomes</article-title><source>Comput. Struct. Biotechnol. J.</source><year>2019</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.csbj.2019.11.011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31908732?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31908732</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XT</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Ming</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assembly of allele-aware, chromosomal-scale autopolyploid genomes based on Hi-C data</article-title><source>Nat. Plants</source><year>2019</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>833</fpage><lpage>845</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41477-019-0487-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31383970?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31383970</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Allele-defined genome of the autopolyploid sugarcane <italic>Saccharum spontaneum</italic> L</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><year>2018</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>1565</fpage><lpage>1573</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41588-018-0237-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30297971?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30297971</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Allele-aware chromosome-level genome assembly and efficient transgene-free genome editing for the autotetraploid cultivated alfalfa</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>2494</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-020-16338-x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7237683?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32427850</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chen, X. Q. et al. A high-quality <italic>Brassica napus</italic> genome reveals expansion of transposable elements, subgenome evolution and disease resistance. <italic>Plant Biotechnol. J</italic>. 10.1111/pbi.13493 (2020).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genomes of the banyan tree and pollinator wasp provide insights into fig-wasp coevolution</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2020</year><volume>183</volume><fpage>875</fpage><lpage>889</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2020.09.043</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 33035453?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33035453</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drew</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The growth of tea</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2019</year><volume>566</volume><fpage>S2</fpage><lpage>S4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/d41586-019-00395-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30728512?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30728512</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The chromosome-scale genome reveals the evolution and diversification after the recent tetraploidization event in tea plant</article-title><source>Hortic. Res.</source><year>2020</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>63</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41438-020-0288-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 33931630?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33931630</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>XC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tea plant genomics: achievements, challenges and perspectives</article-title><source>Hortic. Res.</source><year>2020</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>7</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41438-019-0225-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31908810?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31908810</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Low temperature synergistically promotes wounding-induced indole accumulation by INDUCER OF CBF EXPRESSION-mediated alterations of jasmonic acid signaling in <italic>Camellia sinensis</italic></article-title><source>J. Exp. Bot.</source><year>2020</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>2172</fpage><lpage>2185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erz570</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31900491?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31900491</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dodds</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name><surname>Rathjen</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant immunity: towards an integrated view of plant-pathogen interactions</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Genet.</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>539</fpage><lpage>548</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg2812</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20585331?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20585331</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding the biosyntheses and stress response mechanisms of aroma compounds in tea (<italic>Camellia sinensis</italic>) to safely and effectively improve tea aroma</article-title><source>Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr.</source><year>2018</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>2321</fpage><lpage>2334</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10408398.2018.1506907</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30277806?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30277806</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Draft genome sequence of <italic>Camellia sinensis</italic> var. <italic>sinensis</italic> provides insights into the evolution of the tea genome and tea quality</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2018</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>E4151</fpage><lpage>E4158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1719622115</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29678829?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29678829</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The reference genome of tea plant and resequencing of 81 diverse accessions provide insights into genome evolution and adaptation of tea plants</article-title><source>Mol. Plant</source><year>2020</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1013</fpage><lpage>1026</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molp.2020.04.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32353625</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>QJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The chromosome-level reference genome of tea tree unveils recent bursts of non-autonomous LTR retrotransposons to drive genome size evolution</article-title><source>Mol. Plant</source><year>2020</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>935</fpage><lpage>938</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molp.2020.04.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32353626</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Population sequencing enhances understanding of tea plant evolution</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>4447</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-020-18228-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32895382?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32895382</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The tea tree genome provides insights into tea flavor and independent evolution of caffeine biosynthesis</article-title><source>Mol. Plant</source><year>2017</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>866</fpage><lpage>877</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molp.2017.04.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28473262?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28473262</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome assembly of wild tea tree DASZ reveals pedigree and selection history of tea varieties</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>3719</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-020-17498-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32709943?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32709943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fuchinoue</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of self-incompatibility alleles of major varieties of tea</article-title><source>Jpn. Agr. Res. Q.</source><year>1979</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>48</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genomic analysis of hybrid rice varieties reveals numerous superior alleles that contribute to heterosis</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>6258</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms7258</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25651972?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25651972</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Patterns of genome-wide allele-specific expression in hybrid rice and the implications on the genetic basis of heterosis</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2019</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>5653</fpage><lpage>5658</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1820513116</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30833384?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30833384</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chinese oolong tea: An aromatic beverage produced under multiple stresses</article-title><source>Trends Food Sci. Technol.</source><year>2020</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>242</fpage><lpage>253</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2020.10.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptome and metabolite profiling reveal novel insights into volatile heterosis in the tea plant (<italic>Camellia Sinensis</italic>)</article-title><source>Molecules</source><year>2019</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>3380</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules24183380</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 6767024?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6767024</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cheng, H., Concepcion, G. T., Feng, X., Zhang, H. &#x00026; Li, H. Haplotype-resolved de novo assembly using phased assembly graphs with hifiasm. <italic>Nat Methods</italic><bold>18</bold>, 170&#x02013;175 (2021).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identifying and removing haplotypic duplication in primary genome assemblies</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2020</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>2896</fpage><lpage>2898</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btaa025</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31971576?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31971576</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sim&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Waterhouse</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Panagiotis</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kriventseva</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name><surname>Zdobnov</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BUSCO: assessing genome assembly and annotation completeness with single-copy orthologs</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2015</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>3210</fpage><lpage>3212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv351</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26059717?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26059717</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessing genome assembly quality using the LTR Assembly Index (LAI)</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2018</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>e126</fpage><?supplied-pmid 30107434?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30107434</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cantarel</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MAKER: An easy-to-use annotation pipeline designed for emerging model organism genomes</article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><year>2008</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>188</fpage><lpage>196</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.6743907</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18025269?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18025269</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abrus&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Grundmann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>DeMester</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Makalowski</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TEclass&#x02013;a tool for automated classification of unknown eukaryotic transposable elements</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2009</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1329</fpage><lpage>1330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp084</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19349283?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19349283</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ou</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>LTR_retriever: a highly accurate and sensitive program for identification of long terminal-repeat retrotransposons</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>176</volume><fpage>1410</fpage><lpage>1422</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.17.01310</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29233850?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29233850</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alonge</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Benoit</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Soyk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Major impacts of widespread structural variation on gene expression and crop improvement in tomato</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2020</year><volume>182</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2020.05.021</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32553272?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32553272</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Tholl</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohlmann</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pichersky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The family of terpene synthases in plants: a mid-size family of genes for specialized metabolism that is highly diversified throughout the kingdom</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2011</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>212</fpage><lpage>229</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2011.04520.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21443633?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21443633</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Implementation of <italic>CsLIS/NES</italic> in linalool biosynthesis involves transcript splicing regulation in <italic>Camellia sinensis</italic></article-title><source>Plant Cell Environ.</source><year>2017</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>176</fpage><lpage>186</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pce.13080</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28963730?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28963730</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Formation of (<italic>E</italic>)-nerolidol in tea (<italic>Camellia sinensis</italic>) leaves exposed to multiple stresses during tea manufacturing</article-title><source>Food Chem.</source><year>2017</year><volume>231</volume><fpage>78</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2017.03.122</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28450026?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28450026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Formation of &#x003b1;-Farnesene in tea (<italic>Camellia sinensis</italic>) leaves induced by herbivore-derived wounding and its effect on neighboring tea plants</article-title><source>Int. J. Mol. Sci.</source><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>4151</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms20174151</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>QS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Unraveling a crosstalk regulatory network of temporal aroma accumulation in tea plant (<italic>Camellia sinensis</italic>) leaves by integration of metabolomics and transcriptomics</article-title><source>Environ. Exp. Bot.</source><year>2018</year><volume>149</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envexpbot.2018.02.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stockinger</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilmour</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomashow</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Arabidopsis thaliana CBF1 encodes an AP2 domain-containing transcriptional activator that binds to the C-repeat/DRE, a cis-acting DNA regulatory element that stimulates transcription in response to low temperature and water deficit</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1997</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>1035</fpage><lpage>1040</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.94.3.1035</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19635?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9023378</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Two transcription factors, <italic>DREB1</italic> and <italic>DREB2</italic>, with an EREBP/AP2 DNA binding domain separate two cellular signal transduction pathways in drought- and low-temperature-responsive gene expression, respectively, in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>1998</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1391</fpage><lpage>1406</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.10.8.1391</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9707537?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9707537</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gilmour</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Low temperature regulation of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> CBF family of AP2 transcriptional activators as an early step in cold-induced <italic>COR</italic> gene expression</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>1998</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>433</fpage><lpage>442</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313x.1998.00310.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9881163</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of CBF transcription factors in tea plants and a survey of potential CBF target genes under low temperature</article-title><source>Int. J. Mol. Sci.</source><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>5137</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms20205137</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 6829267?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6829267</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Ban</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide characterization of the c-repeat binding factor (CBF) gene family involved in the response to abiotic stresses in tea plant (<italic>Camellia sinensis</italic>)</article-title><source>Front. Plant Sci.</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>921</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2020.00921</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32849669?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32849669</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O&#x02019;Malley</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cistrome and epicistrome features shape the regulatory DNA landscape</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2016</year><volume>166</volume><fpage>1598</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2016.08.063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27610578</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schuh</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Schieberle</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of the key aroma compounds in the beverage prepared from Darjeeling black tea: quantitative differences between tea leaves and infusion</article-title><source>J. Agric. Food Chem.</source><year>2006</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>916</fpage><lpage>924</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf052495n</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16448203?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16448203</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Combinatorial evolution of a terpene synthase gene cluster explains terpene variations in Oryza</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2020</year><volume>182</volume><fpage>480</fpage><lpage>492</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.19.00948</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31712306?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31712306</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Shamala</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>XK</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of terpene synthase family genes in <italic>Camellia sinensis</italic> with an emphasis on abiotic stress conditions</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>933</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-57805-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31969641?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31969641</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Scenarios of genes-to-terpenoids network led to the identification of a novel &#x003b1;/&#x003b2;-Farnesene/&#x003b2;-ocimene synthase in <italic>Camellia sinensis</italic></article-title><source>Int. J. Mol. Sci.</source><year>2020</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>655</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms21020655</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7013532?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7013532</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldermann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recent studies of the volatile compounds in tea</article-title><source>Food Res. Int.</source><year>2013</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>585</fpage><lpage>599</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2013.02.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Headspace volatiles influenced by infusion matrix and their release persistence: a case study of oolong tea</article-title><source>Food Sci. Biotechnol.</source><year>2019</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1349</fpage><lpage>1358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10068-019-00587-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31695933?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31695933</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dolezel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Greilhuber</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Suda</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimation of nuclear DNA content in plants using flow cytometry</article-title><source>Nat. Protoc.</source><year>2007</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>2233</fpage><lpage>2244</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2007.310</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17853881?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17853881</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wenger</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Peluso</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowell</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunkapiller</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accurate circular consensus long-read sequencing improves variant detection and assembly of a human genome</article-title><source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source><year>2019</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>1155</fpage><lpage>1162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41587-019-0217-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31406327?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31406327</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Servant</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>HiC-Pro: An optimized and flexible pipeline for Hi-C data processing</article-title><source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>259</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-015-0831-x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26619908?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26619908</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Durand</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Juicer provides a one-click system for analyzing loop-resolution Hi-C experiments</article-title><source>Cell Syst.</source><year>2016</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cels.2016.07.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27467249?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27467249</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dudchenko</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>De novo assembly of the aedes aegypti genome using Hi-C yields chromosome-length scaffolds</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2017</year><volume>356</volume><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aal3327</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28336562?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28336562</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ranallo-Benavidez</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaron</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Schatz</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GenomeScope 2.0 and Smudgeplot for reference-free profiling of polyploid genomes</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1432</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-020-14998-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32188846?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32188846</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>TBtools: An integrative toolkit developed for interactive analyses of big biological data</article-title><source>Mol. Plant</source><year>2020</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1194</fpage><lpage>1202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molp.2020.06.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32585190</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Automated de novo identification of repeat sequence families in sequenced genomes</article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><year>2002</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1269</fpage><lpage>1276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.88502</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12176934?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12176934</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pevzner</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>De novo identification of repeat families in large genomes</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2005</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>351</fpage><lpage>358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bti1018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tandem repeats finder: a program to analyze DNA sequences</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>1999</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>573</fpage><lpage>580</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/27.2.573</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9862982?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9862982</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>De novo transcript sequence reconstruction from RNA-seq using the Trinity platform for reference generation and analysis</article-title><source>Nat. Protoc.</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1494</fpage><lpage>1512</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2013.084</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23845962?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23845962</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Improving the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> genome annotation using maximal transcript alignment assemblies</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>5654</fpage><lpage>5666</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkg770</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14500829?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14500829</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lomsadze</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ter-Hovhannisyan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Chernoff</surname><given-names>YO</given-names></name><name><surname>Borodovsky</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene identification in novel eukaryotic genomes by self-training algorithm</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>6494</fpage><lpage>6506</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gki937</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16314312?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16314312</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Korf</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene finding in novel genomes</article-title><source>BMC Bioinforma.</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>59</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-5-59</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stanke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x000f6;ffmann</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgenstern</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Waack</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene prediction in eukaryotes with a generalized hidden Markov model that uses hints from external sources</article-title><source>BMC Bioinforma.</source><year>2006</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>62</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-7-62</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pertea</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pertea</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Leek</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcript-level expression analysis of RNA-seq experiments with HISAT, StringTie and Ballgown</article-title><source>Nat. Protoc.</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1650</fpage><lpage>1667</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2016.095</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27560171?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27560171</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huerta Cepas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>eggNOG 5.0: a hierarchical, functionally and phylogenetically annotated orthology resource based on 5090 organisms and 2502 viruses</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2018</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>D309</fpage><lpage>D314</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gky1085</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 6324079?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6324079</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GMAP: a genomic mapping and alignment program for mRNA and EST sequences</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2005</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>1859</fpage><lpage>1875</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bti310</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15728110?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15728110</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Synteny and collinearity in plant genomes</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2008</year><volume>320</volume><fpage>486</fpage><lpage>488</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1153917</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18436778?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18436778</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kurtz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Versatile and open software for comparing large genomes</article-title><source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>R12</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2004-5-2-r12</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14759262?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14759262</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maria</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Schatz</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assemblytics: a web analytics tool for the detection of variants from an assembly</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2016</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>3021</fpage><lpage>3023</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btw369</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27318204</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>