<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName nlm2jats3.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Plant Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Plant Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-462X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8513690</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2021.740755</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Plant Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Integrated Four Comparative-Omics Reveals the Mechanism of the Terpenoid Biosynthesis in Two Different Overwintering <italic toggle="yes">Cryptomeria fortunei</italic> Phenotypes</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Yingting</given-names></name><uri xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1306367/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>Jiebing</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Hailiang</given-names></name><uri xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1221619/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>Jinyu</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Junjie</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Jin</given-names></name><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/642116/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff><institution>Key Laboratory of Forest Genetics and Biotechnology of Ministry of Education, Co-innovation Center for Sustainable Forestry in Southern China, College of Forestry, Nanjing Forestry University</institution>, <addr-line>Nanjing</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Xue-Rong Zhou, Agriculture and Food, Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation (CSIRO), Australia</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Henrik Toft Simonsen, Technical University of Denmark, Denmark; Atsushi Fukushima, RIKEN, Japan</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Jin Xu, <email>xjinhsh@njfu.edu.cn</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn004"><p>This article was submitted to Plant Metabolism and Chemodiversity, a section of the journal Frontiers in Plant Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>9</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>740755</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>7</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>8</month><year>2021</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2021 Zhang, Cui, Hu, Xue, Yang and Xu.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Zhang, Cui, Hu, Xue, Yang and Xu</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Chinese cedar (<italic toggle="yes">Cryptomeria fortunei</italic>) is a tree species with important ornamental, medicinal, and economic value. Terpenoids extracted from the essential oil of <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> needles have been considered valuable ingredients in the pharmaceutical and cosmetic industries. However, the possible gene regulation mechanisms that limit terpenoid biosynthesis in this genus are poorly understood. Here, we adopted integrated metabolome analysis, transcriptome, small-RNA (sRNA), and degradome sequencing to analyze the differences in terpenoid regulatory mechanisms in two different overwintering <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> phenotypes (wild-type and an evergreen mutant). A total of 1447/6219 differentially synthesized metabolites (DSMs)/unigenes (DEGs) were detected through metabolome/transcriptome analyses, and these DSMs/DEGs were significantly enriched in flavonoid and diterpenoid biosynthesis pathways. In <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> needles, 587 microRNAs (miRNAs), including 67 differentially expressed miRNAs (DERs), were detected. Among them, 8346 targets of 571 miRNAs were predicted using degradome data, and a 72-miRNA-target regulatory network involved in the metabolism of terpenoids and polyketides was constructed. Forty-one targets were further confirmed to be involved in terpenoid backbone and diterpenoid biosynthesis, and target analyses revealed that two miRNAs (i.e., aly-miR168a-5p and aof-miR396a) may be related to the different phenotypes and to differential regulation of diterpenoid biosynthesis. Overall, these results reveal that <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> plants with the evergreen mutation maintain high terpenoid levels in winter through miRNA-target regulation, which provides a valuable resource for essential oil-related bioengineering research.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>cold acclimation</kwd><kwd>transcriptome</kwd><kwd>degradome</kwd><kwd>diterpenoid biosynthesis</kwd><kwd>metabolome analysis</kwd><kwd>miRNA target</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001"><institution-wrap><institution>National Forestry and Grassland Administration</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100007825</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn002"><institution-wrap><institution>Priority Academic Program Development of Jiangsu Higher Education Institutions</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100012246</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn003"><institution-wrap><institution>Science and Technology Postgraduate Education and Research Development Office, Office of the Higher Education Commission</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100016176</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="8"/><table-count count="2"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="62"/><page-count count="18"/><word-count count="12177"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="S1"><title>Introduction</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Cryptomeria fortunei</italic> (Chinese cedar), an endemic to China, is an evergreen tree species of the family Taxodiaceae. It has become a main garden and timber species in southern China due to its beautiful tree shape, rapid growth and great adaptability, and it is important in ecological environment construction and wood production. Furthermore, it has high value as a traditional medicinal material. Research on the chemical components of <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> essential oil is an active field of medicinal research (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Xie et al., 2011</xref>). Studies have shown that compounds extracted from <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> essential oil have excellent detoxification, antiulcer, antioxidant, antifungal, and insecticidal properties, among others (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Matsunaga et al., 2000</xref>; <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Cheng et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2013</xref>); therefore, they have long been used as raw materials in the plant protection, pharmaceutical, and cosmetic industries. Several classes of chemical components, including (oxygenated) mono- (oxygenated), sesqui-, and (oxygenated) diterpenoids, have been shown to be present in the essential oil of <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Xie et al., 2011</xref>). In general, the functional properties of <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> essential oils benefit from the presence of a very large number of active ingredients, especially terpenes, terpene alcohols, and flavonoids (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Cheng et al., 2009</xref>). According to previous reports, within <italic toggle="yes">Cryptomeria</italic>, there are certain differences in the chemical composition of its essential oils among different species, trees of different ages and different places of production, and different tree organs or tissues (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Cheng et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Xie et al., 2011</xref>). Therefore, it is necessary to understand the mechanism underlying terpenoid synthesis in <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> and to enhance its production overall.</p><p>Among the plant specialized metabolites, terpenoids are the most diverse and abundant; to date, more than 75,000 terpenoids have been discovered (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Fujihashi et al., 2018</xref>). Although the structures of plant terpenoids vary greatly, the synthetic precursors of all plant terpenoids are the five-carbon (C5) compound isopentenyl diphosphate (IPP) and its isomer dimethylallyl diphosphate (DMAPP), which undergo rearrangement and cyclization reactions resulting in the synthesis of various terpenoid skeletons. Terpenoids can be divided into hemi- (C5), mono- (C10), sesqui- (C15), di- (C20), tri- (C30), tetra- (C40), and polyterpenoids (C &#x0003e; 40) (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Ashour et al., 2010</xref>) based on the number of C5 units contained in the molecule. Studies have shown that terpenoid synthesis involves two biosynthetic pathways: the mevalonic acid (MVA) pathway, through which sesqui- and triterpenoids are produced, and the 1-deoxy-<sc>D</sc>-xylosyl-5-phosphate (DOXP)/2-C-methyl-<sc>D</sc>-erythritol-4-phosphate (MEP) pathway, through which monoterpenoids, diterpenoids, tetraterpenoids, zeatin, and other terpenoid quinones are synthesized (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Vranov&#x000e1; et al., 2013</xref>). In the life activities of plants, terpenoids are important in signal transduction, resistance to (a)biotic stress, and biological interactions (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Izumi and Hirata, 1997</xref>; <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Grassmann et al., 2002</xref>).</p><p>MicroRNAs (miRNAs) are endogenous non-coding RNAs with a length of 21&#x02013;25 nt and play a vital regulatory role in plant growth and development and adaptation to environmental changes. Specifically, they are important in flower transformation and development, senescence, and (a)biotic stress responses (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Lu and Huang, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Song et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2013</xref>). In recent years, as high-throughput technology has developed, small-RNA (sRNA) sequencing has been widely used in the identification of plant miRNAs, including those of the camphor tree (<italic toggle="yes">Cinnamomum camphora</italic>) (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2019</xref>), Masson pine (<italic toggle="yes">Pinus massoniana</italic>) (<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Ye et al., 2020</xref>), and ginkgo (<italic toggle="yes">Ginkgo biloba</italic>) (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Jia et al., 2020</xref>). In addition, miRNAs play a very important role in regulating gene expression through their ability to shear target messenger RNAs (mRNAs) and to inhibit the translation of targeted mRNAs (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Bartel, 2004</xref>). Computer algorithms such as TargetScan (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Grimson et al., 2007</xref>), MiRanda (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Doron et al., 2008</xref>), and PicTar (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Krek et al., 2005</xref>) are the methods most commonly used to identify miRNA targets. However, the miRNA targets that are currently known are very limited and do not provide a sufficient basis for prediction, and the identification of predicted candidate genes is relatively cumbersome; therefore, it is difficult to achieve high-throughput and large-scale identification. With the emergence of degradome sequencing (degradome-seq), high-throughput identification of plant miRNA target genes has become possible; therefore, this method has been widely used to predict plant miRNA target genes. For example, <italic toggle="yes">C. camphora</italic> (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2019</xref>), <italic toggle="yes">P. massoniana</italic> (<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Ye et al., 2020</xref>), and kidney bean (<italic toggle="yes">Phaseolus vulgaris</italic>) (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Parreira et al., 2021</xref>) have all been shown to harbor a variety of miRNA targets. In recent years, the role of miRNAs and their targets in regulating the biosynthesis and accumulation of specialized metabolites such as flavonoids, terpenoids, and alkaloids in various plants has been reported. For example, in <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, miR156 targets <italic toggle="yes">squamosa promoter binding protein-like</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">SPL9</italic>) and negatively regulates (E)-&#x003b2;-caryophyllene biosynthesis (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Yu et al., 2015</xref>), and in bitter gourd (<italic toggle="yes">Picrorhiza kurroa</italic>), miR4995 targets <italic toggle="yes">3-deoxy-7-phosphoheptulonate synthase</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">DHS</italic>) and affects the production of picroside-I by regulating terpenoid biosynthesis (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Vashisht et al., 2015</xref>). However, there are few reports concerning the regulation of terpene synthesis by miRNAs and their transcription factors (TFs)/target genes in <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic>; therefore, further research is needed to better understand the regulatory role of miRNAs in the production of terpenoids.</p><p>In this study, using two phenotypes of <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> needles [normal (wild-type with yellowish-brown needles in winter, YWt) and an evergreen mutant (GM)] in winter as materials, transcriptome, and metabolome analyses were used to identify differentially synthesized metabolites (DSMs) and unigenes (DEGs), respectively. These DSMs/DEGs were significantly enriched in terpenoid-related pathways. Then, through analysis of the sRNAs and the degradome, miRNAs present in <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> needles and their targets were further identified, and the role of the miRNA-target module in terpenoid biosynthesis was analyzed. Our results reveal the presence of differential molecular mechanisms of terpenoid biosynthesis in different <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> phenotypes in winter; this finding helps direct the selection of <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> for essential oil extraction and provides a theoretical basis for its further genetic improvement to increase its terpenoid content in winter.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="S2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="S2.SS1"><title>Plant Material and Extraction of Total RNA</title><p>Two representative <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> clones with different overwintering phenotypes [#X1 (GM) and #3 (YWt)] cultivated in the Garden Experimental Teaching Center of Nanjing Forestry University (32&#x000b0;04&#x02019;41&#x02033;N, 118&#x000b0;48&#x02019;43&#x02033;E, Nanjing, Jiangsu, China) were selected as experimental materials. For each clone, needle samples were collected from among the upper and middle needles of the secondary lateral branches of 5-year-old trees. According to our previous research and related references, February is the period in which <italic toggle="yes">Cryptomeria</italic> shows the greatest phenotypic differences (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Han et al., 2003</xref>). Therefore, the needle samples were collected on February 15, 2020, and all samples were immediately stored at &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C. Three biological replicates were used as materials for transcriptomic analysis and sRNA sequencing, and six biological replicates were used for metabolome analysis (quantitative analysis of all metabolites).</p><p>Total RNA of <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> was extracted using the RNeasy Plant Mini Kit (Qiagen, Hilden, North Rhine-Westphalia, Germany) following the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. RNA integrity was evaluated with an Agilent 2100 Bioanalyzer (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA, United States), and only RNA with an RNA integrity number (RIN) value &#x0003e;7.0 was used for high-quality sequencing.</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS2"><title><italic toggle="yes">De novo</italic> Transcriptome Sequencing</title><p>Transcriptome sequencing was conducted by OE Biotech Co., Ltd. (Shanghai, China). To obtain clean reads (CRs), adaptor sequences, low-quality reads, and poly-N sequences were removed from the raw data using Trimmomatic version 0.36 (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Bolger et al., 2014</xref>) with the following parameters: LEADING: 3, TRAILING: 3, SLIDINGWINDOW: 4:15, and MINLEN: 50. The CRs were then assembled <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> into transcripts using Trinity version 2.4.0 (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Grabherr et al., 2013</xref>) in paired-end mode, with RF and SS_lib_type as the parameters. The longest transcript was selected as a unigene according to the sequence length and similarity and used in the subsequent functional annotation and expression calculation.</p><p>The unigenes were annotated through alignment with the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI)&#x02019;s non-redundant (Nr), eukaryotic orthologous groups of proteins (KOG), and SwissProt databases using blastx (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Altschul et al., 1990</xref>) with a threshold <italic toggle="yes">E</italic>-value of 10<sup>&#x02013;5</sup>. These resulting SwissProt IDs were mapped to the Gene Ontology (GO) database, and GO annotations of the unigenes were obtained. Finally, the unigenes were compared to the Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) database (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Kanehisa et al., 2008</xref>) to obtain pathway information.</p><p>The fragments per kilobase of exon model per million mapped fragments (FPKM) values (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Trapnell et al., 2010</xref>) of each unigene were calculated using bowtie2 version 2.3.3.1 (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Langmead and Salzberg, 2012</xref>). The functions estimateSizeFactors and nbinomTest in DESeq version 1.26.0 (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Anders and Huber, 2016</xref>) were used to identify DEGs, and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-values &#x0003c; 0.05 and fold change &#x0003e;2 or &#x0003c;0.5 were set as their thresholds. KEGG and GO analyses of these DEGs were performed using R according to the hypergeometric distribution to predict the biological functions and pathways mainly affected by the DEGs. Hierarchical cluster analysis of these DEGs was performed to explore the expression patterns of the related transcripts.<sup><xref rid="footnote1" ref-type="fn">1</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="S2.SS3"><title>sRNA Library Construction and Sequencing</title><p>High-quality CRs were obtained after removing adaptor sequences, sequences &#x0003c;15 or &#x0003e;41 bp in length, reads containing N bases, and low-quality sequences from the raw reads (RRs). The length distribution of CRs was determined to preliminarily evaluate the sRNA distribution of the sample. The CRs were compared to the transcriptome to determine the comparison rate. Non-coding RNAs were annotated as ribosomal RNAs (rRNAs), transfer RNAs (tRNAs), small nuclear RNAs (snRNAs), and small nucleolar RNAs (snoRNAs). The RNAs were aligned and then subjected to a blastn search (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Altschul et al., 1990</xref>) against the Rfam version 10.0<sup><xref rid="footnote2" ref-type="fn">2</xref></sup> and GenBank databases.<sup><xref rid="footnote3" ref-type="fn">3</xref></sup></p><p>Known miRNAs were identified through alignment with the miRBase database version 21.0.<sup><xref rid="footnote4" ref-type="fn">4</xref></sup> Unannotated sRNAs were analyzed using miRDeep2 version 2.0.0.8 (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Friedlnder et al., 2012</xref>) to predict novel miRNAs. The miRNA expression levels were quantified as transcripts per kilobase million (TPM) values. DESeq version 1.26.0 (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Anders and Huber, 2016</xref>) was used to standardize the expression of miRNA in each sample and to calculate the fold change, and the negative binomial distribution test method was used to test the significance of the difference in miRNA expression data. Differentially expressed miRNAs (DERs) were identified with the threshold of <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value &#x0003c; 0.05 and | log2FoldChange| &#x0003e; 1.</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS4"><title>Degradome-seq and Target Gene Identification</title><p>To construct degradation libraries, two 30-&#x003bc;g aliquots of total RNA extracted from the GM and YWt phenotypes, respectively, of <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> were purified using the Total RNA Purification Kit (LC Science, Houston, TX, United States). The mRNAs were connected to 3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032; adaptors, reverse-transcribed using a mixture of biotinylated random primers and mRNAs, and amplified by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) to complete library construction. These constructed libraries were sequenced using an Illumina HiSeq 2500 sequencer (Illumina, San Diego, CA, United States). The single-end read length was 1 &#x000d7; 50 bp, and the sequencing data contained more than 5 million reads.</p><p>The raw sequencing data were filtered using Illumina Pipeline version 1.5. The miRNA targets and their cleavage sites were predicted using the CleaveLand program version 4.0 (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Addo-Quaye et al., 2009</xref>) and mapped to the <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> transcriptome data. Based on the abundance and characteristics of superaccumulated single genes in the <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> transcriptome data, a degradome density file was established. According to the abundance of cleavage site reads (CSRs), miRNA targets can be divided into five categories as the reliability decreases: category 0 (1 maximum CSR), category 1 (&#x0003e;1 maximum CSR), category 2 (CSR abundance &#x0003e; median transcript abundance), category 3 (CSR abundance &#x02264; recorded median transcript abundance), and category 4 (1 RR containing the cleavage site). These target mRNA sequences that matched an sRNA sequence from the sequenced species were predicted by TargetFinder software (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Lavorgna et al., 1999</xref>) with default parameters. To further study miRNAs and their targets, KEGG and GO analyses were performed on all targets.<sup><xref rid="footnote5" ref-type="fn">5</xref></sup> Subsequently, these interaction relationships were applied to construct the entire miRNA&#x02013;gene interaction network, and the network was then visualized in Cytoscape version 3.5.1.<sup><xref rid="footnote6" ref-type="fn">6</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="S2.SS5"><title>Metabolomics Study</title><p>An accurately weighed 80-mg needle sample was transferred to a 1.5-mL microcentrifuge tube and extracted using 20 &#x003bc;L of 1.5 mM 2-chloro-<sc>L</sc>-phenylalanine and 1 mL of 70% methanol. The precooled sample was ground at 60 Hz for 2 min, sonicated at ambient temperature for 0.5 h, allowed to stand at &#x02212;20&#x000b0;C for 20 min, and centrifuged at 13,000 rpm at 4&#x000b0;C for 10 min. Then, 300 &#x003bc;L of the supernatant was evaporated to dryness and reconstituted with 400 &#x003bc;L of 20% methanol. The sample was vortexed well, precooled at 4&#x000b0;C for 2 min and centrifuged for 10 min. Finally, 150 &#x003bc;L of the supernatant was aspirated using a syringe, filtered, and transferred to a liquid chromatography (LC) injection bottle, and stored at &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C for liquid chromatography&#x02013;mass spectrometry (LC&#x02013;MS) determination.</p><p>An LC&#x02013;MS system consisting of an AB ExionLC ultra-high-performance LC instrument in tandem with an AB TripleTOF 6600 plus high-resolution mass spectrometer was used to analyze the metabolic spectrum in positive and negative ESI modes. An ACQUITY UPLC HSS T3 (100 mm &#x000d7; 2.1 mm, 1.8 &#x003bc;m) column was used, and water containing 0.1% formic acid and acetonitrile (<italic toggle="yes">v</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">v</italic>) was used as a binary mobile phase for gradient separation. Sample MS signal acquisition was performed in two ESI modes, and quality control (QC) samples were introduced throughout the entire analysis process to evaluate repeatability. The raw data collected by UNIFI 1.8.1 were processed by the metabolomics processing program Progenesis QI version 2.3 (Non-linear Dynamics, Newcastle, United Kingdom), and identification was then performed based on <ext-link xlink:href="http://www.hmdb.ca/" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.hmdb.ca/</ext-link>, <ext-link xlink:href="http://www.lipidmaps.org/" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.lipidmaps.org/</ext-link> and a self-built database. For the extracted data, the resulting matrix was further reduced through removing peaks for which values were missing in &#x0003e;50% of the samples. Finally, both ion mode data were merged into a table that was imported into the R ropls package.</p><p>After mean centring and Pareto variance scaling, principal component analysis (PCA) and (orthogonal) partial least squares-discriminant analysis [(O)PLS-DA] were performed to visualize the metabolic differences between the experimental groups. In the model score graph, the T2 area of Hotelling shown in the oval shape defines the 95% confidence interval of the model variables. The variable importance in the projection (VIP) ranks the overall contribution of each variable to the OPLS-DA model; VIP &#x0003e;1 indicates a potential biomarker. The default sevenfold cross-validation and 200-response permutation testing methods were used to examine the quality of the model to prevent overfitting. In addition, DSMs were selected based on a combination of the statistical significance threshold of the VIP value obtained from the OPLS-DA model and the <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value of the normalized peak area of the two-tailed Student&#x02019;s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test. Metabolites with VIP values &#x0003e;1.0 and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-values &#x0003c; 0.05 were considered DSMs. In addition, DSMs were mapped to the KEGG database to obtain their common pathway information. The KEGG IDs of the DSMs were used to perform enrichment analysis to obtain the enrichment results of the metabolic pathways. A hypergeometric test was then applied to find pathway entries that were significantly enriched in DSMs compared with the entire background metabolites. The bubble chart of KEGG pathway enrichment analysis was visualized based on <ext-link xlink:href="https://cloud.oebiotech.cn/task/" ext-link-type="uri">https://cloud.oebiotech.cn/task/</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS6"><title>Validation of DERs</title><p>Nine DERs were selected for determination of expression levels using quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR). Based on these obtained sequences, gene-specific primers were designed (<xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 1</xref>).</p><p>MicroRNAs were extracted from 0.1 g needle samples using the miRNA Isolation Kit (Tiangen Biotech Co., Nanjing, Jiangsu, China) following the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. Qualified samples that had been evaluated for integrity, purity, and concentration were used to synthesize first-strand cDNAs using the miRcute Plus miRNA First-Strand cDNA Synthesis Kit (Tiangen Biotech Co.). qRT-PCR was performed on the same instrument as that used by <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al. (2021)</xref> with the following amplification procedure: 95&#x000b0;C predenaturation for 15 min followed by 40 cycles of template denaturation and annealing; a dissociation curve was generated at 60&#x02013;95&#x000b0;C. The 2<sup>&#x02013;&#x00394;</sup>
<sup>&#x00394;</sup>
<sup>Ct</sup> method was used to calculate the relative expression levels with <italic toggle="yes">U6</italic> and cln-miR6725 as references (<xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 1</xref>). All experiments were performed in triplicate, and each sample was examined in three technical replicates.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="S3"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3.SS1"><title>Metabolomic Profiling Analysis</title><p>To investigate the metabolic differences between the <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> phenotypes, we analyzed the non-targeted metabonome of <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> needles using LC&#x02013;MS. The total ion current of 12 samples showed large peak capacity and excellent retention time reproducibility (<xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 1</xref>), indicating that the difference between biological replicates and the error caused by the instrument were both small. In these needles, a total of 9251 compounds with definite formulas were identified (MTBLS3183), and the parameters for metabolite annotation were described according to the guideline by <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Fernie et al. (2011)</xref>, including 5815 lipid-like molecules, accounting for 62.86% of all metabolites. Among them, 173 metabolites were identified as terpenoids, including 87 sesqui-, 35 di-, 32 mono-, 18 tri-, and 1 polyterpenoid(s) (<xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 2</xref>). PCA and (O)PLS-DA accurately divided all the samples into two different clusters, reflecting the obvious difference between green and yellow needles (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figures 1A&#x02013;C</xref>). The accuracy of the OPLS-DA model was also tested using sevenfold cross-validation (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1D</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>Multivariate statistical analysis of the metabolome and differentially synthesized metabolites (DSMs). Plots of principal component analysis (PCA) <bold>(A)</bold>, partial least squares discriminant analysis (PLS-DA) <bold>(B)</bold>, and orthogonal PLS-DA (OPLS-DA) <bold>(C)</bold>. <bold>(A,B)</bold> The <italic toggle="yes">x</italic>- and <italic toggle="yes">y</italic>-axes represent the first (PC1) and the second (PC2) principal components, respectively; <bold>(C)</bold> the <italic toggle="yes">x</italic>- and <italic toggle="yes">y</italic>-axes represent predictive principal components and orthogonal principal components, respectively. <bold>(D)</bold> The 200-response sorting tests of the OPLS-DA model. <bold>(E)</bold> Hierarchical clustering heatmap of DSMs. Each column and row represent a sample and a differentially expressed unigene (DEG), respectively, and the colors indicate the expression levels of DSMs. GM, evergreen mutant; YWt, yellowish-brown needles in winter; GM_1, GM_2, GM_3, GM_4, GM_5, and GM_6 represent six repetitions.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-12-740755-g001" position="float"/></fig><p>A total of 1447 DSMs were detected by combining single- and multidimensional analysis; these DSMs included 31 terpenoids (10 di-, 6 mono-, and 15 sesquiterpenoids) (<xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 3</xref>), and the synthesis of most metabolites was enhanced in GM (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1E</xref> and <xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 4</xref>). In addition, 111 DSMs were enriched in 56 metabolic pathways, of which the top three were &#x0201c;arachidonic acid metabolism&#x0201d; (ath00590), &#x0201c;flavonoid biosynthesis&#x0201d; (ko00941), and &#x0201c;diterpenoid biosynthesis&#x0201d; (ko00904) (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). Therefore, we preliminarily speculated that <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> that display different phenotypes may differentially accumulate these metabolites.</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p>Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes analysis of differentially synthesized metabolites (DSMs). The <italic toggle="yes">x</italic>- and <italic toggle="yes">y</italic>-axes represent the enrichment factor and the pathway term, respectively. The colors and sizes of the dots represent the significance (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>) and the number of metabolites, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-12-740755-g002" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="S3.SS2"><title>Assembly, Annotation, and Enrichment Analysis of the <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> Transcriptome</title><p>To identify genes expressed in <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> needles, six transcriptome libraries (GM_1, GM_2, GM_3, YWt_1, YWt_2, and YWt_3) were generated using total RNA extracted from three biological replicates of each phenotype. A total of 304.79 M RRs were obtained, and the sequencing results were submitted to the NCBI database under registration number PRJNA697258 (SAMN17672908&#x02013;17672913). The low-quality sequences were filtered out, and in total, 302.75 M CRs were obtained; the Q30 (%) was &#x0003e;95.57%, and the gas chromatography (GC) content was 44.19&#x02013;44.33% (<xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 5</xref>). Then, 55,839 single unigenes (submission number: SUB10083705, <xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Tables 6</xref>, <xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">7</xref>) were assembled using Trinity software. The N50 value and the average length were 1219.86 and 1990 bp, respectively. The unigenes expressed in the GM and YWt samples clearly aggregated into different clusters, indicating that the biological reproducibility was good and that the samples could be used for subsequent analysis (<xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 2</xref>). Finally, through BLAST comparison with seven public databases, a total of 27,769 single unigenes were annotated, of which 27,144 unigenes that significantly matched the Nr database accounted for the highest percentage of the total (48.61%) (<xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Tables 6</xref>, <xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">8</xref>).</p><p>In total, 6219 DEGs were detected when the GM and YWt libraries were compared; these included 3096 upregulated and 3123 downregulated DEGs (<xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 3</xref>). Classification of these DEGs by GO function yielded 1950 DEGs, including 913 upregulated and 1037 downregulated DEGs. The enrichment histogram showed that the most enriched category was &#x0201c;biological process&#x0201d; (BP), followed by &#x0201c;cellular component&#x0201d; (CC) and &#x0201c;molecular function&#x0201d; (MF) (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>). In BP, the most enriched subcategory was &#x0201c;biological regulation,&#x0201d; followed by &#x0201c;metabolic process&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;response to stimulus&#x0201d;; &#x0201c;cell,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;cell part,&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;organelle&#x0201d;; and &#x0201c;binding,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;catalytic activity,&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;transporter activity&#x0201d; were the three most enriched subcategories in CC and MF, respectively. Directed acyclic graphs were used to display the results of the GO structure, and the GO terms were enriched in the following order: CC, MF, and BP (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3B</xref>). A total of 669 DEGs were enriched in KEGG pathways; the most significantly enriched pathway was &#x0201c;carbohydrate metabolism,&#x0201d; followed by &#x0201c;biosynthesis of other specialized metabolites&#x0201d; (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3C</xref>); 805 DEGs were enriched for 112 KEGG terms, and the most highly enriched ones were &#x0201c;phenylpropanoid and flavonoid biosynthesis,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;glutathione metabolism,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;plant-pathogen interaction,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;cyanoamino acid metabolism,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;starch and sucrose metabolism,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;brassinosteroid biosynthesis,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;fructose and mannose metabolism,&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;diterpenoid biosynthesis&#x0201d; (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3D</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>FIGURE 3</label><caption><p>Functional classification of differentially expressed unigenes (DEGs). <bold>(A)</bold> Comparison of the distribution of DEGs at the GO level. Red/green indicates GO entries enriched for up-/downregulated DEGs; the <italic toggle="yes">x</italic>-axis is the name of the entry, and the <italic toggle="yes">y</italic>-axis represents the number of unigenes in the corresponding entry and its percentage. <bold>(B)</bold> Directed acyclic graphs of three main categories. The 10 most significant nodes are represented by rectangles; the colors of the rectangles represent the significance of enrichment, and the significance increases as the color changes from yellow to red. The basic information on each node is displayed in the corresponding graph. <bold>(C)</bold> KEGG distribution map of DEGs. The <italic toggle="yes">x</italic>-axis shows the up- and downregulated DEGs annotated to each pathway and all these DEGs annotated to the KEGG pathway to the total number (%); the <italic toggle="yes">y</italic>-axis indicates the name of the pathway, and the number on the right side of the column indicates the number of DEGs annotated to each pathway. <bold>(D)</bold> KEGG enrichment analysis of DEGs. The <italic toggle="yes">x</italic>- and <italic toggle="yes">y</italic>-axes represent the enrichment score and the pathway term, respectively. The colors and sizes of the dots represent the significance (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>) and the number of unigenes, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-12-740755-g003" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="S3.SS3"><title>High-Throughput sRNA Sequencing</title><p>To identify the DERs related to the phenotypic differences between the two <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> strains, six independent sRNA libraries were generated in February, and the sequencing results were submitted to the NCBI database; the sequence read file registration number is PRJNA720228 (SAMN18644350&#x02013;18644352, 18644359&#x02013;18644361). A total of 254.59 M RRs were obtained, and 21.00&#x02013;26.99 M CRs were obtained in each library after removal of low-quality reads, poly-N sequences, adaptor sequences, and reads &#x0003c;15 or &#x0003e;41 bp in length (<xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 9</xref>). A total of 120,677,469 reads were mapped to the aforementioned transcriptome; approximately 0.146% (208,203) of the sRNA reads were mapped to non-coding RNAs (i.e., rRNAs, tRNAs, snRNAs, and <italic toggle="yes">cis</italic>-regulatory elements) in the Pfam database, and an average of 465,479.33 localization reads in each library were recognized as known miRNAs (<xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 9</xref>). The most abundant sequence among the <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> sRNAs was the 21-nt sRNA tag (<xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 4</xref>).</p><p>A total of 587 miRNAs were detected; 439 were expressed in both phenotypes, and 67 and 81 were expressed in only GM or YWt, respectively (<xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 5A</xref>). A total of 391 miRNAs were identified as known miRNAs, 359 of which were distributed in 40 miRNA families (<xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 5B</xref>). Sixty-seven DERs showed significant differences between the two phenotypes, including 29 downregulated and 38 upregulated miRNAs in GM (<xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 6</xref>). Nine DERs were selected for qRT-PCR, and the expression profile of each miRNA was consistent with the sRNA-seq data (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>), verifying the reliability of the sRNA results.</p><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>FIGURE 4</label><caption><p>Quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR) validation of selected DERs. The <italic toggle="yes">x</italic>- and <italic toggle="yes">y</italic>-axes represent the sample (GM, evergreen mutant; YWt, yellowish-brown needles in winter) and the transcripts per kilobase million (TPM) or relative expression level, and the values shown represent the mean &#x000b1; SD; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-12-740755-g004" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="S3.SS4"><title>miRNA Targets Identified Through Degradome-seq</title><p>In total, 84,600,973 RRs were obtained from both GM and YWt degradomes, representing 9,473,983 and 31,301,265 unique RRs, respectively (<xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 10</xref>). After removal of the 3&#x02032; adaptor and shorter cut label reads (&#x0003c;15 nt), 7,223,211 (76.24% of the unique mappable reads) and 5,795,795 (18.52%) unique reads were successfully mapped to 42,337 (75.82% of all 55,839 reference transcriptomes) and 41,195 (73.77%) single genes, respectively (<xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 10</xref>).</p><p>A total of 8346 target sites were identified for 571 miRNAs (<xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 7</xref>); these included 3910 targets of 375 known miRNAs and 4436 targets of 196 novel miRNAs. In GM, 2389 (28.62%) targets belonged to category 0, 1, or 2, and 3644 targets were classified into category 3 or 4, while in YWt, 2019 (24.19%), the targets belonged to category 0, 1, or 2, and 3068 targets were classified into the other two categories (<xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 11</xref>). It is worth noting that a certain miRNA was involved in regulating multiple targets. For example, gma-miR396h, gma-miR6300, novel116_star, novel132_mature, novel20_star, novel59_mature, novel72_star, and osa-miR414 had more than 80 targets. In contrast, single genes are usually regulated by multiple miRNAs. For example, <italic toggle="yes">TRINITY_DN8796_c0_g1_i1_2</italic> may be regulated by aly-miR166b-5p, aly-miR396b-5p, gma-miR396h, and hbr-miR396a. In addition, some targets were annotated as TFs in <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic>, such as <italic toggle="yes">APETALA2</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">AP2</italic>) and <italic toggle="yes">v-myb avian myeloblastosis viral oncogene homolog</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">MYB</italic>), indicating that <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> miRNAs may have the ability to target TF gene families.</p></sec><sec id="S3.SS5"><title>Enrichment Analyses of miRNA Targets</title><p>The functions of all targets were divided into three categories that included 54 GO terms by GO analysis. In BP, &#x0201c;cellular process,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;single-organism process,&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;metabolic process&#x0201d; had the highest number of target genes; in CC, the targets were mainly involved in &#x0201c;cell&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;cell part,&#x0201d; and in MF, the targets were mostly divided into &#x0201c;binding&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;catalytic activity&#x0201d; components (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>FIGURE 5</label><caption><p>Gene Ontology classification of targets in <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic>. The <italic toggle="yes">x</italic>-axis is the entry name, and the <italic toggle="yes">y</italic>-axis represents the number of genes in the corresponding entry.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-12-740755-g005" position="float"/></fig><p>Based on the KEGG analysis, these targets were matched to five categories: &#x0201c;genetic information processing,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;metabolism,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;organismal systems,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;cellular processes,&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;environmental information processing&#x0201d;; these categories represented 19 metabolic pathways. Among these pathways, &#x0201c;global and overview maps&#x0201d; (676), &#x0201c;carbohydrate metabolism&#x0201d; (254), and &#x0201c;translation&#x0201d; (239) were the most abundant (<xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 8A</xref>). In addition, 72 and 48 targets were annotated to &#x0201c;metabolism of terpenoids and polyketides (TP)&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;biosynthesis of other specialized metabolites,&#x0201d; respectively (<xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 8A</xref>). Notably, metabolism was the category with the highest number of annotated pathways. In metabolism, &#x0201c;genetic information processing and organismal systems,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;sesquiterpenoid and triterpenoid biosynthesis&#x0201d; (ko00909, 55.6%), &#x0201c;proteasome&#x0201d; (ko03050, 43.1%), and &#x0201c;circadian rhythm-plant&#x0201d; (ko04712, 48.9%) had the highest proportions of targets in each pathway (<xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 8B</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S3.SS6"><title>Comprehensive Analysis of TP</title><p>The metabolome, transcriptome, and miRNA target analyses described above showed that terpenoid and polyketide biosynthesis was significantly enriched. Therefore, we next focused on analyzing these metabolic pathways.</p><p>The miRNA targets related to the metabolism of TP mainly included nine main pathways, among which &#x0201c;terpenoid backbone biosynthesis,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;carotenoid biosynthesis,&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;diterpenoid biosynthesis&#x0201d; (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) were more enriched; targets involved in &#x0201c;terpenoid backbone biosynthesis&#x0201d; (23, 31.94%), &#x0201c;carotenoid biosynthesis&#x0201d; (16, 22.22%), and &#x0201c;diterpenoid biosynthesis&#x0201d; (8, 11.11%) accounted for more than 65% of the total targets (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref> and <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). We measured the levels of metabolites related to TP and found that except for the metabolites related to carotenoid biosynthesis, which were reduced in GM, most of the metabolites were significantly enhanced in GM (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). In particular, in the diterpenoid biosynthesis pathway, the levels of gibberellin A14 and gibberellin A53 aldehydes exceeded the sum of the levels of the other 20 metabolites, and the levels of these metabolites in GM were 14.14 and 8.46 times those in YWt, respectively (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>TABLE 1</label><caption><p>MicroRNAs target functions involved in the metabolism of terpenoids and polyketides.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pathway</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene number</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unigene</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Terpenoid backbone biosynthesis</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN25002_c0_g2_i1_3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">atoB</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN26290_c0_g2_i2_2</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN22892_c0_g1_i8_1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">DHDDS</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN14808_c0_g1_i1_3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">DXS</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN24104_c0_g1_i15_1</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN26364_c0_g1_i1_3</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN11334_c0_g1_i2_3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">FDPS</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN23287_c0_g1_i4_1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">FNTA</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN26775_c0_g1_i15_2</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN22784_c0_g2_i1_3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">FOLK</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN28038_c0_g1_i4_2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">gcpE</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN14344_c0_g1_i1_3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">GGPS</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN17191_c0_g1_i1_1</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN25852_c0_g1_i1_2</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN14418_c0_g1_i1_3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">GPS</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN27103_c0_g1_i13_1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">HMGCR</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN27185_c0_g2_i2_3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">HMGCS</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN27344_c0_g2_i7_1</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN6885_c0_g1_i1_1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">ispD</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN26502_c0_g1_i2_1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">ispH</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN28637_c0_g1_i1_3</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN6836_c0_g1_i1_1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">ispS</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN9031_c0_g1_i1_3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">MVD</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carotenoid biosynthesis</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN24797_c0_g1_i6_2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">CHYB</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN20337_c0_g1_i5_3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">crtB</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN23115_c0_g1_i2_1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">crtZ</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN18752_c0_g1_i2_3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">CYP97C1</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN20920_c0_g1_i1_1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">ECA4</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN21486_c0_g1_i1_1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">lcyB</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN27821_c0_g1_i8_2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">lcyE</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN28603_c0_g2_i1_2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">NCED</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN25721_c0_g1_i1_3</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN15115_c0_g1_i1_3</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN21999_c0_g1_i2_3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">PDS</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN7562_c0_g1_i1_3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">VDE</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN19004_c0_g1_i2_3</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN19208_c0_g1_i6_3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">ZDS</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN24472_c0_g1_i7_1</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN21855_c0_g1_i2_2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">ZEP</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diterpenoid biosynthesis</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN25477_c0_g1_i1_3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">(13E)-labda-7,13-dien-17-ol synthase</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN26490_c0_g1_i9_3</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN27239_c0_g1_i2_2</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN27939_c0_g1_i4_3</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN29593_c0_g1_i2_2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">CPSent</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN29820_c0_g1_i21_2</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN30241_c0_g1_i2_2</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN30372_c1_g1_i15_2</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brassinosteroid biosynthesis</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN29137_c0_g1_i5_2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">BAS1</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN21161_c0_g1_i2_3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">CPD</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN19646_c0_g1_i3_2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">CYP90D1</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN22770_c0_g1_i6_3</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN23701_c0_g1_i8_1</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN16116_c0_g1_i4_2</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN19591_c0_g1_i1_2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">DET2</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN31028_c0_g1_i1_2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">DWF4</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zeatin biosynthesis</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN11266_c0_g1_i3_1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">CYP735A</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN14604_c0_g1_i2_3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">miaA</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN15706_c0_g1_i1_3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">CKX</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN18651_c0_g1_i4_3</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN26430_c1_g1_i4_3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">CISZOG</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN26700_c0_g1_i7_1</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN28118_c0_g3_i1_3</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sesquiterpenoid and triterpenoid biosynthesis</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN23474_c0_g1_i1_1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">GDS</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN28996_c0_g1_i3_2</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN26528_c0_g1_i6_1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">FDFT1</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN30068_c0_g2_i4_2</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN25360_c0_g1_i1_3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">SQLE</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monoterpenoid biosynthesis</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN26243_c0_g3_i8_1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">MD</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN30477_c0_g1_i4_2</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN30477_c0_g2_i2_2</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polyketide sugar unit biosynthesis</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN26730_c0_g1_i3_2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">gmer</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limonene and pinene degradation</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRINITY_DN17042_c0_g1_i2_3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">ALDH</italic>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t1fn1"><p>
<italic toggle="yes">atoB, acetyl-CoA C-acetyltransferase; <italic toggle="yes">ALDH</italic>, aldehyde dehydrogenase (NAD+); <italic toggle="yes">BAS1</italic>, PHYB activation tagged suppressor 1; <italic toggle="yes">CHYB</italic>, beta-ring hydroxylase; <italic toggle="yes">CISZOG</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">cis</italic>-zeatin <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-glucosyltransferase; <italic toggle="yes">CKX</italic>, cytokinin dehydrogenase; <italic toggle="yes">CPD</italic>, cytochrome P450 family 90 subfamily A polypeptide 1; <italic toggle="yes">CPSent</italic>, ent-copalyl diphosphate synthase; <italic toggle="yes">crtB</italic>, 15-<italic toggle="yes">cis</italic>-phytoene synthase; <italic toggle="yes">crtZ</italic>, beta-carotene 3-hydroxylase; <italic toggle="yes">CYP735A</italic>, cytokinin <italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-hydroxylase; <italic toggle="yes">CYP97C1</italic>, carotene epsilon-monooxygenase; <italic toggle="yes">CYP90D1</italic>, 3-epi-6-deoxocathasterone 23-monooxygenase; <italic toggle="yes">DET2</italic>, steroid 5-alpha-reductase; <italic toggle="yes">DHDDS</italic>, ditrans, polycis-polyprenyl diphosphate synthase; <italic toggle="yes">DWF4</italic>, steroid 22-alpha-hydroxylase; <italic toggle="yes">DXS</italic>, 1-deoxy-<sc>D</sc>-xylulose-5-phosphate synthase; <italic toggle="yes">ECA4</italic>, Ca<sup>2+</sup>-transporting ATPase; <italic toggle="yes">FDFT1</italic>, farnesyl-diphosphate farnesyltransferase; <italic toggle="yes">FDPS</italic>, farnesyl diphosphate synthase; <italic toggle="yes">FNTA</italic>, protein farnesyltransferase/geranylgeranyltransferase type-1 subunit alpha; <italic toggle="yes">FOLK</italic>, farnesol kinase; <italic toggle="yes">gcpE</italic>, (E)-4-hydroxy-3-methylbut-2-enyl-diphosphate synthase; <italic toggle="yes">GDS</italic>, (&#x02212;)-germacrene D synthase; <italic toggle="yes">GGPS</italic>, geranylgeranyl diphosphate synthase; <italic toggle="yes">gmer</italic>, 3,5-epimerase/4-reductase; <italic toggle="yes">GPS</italic>, all-<italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-non-aprenyl-diphosphate synthase; <italic toggle="yes">HMGCR</italic>, hydroxymethylglutaryl-CoA reductase (NADPH); <italic toggle="yes">HMGCS</italic>, hydroxymethylglutaryl-CoA synthase; <italic toggle="yes">ispD</italic>, 2-C-methyl-<sc>D</sc>-erythritol 4-phosphate cytidylyltransferase; <italic toggle="yes">ispH</italic>, 4-hydroxy-3-methylbut-2-en-1-yl diphosphate reductase; <italic toggle="yes">ispS</italic>, isoprene synthase; <italic toggle="yes">lcyB</italic>, lycopene beta-cyclase; <italic toggle="yes">lcyE</italic>, lycopene epsilon-cyclase; <italic toggle="yes">miaA</italic>, tRNA dimethylallyltransferase; <italic toggle="yes">MD</italic>, (+)-neomenthol dehydrogenase; <italic toggle="yes">MVD</italic>, diphosphomevalonate decarboxylase; <italic toggle="yes">NCED</italic>, 9-<italic toggle="yes">cis</italic>-epoxycarotenoid dioxygenase; <italic toggle="yes">PDS</italic>, 15-<italic toggle="yes">cis</italic>-phytoene desaturase; <italic toggle="yes">SQLE</italic>, squalene monooxygenase; <italic toggle="yes">VDE</italic>, violaxanthin de-epoxidase; <italic toggle="yes">ZDS</italic>, zeta-carotene desaturase; <italic toggle="yes">ZEP</italic>, zeaxanthin epoxidase.</italic>
</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>TABLE 2</label><caption><p>Metabolites in terpenoids and polyketides.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolite</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Annotation</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GM</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">YWt</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Teasterone</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brassinosteroid biosynthesis</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.34 &#x000b1; 5.32</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08 &#x000b1; 1.24</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8&#x02032;-Hydroxyabscisate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carotenoid biosynthesis</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 &#x000b1; 0.55</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.79 &#x000b1; 17.82</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abscisic acid glucose ester</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37 &#x000b1; 0.77</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strigolactone ABC-rings</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57 &#x000b1; 0.88</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.42 &#x000b1; 4.38</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Xanthoxin</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 &#x000b1; 0.90</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.59 &#x000b1; 5.29</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(+)-Sandaracopimaradiene</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diterpenoid biosynthesis</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.58 &#x000b1; 2.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.93 &#x000b1; 1.23</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10-Deacetyl-2-debenzoylbaccatin III</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.41 &#x000b1; 2.49</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22 &#x000b1; 0.08</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10-Deacetylbaccatin III</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.63 &#x000b1; 1.94</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gibberellin A12</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.99 &#x000b1; 3.73</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.77 &#x000b1; 2.29</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gibberellin A14</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1894.47 &#x000b1; 173.60</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134.02 &#x000b1; 28.60</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gibberellin A3</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">393.68 &#x000b1; 39.33</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.30 &#x000b1; 11.36</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gibberellin A34</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.65 &#x000b1; 1.87</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">139.91 &#x000b1; 5.77</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gibberellin A53 aldehyde</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1298.52 &#x000b1; 35.72</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">153.51 &#x000b1; 35.72</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gibberellin A8-catabolite</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.34 &#x000b1; 1.59</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.81 &#x000b1; 2.63</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isopimaric acid</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.97 &#x000b1; 28.49</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nocardicin C</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monobactam biosynthesis</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">355.91 &#x000b1; 28.94</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.27 &#x000b1; 13.83</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(5R)-albaflavenol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sesquiterpenoid and triterpenoid biosynthesis</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.78 &#x000b1; 7.28</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.76 &#x000b1; 3.78</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(5S)-albaflavenol</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.25 &#x000b1; 3.23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.70 &#x000b1; 3.83</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gossypol</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.40 &#x000b1; 3.49</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.63 &#x000b1; 0.32</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All-<italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-heptaprenyl diphosphate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Terpenoid backbone biosynthesis</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">282.89 &#x000b1; 29.65</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coenzyme Q9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ubiquinone and other terpenoid-quinone biosynthesis</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.60 &#x000b1; 10.56</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.87 &#x000b1; 2.82</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deoxyshikonin</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.04 &#x000b1; 3.40</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32 &#x000b1; 0.49</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dihydrozeatin-O-glucoside</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zeatin biosynthesis</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">155.28 &#x000b1; 5.57</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.50 &#x000b1; 2.14</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t2fn1"><p>
<italic toggle="yes">The relative quantitative results (no unit) were calculated based on the peak area, and the values are the average of six replicate (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6) values. GM, #X1, evergreen mutant; YWt, #3, yellowish-brown needles in winter.</italic>
</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>FIGURE 6</label><caption><p>MicroRNA regulatory network involved in the metabolism of terpenoids and polyketides. The red squares indicate metabolic pathways, the yellow triangles indicate genes, and the blue circles indicate miRNAs. The dotted lines with arrows indicate how the miRNAs regulate specific genes. The abbreviation of each gene is as follows: <italic toggle="yes">AACT</italic>, acetyl-CoA C-acetyltransferase; <italic toggle="yes">ALDH</italic>, aldehyde dehydrogenase; <italic toggle="yes">BAS1</italic>, PHYB activation tagged suppressor 1; <italic toggle="yes">CHYB</italic>, beta-ring hydroxylase; <italic toggle="yes">CISZOG</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">cis</italic>-zeatin <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-glucosyltransferase; <italic toggle="yes">CKX</italic>, cytokinin dehydrogenase; <italic toggle="yes">CPD</italic>, cytochrome P450 family 90 subfamily A polypeptide 1; <italic toggle="yes">CPSent</italic>, ent-copalyl diphosphate synthase; <italic toggle="yes">crtB</italic>, 15-<italic toggle="yes">cis</italic>-phytoene synthase; <italic toggle="yes">crtZ</italic>, beta-carotene 3-hydroxylase; <italic toggle="yes">CYP735A</italic>, cytokinin <italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-hydroxylase; <italic toggle="yes">CYP90D1</italic>, 3-epi-6-deoxocathasterone 23-monooxygenase; <italic toggle="yes">CYP97C1</italic>, carotene epsilon-monooxygenase; <italic toggle="yes">DET2</italic>, steroid 5-alpha-reductase; <italic toggle="yes">DHDDS</italic>, ditrans, polycis-polyprenyl diphosphate synthase; <italic toggle="yes">DMAPP-tRNA transferase</italic>, tRNA dimethylallyltransferase; <italic toggle="yes">DWF4</italic>, steroid 22-alpha-hydroxylase; <italic toggle="yes">DXS</italic>, 1-deoxy-<sc>D</sc>-xylulose-5-phosphate synthase; <italic toggle="yes">ECA4</italic>, Ca<sup>2+</sup>-transporting ATPase; <italic toggle="yes">FDFT1</italic>, farnesyl-diphosphate farnesyltransferase; <italic toggle="yes">FDPS</italic>, farnesyl diphosphate synthase; <italic toggle="yes">FNTA</italic>, protein farnesyltransferase/geranylgeranyltransferase type-1 subunit alpha; <italic toggle="yes">FOLK</italic>, farnesol kinase; <italic toggle="yes">GDS</italic>, (&#x02013;)-germacrene D synthase; <italic toggle="yes">gcpE</italic>, (E)-4-hydroxy-3-methylbut-2-enyl-diphosphate synthase; <italic toggle="yes">gmer</italic>, GDP-4-keto-6-deoxy-<sc>D</sc>-mannose-3,5-epimerase-4-reductase; <italic toggle="yes">GGPS</italic>, geranyl diphosphate synthase; <italic toggle="yes">HMGCR</italic>, hydroxymethylglutaryl-CoA reductase; <italic toggle="yes">HMGCS</italic>, hydroxymethylglutaryl-CoA synthase; <italic toggle="yes">ispD</italic>, 2-C-methyl-<sc>D</sc>-erythritol 4-phosphate cytidylyltransferase; <italic toggle="yes">ispH</italic>, 4-hydroxy-3-methylbut-2-en-1-yl diphosphate reductase; <italic toggle="yes">ispS</italic>, isoprene synthase; <italic toggle="yes">lcyB</italic>, lycopene beta-cyclase; <italic toggle="yes">lcyE</italic>, lycopene epsilon-cyclase; <italic toggle="yes">MD</italic>, (+)-neomenthol dehydrogenase; <italic toggle="yes">miaA</italic>, tRNA dimethylallyltransferase; <italic toggle="yes">MVD</italic>, diphosphomevalonate decarboxylase; <italic toggle="yes">NCED</italic>, 9-<italic toggle="yes">cis</italic>-epoxycarotenoid dioxygenase; <italic toggle="yes">PDS</italic>, 15-<italic toggle="yes">cis</italic>-phytoene desaturase; <italic toggle="yes">GPS</italic>, geranyl-diphosphate specific/all-<italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-non-aprenyl-diphosphate synthase; <italic toggle="yes">SQLE</italic>, squalene monooxygenase; <italic toggle="yes">VDE</italic>, violaxanthin de-epoxidase; <italic toggle="yes">ZDS</italic>, zeta-carotene desaturase; <italic toggle="yes">ZEP</italic>, zeaxanthin epoxidase.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-12-740755-g006" position="float"/></fig><p>Based on these findings, we inferred that diterpenoid biosynthesis (including biosynthesis of the terpenoid backbone) is important in the formation of evergreen mutations in GM. Forty-one miRNA targets were related to terpenoid backbone and diterpenoid biosynthesis (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7A</xref>). Thirty-one target pairs, including eight known miRNA targets [atr-miR396d-geranylgeranyl diphosphate synthase (<italic toggle="yes">GGPS</italic>), gma-miR6300-hydroxymethylglutaryl-CoA reductase (<italic toggle="yes">HMGCR</italic>), 2 gra-miR482-farnesyltransferase/geranylgeranyltransferase type-1 subunit alpha (<italic toggle="yes">FNTA</italic>), mtr-miR5261-geranyl-diphosphate specific/all-<italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-non-aprenyl-diphosphate synthase (<italic toggle="yes">GPS</italic>), pab-miR394a-isoprene synthase (<italic toggle="yes">ispS</italic>), vvi-miR159a-ditrans, polycis-polyprenyl diphosphate synthase (<italic toggle="yes">DHDDS</italic>), and vvi-miR172a-diphosphomevalonate decarboxylase (<italic toggle="yes">MVD</italic>)], were related to terpenoid backbone biosynthesis. Among them, the DEG <italic toggle="yes">ispS</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">TRINITY_DN6836_c0_g1_i1_1</italic>) cleaved by novel106_mature and pab-miR394a was identified as participating in &#x0201c;isoprene synthesis&#x0201d; (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7B</xref>). Twenty-three novel miRNA targets were related to terpenoid backbone biosynthesis, which included only contains three DERs (novel59_mature, novel106_mature, and novel5_star), and they were all highly expressed in GM; however, their targets were not significantly expressed (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7B</xref>). Ten target pairs were identified as being involved in diterpenoid biosynthesis, namely, 6 <italic toggle="yes">ent-copalyl diphosphate synthase</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">ent</italic>) target genes cut by aly-miR168a-5p, aof-miR396a, gma-miR395d, novel28_mature, novel29_mature, and novel40_star and 4 <italic toggle="yes">(13E)-labda-7,13-dien-15-ol synthase</italic> target genes cut by novel59_mature, pta-miR1314, and cme-miR828 (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7C</xref>). Among them, aly-miR168a-5p, aof-miR396a, and novel40_star were significantly upregulated (by 361.635, 29.540, and 20.516%, respectively) in YWt compared with GM, while others (gma-miR395d, novel28_mature, novel29_mature, novel59_mature, pta-miR1314, and cme-miR828) were significantly upregulated in GM (28.144&#x02013;52.122%). It is worth noting that the targets of aly-miR168a-5p, aof-miR396a, novel59_mature, and cme-miR828 were significantly upregulated (by 40.144&#x02013;163.608%) in GM compared with YWt.</p><fig position="float" id="F7"><label>FIGURE 7</label><caption><p>Analysis of miRNA targets involved in terpenoid and polyketide biosynthesis (TPB). <bold>(A)</bold> miRNA targets involved in TPB. miRNA cleavage is indicated by solid lines with red &#x0201c;T&#x0201d; arrows. miRNA targets involved in TPB <bold>(B)</bold> and diterpenoid biosynthesis <bold>(C)</bold>. The pseudo-color bar at the bottom of the middle represents the fragments per kilobase of exon per million (FPKM) value, GM, evergreen mutant; YWt, yellowish-brown needles in winter. The abbreviation of each gene/metabolite is as follows: <italic toggle="yes">atoB</italic>, acetyl-CoA acetyltransferase; <italic toggle="yes">CMK</italic>, 4-(cytidine 5-diphospho)-2-C-methyl-<sc>D</sc>-erythritol kinase; <italic toggle="yes">CPSent</italic>, ent-copalyl diphosphate synthase; <italic toggle="yes">crtB</italic>, 15-<italic toggle="yes">cis</italic>-phytoene synthase; <italic toggle="yes">DHDDS</italic>, ditrans, polycis-polyprenyl diphosphate synthase; <italic toggle="yes">DMAPP</italic>, dimethylallyl diphosphate; <italic toggle="yes">DXR</italic>, 1-deoxy-<sc>D</sc>-xylulose 5-phosphate reductoisomerase; <italic toggle="yes">DXS</italic>, 1-deoxy-<sc>D</sc>-xylulose-5-phosphate synthase; <italic toggle="yes">FDPS</italic>, farnesyl diphosphate synthase; <italic toggle="yes">FNTA</italic>, protein farnesyltransferase/geranylgeranyltransferase type-1 subunit alpha; <italic toggle="yes">FOLK</italic>, farnesol kinase; <italic toggle="yes">FPP</italic>, farnesyl diphosphate; <italic toggle="yes">FPPS</italic>, farnesyl pyrophosphate synthase; <italic toggle="yes">gcpE</italic>, (E)-4-hydroxy-3-methylbut-2-enyl-diphosphate synthase; <italic toggle="yes">GGPP</italic>, geranylgeranyl diphosphate; <italic toggle="yes">GGPS</italic>, geranylgeranyl diphosphate synthase; <italic toggle="yes">GPP</italic>, geranyl pyrophosphate; <italic toggle="yes">HDR</italic>, 4-hydroxy-3-methylbut-2-enyl diphosphate reductase; <italic toggle="yes">HMBPP</italic>, (E)-4-hydroxy-3-methyl-but-2-enyl pyrophosphate; <italic toggle="yes">HMGCR</italic>, hydroxymethylglutaryl-CoA reductase; <italic toggle="yes">HMGCS</italic>, hydroxymethylglutaryl-CoA synthase; <italic toggle="yes">IDI</italic>, isopentenyl diphosphate isomerase; <italic toggle="yes">IPP</italic>, isopentenyl diphosphate; <italic toggle="yes">iSPD</italic>, 2-C-methyl-<sc>D</sc>-erythritol 4-phosphate cytidylyltransferase; <italic toggle="yes">iSPH</italic>, 4-hydroxy-3-methylbut-2-en-1-yl diphosphate reductase; <italic toggle="yes">iSPS</italic>, isoprene synthase; <italic toggle="yes">MCS</italic>, 2-C-methyl-<sc>D</sc>-erythritol 2,4-cyclodiphosphate synthase; MEP/DOXP, 2-C-methyl-<sc>D</sc>-erythritol 4-phosphate/1-deoxy-<sc>D</sc>-xylulose 5-phosphate; <italic toggle="yes">MVD</italic>, diphosphomevalonate decarboxylase; <italic toggle="yes">MVK</italic>, mevalonate kinase; Non-aprenyl-PP, non-aprenyl pyrophosphate; Phytyl-PP, phytyl pyrophosphate; <italic toggle="yes">PMK</italic>, phosphomevalonate kinase; <italic toggle="yes">GPS</italic>, geranyl-diphosphate specific/all-<italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-non-aprenyl-diphosphate synthase.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-12-740755-g007" position="float"/></fig><p>To date, mainly six TF families [<italic toggle="yes">AP2/ethylene responsive factor</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">ERF</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">basic helix-loop-helix</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">bHLH</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">MYB</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">NAM, ATAF, and CUC</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">NAC</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">WRKY</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">basic leucine zipper</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">bZIP</italic>)] have been reported in plants in relation to the metabolism of terpenoids (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2019</xref>). In the study, only three TF families (12 <italic toggle="yes">AP2</italic>-like factors, 61 <italic toggle="yes">MYBs</italic>, and 2 <italic toggle="yes">WRKYs</italic>) were identified (<xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 12</xref>); among them, only five miRNAs (aly-miR172e-3p, cme-miR319c, novel137_mature, osa-miR159d, and zma-miR159e-3p) were differentially expressed. These findings suggest that these miRNA targets may play a vital role in differential diterpenoid biosynthesis and biological adaptation.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="S4"><title>Discussion</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Cryptomeria fortunei</italic>, a very important industrial essential oil tree species in China, contains an especially large amount of natural terpenes (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Yao et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Xie et al., 2011</xref>). miRNAs play an important role in the life activities of plants by regulating gene expression (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Bulgakov and Avramenko, 2015</xref>). In addition, a role for miRNAs in regulating plant specialized metabolites has been reported in an increasing number of plant species (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Vashisht et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Gupta et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2017</xref>). However, the possible regulatory role of <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> miRNA in terpenoid biosynthesis is still unclear. Therefore, we used metabonome, transcriptome, sRNA, and degradome-seq to explore the potential miRNA regulatory network of terpenoids in <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> needles, with the goal of improving the level of terpenoid synthesis in winter.</p><sec id="S4.SS1"><title>Terpenoid Metabolites Were Differentially Produced in the Two Studied Phenotypes of <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic></title><p>In <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> needles, a total of 173 terpenoid metabolites were identified; these were primarily sesquiterpenoids but also included a variety of di-, mono-, and triterpenoids (<xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 2</xref>). Previous phytochemical studies of the branches, needles, heartwood, cones, and bark of <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> have also isolated a variety of terpenoids, including mono-, sesqui-, and diterpenoids (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Yao et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Wu and Zhao, 2010</xref>), supporting the idea that terpenoids are present in large amounts in <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic>. However, there are obvious differences in the types and levels of compounds reported to be present. For example, <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Xie et al. (2011)</xref> identified only 68 terpenoids from the essential oil of <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> using GC&#x02013;MS. These differences in terpenoid metabolites may be related to the plant genetic background, environment, tissues/organs, sampling time, and many other factors.</p><p>We identified 31 terpenoids that were differentially biosynthesized in the two <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> phenotypes analyzed in this study (<xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 3</xref>). Both metabolome and transcriptome functional analyses showed that DEGs/DSMs were enriched for diterpenoid biosynthesis (ko00904) (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref>, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3D</xref>). Therefore, we speculated that each of these two phenotypes of <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> may have its own unique diterpenoid metabolic mechanisms. However, their specific biological regulatory mechanisms need to be further analyzed.</p></sec><sec id="S4.SS2"><title>miRNA TF Targets May Regulate Terpenoid Synthesis</title><p>A number of studies have shown that the production of terpenoid substances is strictly regulated by microribonucleic acids through TFs. We identified three TF families (<italic toggle="yes">AP2</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">MYB</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">WRKY</italic>), most of which were <italic toggle="yes">MYBs</italic> and 35 <italic toggle="yes">MYBs</italic> were cut by miR828/858 (<xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 12</xref>). Other studies have also found that most of the target genes of miR858/828 belong to <italic toggle="yes">MYBs</italic>, especially <italic toggle="yes">R2R3-MYB</italic> TFs. For example, up to 20 <italic toggle="yes">R2R3-MYBs</italic> are involved in cotton fiber development (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Guan et al., 2014</xref>), and most of them are related to the metabolic pathways of phenylpropanes. However, few studies have examined the synthesis of terpenoids. In loblolly pine (<italic toggle="yes">Pinus taeda</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">PtMYB14</italic> positively regulates the production of multiple sesquiterpenes (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Bedon et al., 2010</xref>); in <italic toggle="yes">A. thaliana</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">AtMYB</italic> TFs increase terpenoid volatiles, not only by activating the transcription of the <italic toggle="yes">trehalose-6-phosphate synthase</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">TPS</italic>) gene but also by enhancing the metabolic flux to the isoprenoid pathway, while <italic toggle="yes">MsMYB</italic> negatively regulates the accumulation of monoterpenes and interferes with the synthesis of sesquiterpenes and diterpene derivatives in spearmint (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Reddy et al., 2017</xref>). Therefore, whether a specific <italic toggle="yes">MYB</italic> regulates terpenoid synthesis and how to regulate it (e.g., negative/positive regulation, which structural gene to regulate) remains to be further studied. In addition, in <italic toggle="yes">Artemisia annua</italic>, the <italic toggle="yes">AP2</italic> TFs <italic toggle="yes">AaERF1/2</italic> participate in actively regulating expression of the sesquiterpene synthase gene (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Yu et al., 2012</xref>). In Asian cotton (<italic toggle="yes">Gossypium arboreum</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">GaWRKY1</italic> activates the transcription of the sesquiterpene synthase gene encoding cadinene synthase (<italic toggle="yes">CAD1</italic>), which leads to the biosynthesis of sesquiterpene gossypol (<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2004</xref>), which is similar to our research results. Other TFs have also been found to be involved in the biosynthesis of terpenes. For example, in <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic>, miR156 regulates the content of active ingredients such as sesquiterpenes by downregulating its target gene <italic toggle="yes">SPL9</italic> (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Yu et al., 2015</xref>). Therefore, it is still necessary to enrich the sample tissues and the cedar leaves of different growth stages in follow-up studies to further explore the mechanism by which miRNA-TF regulates terpenoid biosynthesis.</p></sec><sec id="S4.SS3"><title>miRNA Target Genes Play an Important Role in Regulating Diterpenoid Synthesis</title><p>MicroRNAs usually partially or completely match their target genes, leading to endonuclease digestion or translation inhibition and thereby regulate the expression of the target genes and play important roles. Therefore, searching for target genes is of great value for elucidating the biological functions of miRNAs. Degradome-seq, which offers high throughput and coverage, has been suggested to significantly increase the probability of capturing target miRNA fragments and to provide a statistically significant number of all target sites for each miRNA (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Pantaleo et al., 2010</xref>). It has therefore been widely used in research on plant miRNA targets (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Ye et al., 2020</xref>). miRNA targets were identified by degradome-seq; through GO and KEGG analysis, these miRNA targets were found to be involved in a variety of molecular biological regulatory pathways, including terpenoid and polyketide biosynthesis (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref> and <xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 8</xref>). Further miRNA target and metabolite analysis showed that terpenoid backbone biosynthesis, diterpenoid biosynthesis and carotenoid biosynthesis play a vital role in terpenoid biosynthesis in <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref> and <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Tables 1</xref>, <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). In addition, most of the orange-color-related DSMs in carotenoid biosynthesis were significantly upregulated in YWt, and most of the remaining terpenoid and polyketide biosynthesis-related metabolites were upregulated in GM (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). As a common precursor, geranylgeranyl diphosphate (GGPP) has three main routes of metabolism: (1) <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> a reaction catalyzed by <italic toggle="yes">phytoene synthase</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">PSY</italic>), GGPP is further condensed to phytoene (C40) and participates in carotenoid biosynthesis; (2) <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> a reaction catalyzed by <italic toggle="yes">geranylgeranyl reductase</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">GGR</italic>), GGPP eventually forms the phytol side chain of chlorophyll; and (3) <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> a reaction catalyzed by <italic toggle="yes">diterpene synthase</italic>, various diterpene compounds, including gibberellin A and some phytoalexins, are formed. Therefore, we inferred that in <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> terpenoid backbone biosynthesis, the precursor GGPP is allocated to different metabolic branches, such as carotenoid and diterpenoid biosynthesis; that is, YWt contains more carotenoids than GM, and GM contains more diterpenoids than YWt, resulting in differences in needle color between GM and YWt due to differential synthesis of diterpenoids (<xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F8"><label>FIGURE 8</label><caption><p>Simplified model of aly-miR168a-5p- and aof-miR396a-CPSent regulating diterpenoid biosynthesis. Red/blue text indicates up-/downregulated genes; the sizes of the arrows indicate the amount of metabolic flow; and pseudo-color bar at the bottom of the middle represents the fragments per kilobase of exon per million (FPKM) value. <italic toggle="yes">CPSent</italic>, ent-copalyl diphosphate synthase; <italic toggle="yes">GGPP</italic>, geranylgeranyl diphosphate; GM, evergreen mutant; YWt, yellowish-brown needles in winter.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-12-740755-g008" position="float"/></fig><p>One miRNA can regulate hundreds of targets, and one target can also be regulated by multiple miRNAs (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Licursi et al., 2019</xref>), thus constructing a complex interlocking miRNA-target regulatory network (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>). Among them, we identified 41 miRNA targets synthesized <italic toggle="yes">via C. fortunei</italic> terpenoid backbone biosynthesis and diterpenoids. For many modules, the expression pattern of miRNA was opposite to that of its target genes, indicating that these miRNAs could negatively regulate their targets (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Figures 7B,C</xref>). In terpenoid backbone biosynthesis, we identified multiple known miRNAs (atr-miR396d, gma-miR6300, gra-miR482, mtr-miR5261, pab-miR394a, vvi-miR159a, and miR172a) that regulated structural gene (such as <italic toggle="yes">GGPS</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">HMGCR</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">FNTA</italic>) (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7A</xref>). In Chinese toon (<italic toggle="yes">Toona sinensis</italic>) sprouts, tsi-miR408-3p, tsi-miR171a, tsi-miR390b-5p, and tsi-miR-1260 target these unigenes, such as <italic toggle="yes">HMGCR</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">MEP</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">1-deoxy-<sc>D</sc>-xylulose-5-phosphate synthase</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">DXS</italic>) (<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et al., 2021</xref>); only three miRNA-enzyme gene pairs related to terpenoid biosynthesis have been identified in tea trees (<italic toggle="yes">Camellia sinensis</italic>) (<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et al., 2018</xref>). There are some differences in miRNA targets, which may be related to species specificity, but these also confirm that miRNAs are indeed involved in the biosynthesis of terpenoids. We also identified multiple novel miRNA targets in this pathway (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7A</xref>), which is similar to the phenomenon in <italic toggle="yes">T. sinensis</italic> sprouts (<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et al., 2021</xref>). Novel miRNAs are a type of speculative miRNA, which indicates that these genes may be the basis of specific biological functions in <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic>, and further experiments are needed to determine the functions of these novel miRNAs. Interestingly, the differentially expressed target gene <italic toggle="yes">ispS</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">TRINITY_DN6836_c0_g1_i1_1</italic>) cut by novel106_mature and pab-miR394a was identified as participating in &#x0201c;isoprene synthesis&#x0201d; (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref>). The interpretation of miRNA regulatory functions is inseparable from its target genes. In land plants, the target gene <italic toggle="yes">ispS</italic> is located in the chloroplast (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Sasaki et al., 2005</xref>), where it catalyzes the conversion of the intermediate substrate DMAPP to isoprene (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Silver and Fall, 1991</xref>). In our previous research, we found that the chloroplasts in GM were basically intact, whereas the chloroplast structure in YWt was destroyed in winter. Therefore, it was also confirmed that the synthesis of <italic toggle="yes">ispS</italic> was indeed inhibited in YWt. Previous studies have shown that isoprene, a volatile C5 terpenoid compound, is synthesized by plants and that the biological release of isoprene by plants has a certain protective effect (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Kksal et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Oku et al., 2015</xref>). Therefore, we inferred that GM could produce more isoprene to enhance its adaptability to low temperatures.</p><p>In the diterpenoid biosynthesis modules, that is, in aly-miR168a-5p- and aof-miR396a-<italic toggle="yes">CPSent</italic> and in novel59_mature- and cme-miR828-<italic toggle="yes">(13E)-labda-7,13-dien-15-ol synthase</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">CPSKSL1</italic>), the target genes were upregulated in GM (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7C</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">CPSent</italic> is a key enzyme in the gibberellin biosynthesis pathway in plants (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Otomo et al., 2004</xref>) and in the phytoalexin synthesis pathway. It catalyzes the cyclization of GGDP to ent-copalyl diphosphate (CDP) (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2010</xref>). Gibberellin is a very important plant hormone in higher plants. It regulates stem elongation, leaf expansion, flower differentiation and seed and fruit development, breaks dormancy, promotes germination, reduces organ shedding, and participates in many other physiological processes (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Lang, 1957</xref>). Phytoalexins are small-molecular-weight compounds with antimicrobial activity that are synthesized and rapidly accumulate in the body when plants are attacked by biological or non-biological threats. The phytoalexins that have been isolated and identified to date can be roughly divided into terpenes, flavonoids, flavanones, and alkaloids. The phytoalexin components of these diterpenoids enhance the disease resistance of plants and their resistance to related exogenous damage to some extent. Therefore, we inferred that compared with YWt, the low expression of aly-miR168a-5p and aof-miR396a in GM promoted high expression of its target <italic toggle="yes">CPSent</italic> genes (<italic toggle="yes">TRINITY_DN30372_c1_g1_i15_2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">TRINITY_DN29820_c0_g1_i21_2</italic>), which in turn promoted the accumulation of gibberellins such as gibberellin A12, A14, and A3, gibberellin A53 aldehyde and gibberellin A8 catabolite (<xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8</xref>). Therefore, GM exhibited reduced dormancy and remained green, a condition that ensured that it could produce more diterpenoids (<xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8</xref>). The bifunctional <italic toggle="yes">CPSKSL1</italic> gene product catalyzes the formation of the inner double bond isomer of cobalt cyclopentadiphosphate (CPP) and subsequently replaces diphosphate with a hydroxyl group to form labda-7,13E-dien-15-ol (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Mafu et al., 2011</xref>). Although the latter compound is a known plant metabolite, its biosynthesis has not yet been studied, and further experimental verification is needed.</p></sec><sec id="S4.SS4"><title>miRNA Targets Play a Role in Regulating Flavonoid Biosynthesis to Some Extent</title><p>Differentially synthesized metabolites, DEGs, and miRNA targets were all significantly enriched in the flavonoid metabolism pathway (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref>, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3D</xref> and <xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 9</xref>). (+)-Catechin, epicatechin, luteoforol, and pentahydroxyflavanone were significantly upregulated in YWt; in that phenotype, the level of epicatechin was 11.81-fold higher than that in GM and much higher than the levels of other metabolites; afzelechin, homoeriodictyol, and pinocembrin were significantly upregulated in GM (<xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 13</xref>). These results showed that the two phenotypes of <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> exhibited significant differences in flavonoid metabolism.</p><p>A total of 22 miRNA targets were related to flavonoids (<xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 9</xref>). We further selected target pairs with different target genes, that is, ata-miR395b-3p-<italic toggle="yes">flavonol synthase</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">FLS</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">TRINITY_DN24453_c0_g1_i3_1</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">TRINITY_DN29464_c0_g1_i4_2</italic>), novel116_star-<italic toggle="yes">chalcone synthase</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">CHS</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">TRINITY_DN26891_c0_g2_i2_3</italic>), novel20_star-<italic toggle="yes">flavanone 3-hydroxylase gene</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">F3H</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">TRINIT Y_DN19610_c1_g1_i2_1</italic>), novel55_mature-<italic toggle="yes">leucoanthocyanidin dioxygenase</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">LDOX</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">TRINITY_DN27808_c0_g1_i2_3</italic>), and lja-miR398-3p-<italic toggle="yes">leucoanthocyanidin reductase</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">LAR</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">TRINITY_DN23847_c0_g1_i4_1</italic>), and we found that only <italic toggle="yes">LAR</italic> was upregulated in GM, whereas the remaining target genes were upregulated in YWt. Studies have shown that miR395 acts on target genes and negatively regulates the key flavonoid gene <italic toggle="yes">FLS</italic>, which ultimately affects the accumulation of flavonoids (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2018</xref>). Therefore, we believe that <italic toggle="yes">FLS</italic> is highly expressed in YWt and that this expression promotes flavonoid accumulation. Novel116_star, novel20_star, and novel55_mature are novel predicted miRNAs, with 204, 126, and 16 predicted targets, respectively, most of which are unknown. These genes showed no homology with genes from other species, indicating that they may support specific functions in <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic>. In addition, few studies have examined the role of miR398 in regulating flavonoid biosynthesis, and further experiments are needed to determine the functions of these miRNAs.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusion" id="S5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>In summary, we analyzed the transcriptome, metabolome, sRNA, and degradome of two different overwintering <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> phenotypes. The results of the metabolome and transcriptome analyses showed that DSMs and DEGs were enriched in the diterpenoid pathway. The miRNAs and their targets in <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> needles were then identified, and the miRNA targets involved in terpenoid biosynthesis were analyzed. The module (aly-miR168a-5p- and aof-miR396a-<italic toggle="yes">CPSent</italic>) may be a potential key factor in the mechanism of differential diterpenoid synthesis in winter. In addition, we also identified three miRNA-TF families, that may be related to terpenoid biosynthesis, but further experimental verification is required. These findings provide reference information regarding diterpenoid regulatory mechanisms in <italic toggle="yes">C. fortunei</italic> and valuable resources for bioengineering research related to plant production of essential oils in winter.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="S6"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The datasets presented in this study can be found in online repositories. The names of the repository/repositories and accession number(s) can be found below: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genbank/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genbank/</ext-link>, <ext-link xlink:href="PRJNA697258" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">PRJNA697258</ext-link>; <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genbank/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genbank/</ext-link>, <ext-link xlink:href="PRJNA720228" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">PRJNA720228</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>JX conceived and designed the experiments. JX and YZ performed the experiments and wrote the manuscript. JC, HH, JYX, and JY analyzed the data. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="pudiscl1"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="funding-information" id="S8"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by China&#x02019;s State Forestry Administration, Forestry Public Welfare Industry Research (201304104), and the Priority Academic Program Development of Jiangsu Higher Education Institutions (PAPD).</p></sec><fn-group><fn id="footnote1"><label>1</label><p>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://cloud.oebiotech.cn/task/" ext-link-type="uri">https://cloud.oebiotech.cn/task/</ext-link>
</p></fn><fn id="footnote2"><label>2</label><p>
<ext-link xlink:href="http://www.sanger.ac.uk/software/Rfam" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.sanger.ac.uk/software/Rfam</ext-link>
</p></fn><fn id="footnote3"><label>3</label><p>
<ext-link xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genbank/" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genbank/</ext-link>
</p></fn><fn id="footnote4"><label>4</label><p>
<ext-link xlink:href="http://www.mirbase.org/" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.mirbase.org/</ext-link>
</p></fn><fn id="footnote5"><label>5</label><p>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.omicshare.com/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.omicshare.com/</ext-link>
</p></fn><fn id="footnote6"><label>6</label><p>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://cytoscape.org/" ext-link-type="uri">https://cytoscape.org/</ext-link>
</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="S9"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpls.2021.740755/full#supplementary-material" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpls.2021.740755/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material id="FS1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="FS2" position="float" content-type="local-data"><media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_2.zip"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Addo-Quaye</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Axtell</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>CleaveLand: a pipeline for using degradome data to find cleaved small RNA targets.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Bioinformatics</italic></source>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>130</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>131</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btn604</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19017659?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19017659</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>S. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gish</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>E. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipman</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Basic local alignment search tool.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J. Mol. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>215</volume>
<fpage>403</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>410</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-2836(05)80360-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2231712</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <source><italic toggle="yes">Differential Expression of RNA-Seq Data at the Gene Level&#x02013;the DESeq Package.</italic></source> Available Online at: <ext-link xlink:href="http://mirrors.ustc.edu.cn/bioc/3.4/bioc/vignettes/DESeq/inst/doc/DESeq.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">http://mirrors.ustc.edu.cn/bioc/3.4/bioc/vignettes/DESeq/inst/doc/DESeq.pdf</ext-link> [accessed Jan 12, 2016]</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashour</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wink</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gershenzon</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). &#x0201c;<article-title>Biochemistry of terpenoids: monoterpenes, sesquiterpenes and diterpenes</article-title>&#x0201d;, in <source><italic toggle="yes">Annual Plant Review</italic></source>
<role>ed.</role> M. Wink (Blackwell, Singapore: Wiley), 258&#x02013;303.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>MicroRNAs: genomics, biogenesis, mechanism, and function.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Cell</italic></source>
<volume>116</volume>
<fpage>281</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>297</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(04)00045-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14744438</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bedon</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bomal</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Caron</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Levasseur</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyle</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mansfield</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Subgroup 4 R2R3-MYBs in conifer trees: gene family expansion and contribution to the isoprenoid- and flavonoid-oriented responses.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J. Exp. Bot.</italic></source>
<volume>61</volume>
<fpage>3847</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3864</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erq196</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20732878?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20732878</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bolger</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marc</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bjoern</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Trimmomatic: a flexible trimmer for Illumina sequence data.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Bioinformatics</italic></source>
<volume>30</volume>
<fpage>2114</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2120</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu170</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24695404?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24695404</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bulgakov</surname><given-names>V. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Avramenko</surname><given-names>T. V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>New opportunities for the regulation of secondary metabolism in plants: focus on microRNAs.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Biotechnol. Lett.</italic></source>
<volume>37</volume>
<fpage>1719</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1727</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10529-015-1863-8</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26003096?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26003096</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Deep sequencing identifies miRNAs and their target genes involved in the biosynthesis of terpenoids in <italic toggle="yes">Cinnamomum camphora</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Ind. Crop. Prod.</italic></source>
<volume>145</volume>:<issue>111853</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2019.111853</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>E. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>C. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>S. T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Variations in insecticidal activity and chemical compositions of leaf essential oils from <italic toggle="yes">Cryptomeria japonica</italic> at different ages.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Bioresource Technol.</italic></source>
<volume>100</volume>
<fpage>465</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>470</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2007.11.060</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18178080?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18178080</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>C. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>S. T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Chemical composition and antitermitic activity against coptotermes formosanus shiraki of <italic toggle="yes">Cryptomeria japonica</italic> leaf essential oil.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Chem. Biodivers.</italic></source>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>352</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>358</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cbdv.201100243</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22344910?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22344910</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doron</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Manda</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aaron</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marks</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chris</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The microRNA.org resource: targets and expression.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Nucleic Acids Res.</italic></source>
<volume>36</volume>
<fpage>D149</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D153</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm995</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18158296?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18158296</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fernie</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aharoni</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Willmitzer</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stitt</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tohge</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kopka</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Recommendations for Reporting Metabolite Data.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Plant Cell</italic></source>
<volume>23</volume>
<fpage>2477</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2482</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.111.086272</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21771932?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21771932</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friedlnder</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackowiak</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nikolaus</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>MiRDeep2 accurately identifies known and hundreds of novel microRNA genes in seven animal clades.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Nucleic Acids Res.</italic></source>
<volume>40</volume>
<fpage>37</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>52</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkr688</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21911355?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21911355</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujihashi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Crystal structure and functional analysis of large-terpene synthases belonging to a newly found subclass.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Chem. Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>3754</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3758</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/c8sc00289d</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29780507?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29780507</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grabherr</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yassour</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>J. Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amit</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Trinity: reconstructing a full-length transcriptome without a genome from RNA-Seq data.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Nat. Biotechnol.</italic></source>
<volume>29</volume>
<fpage>644</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>652</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.1883</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21572440?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21572440</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grassmann</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hippeli</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elstner</surname><given-names>E. F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Plant&#x02019;s defence and its benefits for animals and medicine: role of phenolics and terpenoids in avoiding oxygen stress.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Plant Physiol. Bioch.</italic></source>
<volume>40</volume>
<fpage>471</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>478</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0981-9428(02)01395-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grimson</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farh</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>W. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrett-Engele</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>L. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>MicroRNA targeting specificity in mammals: determinants beyond seed pairing.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Mol. Cell</italic></source>
<volume>27</volume>
<fpage>91</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>105</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2007.06.017</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 17612493?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17612493</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nah</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stelly</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>miR828 and miR858 regulate homoeologous MYB2 gene functions in <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis trichome</italic> and cotton fibre development.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Nat. Commun.</italic></source>
<volume>5</volume>:<issue>3050</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms4050</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24430011?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24430011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>O. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karkute</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meena</surname><given-names>N. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahuja</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Contemporary understanding of miRNA-Based regulation of secondary metabolites biosynthesis in plants.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Front. Plant Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>:<issue>374</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2017.00374</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28424705?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28424705</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinohara</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kakubari</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Photoprotective role of rhodoxanthin during cold acclimation in <italic toggle="yes">Cryptomeria japonica</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Plant Cell Environ.</italic></source>
<volume>26</volume>
<fpage>715</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>723</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-3040.2003.01008.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Izumi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirata</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Signal transduction against the terpenoid-stimulation in the liverwort cells.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Chem. Lett.</italic></source>
<volume>26</volume>
<fpage>1117</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1118</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1246/cl.1997.1117</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27682988?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27682988</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Embryo transcriptome and miRNA analyses reveal the regulatory network of seed dormancy in <italic toggle="yes">Ginkgo biloba</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Tree Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>41</volume>
<fpage>571</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>588</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/treephys/tpaa023</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 32159802?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32159802</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kanehisa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Araki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hattori</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirakawa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>KEGG for linking genomes to life and the environment.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Nucleic Acids Res.</italic></source>
<volume>36</volume>
<fpage>480</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>484</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm882</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18077471?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18077471</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>C. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gwak</surname><given-names>K. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>I. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Whitening and antioxidant activities of bornyl acetate and nezukol fractionated from <italic toggle="yes">Cryptomeria japonica</italic> essential oil.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Int. J. Cosmetic Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>35</volume>
<fpage>484</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>490</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ics.12069</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23714012?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23714012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kksal</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmer</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnitzler</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Christianson</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Structure of isoprene synthase illuminates the chemical mechanism of teragram atmospheric carbon emission.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J. Mol. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>402</volume>
<fpage>363</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>373</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmb.2010.07.009</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20624401?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20624401</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krek</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gr&#x000fc;n</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Poy</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>E. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Combinatorial microRNA target predictions.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Nat. Genet.</italic></source>
<volume>37</volume>
<fpage>495</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>500</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng1536</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15806104?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15806104</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1957</year>). <article-title>The effect of gibberellin upon flower formation.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</italic></source>
<volume>43</volume>
<fpage>709</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>717</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.43.8.709</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16590073?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16590073</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Langmead</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Fast gapped-read alignment with Bowtie 2.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Nat. Methods</italic></source>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>357</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>359</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1923</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22388286?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22388286</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lavorgna</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guffanti</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borsani</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballabio</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boncinelli</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>TargetFinder: searching annotated sequence databases for target genes of transcription factors.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Bioinformatics</italic></source>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>172</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>173</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/15.2.172</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 10089203?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10089203</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Effects of blue light on flavonoid accumulation linked to the expression of miR393, miR394 and miR395 in longan embryogenic calli.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>
<volume>13</volume>:<issue>e191444</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0191444</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29381727?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29381727</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Licursi</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Conte</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiscon</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paci</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>MIENTURNET: an interactive web tool for microRNA-target enrichment and network-based analysis.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Bioinformatics</italic></source>
<volume>20</volume>:<issue>545</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12859-019-3105-x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 31684860?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31684860</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>S. T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Chemical composition and antifungal activity of essential oils from different tissues of Japanese Cedar (<italic toggle="yes">Cryptomeria japonica</italic>).</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J. Agric. Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>53</volume>
<fpage>614</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>619</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf0484529</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15686410?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15686410</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Regulation of fatty acid and flavonoid biosynthesis by miRNAs in <italic toggle="yes">Lonicera japonica</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">RSC Adv.</italic></source>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>35426</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>35437</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C7RA05800D</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>X. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Plant miRNAs and abiotic stress responses.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun.</italic></source>
<volume>368</volume>
<fpage>458</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>462</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2008.02.007</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18267107?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18267107</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mafu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillwig</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>A novel labda-7,13e-dien-15-ol-producing bifunctional diterpene synthase from <italic toggle="yes">Selaginella moellendorffii</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Chembiochem</italic></source>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>1984</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1987</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cbic.201100336</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21751328?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21751328</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsunaga</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawasuji</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sagioka</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Isolation of the antiulcer compound in essential oil from the leaves of <italic toggle="yes">Cryptomeria japonica</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Biol. Pharm. Bull.</italic></source>
<volume>23</volume>
<fpage>595</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>598</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1248/bpb.23.595</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 10823671?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10823671</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oku</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Inafuku</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takamine</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishmael</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukuta</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Molecular cloning and biochemical characterization of isoprene synthases from the tropical trees <italic toggle="yes">Ficus virgata</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Ficus septica</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Casuarina equisetifolia</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J. Plant Res.</italic></source>
<volume>128</volume>
<fpage>849</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>861</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10265-015-0740-9</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26081976?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26081976</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Otomo</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenmoku</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oikawa</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000f6;nig</surname><given-names>W. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toshima</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitsuhashi</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Biological functions of ent- and syn-copalyl diphosphate synthases in rice: key enzymes for the branch point of gibberellin and phytoalexin biosynthesis.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Plant J.</italic></source>
<volume>39</volume>
<fpage>886</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>893</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2004.02175.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15341631?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15341631</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pantaleo</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Szittya</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moxon</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miozzi</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moulton</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalmay</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Identification of grapevine microRNAs and their targets using high&#x02212;throughput sequencing and degradome analysis.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Plant J.</italic></source>
<volume>62</volume>
<fpage>960</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>976</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2010.04208.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20230504</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parreira</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cappuccio</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balestrazzi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fevereiro</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ara&#x000fa;jo</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2021</year>). <article-title>MicroRNAs expression dynamics reveal post-transcriptional mechanisms regulating seed development in <italic toggle="yes">Phaseolus vulgaris</italic> L.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Hortic. Res.</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>:<issue>18</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41438-020-00448-0</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 33436559?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33436559</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>V. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhar</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Venkatesh</surname><given-names>P. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Spearmint R2R3-MYB transcription factor <italic toggle="yes">MsMYB</italic> negatively regulates monoterpene production and suppresses the expression of geranyl diphosphate synthase large subunit (<italic toggle="yes">MsGPPS.LSU</italic>).</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Plant Biotechnol. J.</italic></source>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>1105</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1119</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pbi.12701</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28160379?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28160379</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohara</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yazaki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Gene expression and characterization of isoprene synthase from Populus alba.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">FEBS Lett.</italic></source>
<volume>579</volume>
<fpage>2514</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2518</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.febslet.2005.03.066</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15848197?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15848197</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fall</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Enzymatic synthesis of isoprene from dimethylallyl diphosphate in aspen leaf extracts.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>97</volume>
<fpage>1588</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1591</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.97.4.1588</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16668590?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16668590</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ci</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Sexual dimorphism floral microRNA profiling and target gene expression in andromonoecious poplar (<italic toggle="yes">Populus tomentosa</italic>).</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>:<issue>e62681</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062681</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23667507?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23667507</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pertea</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mortazavi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baren</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Transcript assembly and quantification by RNA-Seq reveals unannotated transcripts and isoform switching during cell differentiation.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Nat. Biotechnol.</italic></source>
<volume>28</volume>
<fpage>511</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>515</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.1621</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20436464?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20436464</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vashisht</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pal</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chanumolu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>T. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chauhan</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Mining NGS transcriptomes for miRNAs and dissecting their role in regulating growth, development, and secondary metabolites production in different organs of a medicinal herb, <italic toggle="yes">Picrorhiza kurroa</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Planta</italic></source>
<volume>241</volume>
<fpage>1255</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1268</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00425-015-2255-y</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25663583?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25663583</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vranov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruissem</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Network analysis of the MVA and MEP pathways for isoprenoid synthesis.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Annu. Rev. Plant Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>64</volume>
<fpage>665</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>700</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-arplant-050312-120116</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23451776?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23451776</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>W. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>F. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>C. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>S. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>S. T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Essential oil from the leaves of <italic toggle="yes">Cryptomeria japonica</italic> acts as a silverfish (<italic toggle="yes">Lepisma saccharina</italic>) repellent and insecticide.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J. Wood Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>52</volume>
<fpage>522</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>526</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10086-006-0806-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>W. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>New sesquiterpene and triterpene from the fruits of <italic toggle="yes">Cryptomeria fortunei</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J. Asian Nat. Prod. Res.</italic></source>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>382</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>387</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10286021003785565</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20496195?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20496195</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Comparative analysis of essential oil components of two <italic toggle="yes">Cryptomeria</italic> species from China.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Ind. Crop. Prod.</italic></source>
<volume>34</volume>
<fpage>1226</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1230</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2011.04.016</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillwig</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prisic</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coates</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Functional identification of rice syn-copalyl diphosphate synthase and its role in initiating biosynthesis of diterpenoid phytoalexin/allelopathic natural products.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Plant J.</italic></source>
<volume>39</volume>
<fpage>309</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>318</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2004.02137.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15255861?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15255861</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ying</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>High-Throughput sequencing and degradome analysis identify miRNAs and their targets involved in fruit senescence of <italic toggle="yes">Fragaria ananassa</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>:<issue>e70959</issue>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grierson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Integration of metabolite profiling and transcriptome analysis reveals genes related to volatile terpenoid metabolism in finger citron (<italic toggle="yes">C. medica</italic> var. <italic toggle="yes">sarcodactylis</italic>).</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Molecules</italic></source>
<volume>24</volume>:<issue>2564</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules24142564</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 31311090?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31311090</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X. Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Characterization of <italic toggle="yes">GaWRKY1</italic>, a cotton transcription factor that regulates the sesquiterpene synthase gene (+)-delta-cadinene synthase-A.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>135</volume>
<fpage>507</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>515</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.104.038612</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15133151?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15133151</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ke</surname><given-names>C. Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Abietane diterpenoids from the bark of <italic toggle="yes">Cryptomeria fortunei</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J. Nat. Prod.</italic></source>
<volume>71</volume>
<fpage>1242</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1246</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/np8002063</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18549276?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18549276</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Small RNA and degradome sequencing reveal roles of miRNAs in strobilus development in masson pine (<italic toggle="yes">Pinus massoniana</italic>).</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Ind. Crop. Prod.</italic></source>
<volume>154</volume>:<issue>112724</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2020.112724</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Z. X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J. X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C. Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X. Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>The jasmonate-responsive AP2/ERF transcription factors <italic toggle="yes">AaERF1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">AaERF2</italic> positively regulate artemisinin biosynthesis in <italic toggle="yes">Artemisia annua</italic> L.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Mol. Plant</italic></source>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>353</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>365</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/mp/ssr087</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22104293?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22104293</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Z. X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Progressive regulation of sesquiterpene biosynthesis in <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic> and patchouli (<italic toggle="yes">Pogostemon cablin</italic>) by the miR156-targeted SPL transcription factors.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Mol. Plant</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>98</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>110</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molp.2014.11.002</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25578275?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25578275</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2021</year>). <article-title>Selection and verification of appropriate reference genes for expression normalization in <italic toggle="yes">Cryptomeria fortunei</italic> under abiotic stress and hormone treatments.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Genes</italic></source>
<volume>12</volume>:<issue>791</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/genes12060791</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 34064253?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34064253</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2021</year>). <article-title>Comparative analysis of miRNA expression profiles provides insight into regulation of biosynthesis of flavonoids and terpenoids between two varieties of <italic toggle="yes">Toona sinensis</italic> sprouts.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J. Plant Biol.</italic></source>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12374-021-09321-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mi</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Revealing of the microRNA involved regulatory gene networks on terpenoid biosynthesis in <italic toggle="yes">Camellia sinensis</italic> in different growing time points.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J. Agr. Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>66</volume>
<fpage>12604</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12616</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jafc.8b05345</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 30400742?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30400742</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>AP2</term><def><p>APETALA2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BP</term><def><p>biological process</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CC</term><def><p>cellular component</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>
<italic toggle="yes">CPSent</italic>
</term><def><p>
<italic toggle="yes">ent-copalyl diphosphate synthase</italic>
</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CRs</term><def><p>clean reads</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CSRs</term><def><p>cleavage site reads</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DEGs</term><def><p>differentially expressed unigenes</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DSMs</term><def><p>differentially synthesized metabolites</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DERs</term><def><p>differentially expressed miRNAs</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GGPP</term><def><p>geranylgeranyl diphosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GO</term><def><p>Gene Ontology</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>
<italic toggle="yes">ispS</italic>
</term><def><p>
<italic toggle="yes">isoprene synthase</italic>
</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>KEGG</term><def><p>Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LC&#x02013;MS</term><def><p>liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MF</term><def><p>molecular function</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>miRNAs</term><def><p>microRNAs</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MYB</term><def><p>v-myb avian myeloblastosis viral oncogene homolog</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>(O)PLS-DA</term><def><p>(orthogonal) partial least squares-discriminant analysis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>qRT-PCR</term><def><p>quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RRs</term><def><p>raw reads</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>sRNA</term><def><p>small RNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TFs</term><def><p>transcription factors</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TP</term><def><p>terpenoids and polyketides</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>VIP</term><def><p>variable importance in the projection.</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></back></article>