<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Plant Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Plant Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-462X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4709469</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2015.01232</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Plant Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Emission and Accumulation of Monoterpene and the Key Terpene Synthase (TPS) Associated with Monoterpene Biosynthesis in <italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic> Lour</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Xiangling</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/305956/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Cai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Riru</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Xuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Jing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/233933/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>Jingjing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Caiyun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/258971/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Key Laboratory for Biology of Horticultural Plants, Ministry of Education, College of Horticulture and Forestry Sciences, Huazhong Agricultural University</institution><country>Wuhan, China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>School of Nuclear Technology and Chemistry and Biology, Hubei University of Science and Technology</institution><country>Xianning, China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: <italic>Susana M. P. Carvalho, University of Porto, Portugal</italic></p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: <italic>Daniel A. Jacobo-Vel&#x000e1;zquez, Tecnol&#x000f3;gico de Monterrey, Mexico; Hao Peng, Washington State University, USA</italic></p></fn><corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: <italic>Caiyun Wang, <email xlink:type="simple">wangcy@mail.hzau.edu.cn</email></italic></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p>This article was submitted to Crop Science and Horticulture, a section of the journal Frontiers in Plant Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>1</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>1232</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>9</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2016 Zeng, Liu, Zheng, Cai, Luo, Zou and Wang.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Zeng, Liu, Zheng, Cai, Luo, Zou and Wang</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) or licensor are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic> is an ornamental and economically important plant known for its magnificent aroma, and the most important aroma-active compounds in flowers are monoterpenes, mainly &#x003b2;-ocimene, linalool and linalool derivatives. To understand the molecular mechanism of monoterpene production, we analyzed the emission and accumulation patterns of these compounds and the transcript levels of the genes involved in their biosynthesis in two <italic>O. fragrans</italic> cultivars during flowering stages. The results showed that both emission and accumulation of monoterpenes varied with flower development and glycosylation had an important impact on floral linalool emission during this process. Gene expression demonstrated that the transcript levels of terpene synthase (<italic>TPS</italic>) genes probably played a key role in monoterpene production, compared to the genes in the MEP pathway. Phylogenetic analysis showed that <italic>Of</italic>TPS1 and <italic>Of</italic>TPS2 belonged to a TPS-g subfamily, and <italic>Of</italic>TPS3 and <italic>Of</italic>TPS4 clustered into a TPS-b subfamily. Their transient and stable expression in tobacco leaves suggested that <italic>Of</italic>TPS1 and <italic>Of</italic>TPS2 exclusively produced &#x003b2;-linalool, and <italic>trans</italic>-&#x003b2;-ocimene was the sole product from <italic>Of</italic>TPS3, while <italic>Of</italic>TPS4, a predictive sesquiterpene synthase, produced &#x003b1;-farnesene. These results indicate that <italic>OfTPS1</italic>, <italic>OfTPS2</italic>, and <italic>OfTPS3</italic> could account for the major floral monoterpenes, linalool and <italic>trans</italic>-&#x003b2;-ocimene, produced in <italic>O. fragrans</italic> flowers.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic></kwd><kwd>MEP pathway</kwd><kwd>terpene synthase</kwd><kwd>monoterpenes</kwd><kwd>glycosylation</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001">Doctoral Fund of the Ministry of Education of China<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100002367</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn001">Project No 20130146110022</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn002">Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100002367</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn002">Project No 2013PY088</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn003">Hubei Collaborative Innovation Center for the Characteristic Resources Exploitation of Dabie Mountains<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100002367</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn003">Project No 2015TD02</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="7"/><table-count count="1"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="61"/><page-count count="16"/><word-count count="0"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Sweet <italic>osmanthus (Osmanthus fragrans</italic> Lour.), belonging to the Oleaceae family, is a well-known ornamental and economically important, aromatic woody plant, with the flower having a long history in China. Horticultural cultivars have spread throughout Thailand, India, and the Caucasus region (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Baldermann et al., 2010</xref>). Because of its extremely powerful and unique aroma, flowers and the essential oils of <italic>O. fragrans</italic> are in high demand for the production of expensive perfumes, flavorings and cosmetics (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Cai et al., 2014</xref>). The fresh flowers are very rich in floral volatiles, including terpenoids, aromatic compounds, C6 compounds and esters. The qualitative and quantitative variability of these compounds in flowers usually depends on the cultivar and developmental stage (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Cao et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Sun et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Xin et al., 2013</xref>). The terpenoids, including &#x003b2;-ionone, &#x003b2;-ocimene, &#x003b2;-linalool, and linalool derivatives, have been detected as dominant components of fresh flower volatiles and essential oils (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Sun et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Xin et al., 2013</xref>), and are important in the aroma formation of <italic>O. fragrans</italic> (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Cai et al., 2014</xref>). Of the terpenes, &#x003b2;-ionone is ubiquitous in <italic>O. fragrans</italic> flowers and its biosynthesis has been reported at the molecular level (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Baldermann et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Han et al., 2014</xref>). However, the molecular mechanism for the formation of monoterpenes such as &#x003b2;-ocimene and linalool in <italic>O. fragrans</italic> is not clear.</p><p>In plants, monoterpenes are mainly synthesized through the plastidial methylerythritol 4-phosphate (MEP) pathway, providing terpene precursors isopentenyl diphosphate (IPP) and its allylic isomer, dimethylallyl diphosphate (DMAPP; <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Dudareva et al., 2013</xref>). Quantitative variation in monoterpene production can be controlled by substrate flux through the MEP pathway (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Munoz-Bertomeu et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Battilana et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">K&#x000fc;lheim et al., 2011</xref>). The first step in the MEP pathway is the condensation of pyruvate and D-glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate (G3P) to 1-deoxy-<sc>D</sc>-xylulose 5-phosphate (DXP; <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Dudareva et al., 2013</xref>). The first enzyme, DXP synthase (DXS), has been considered the rate-limiting enzyme for the MEP pathway flux, because of the close correlation between the gene expression and the content of plastid isoprenoids such as monoterpenes and carotenoids (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Est&#x000e9;vez et al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Xie et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Battilana et al., 2009</xref>). The second and sixth enzyme in the pathway, DXP reductoisomerase (DXR) and 4-hydroxy-3-methylbut-2-en-1-yl diphosphate synthase (HDS), are also potential regulatory control points (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Mahmoud and Croteau, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Carretero-Paulet et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">K&#x000fc;lheim et al., 2011</xref>). However, the rate-limiting role of each of these enzymes in controlling the pathway flux appears to vary among plants (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Cordoba et al., 2009</xref>).</p><p>Under the catalytic action of geranyl pyrophosphate synthase (GPPS), IPP, and DMAPP are condensed head-to-tail to produce geranyl diphosphate (GPP), the monoterpene substrate (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Dudareva et al., 2013</xref>). Catalysis of this linear precursor, GPP, to a broad variety of monoterpenes is by the terpene synthase (TPS) family (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Degenhardt et al., 2009</xref>). TPS enzymes from different plant species have distinct phylogenetic relationships and have been classified into seven subfamilies, designated <italic>TPS</italic>-a to <italic>TPS</italic>-g (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2011</xref>). Despite intriguing differences between the subfamilies, there are three conserved motifs: an arginine-rich N-terminal RR(x8)W motif required for cyclization of the GPP substrate; an aspartate-rich DDxxD motif that interacts with divalent metal (usually Mg<sup>2+</sup> or Mn<sup>2+</sup>) ions involved in positioning the substrate for catalysis, and (N, D)Dxx(S,T)xxxE, required for second metal ion binding (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Degenhardt et al., 2009</xref>). The RR(x8)W motif is involved in producing cyclic monoterpenes, and is absent in TPSs that produce acyclic products (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2011</xref>). Many TPSs have the ability to produce multiple terpenes from a single prenyl diphosphate substrate <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Martin et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Green et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Nieuwenhuizen et al., 2013</xref>) or <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Davidovich-Rikanati et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Green et al., 2012</xref>). For example, the occasional complex terpene blend has been found in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> and <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic>, often produced only by a limited number of multiproduct TPS enzymes (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Tholl et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Garms et al., 2010</xref>). To date, TPSs have been identified and characterized in many plants, including <italic>Antirrhinum majus</italic> (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Dudareva et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Nagegowda et al., 2008</xref>), <italic>Actinidia</italic> species (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Nieuwenhuizen et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Green et al., 2012</xref>) and <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Martin et al., 2010</xref>). Despite monoterpenes making a significant contribution to the floral aroma and being rich in <italic>O. fragrans</italic> flowers, little is known about the <italic>TPS</italic> genes responsible for production of the major monoterpenes.</p><p>The biosynthetic monoterpenes are able to undergo complex processes of storage and conversion, which lead to the inconsistency between monoterpene release and gene transcript level (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Green et al., 2012</xref>). Glycosides are a potential source of aroma and flavor compounds, and play important roles in controlling the release of the floral volatiles in flowers and fruit (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Schwab et al., 2015</xref>). The glycoside volatiles are odorless and could release free aroma volatiles under the hydrolysis of &#x003b2;-glucosidase (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Yauk et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Schwab et al., 2015</xref>). They are highly valued in the flavor industry for enhancing the flavor and quality of grape wine and tea, and modifying the overall aroma during maturation, storage and processing in fruit (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Birti&#x00107; et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Garcia et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Yauk et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Ohgami et al., 2015</xref>). In flowers, the organoleptic aroma contributed by free volatiles and the content of essential oil composed of non-glycoside volatiles accumulating in fresh flowers have received more attention compared to the few studies on the volatile glycoside (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Picone et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Green et al., 2012</xref>). It has been reported that glycosidically bound volatiles are more abundant than the free forms and are potentially a major source of aroma in flowers (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Aurore et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Wen et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Yauk et al., 2014</xref>). <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al. (2005)</xref> found that &#x003b2;-<sc>D</sc>-glucosidase hydrolysis in fresh <italic>O. fragrans</italic> flowers enhanced the mass fractions of monoterpene volatiles. However, further research is needed on the glycoside monoterpenes in <italic>O. fragrans</italic>. Moreover, release of the bound volatile aglycones is dependent on flower development (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Reuveni et al., 1999</xref>). Therefore, the connection between different forms of volatiles is fundamental for understanding the molecular mechanism of monoterpene biosynthesis.</p><p>Here, we give a detailed analysis of the emission and accumulation of floral monoterpenes in two <italic>O. fragrans</italic> cultivars during flowering. A total of 18 genes, including 13 MEP pathway genes from <italic>DXS</italic> to <italic>IDI</italic>, one <italic>GPPS</italic> and four <italic>TPS</italic> genes, were obtained by transcriptome sequencing and their expression levels were analyzed by real-time qPCR. Intriguing differences were found in the transcript levels of four <italic>TPS</italic>s. Furthermore, functional characterization of TPSs and their involvement in major monoterpene production in <italic>O. fragrans</italic> flowers are described. This work provides a better understanding of the molecular mechanism of monoterpene biosynthesis, and will also help in the biotechnological enhancement and modification of aroma in <italic>O. fragrans</italic>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s1"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Plant Materials</title><p>The &#x02018;Liuye Jingui&#x02019; (abbreviated as &#x02018;Liuye&#x02019;) and &#x02018;Gecheng Dangui&#x02019; (abbreviated as &#x02018;Gecheng&#x02019;) cultivars of <italic>O. fragrans</italic> were grown in the campus nursery of Huazhong Agriculture University in Wuhan, China. Flower opening in <italic>O. fragrans</italic> was divided into four stages (<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">Zou et al., 2014</xref>): tight bud stage (S1); initial flowering stage (S2); full flowering stage (S3); and late full flowering stage (S4). Flowers were harvested at about 10 a.m. in October 2013. Each sample at each flowering stages was separated into two parts. One was directly used for headspace volatile analysis, and the other was immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen for volatile solvent and glycoside extraction, and RNA extraction.</p></sec><sec><title>SPME Collection and Solvent Extraction</title><p>The released floral volatiles were collected by solid-phase microextraction (SPME; <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Cai et al., 2014</xref>). In triplicate, 2 g fresh flowers were placed into a 20 ml capped SPME vial and incubated at 25 &#x000b1; 2&#x000b0;C for 30 min. SPME fiber (50/30 &#x003bc;m DVB/CAR/PDMS on a 2 cm Stable Flex fiber, Supelco Inc. Bellefonte, PA, USA) was then exposed to the headspace of the capped vial for 30 min. The fiber was injected manually and desorbed in the injection port of the gas chromatograph (GC) with helium as the carrier gas. The fiber was desorbed for 5 min at 250&#x000b0;C in splitless mode. Before each set of samples was assayed, the fiber was conditioned for 1 h at 250&#x000b0;C in the injection port of the GC-MS and a fiber blank recorded.</p><p>The accumulated free floral volatiles were collected by solvent extraction (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Green et al., 2012</xref>). In triplicate, 2 g frozen flowers, harvested at the equivalent time points to the SPME sampling, were ground to a fine powder in liquid nitrogen, transferred to a 50 ml centrifuge tube and extracted twice with 10 ml pentane/Et2O (1:1 v/v) for 30 min with gentle shaking. The two extractions were combined and stored overnight at -20&#x000b0;C. The following day, the upper solvent layer was carefully separated from the lower frozen water layer and reduced to 2 ml under a gentle stream of nitrogen. The concentrated extract, with 47.3 ng/&#x003bc;l cyclohexanone added as internal standard, was passed through a column of anhydrous MgSO<sub>4</sub> to remove any remaining water, and then injected into the GC.</p></sec><sec><title>Glycoside Extraction</title><p>Glycoside analysis was carried out according to <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Green et al. (2012)</xref> with minor modifications. In triplicate 2 g frozen flowers, harvested at the equivalent time points to the headspace sampling, were ground to a fine power in liquid nitrogen, transferred to a 50 ml centrifuge tube and resuspended in 30 ml ddH<sub>2</sub>O. The sample was centrifuged at 8,000 <italic>g</italic> for 15 min at 4&#x000b0;C and the supernatant run on a 15 mm &#x000d7; 25 mm i.d. Amberlite XAD-2 column (Supelco, Bellefonte, PA, USA) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions, at the rate of 3 ml/min. Soluble sugars and acids were removed with 40 ml water and free volatiles by the addition of 40 ml pentane/Et2O (1:1 v/v). Bound glycosides were eluted with 20 ml methanol and evaporated to dryness in a rotary evaporator. The resulting glycoside pellet was resuspended in 2 ml deglycosylation buffer (200 mM Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>, 220 mM citric acid, pH 5.0) and re-extracted three times with 1 ml pentane/Et2O (1:1 v/v) to remove any remaining free compounds.</p><p>Enzymatic hydrolysis was carried out using &#x003b2;-glucosidase (6 u/mg; Sigma&#x02013;Aldrich, Co, LLC, USA), dissolved in deglycosylation buffer, at a concentration of 10 mg/ml. The hydrolysis sample was overlaid with 1 ml Et2O and incubated at 40&#x000b0;C for 36 h. Following incubation, the sample was extracted a further three times with 1 ml Et2O. Prior to GC-MS analysis, the pooled extracts, with the addition of 47.3 ng/&#x003bc;l cyclohexanone as internal standard, were passed through a column of anhydrous MgSO<sub>4</sub> and reduced to 0.5 ml under a gentle stream of nitrogen.</p></sec><sec><title>GC-MS Analysis</title><p>The samples of the SPME collected, solvent extracted (1 &#x003bc;l) and glycoside volatiles (1 &#x003bc;l) were separated on a 30 m &#x000d7; 0.25 mm &#x000d7; 0.25 &#x003bc;m HP-5 capillary column (Thermo Scientific, Bellefonte, PA, USA). The system was a TRACE GC Ultra GC coupled to a DSQ II mass spectrometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA). The GC-MS was performed according to <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Cai et al. (2014)</xref>. The GC oven ramp for SPME collected volatiles was at 40&#x000b0;C for 3 min, 3&#x000b0;C/min to 73&#x000b0;C and held for 3 min, 5&#x000b0;C/min to 220&#x000b0;C and held for 1 min. The GC oven ramp for the solvent extracted and glycoside volatiles was at 40&#x000b0;C for 3 min, 3&#x000b0;C/min to 73&#x000b0;C and held for 3 min, 5&#x000b0;C/min to 240&#x000b0;C and held for 10 min. The flow rate of the helium (99.999%) carrier gas was 1.2 ml/min. The transfer line temperature was 280&#x000b0;C. For the mass detector, the ion source temperature was set at 230&#x000b0;C, with electronic impact (EI) mode at 70 eV over the mass range m/z 40&#x02013;450 amu. A C8&#x02013;C40 alkane standard solution (Sigma&#x02013;Aldrich, Co., LLC., USA) was analyzed regularly to provide references for calculation of retention time (Kovats) indices (RIs) and to monitor system performance. Identification of the compounds was based on a comparison of their mass spectra and retention indices (RIs) with the authentic standards and published data, as well as standard mass spectra in the NIST05. Relative quantification of the target compounds for emission was by measuring peak areas, and for accumulation using the internal standard method.</p></sec><sec><title>RNA Extraction and Real-Time PCR</title><p>Total RNA was isolated from 0.20 g frozen flowers using TRIzol reagent (CoWin Biotech Co., Ltd., Beijing, China), following the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions, and then treated with RQ1 DNase I (Promega, Madison, WI, USA) to remove genomic DNA. To synthesize first-strand cDNA, 3.50 &#x003bc;g total RNA was used with the RevertAid<sup>TM</sup> First Strand cDNA Synthesis Kit (Fermentas, Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc., USA) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. The synthetic first-strand cDNAs were diluted 10-fold for gene expression analysis.</p><p>Gene expression was detected by qRT-PCR in both &#x02018;Gecheng&#x02019; and &#x02018;Liuye&#x02019; flowers at four flowering stages. The qRT-PCR was performed on an Applied Biosystems 7500 Fast Real-Time PCR platform with the SYBR<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> Premix Ex Taq<sup>TM</sup> II mix (Takara Biotechnology Co., Ltd., Dalian, China), according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions, and the results were analyzed using the Applied Biosystems 7500 software (Applied Biosystems Life Technologies). Three biological replicates were tested, and reactions carried out in triplicate. Relative transcript levels were calculated by the 2<sup>-&#x00394;&#x00394;Ct</sup> method using &#x003b2;<italic>-actin</italic> as the endogenous control gene for data normalization. The primers for qRT-PCR analysis are listed in Supplemental Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S2</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Isolation of <italic>OfTPS</italic> Genes</title><p>Based on the <italic>TPS</italic> unigene sequences from the transcriptome sequencing of <italic>O. fragrans</italic> flowers, the full-lengths of four <italic>TPS</italic> genes were obtained using the SMARTER<sup>TM</sup> RACE method. The 5&#x02032; and 3&#x02032;-RACE-Ready cDNAs were separately synthesized using the BD SMARTER<sup>TM</sup> RACE cDNA Amplification Kit (Clontech, Mountain View, CA, USA). The amplified <italic>OfTPS</italic>s sequences were cloned into pEASY-T1 (TransGene Biotech CO., LTD, Beijing, China) and at least three independent clones were sequenced to check for PCR errors. The <italic>OfTPS</italic>s open reading frame (ORF) was predicted using the NCBI ORF Finder<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn01">1</xref></sup>. All primers used are listed in Supplemental Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S2</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Multiple Sequence Alignment and Phylogenetic Analysis</title><p>The DNAMAN 6.0 software (Lynnon Biosoft, USA) was used for multiple sequence alignment, and the phylogenetic tree constructed using the default parameters of the MEGA 6.1 software. The MEGA employed Clustal W2 software to generate multiple alignments and construction of the phylogenetic tree was based on the neighbor-joining computational method with 1000 bootstrap replicates. The bioinformatics tools ChloroP<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn02">2</xref></sup> and TargetP<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn03">3</xref></sup> were used to predict the intracellular localization of <italic>Of</italic>TPS proteins.</p></sec><sec><title>Transient and Stable Expression of <italic>OfTPS</italic> Genes in Tobacco</title><p>Full-length <italic>OfTPS</italic> ORFs were obtained from the pESAY-T1 vectors containing the target genes, using FastDigest enzymes (Fermentas, Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc., USA). <italic>OfTPS1</italic>, <italic>OfTPS2</italic>, and <italic>OfTPS3</italic> were digested with KpnI-XbaI, and <italic>OfTPS4</italic> with SmaI-XbaI. The restriction enzyme-generated inserts were cloned into the same restriction sites of the pCAMBIA 2300 binary vector to create pCAMBIA 2300::<italic>OfTPSs</italic> using T4 DNA ligase (Fermentas, Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc., USA). pCAMBIA 2300 contained the CaMV 35S promoter and nos-terminator. The pCAMBIA 2300::p19 was created by digesting the pGH-p19 vector using SmaI-XbaI to clone into the pCAMBIA 2300 vector, as described above. These plasmids were transformed in <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> strain EHA105 by electroporation.</p><p>Four to 6-week-old greenhouse-grown <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> seedlings were infiltrated with the <italic>A. tumefaciens</italic> strain EHA105, harboring the pCAMBIA 2300::<italic>OfTPSs</italic> and pCAMBIA 2300::p19, as described previously (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Hellens et al., 2005</xref>). When freshly grown <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> cultures reached an OD<sub>600</sub>
<sub>nm</sub> of 0.6&#x02013;0.8, they were centrifuged and resuspended in infiltration media (10 mM MES, 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 200 &#x003bc;M acetosyringone). The suspensions were adjusted to an OD<sub>600</sub>
<sub>nm</sub> of between 1.0 and 2.0, and incubated without shaking at 28&#x000b0;C for 2 h. The target gene and viral suppressor p19 <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> cultures were mixed in a 1:1 ratio before injection into <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> leaves using a syringe. After 5 days, 2 g of the treated leaves were harvested and placed in a 20 ml SPME vial for volatile analysis (as above).</p><p>Leaf disks of <italic>N. tabacum</italic> were transformed by co-culture with <italic>A. tumefaciens</italic> strain EHA105 harboring the pCAMBIA 2300::<italic>OfTPSs</italic> binary vector. Three to five independent transformed lines were obtained. The transformed plants, obtained after selection with kanamycin, were confirmed by semi quantitative RT-PCR with 2x Es Taq MasterMix (CoWin Biotech Co., Ltd, Beijing, China) and GAPDH as the reference gene. 2 g leaves of the transformed plants were used for volatile analysis.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Analysis of Monoterpene Emission and Accumulation in <italic>O. fragrans</italic> Flowers</title><p>Solid-phase microextraction-GC-MS analysis identified a total of 33 volatile compounds in two cultivars of &#x02018;Gecheng&#x02019; and &#x02018;Liuye&#x02019; at the initial flowering stage (S2), assigned to monoterpene, norisoprenoid, aromatic and fatty acid-related compounds (Supplemental Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S1</xref>). Seventeen monoterpenes were found in the two cultivars, with &#x003b2;-ocimene, linalool and derivatives the dominant components in both cultivars. However, the content of monoterpenes differed in the two cultivars (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref></bold>). The relative content of total monoterpenes was higher in &#x02018;Gecheng&#x02019; (70%) than &#x02018;Liuye&#x02019; (5%). In particular, <italic>trans</italic>-&#x003b2;-ocimene and linalool accounted for 44 and 23% of the total volatiles in &#x02018;Gecheng&#x02019;, but for only 1 and 2% in &#x02018;Liuye&#x02019; (Supplemental Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S1</xref>). The emission of <italic>cis</italic>-&#x003b2;-ocimene, <italic>trans</italic>-&#x003b2;-ocimene, linalool and linalool derivatives in both &#x02018;Gecheng&#x02019; and &#x02018;Liuye&#x02019; flowers showed a similar pattern, increasing from S1 to S3 and decreasing at S4 (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A&#x02013;D</xref></bold> and <bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref></bold>). The peak of &#x003b2;-ocimene and linalool emission occurred at S2 in &#x02018;Gecheng&#x02019; and at S3 in &#x02018;Liuye,&#x02019; while the peak of the linalool derivatives in both cultivars was at S3. The &#x003b2;-ocimene and linalool emissions at S2 were much higher in &#x02018;Gecheng&#x02019; than &#x02018;Liuye.&#x02019; The emissions of all linalool derivatives were higher in &#x02018;Gecheng&#x02019; throughout the flowering stages.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p><bold>Gas chromatograph (GC) trace of floral volatile emission in <italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic> at the initial flowering stage (S2). (A)</bold> Liuye, <bold>(B)</bold> Gecheng. (1) <italic>cis</italic>-&#x003b2;-ocimene; (2) <italic>trans</italic>-&#x003b2;-ocimene; (3) <italic>cis</italic>-Linalool oxide (furanoid); (4) <italic>trans</italic>-linalool oxide (furanoid); (5) &#x003b2;-linalool; (6) <italic>cis</italic>-linalool oxide (pyranoid); (7) <italic>trans</italic>-linalool oxide (pyranoid).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-06-01232-g001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p><bold>Emission and accumulation of monoterpenes and their derivatives in <italic>O. fragrans</italic> flowers at four stages. (A&#x02013;D)</bold> Emission abundance of monoterpenes and their derivative volatiles: <bold>(A)</bold>
<italic>cis</italic>-&#x003b2;-ocimene; <bold>(B)</bold>
<italic>trans</italic>-&#x003b2;-ocimene; <bold>(C)</bold> linalool, and <bold>(D)</bold> total linalool derivatives. <bold>(E,F)</bold> Free accumulation of linalool and its derivatives: <bold>(E)</bold> linalool and <bold>(F)</bold> total linalool derivatives. <bold>(G,H)</bold> Glycoside accumulation of linalool and its derivatives: <bold>(G)</bold> linalool and <bold>(H)</bold> total linalool derivatives. The four flowering stages are: (S1) tight bud stage; (S2) initial flowering stage; (S3) full flowering stage, and (S4) late full flowering stage. Data are presented as mean &#x000b1; SE (<italic>n</italic> = 3). The asterisks indicate significant differences between the values of &#x02018;Liuye&#x02019; and &#x02018;Gecheng&#x02019; at a given flower stage calculated by the Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test (<sup>&#x02217;</sup><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-06-01232-g002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>FIGURE 3</label><caption><p><bold>Emission and accumulation of linalool derivatives in <italic>O. fragrans</italic> flowers at four stages. (A)</bold> Emission of linalool derivatives. <bold>(B)</bold> Accumulation of free linalool derivatives. <bold>(C)</bold> Accumulation of glycosylated linalool derivatives. Flower stages are: (S1) tight bud stage; (S2) initial flowering stage; (S3) full flowering stage, and (S4) late full flowering stage. Data are presented as mean &#x000b1; SE (<italic>n</italic> = 3). The asterisks indicate significant differences between the values of &#x02018;Liuye&#x02019; and &#x02018;Gecheng&#x02019; at a given flower stage calculated by the Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test (<sup>&#x02217;</sup><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-06-01232-g003"/></fig><p>The accumulation of free monoterpenes in flowers was analyzed by solvent extraction, combining with GC-MS, collecting samples at the same stage as for SPME (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2E,F</xref></bold> and <bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref></bold>). Compared with the emitted monoterpenes, &#x003b2;-ocimene was barely detectable, but an abundance of linalool and derivatives accumulated in <italic>O. fragrans</italic> flowers. <italic>Cis</italic>-8-hydroxylinalool and 8-hydroxylinalool, the linalolol derivatives, were not detected as emitted floral volatiles but were found in solvent extracts. The accumulation pattern of linalool was consistent with the emission pattern in both cultivars, increasing from S1 to S3 and decreasing slightly at S4. The accumulation of linalool oxides continuously increased up to S3 and slightly decreased at S4, except for <italic>trans</italic>-linalool oxide(fur) in &#x02018;Gecheng,&#x02019; which was still increasing at S4. The accumulation of <italic>cis</italic>-8-hydroxylinalool and 8-hydroxylinalool in &#x02018;Gecheng&#x02019; gradually increased during the flowering stages, reaching the maximum at S4, while they basically remained steady in &#x02018;Liuye,&#x02019; dropping slightly at S3. More linalool was accumulated in &#x02018;Gecheng&#x02019; at S1 and S2, but in &#x02018;Liuye&#x02019; at S3 and S4. The result was just the contrary to <italic>cis</italic>-8-hydroxylinalool and 8-hydroxylinalool. There was much more accumulation of linalool oxides in &#x02018;Gecheng&#x02019; compared to &#x02018;Liuye&#x02019; during flowering.</p><p>Floral glycosylated volatiles were extracted from <italic>O. fragrans</italic> flowers and analyzed by GC-MS after enzymatic hydrolysis (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2G,H</xref></bold> and <bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref></bold>; <bold>Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref></bold>). Due to lack of hydoxylation in &#x003b2;-ocimene, only linalool and its derivatives were detected in glycosylated forms in <italic>O. fragrans</italic> flowers. In both cultivars, the glycosylated linalool and derivatives continuously increased during flowering, except for linalool in &#x02018;Gecheng,&#x02019; which remained stable throughout the flowering stages. After S2, more glycosylated linalool accumulated in &#x02018;Liuye&#x02019; than in &#x02018;Gecheng.&#x02019; The glycosylated linalool derivatives as <italic>trans</italic>-linalool oxide (furan and pyran), <italic>cis</italic>-8-hydroxylinalool and 8-hydroxylinalool accumulated much more in &#x02018;Gecheng&#x02019; than &#x02018;Liuye&#x02019; throughout the flowering process. The percentage of glycosylation of linalool continued increasing in &#x02018;Liuye&#x02019; from S1 to S4, but maintained a lower fraction in &#x02018;Gecheng.&#x02019; Although the percentage of glycoside linalool oxides changed irregularly, total linalool derivatives in glycoside forms continued increasing in both cultivars from S1 to S4, due to the dominant components, <italic>cis</italic>-8-hydroxylinalool and 8-hydroxylinalool, were constantly increasing.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Glycosylation of linalool and its derivatives in &#x02018;Liuye&#x02019; and &#x02018;Gecheng&#x02019; cultivars of <italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic> flowers at four stages.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="8" rowspan="1">Glycoside (% of total accumulation)<hr/></th></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Liuye<hr/></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Gecheng<hr/></th></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compounds</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S1</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S2</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S3</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S4</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S1</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S2</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S3</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S4</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2;-linalool</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.03 &#x000b1; 2.19</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.97 &#x000b1; 0.15</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.22 &#x000b1; 1.43</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.44 &#x000b1; 1.22</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.96 &#x000b1; 0.39</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold> 2.36 &#x000b1; 0.24</bold></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold> 4.49 &#x000b1; 1.05</bold></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold> 7.60 &#x000b1; 1.54</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total linalool derivatives</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.89 &#x000b1; 3.16</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.19 &#x000b1; 3.42</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.71 &#x000b1; 11.74</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.88 &#x000b1; 4.93</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>43.69 &#x000b1; 8.50</bold></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>67.58 &#x000b1; 12.70</bold></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.76 &#x000b1; 7.56</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.52 &#x000b1; 6.10</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cis</italic>-linalool oxide (furan)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.44 &#x000b1; 5.36</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.97 &#x000b1; 4.38</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.56 &#x000b1; 8.36</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.65 &#x000b1; 5.56</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>12.79 &#x000b1; 2.70</bold></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>10.29 &#x000b1; 0.37</bold></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.33 &#x000b1; 1.07</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.56 &#x000b1; 5.80</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Trans</italic>-linalool oxide (furan)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.10 &#x000b1; 12.30</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.80 &#x000b1; 1.38</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.51 &#x000b1; 9.60</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.62 &#x000b1; 10.76</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>18.39 &#x000b1; 2.41</bold></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>34.81 &#x000b1; 0.37</bold></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.21 &#x000b1; 12.35</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.03 &#x000b1; 8.18</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cis</italic>-linalool oxide (pyran)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.19 &#x000b1; 2.63</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.06 &#x000b1; 6.81</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.04 &#x000b1; 5.03</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.45 &#x000b1; 1.72</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.43 &#x000b1; 7.34</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>16.82 &#x000b1; 2.84</bold></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>19.50 &#x000b1; 4.16</bold></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>40.49 &#x000b1; 4.73</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Trans</italic>-linalool oxide (pyran)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.29 &#x000b1; 15.68</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.70 &#x000b1; 2.16</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.40 &#x000b1; 2.70</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.89 &#x000b1; 6.30</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>24.10 &#x000b1; 7.80</bold></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>38.85 &#x000b1; 8.91</bold></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.63 &#x000b1; 9.82</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.56 &#x000b1; 10.48</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8-hydroxylinalool</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.14 &#x000b1; 3.40</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.58 &#x000b1; 11.50</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.03 &#x000b1; 12.90</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.73 &#x000b1; 5.82</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>29.65 &#x000b1; 6.13</bold></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>82.49 &#x000b1; 10.55</bold></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.33 &#x000b1; 4.34</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.08 &#x000b1; 6.48</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cis</italic>-8-hydroxylinalool</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.60 &#x000b1; 1.58</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.06 &#x000b1; 5.45</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.09 &#x000b1; 14.33</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.53 &#x000b1; 4.32</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>52.29 &#x000b1; 12.31</bold></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>79.63 &#x000b1; 13.24</bold></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>91.32 &#x000b1; 5.09</bold></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.54 &#x000b1; 3.64</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib><italic>Data are presented as mean &#x000b1; SE (<italic>n</italic> = 3). The values in bold indicate significant differences to the &#x02018;Liuye&#x02019; values at a given flower stage ( Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05)</italic>.</attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Expression Analysis of Genes Involved in Monoterpene Biosynthesis in <italic>O. fragrans</italic> Flowers</title><p>The MEP pathway produces IPP and DMAPP for production of monoterpenes (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Munoz-Bertomeu et al., 2006</xref>) and TPS is the final enzyme converting the precursor GPP to kinds of monoterpenes (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Degenhardt et al., 2009</xref>). The transcript levels of thirteen genes involved in the eight enzyme reaction stages of the MEP pathway, one <italic>GPPS</italic>, and four <italic>TPS</italic>s were analyzed by real-time qPCR (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref></bold>).</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>FIGURE 4</label><caption><p><bold>Expression of genes involved in monoterpene biosynthesis in <italic>O. fragrans</italic> flowers at four stages</bold>. Flower stages are: (S1) tight bud stage; (S2) initial flowering stage; (S3) full flowering stage, and (S4) late full flowering stage. The relative abundance was determined using a 2<sup>-&#x00394;&#x00394;Ct</sup> method with &#x003b2;-actin as the reference gene. Results represent the mean &#x000b1; SE of three technical repetitions and three biological replicates. The asterisks indicate significant differences between the values of &#x02018;Liuye&#x02019; and &#x02018;Gecheng&#x02019; at a given flower stage calculated by the Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test (<sup>&#x02217;</sup><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01). Abbreviations: G3P, glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate; DXP, 1-deoxy-<sc>D</sc>-xylulose 5-phosphate; MEP, methylerythritol phosphate; CDP-ME, 4-diphosphocytidyl-2-C-methyl-<sc>D</sc>-erythritol; CDP-MEP, CDP-ME 2-phosphate; MECPD, 2-C-methyl-<sc>D</sc>-erythritol 2,4-cyclodiphosphate; HMBPP, (E)-4-hydroxy-3-methylbut-2-en-1-yl diphosphate; IPP, isopentenyl pyrophosphate; DMAPP, dimethylallyl pyrophosphate; GPP, geranyl pyrophosphate; MVP, mevalonate 5-phosphate; FPP, farnesyl pyrophosphate; DXS, 1-deoxy-<sc>D</sc>-xylulose 5-phosphate synthase; DXR, 1-deoxy-<sc>D</sc>-xylulose 5-phosphate reductoisomerase; MCT, 2-C-methyl-<sc>D</sc>-erythritol 4-phosphate cytidylyltransferase; CMK, 4-(cytidine 5&#x02032;-diphospho)-2-<italic>C</italic>-methyl-<sc>D</sc>-erythritol kinase; MECPS, 2-<italic>C</italic>-methyl-<sc>D</sc>-erythritol 2,4-cyclodiphosphate synthase; HDS, 4-hydroxy-3-methylbut-2-en-1-yl diphosphate synthase; IDS, isopentenyl diphosphate synthase; IDI, isopentenyl pyrophosphate isomerase; GPPS, geranyl pyrophosphate synthase; TPS, terpene synthase.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-06-01232-g004"/></fig><p>In the MEP pathway, the expression levels of <italic>DXR</italic>, <italic>CMK1</italic>, and <italic>MCT1</italic> remained stable in the two cultivars throughout the flowering stages, and only subtle differences (&#x0003c;2 fold) were detected in <italic>DXS1</italic>, <italic>MECPS</italic>, <italic>HDS</italic>, <italic>IDS1</italic>, <italic>IDS2</italic>, and <italic>IDS3</italic> expression between the two cultivars. There was higher expression of <italic>CMK2</italic>, <italic>MCT2</italic>, and <italic>IDI</italic> in &#x02018;Gecheng&#x02019; than &#x02018;Liuye&#x02019; from S1 to S4, but the difference was no more than threefold between the two cultivars, except for <italic>MCT2</italic> at S3. <italic>DXS2</italic> expression was no more than threefold higher in &#x02018;Liuye&#x02019; than &#x02018;Gecheng&#x02019; from S2 to S4. These results showed that, during flowering, there were minor differences between the two cultivars in the expression of most genes in the MEP pathway. Expression of <italic>GPPS</italic> was the same in both cultivars at S1, but three&#x02013;fivefold higher in &#x02018;Liuye&#x02019; from S2 to S4. Regarding the <italic>TPS</italic> genes, there was no apparent difference between the two cultivars during flowering for <italic>TPS2</italic> and <italic>TPS4</italic> expression, which gradually increased from S1 to S3 followed by a dramatic increase at S4. However, it is worth noting that the expression of <italic>TPS1</italic> and <italic>TPS3</italic> was more than 100-fold higher in &#x02018;Gecheng&#x02019; compared to &#x02018;Liuye&#x02019; throughout flowering stage. <italic>TPS1</italic> expression consistently increased from S1 to S4, while <italic>TPS3</italic> had the highest level of transcript accumulation at S3 in the two cultivars. The differences in the levels of <italic>TPS</italic> gene expression between &#x02018;Gecheng&#x02019; and &#x02018;Liuye&#x02019; indicated their important contribution to monoterpene formation in <italic>O. fragrans</italic> flowers.</p></sec><sec><title>Sequence Characterization of <italic>TPS</italic> Genes from <italic>O. fragrans</italic> Flowers</title><p>The four full-length <italic>TPS</italic> genes were cloned using the RACE-PCR method. Their ORF sequences were 1746, 1668, 1776, and 1647 bp, respectively, designated <italic>OfTPS1</italic>, <italic>OfTPS2</italic>, <italic>OfTPS3</italic>, and <italic>OfTPS4</italic> (GeneBank no. KT591180 to KT591183). The sequences of these four genes were identical in the cultivars &#x02018;Gecheng&#x02019; and &#x02018;Liuye.&#x02019; The four encoded proteins had highly conserved elements of TPSs, the DDxxD motif and the (N,D)D(L,I,V)x(S,T)xxxE motif, implying that they had the same capacity to bind the diphosphate group substrate (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref></bold>). The N-terminal RR(x)<sub>8</sub>W motif, involved in producing cyclic monoterpenes and absent in TPSs that produce acyclic products, only appeared in OfTPS4 (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref></bold>). Using the &#x02018;ChloroP&#x02019; and &#x02018;TargetP&#x02019; programs<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn04">4</xref></sup>, <italic>Of</italic>TPS1 and <italic>Of</italic>TPS3 were found to contain an extended N-terminus, recognized as a signal peptide, with a length of 47 and 38 amino acids, respectively. Phylogenetic analysis of the predicted amino acid sequences compared with TPS protein sequences in other species indicated that <italic>Of</italic>TPS1and <italic>Of</italic>TPS2 belong to the TPS-g subfamily, which lacks the RR(x)<sub>8</sub>W motif and mainly produce acyclic terpenes (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref></bold>). <italic>Of</italic>TPS1 and <italic>Of</italic>TPS2 divided into two distinct clades. <italic>Of</italic>TPS1 grouped together with geraniol synthase and linalool synthase from <italic>Olea europaea</italic> and <italic>Ocimum basilicam</italic> in one clade, and <italic>Of</italic>TPS2 in the clade with linalool synthase, nerolidol/linalool synthase, myrcene synthase and ocimene synthase of <italic>A. majus</italic>. <italic>Of</italic>TPS3 and <italic>Of</italic>TPS4 fell into the TPS-b subfamily, covering angiosperm monoterpene synthases (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref></bold>). <italic>Of</italic>TPS1, <italic>Of</italic>TPS3, and <italic>Of</italic>TPS4 showed highest amino acid sequence identity with geraniol synthase (90%), <italic>Oe</italic>TPS3 (90%), and <italic>Oe</italic>TPS2 (89%) from <italic>O. europaea</italic>, respectively. These results illustrate that they were the remaining uncharacterized TPSs and close to the similarly functional TPSs of <italic>O. europaea</italic>, also belonging to the Oleaceae family.</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>FIGURE 5</label><caption><p><bold>Alignment of the amino acid sequences of <italic>Of</italic>TPS1, <italic>Of</italic>TPS2, <italic>Of</italic>TPS3, and <italic>Of</italic>TPS4</bold>. Amino acids identical in all four proteins are shaded black and those identical in three proteins are shaded gray. The three highly conserved motifs are labeled RR-(x)<sub>8</sub>-W, DDxxD and (N,D)Dxx(S,T)xxxE, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-06-01232-g005"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>FIGURE 6</label><caption><p><bold>Phylogenetic analysis of selected plant terpene synthases (TPSs) based on estimation of pair-wise distances at the amino acid level</bold>. Clusters corresponding to five TPS subfamilies (TPS-a,TPS-b, TPS-d, TPS-g, and TPS-f) are apparent. The Clustal W 2.0 algorithm was used for the alignment. Trees were inferred with the neighbor-joining (NJ) method and <italic>n</italic> = 1000 replicates for bootstrapping.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-06-01232-g006"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Functional Identification of <italic>OfTPS</italic> Genes <italic>in Planta</italic></title><p>To investigate the volatiles produced by <italic>OfTPS</italic>s <italic>in planta</italic>, transient plant expression (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Hellens et al., 2005</xref>) was carried out by infiltration of <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> leaves using <italic>A. tumefaciens</italic> carrying pCAMBIA 2300::<italic>OfTPS</italic>s. Samples were taken 5&#x02013;6 days after inoculation and emitted volatiles were analyzed by SPME headspace sampling. Over-expression of <italic>OfTPS1</italic> and <italic>OfTPS2</italic> produced large amounts of &#x003b2;-linalool, with no other products detected. Only <italic>trans</italic>-&#x003b2;-ocimene was detected in tobacco leaves over-expressing <italic>OfTPS3</italic>, and &#x003b1;-farnesene was the only product in those over-expressing <italic>OfTPS4</italic>. No related products were observed in control leaves infiltrated with empty binary vectors (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7A,C</xref></bold>).</p><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>FIGURE 7</label><caption><p><bold>Functional characterization of terpene synthases (TPSs) from <italic>O. fragrans in planta.</italic><bold>(A)</bold> GC trace of leaves of transiently expressed <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> plants. (B)</bold> GC trace of leaves of transgenic <italic>N. tabacum</italic> plants. <bold>(C)</bold> Mass spectra of the products: (1) &#x003b2;-linalool, (2) <italic>trans</italic>-&#x003b2;-ocimene, (3) &#x003b1;-farnesene. Products were confirmed by comparison with authentic standards and/or GC-MS retention indices. <bold>(D)</bold> Semi-quantitative RT-PCR assay of <italic>Of</italic>TPS genes in transgenic <italic>N. tabacum</italic> plants.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-06-01232-g007"/></fig><p>Moreover, stably transformed <italic>N. tabacum</italic> plants were obtained through transformation with <italic>A. tumefaciens</italic> strain EHA105 harboring the pCAMBIA 2300::<italic>OfTPS</italic>s. Positive transgenic plants were further identified by semi-quantitative RT-PCR (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7D</xref></bold>). The volatile products of the <italic>OfTPS</italic> transformed plants were detected by SPME-GC-MS, and the results were the same as those from transient expression in plants (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7B</xref></bold>). These results suggest that both <italic>OfTPS1</italic> and <italic>OfTPS2</italic> are involved in synthesis of the same terpene product, &#x003b2;-linalool, and <italic>OfTPS3</italic> and <italic>OfTPS4</italic> are related to <italic>trans</italic>-&#x003b2;-ocimene and &#x003b1;-farnesene synthesis <italic>in planta</italic>, respectively.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Monoterpenes are common components of floral scent and play a role in attracting pollinators in plants (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Dudareva and Pichersky, 2006</xref>). Previous studies focusing on floral volatiles composition from <italic>O. fragrans</italic> have identified about 20 monoterpenes and find that monoterpenes such as &#x003b2;-ocimene, linalool and linalool derivatives are the major components of floral volatiles in most cultivars (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Cao et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Sun et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Xin et al., 2013</xref>). In an earlier study, we also identified these compounds as important aroma-active compounds in <italic>O. fragrans</italic> flowers, with the two cultivars of &#x02018;Gecheng&#x02019; and &#x02018;Liuye&#x02019; having distinct monoterpene emission profiles (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Cai et al., 2014</xref>). The current study gives basically identical results: monoterpenes, especially <italic>trans</italic>-&#x003b2;-ocimene and linalool, make up a large amount of the floral volatiles in &#x02018;Gecheng&#x02019; but only a trace in &#x02018;Liuye&#x02019; (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref></bold> and Supplemental Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S1</xref>). The results confirmed that &#x02018;Liuye&#x02019; only produces small amounts of monoterpenes, unlike most <italic>O. fragrans</italic> cultivars, so this cultivar can be used as contrasting materials for our further study on the molecular mechanism of monoterpene biosynthesis.</p><sec><title>Monoterpenes Emission and Glycosylation in <italic>O. fragrans</italic> Flowers</title><p>The emission of floral volatiles in <italic>A. majus</italic> and the content of essential oil in <italic>Lavandula</italic> species can vary with flower development (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Dudareva et al., 2000</xref>, <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Lane et al., 2010</xref>). We analyzed the emission and accumulation patterns of the dominant monoterpenes in two <italic>O. fragrans</italic> cultivars throughout the flowering stages. The highest levels of &#x003b2;-ocimene and linalool were found at the initial flowering stage in &#x02018;Gecheng&#x02019; and at the full flowering stage in &#x02018;Liuye,&#x02019; with emission of linalool derivatives reaching a peak at the initial or full flowering stage. These emission patterns were consistent with the other cultivars (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2008</xref>) and the concentrated emission of monoterpenes coincided with the optimal time for organoleptic aroma and pollination in <italic>O. fragrans</italic> (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Baldermann et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">Zhang, 2013</xref>). Moreover, the accumulation pattern of free linalool in the two cultivars was consistent with its emission, reaching the highest level in &#x02018;Gecheng&#x02019; at the initial flowering stage and in &#x02018;Liuye&#x02019; at the full flowering stage. Meanwhile, a parallel trend was observed between accumulation of free linalool oxides and their emission from the tight bud stage to the full flowering stage. These results suggested that both emission and accumulation of monoterpene are controlled by flower development, and the accumulation of free monoterpenes in flowers is directly proportional to their emission in <italic>O. fragrans</italic> flowers.</p><p>It has been reported that glycosylation might be involved in regulating the release of floral volatiles. For example, the decrease of glycosylated 2-phenylethanol in flowers correlating with rhythmic emission has demonstrated that glycosylation has an impact on floral 2-phenylethanol rhythmical release in <italic>Rosa damascena</italic> (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Picone et al., 2004</xref>). But the glycosylation profile cannot account for the different rhythmic patterns of (E)-nerolidol accumulation and emission in <italic>Actinidia chinensis</italic> (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Green et al., 2012</xref>). In this study, the accumulation and emission of linalool and its oxides in <italic>O. fragrans</italic> flowers shared parallel patterns from the tight bud stage to the full flowering stage. However, significant amounts of glycosylated linalool and its oxides were found during this period, and their accumulation continuously increased, especially at late full flowering stage when only a small amount of linalool and its oxides were released. These results showed that glycosylation was likely to have an impact on the linalool release in <italic>O. fragrans</italic> flowers at different flowering stages. Beside direct glycosylation, linalool tends to enzymatically convert to more stable linalool derivatives such as 8-hydroxylinalool and then is stored in plant tissues in glycosylated forms (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Lewinsohn et al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Green et al., 2012</xref>). In <italic>O. fragrans</italic> flowers, a large amount of linalool derivatives, especially <italic>cis</italic>-8-hydroxylinalool and 8-hydroxylinalool, were found and depleted the pool of linalool. These results showed the complexity of linalool metabolism, and further research on the accumulation and emission of linalool and its derivative should consider the action of glucosidase, cytochrome, P450 or cyclase for further catalytic conversion.</p></sec><sec><title>MEP Pathway Genes Analysis of <italic>O. fragrans</italic> Flowers</title><p>Monoterpene biosynthesis depends on the MEP pathway and the GPPS enzyme providing the GPP substrate (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2011</xref>). To discover the key gene controlling monoterpenes formation, the expression of genes involving in these enzymatic reactions were monitored in &#x02018;Gecheng&#x02019; and &#x02018;Liuye&#x02019; during flowering stages. It has been reported that, except for <italic>DXS</italic> and <italic>IDI</italic>, the other enzymes of the MEP pathway are encoded by single copy genes in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Cordoba et al., 2009</xref>). Two distinctive forms <italic>of CMK</italic> and <italic>IDS</italic> have been found in gymnosperms such as <italic>Ginkgo biloba</italic> and <italic>Pinus taeda</italic> (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2008a</xref>,<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>). Two different gene expression patterns of <italic>CMK, MCT</italic>, and <italic>IDS</italic> in two cultivars throughout the flowering stages indicated that at least two forms exist in <italic>O. fragrans</italic>. This suggested that regulation of metabolic flux by a multigene is also present at the mid-point of the MEP pathway in addition to the first step of this pathway in <italic>O. fragrans.</italic></p><p>As the over-expression of DXS in transgenic <italic>A. thaliana</italic> and tomato result in an increase in plastid isoprenoids such as diterpenes and carotenoids, the DXS enzyme has been considered as a rate-limiting enzyme for MEP pathway flux (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Enfissi et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Carretero-Paulet et al., 2006</xref>). In glandular trichomes of <italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic>, the transcript abundance of <italic>DXS</italic> correlates with oil yield which consists mostly of monoterpenes (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Xie et al., 2008</xref>). In <italic>V. vinifera</italic>, <italic>DXS</italic> co-localizes with a major QTL for the accumulation of linalool, nerol and geraniol (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Battilana et al., 2009</xref>). During the berry development, <italic>DXS</italic> expression shows a significant correlation with the accumulation profile of these monoterpenes (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Battilana et al., 2011</xref>). However, in this study, <italic>DXS</italic> gene expression did not agree with the emission and accumulation profiles of monoterpenes from <italic>O. fragrans</italic> flowers. On the contrary, there was a higher expression of <italic>DXS2</italic> in &#x02018;Liuye&#x02019; producing less monoterpenes from flowers. In the second step of the MEP pathway, DXR has also been suggested as a rate-limiting enzyme in <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, <italic>Mentha piperita</italic>, <italic>O. basilicum</italic> (<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Wildung and Croteau, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Carretero-Paulet et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Xie et al., 2008</xref>). However, the expression of <italic>DXR</italic> was also inconsistent with the monoterpenes production in <italic>O. fragrans</italic>. <italic>HDS</italic> and <italic>IDS</italic> is associated with foliar concentrations of the monoterpene 1,8-cineole in <italic>Eucalyptus globulus</italic> (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">K&#x000fc;lheim et al., 2011</xref>). Here, there was no connection between gene expression of <italic>HDS</italic> and <italic>IDS</italic> and the production of monoterpenes. Therefore, we concluded that these MEP pathway genes controlling the pathway flux in other species was not the rate-limiting factor for monoterpene biosynthesis in <italic>O. fragrans.</italic> Unexpectedly, the level of expression of <italic>CMK</italic>2 and <italic>MCT</italic>2 was higher in &#x02018;Gecheng&#x02019; than in &#x02018;Liuye.&#x02019; There were no reports about the connection between CMK, MCT, and monoterpene production, however, their gene expression seemed to be consistent with monoterpene emission in <italic>O. fragrans</italic>, the roles of <italic>CMK</italic> and <italic>MCT</italic> need further analysis.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>OfTPS</italic> Genes Expression in <italic>O. fragrans</italic> Flowers</title><p>Transcriptional control of <italic>TPS</italic> genes has been shown to regulate the production of certain monoterpenes. For example, both spatial and temporal <italic>AlstroTPS</italic> expression correlates well with myrcene emission in scented <italic>Alstroemeria</italic> genotypes (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Aros et al., 2012</xref>). Also, a concerted increase between expression of <italic>LaLINS</italic> and accumulation of linalool has been reported in the essential oil of <italic>Lavandula angustifolia</italic> during flower development (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Lane et al., 2010</xref>). Similar results have been found in plants such as <italic>A. majus</italic> (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Dudareva et al., 2003</xref>) and <italic>Origanum vulgare</italic> (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Crocoll et al., 2010</xref>). In this study, <italic>TPS2</italic> and <italic>TPS4</italic> expression showed a drastic increase from full flowering stage to late full flowering stage but no difference between &#x02018;Gecheng&#x02019; and &#x02018;Liuye&#x02019; during flowering stages, which was not consistent with the emission and accumulation of monoterpene in the two cultivars. Interestingly, expression of <italic>TPS1</italic> and <italic>TPS3</italic> was more than 100 fold higher in &#x02018;Gecheng&#x02019; as compared to &#x02018;Liuye,&#x02019; and their expression was in agreement with the production of monoterpene during flowering. These results indicated a direct contribution of <italic>TPS1</italic> and <italic>TPS3</italic> to monoterpenes production in flowers of <italic>O. fragrans.</italic> Carotenoid and monoterpene biosynthesis share the same pathway, which indicates a possible competition for the IPP and DMAPP precursors (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Botella-Pav&#x000ed;a et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Dudareva et al., 2013</xref>). However, although the production of monoterpenes in &#x02018;Liuye,&#x02019; containing trace amounts of carotenoids, was low and &#x02018;Gecheng,&#x02019; with large mounts of carotenoids still produced a lot of monoterpenes, this was only related to <italic>TPS</italic> genes expression. The results further demonstrated that the transcript levels of <italic>TPS</italic> genes on monoterpene production had a greater effect compared with the competition of carotenoid synthesis. This led to the conclusion that transcriptional regulation of <italic>TPS</italic> genes, especially <italic>TPS1</italic> and <italic>TPS3</italic>, was likely to be the most important mechanism for controlling production of the monoterpenes linalool or &#x003b2;-ocimene in <italic>O. fragrans</italic> flowers.</p></sec><sec><title>Sequence and Functional Characterization of <italic>O. fragrans TPS</italic> Genes</title><p>The putative functions of the four isolated TPSs from <italic>O. fragrans</italic> were initially predicted according to the conserved motifs and amino acid sequence similarity with known TPSs from other species. The four <italic>Of</italic>TPSs shared the conserved motifs DDxxD and (N,D)Dxx(S,T)xxxE) with other TPSs. <italic>Of</italic>TPS1 and <italic>Of</italic>TPS3 had the typical putative plastid targeting signal peptides but lacked the RR(x)<sub>8</sub>W motif in the N-terminal, which indicated they probably encoded acyclic monoterpene synthases. Phylogenetic analysis placed <italic>Of</italic>TPS1 in the TPS-g subfamily defined by monoterpene synthases, that produce acyclic scent compounds such as myrcene and ocimene in <italic>A. majus</italic> (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Dudareva et al., 2003</xref>), and linalool in <italic>A. thaliana</italic> (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2003</xref>) and <italic>V. vinifera</italic> (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Martin et al., 2010</xref>). Although <italic>Of</italic>TPS2 also belonged to the TPS-g subfamily, it was not clear whether this gene encodes a mono-TPS or sesqui-TPS, due to its unpredictable signal peptide and clustering with the bifunctional linalool/nerolidol synthase of <italic>A. majus</italic> (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Nagegowda et al., 2008</xref>), <italic>V. vinifera</italic> (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Martin et al., 2010</xref>), and <italic>A. chinensis</italic> (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Green et al., 2012</xref>). <italic>Of</italic>TPS3 and <italic>Of</italic>TPS4 clustered into the TPS-b subfamily in which all characterized TPSs are either monoterpene synthases, including all <italic>A. thaliana</italic> monoterpene synthases except linalool synthase (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2003</xref>) and <italic>V. vinifera</italic> ocimene synthases (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Martin et al., 2010</xref>), or isoprene synthases (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2011</xref>). But <italic>Of</italic>TPS4 clustered with &#x003b1;-farnesene synthase from <italic>Malus domestica</italic> (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Nieuwenhuizen et al., 2013</xref>) and <italic>V. vinifera</italic> (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Martin et al., 2010</xref>). Of the four <italic>Of</italic>TPS proteins, only <italic>Of</italic>TPS4 had the RR(x)<sub>8</sub>W motif that is present in all cyclic monoterpene synthases and most sesquiterpene and diterpene synthases (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Hyatt et al., 2007</xref>), which may play a role in triggering isomerization-cyclization or act to stabilize the protein (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Whittington et al., 2002a</xref>,<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>). Moreover, the unapparent signal peptide and high homology with &#x003b1;-farnesene synthase in phylogenetic analysis suggested that <italic>Of</italic>TPS4 was most likely a sesquiterpene synthase.</p><p>Transient and stable expression in tobacco leaves further confirm the function of <italic>OfTPS</italic> genes <italic>in planta</italic>, which could partly explain the production of major monoterpene volatiles in <italic>O. fragrans</italic> flowers. Over-expression of <italic>OfTPS1</italic> and <italic>OfTPS3</italic> genes in tobacco leaves resulted in the formation of only &#x003b2;-linalool and <italic>trans</italic>-&#x003b2;-ocimene, respectively. <italic>Of</italic>TPS2, that may be a bifunctional linalool/nerolidol synthase, produced &#x003b2;-linalool exclusively in over-expressing tobacco leaves. As previously speculated, sesquiterpene &#x003b1;-farnesene was the sole product emitted from tobacco leaves over-expressing <italic>OfTPS4</italic>. Most of the TPS enzymes from <italic>V. vinifera</italic> are multiple-product enzymes that can act on one substrate to produce more than one product (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Martin et al., 2010</xref>). However, there was only a single product of the four <italic>OfTPS</italic>s in the over-expressing tobacco leaves. The TPS enzyme, that produces the same single product, has also been found in <italic>V. vinifera</italic> and <italic>M. domestica</italic> (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Pechous and Whitaker, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Martin et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Nieuwenhuizen et al., 2013</xref>). <italic>Of</italic>TPS1, <italic>Of</italic>TPS3, and <italic>Of</italic>TPS4 showed high homology with <italic>Oe</italic>GES, <italic>Oe</italic>TPS3, and <italic>Oe</italic>TPS2 from <italic>O. europaea</italic>, respectively (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref></bold>). The homologous TPS proteins from <italic>O. fragrans</italic> and <italic>O. europaea</italic> had entirely different enzyme activities. Heterologous expression in a bacterial system has demonstrated that OeGES is a geraniol synthase only producing geraniol, and OeTPS2 and OeTPS3 have no enzymatic activity (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Vezzaro et al., 2012</xref>). <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Fischer et al. (2013)</xref>, expressing <italic>O. basilicum</italic> geraniol synthase in <italic>V. vinifera</italic>, <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> and a microbial system, has shown that the genetic background of the heterologous expression host could have an influence on minor products but not on the main product. Nevertheless the major monoterpene compounds (&#x003b2;-linalool and <italic>trans</italic>-&#x003b2;-ocimene) found in <italic>O. fragrans</italic> flowers have been detected in tobacco leaves over-expressing <italic>OfTPS1</italic>, <italic>OfTPS2</italic>, and <italic>OfTPS3</italic>. Moreover, gene expression of <italic>OfTPS1</italic> and <italic>OfTPS3</italic> are closely correlated to the accumulation or emission of &#x003b2;-linalool and <italic>trans</italic>-&#x003b2;-ocimene in <italic>O. fragrans</italic> flowers. Therefore, we conclude that <italic>OfTPS1</italic> and <italic>OfTPS3</italic> are separately the key genes associating with &#x003b2;-linalool and <italic>trans</italic>-&#x003b2;-ocimene production in <italic>O. fragrans</italic> flowers.</p><p>This study provided the molecular basis for the production of major monoterpenes in <italic>O. fragrans.</italic> The monoterpenes emission and accumulation profiles open the way to further understand the role of monoterpenes in the physiology and pollination biology of <italic>O. fragrans</italic> flowers. Understanding the expression of the MEP pathway genes in relation to monoterpene metabolism could generate vital information regarding the regulation of monoterpene biosynthesis in higher plants. The findings on the key TPS genes responsible for formation of the major monoterpenes would be a great advantage for breeding and manipulation of scent related-enzymes to enhance the ornamental and economic value in <italic>O. fragrans</italic> as well as in other plants in the future.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Author Contributions</title><p>XZ, CW designed the research; XZ, CL, XC, and JZ performed the research; XZ, RZ, and CL analyzed the data; XZ wrote the article; CW, JL, and RZ critically read the article.</p></sec><sec><title>Conflict of Interest Statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>This research was supported by the Doctoral Fund of the Ministry of Education of China (Project No 20130146110022), Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities (Project No 2013PY088) and Hubei Collaborative Innovation Center for the Characteristic Resources Exploitation of Dabie Mountains (Project No 2015TD02).</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="fn01"><label>1</label><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gorf/orfig.cgi">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gorf/orfig.cgi</ext-link></p></fn><fn id="fn02"><label>2</label><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/ChloroP/">http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/ChloroP/</ext-link></p></fn><fn id="fn03"><label>3</label><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/TargetP/">http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/TargetP/</ext-link></p></fn><fn id="fn04"><label>4</label><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/">http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/</ext-link></p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="supplementary material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://journal.frontiersin.org/article/10.3389/fpls.2015.01232">http://journal.frontiersin.org/article/10.3389/fpls.2015.01232</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1"><media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.DOCX"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aros</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Allemann</surname><given-names>R. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>C. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosati</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Volatile emissions of scented <italic>Alstroemeria</italic> genotypes are dominated by terpenes, and a myrcene synthase gene is highly expressed in scented <italic>Alstroemeria</italic> flowers.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Exp. Bot.</italic></source>
<volume>63</volume>
<fpage>2739</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2752</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/err456</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22268153</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aurore</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ginies</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganou-parfait</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Renard</surname><given-names>C. M. G. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fahrasmane</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Comparative study of free and glycoconjugated volatile compounds of three banana cultivars from French West Indies: Cavendish, Frayssinette and Plantain.</article-title>
<source><italic>Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>129</volume>
<fpage>28</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2011.01.104</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baldermann</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurosawa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurobayashi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleischmann</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Functional characterization of a carotenoid cleavage dioxygenase 1 and its relation to the carotenoid accumulation and volatile emission during the floral development of <italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic> Lour.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Exp. Bot.</italic></source>
<volume>61</volume>
<fpage>2967</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2977</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erq123</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20478967</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Battilana</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Costantini</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Emanuelli</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sevini</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Segala</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moser</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The 1-deoxy-dxylulose 5-phosphate synthase gene co-localizes with a major QTL affecting monoterpene content in grapevine.</article-title>
<source><italic>Theor. Appl. Genet.</italic></source>
<volume>118</volume>
<fpage>653</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>669</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-008-0927-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19037624</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Battilana</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Emanuelli</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gambino</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gribaudo</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasperi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boss</surname><given-names>P. K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Functional effect of grapevine 1-deoxy-D-xylulose 5-phosphate synthase substitution K284N on <italic>Muscat flavour</italic> formation.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Exp. Bot.</italic></source>
<volume>62</volume>
<fpage>5497</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5508</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/err231</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21868399</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Birti&#x00107;</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ginies</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Causse</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Renard</surname><given-names>C. M. G. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Changes in volatiles and glycosides during fruit maturation of two contrasted tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>) lines.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Agric. Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>57</volume>
<fpage>591</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>598</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf8023062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19154163</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Botella-Pav&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Besumbes</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carretero-Paulet</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boronat</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Concepci&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Regulation of carotenoid biosynthesis in plants:evidence for a key role of hydroxymethylbutenyl diphosphate reductase in controlling the supply of plastidial isoprenoid precursors.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant J.</italic></source>
<volume>40</volume>
<fpage>188</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>199</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2004.02198.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15447646</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mai</surname><given-names>R. Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>X. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Analysis of aroma-active compounds in three sweet osmanthus (<italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic>) cultivars by gas-chromatography-olfactometry and GC-mass spectrometry.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Zhejiang Univ. Sci. B</italic></source>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>638</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>648</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1631/jzus.B1400058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25001223</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>GC/MS fingerprint analysis of <italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic> Lour. in different varieties.</article-title>
<source><italic>Acta Hort. Sin.</italic></source>
<volume>36</volume>
<fpage>391</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>398</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carretero-Paulet</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cair&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Botella-Pav&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Besumbes</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boronat</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Enhanced flux through the methylerythritol 4-phosphate pathway in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants overexpressing deoxyxylulose 5-phosphate reductoisomerase.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Mol. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>62</volume>
<fpage>683</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>695</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-006-9051-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16941216</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tholl</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohlmann</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pichersky</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The family of terpene synthases in plants: a mid-size family of genes for specialized metabolism that is highly diversified throughout the kingdom.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant J.</italic></source>
<volume>66</volume>
<fpage>212</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>229</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2011.04520.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21443633</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tholl</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x02019;Auria</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farooq</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pichersky</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gershenzon</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Biosynthesis and emission of terpenoid volatiles from <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flowers.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell</italic></source>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>481</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>494</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.007989</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12566586</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yauk</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nieuwenhuizen</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matich</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Characterisation of an (S)-linalool synthase from kiwifruit (<italic>Actinidia arguta</italic>) that catalyses the first committed step in the production of floral lilac compounds.</article-title>
<source><italic>Funct. Plant. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>37</volume>
<fpage>232</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>243</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/FP09179</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cordoba</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salmi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leon</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Unravelling the regulatory mechanisms that modulate the MEP pathway in higher plants.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Exp. Bot.</italic></source>
<volume>60</volume>
<fpage>2933</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2943</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erp190</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19584121</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crocoll</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Asbach</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Novak</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gershenzon</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Degenhardt</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Terpene synthases of oregano (<italic>Origanum vulgare</italic> L.) and their roles in the pathway and regulation of terpene biosynthesis.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Mol. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>73</volume>
<fpage>587</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>603</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-010-9636-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20419468</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davidovich-Rikanati</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewinsohn</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bar</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iijima</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pichersky</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sitrit</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Overexpression of the lemon basil &#x003b1;-zingiberene synthase gene increases both mono- and sesquiterpene contents in tomato fruit.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant J.</italic></source>
<volume>56</volume>
<fpage>228</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>238</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2008.03599.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18643974</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Degenhardt</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000f6;llner</surname><given-names>T. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gershenzon</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Monoterpene and sesquiterpene synthases and the origin of terpene skeletal diversity in plants.</article-title>
<source><italic>Phytochemistry</italic></source>
<volume>70</volume>
<fpage>1621</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1637</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2009.07.030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19793600</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dudareva</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klempien</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muhlemann</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Biosynthesis, function and metabolic engineering of plant volatile organic compounds.</article-title>
<source><italic>New Phytol.</italic></source>
<volume>198</volume>
<fpage>16</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.12145</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23383981</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dudareva</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kish</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolosova</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorenstein</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Faldt</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>(E)-&#x003b2;-ocimene and myrcene synthase genes of floral scent biosynthesis in snapdragon: function and expression of three terpene synthase genes of a new terpene synthase subfamily.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell</italic></source>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>1227</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1241</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.011015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12724546</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dudareva</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murfitt</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorenstein</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolosova</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kish</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Developmental regulation of methyl benzoate biosynthesis and emission in snapdragon flowers.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell</italic></source>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>949</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>961</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/3871221</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10852939</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dudareva</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pichersky</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). &#x0201c;<article-title>Floral scent metabolic pathways: their regulation and evolution</article-title>,&#x0201d; in <source><italic>Biology of Floral Scent</italic>,</source>
<role>eds</role>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Dudareva</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pichersky</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Boca Raton, FL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>CRC/Taylor and Francis</publisher-name>), <fpage>55</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>78</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Enfissi</surname><given-names>E. M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lois</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boronat</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuch</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bramley</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Metabolic engineering of the mevalonate and non-mevalonate isopentenyl diphosphate-forming pathways for the production of health-promoting isoprenoids in tomato.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Biotechnol. J.</italic></source>
<volume>3</volume>
<fpage>17</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1467-7652.2004.00091.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17168896</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Est&#x000e9;vez</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cantero</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reindl</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reichler</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Le&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>1-Deoxy-D-xylulose-5-phosphate synthase, a limiting enzyme for plastidic isoprenoid biosynthesis in plants.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Biol. Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>276</volume>
<fpage>22901</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22909</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M100854200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11264287</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>M. J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Claudel</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perrin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ginglinger</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gertz</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Specificity of <italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> geraniol synthase modified by its expression in different heterologous systems.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Biotechnol.</italic></source>
<volume>163</volume>
<fpage>24</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>29</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbiotec.2012.10.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23108028</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>C. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>R. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Winz</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Quek</surname><given-names>S. Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Changes in the bound aroma profiles of &#x02018;Hayward&#x02019; and &#x02018;Hort16A&#x02019; kiwifruit (<italic>Actinidia</italic> spp.) during ripening and GC-olfactometry analysis.</article-title>
<source><italic>Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>137</volume>
<fpage>45</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>54</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2012.10.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23199989</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garms</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kollner</surname><given-names>T. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boland</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>A multiproduct terpene synthase from <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic> generates cadalane sesquiterpenes via two different mechanisms.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Organ. Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>75</volume>
<fpage>5590</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5600</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jo100917c</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nieuwenhuizen</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matich</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bunn</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Identification, functional characterization, and regulation of the enzyme responsible for floral (E)-nerolidol biosynthesis in kiwifruit (<italic>Actinidia chinensis</italic>).</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Exp. Bot.</italic></source>
<volume>63</volume>
<fpage>1951</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1967</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/err393</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22162874</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Differential expression of carotenoid-related genes determines diversified carotenoid coloration in flower petal of <italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Tree Genet. Genomes</italic></source>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>329</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>338</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00425-010-1222-x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hellens</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Allan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Friel</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolitho</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grafton</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Templeton</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Transient expression vectors for functional genomics, quantification of promoter activity and RNA silencing in plants.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Methods</italic></source>
<volume>1</volume>:<issue>13</issue>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4811-1-13</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hyatt</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Youn</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Santhamma</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coates</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Croteau</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Structure of limonene synthase, a simple model for terpenoid cyclase catalysis.</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</italic></source>
<volume>104</volume>
<fpage>5360</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5365</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0700915104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17372193</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuzuyama</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S. U.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008a</year>). <article-title>Two copies of 4-(cytidine 5-diphospho)-2-C-methyl-D-erythritol kinase (CMK) gene in <italic>Ginkgo biloba</italic>: molecular cloning and functional characterization.</article-title>
<source><italic>Planta</italic></source>
<volume>228</volume>
<fpage>941</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>950</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00425-008-0794-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18668260</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuzuyama</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Y. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sando</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S. U.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008b</year>). <article-title>1-Hydroxy-2-methyl-2-(E)-butenyl 4-diphosphate reductase (IDS) is encoded by multicopy genes in gymnosperms <italic>Ginkgo biloba</italic> and <italic>Pinus taeda</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Planta</italic></source>
<volume>227</volume>
<fpage>287</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>298</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00425-007-0616-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17763867</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>K&#x000fc;lheim</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeoh</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallis</surname><given-names>I. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Laffan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>G. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Folev</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The molecular basis of quantitative variation in foliar secondary metabolites in <italic>Eucalyptus globulus</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>New Phytol.</italic></source>
<volume>191</volume>
<fpage>1041</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1053</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2011.03769.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21609332</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boecklemann</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Woronuk</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarker</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahmoud</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>A genomics resource for investigating regulation of essential oil production in <italic>Lavandula angustifolia</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Planta</italic></source>
<volume>231</volume>
<fpage>835</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>845</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00425-009-1090-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20043174</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lewinsohn</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schalechet</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsui</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tadmor</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Enhanced levels of the aroma and flavor compound S-linalool by metabolic engineering of the terpenoid pathway in tomato fruits.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>127</volume>
<fpage>1256</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1265</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.010293</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11706204</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Study on chemical constituents of fragrance releases from fresh flowers of three different <italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic> Lour. During different florescences.</article-title>
<source><italic>Chem. Ind. For. Prod.</italic></source>
<volume>28</volume>
<fpage>75</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>80</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahmoud</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Croteau</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Metabolic engineering of essential oil yield and composition in mint by altering expression of deoxyxylulose phosphate reductoisomerase and menthofuran synthase.</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</italic></source>
<volume>98</volume>
<fpage>8915</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8920</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.141237298</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11427737</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aubourg</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schouwey</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Daviet</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schalk</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toub</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Functional annotation, genome organization and phylogeny of the grapevine (<italic>Vitis vinifera</italic>) terpene synthase gene family based on genome assembly, FLcDNA cloning, and enzyme assays.</article-title>
<source><italic>BMC Plant Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>10</volume>:<issue>226</issue>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-10-226</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Munoz-Bertomeu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arrillaga</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ros</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Segura</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Up-regulation of 1-deoxy-D-xylulose-5-phosphate synthase enhances production of essential oils in transgenic spike lavender.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>142</volume>
<fpage>890</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>900</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.106.086355</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16980564</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagegowda</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gutensohn</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkerson</surname><given-names>C. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudareva</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Two nearly identical terpene synthases catalyze the formation of nerolidol and linalool in snapdragon flowers.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant J.</italic></source>
<volume>55</volume>
<fpage>224</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>239</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2008.03496.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18363779</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nieuwenhuizen</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailleul</surname><given-names>E. J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matich</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M. Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Functional genomics reveals that a compact terpene synthase gene family can account for terpene volatile production in apple.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>161</volume>
<fpage>787</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>804</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.112.208249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23256150</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nieuwenhuizen</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matich</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yauk</surname><given-names>Y. K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Two terpene synthases are responsible for the major sesquiterpenes emitted from the flowers of kiwifruit (<italic>Actinidia deliciosa</italic>).</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Exp. Bot.</italic></source>
<volume>60</volume>
<fpage>3203</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3219</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erp162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19516075</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohgami</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ono</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Horikawa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murata</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Totsuka</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toyonaga</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Volatile glycosylation in tea plants: sequential glycosylations for the biosynthesis of aroma &#x003b2;-primeverosides are catalyzed by two <italic>Camellia sinensis</italic> glycosyltransferase.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>168</volume>
<fpage>464</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>477</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.15.00403</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25922059</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pechous</surname><given-names>S. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitaker</surname><given-names>B. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Cloning and functional expression of an (E, E)-&#x003b1;-farnesene synthase cDNA from peel tissue of apple fruit.</article-title>
<source><italic>Planta</italic></source>
<volume>219</volume>
<fpage>84</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>94</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14740213</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Picone</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clery</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>MacTavish</surname><given-names>H. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turnbull</surname><given-names>C. G. N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Rhythmic emission of floral volatiles from <italic>Rosa damascena</italic> semperflorens cv. &#x02018;<italic>Quatre Saisons.</italic>&#x02019;</article-title>
<source><italic>Planta</italic></source>
<volume>219</volume>
<fpage>468</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>478</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00425-004-1250-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15054660</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reuveni</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sagi</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Evnor</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hetzroni</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>&#x003b2;-glucosidase activity is involved in scent production in <italic>Narcissus</italic> flowers.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>147</volume>
<fpage>19</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0168-9452(99)00097-7</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwab</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>T. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giri</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>W&#x000fc;st</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Potential applications of glucosyltransferases in terpene glucoside production: impacts on the use of aroma and fragrance.</article-title>
<source><italic>Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</italic></source>
<volume>99</volume>
<fpage>165</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>174</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-014-6229-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25431013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>HS-SPME-GC-MS analysis of different <italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic> cultivars from Guilin Garden in Shanghai.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Fujian For. Coll.</italic></source>
<volume>32</volume>
<fpage>39</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tholl</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Petri</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gershenzon</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pichersky</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Two sesquiterpene synthases are responsible for the complex mixture of sesquiterpenes emitted from <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flowers.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant J.</italic></source>
<volume>42</volume>
<fpage>757</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>771</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2005.02417.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15918888</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vezzaro</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>S. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nonis</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramina</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Degenhardt</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruperti</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Isolation and characterization of terpene synthases potentially involved in flavor development of ripening olive (<italic>Olea europaea</italic>) fruits.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>169</volume>
<fpage>908</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>914</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jplph.2012.01.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22475500</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Variations in the components of <italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic> Lour essential oil at different stages of flowering.</article-title>
<source><italic>Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>114</volume>
<fpage>233</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>236</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2008.12.014</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>Y. Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>B. Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>Y. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Q. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C. Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Free and glycosidically bound aroma compounds in cherry (<italic>Prunus avium</italic> L).</article-title>
<source><italic>Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>152</volume>
<fpage>29</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>36</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2013.11.092</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24444903</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whittington</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wise</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Croteau</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Christianson</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002a</year>). <article-title>Insights into monoterpene cyclization reactions in biology: crystal structure of (+)-bornyl diphosphate synthase.</article-title>
<source><italic>Biochemistry</italic></source>
<volume>41</volume>:<issue>8973</issue>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whittington</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wise</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Urbansky</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coates</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Croteau</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Christianson</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002b</year>). <article-title>Bornyl diphosphate synthase: structure and strategy for carbocation manipulation by a terpenoid cyclase.</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</italic></source>
<volume>99</volume>
<fpage>15375</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15380</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.232591099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12432096</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wildung</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Croteau</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Genetic engineering of peppermint for improved essential oil composition and yield.</article-title>
<source><italic>Transgenic Res.</italic></source>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>365</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>372</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11248-005-5475-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16201403</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kapteyn</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gang</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>A systems biology investigation of the MEP/terpenoid and shikimate/phenylpropanoid pathways points to multiple levels of metabolic control in sweet basil glandular trichomes.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant J.</italic></source>
<volume>54</volume>
<fpage>349</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>361</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2008.03429.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18248593</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xin</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Characterization of volatile compounds in flowers from four groups of sweet osmanthus (<italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic>) cultivars.</article-title>
<source><italic>Can. J. Plant Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>93</volume>
<fpage>923</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>931</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4141/cjps2012-333</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Effect of &#x003b2;-D-glucosidase on aromatic compounds of sweet osmanthus.</article-title>
<source><italic>Fine Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>22</volume>
<fpage>924</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>926</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yauk</surname><given-names>Y. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ged</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matich</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tessarotto</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooney</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Manipulation of flavour and aroma compound sequestration and release using a glycosyltransferase with specificity for terpene alcohols.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant J.</italic></source>
<volume>80</volume>
<fpage>317</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>330</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.12634</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25088478</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <source><italic>Pollination Biology of Osmanthus fragrans Lour.</italic></source>
<publisher-name>Ph.D. dissertation, University of Nanjing Forestry, Nanjing</publisher-name>, <fpage>16</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C. Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Increase in DNA fragmentation and the role of ethylene and reactive oxygen species in petal senescence of <italic>Osmanthus fragrans</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Postharvest Biol. Technol.</italic></source>
<volume>93</volume>
<fpage>97</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>105</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.postharvbio.2014.02.015</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>