<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8566568</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1026</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-01026-7</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>RNASeq analysis of drought-stressed guayule reveals the role of gene transcription for modulating rubber, resin, and carbohydrate synthesis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Chen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Ponciano</surname><given-names>Grisel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huo</surname><given-names>Naxin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Yong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ilut</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>McMahan</surname><given-names>Colleen</given-names></name><address><email>colleen.mcmahan@usda.gov</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.507310.0</institution-id><institution>USDA Agricultural Research Service, Western Regional Research Center, </institution></institution-wrap>Albany, CA 94710 USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5386.8</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">000000041936877X</institution-id><institution>Plant Breeding and Genetics Section, School of Integrative Plant Science, </institution><institution>Cornell University, </institution></institution-wrap>Ithaca, NY 14853 USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>3</day><month>11</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>3</day><month>11</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>21610</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>5</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>10</month><year>2021</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2021</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">The drought-adapted shrub guayule (<italic>Parthenium argentatum</italic>) produces rubber, a natural product of major commercial importance, and two co-products with potential industrial use: terpene resin and the carbohydrate fructan. The rubber content of guayule plants subjected to water stress is higher compared to that of well-irrigated plants, a fact consistently reported in guayule field evaluations. To better understand how drought influences rubber biosynthesis at the molecular level, a comprehensive transcriptome database was built from drought-stressed guayule stem tissues using de novo RNA-seq and genome-guided assembly, followed by annotation and expression analysis. Despite having higher rubber content, most rubber biosynthesis related genes were down-regulated in drought-stressed guayule, compared to well-irrigated plants, suggesting post-transcriptional effects may regulate drought-induced rubber accumulation. On the other hand, terpene resin biosynthesis genes were unevenly affected by water stress, implying unique environmental influences over transcriptional control of different terpene compounds or classes. Finally, drought induced expression of fructan catabolism genes in guayule and significantly suppressed these fructan biosynthesis genes. It appears then, that in guayule cultivation, irrigation levels might be calibrated in such a regime to enable tunable accumulation of rubber, resin and fructan.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Biotechnology</kwd><kwd>Computational biology and bioinformatics</kwd><kwd>Molecular biology</kwd><kwd>Plant sciences</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>USDA-NIFA-BRDI</institution></funding-source><award-id>2012-10006-19391 OH</award-id><award-id>2012-10006-19391 OH</award-id><award-id>2012-10006-19391 OH</award-id><award-id>2012-10006-19391 OH</award-id><award-id>2012-10006-19391 OH</award-id><award-id>2012-10006-19391 OH</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Chen</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponciano</surname><given-names>Grisel</given-names></name><name><surname>Huo</surname><given-names>Naxin</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Yong</given-names></name><name><surname>Ilut</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name><name><surname>McMahan</surname><given-names>Colleen</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2021</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Guayule (<italic>Parthenium argentatum</italic> A. Gray), the perennial desert shrub native to the Southwestern United States and northern Mexico, is a rubber-producing plant adapted to arid and semiarid regions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. Large scale guayule cultivation in the United States could provide a domestic source of natural rubber (NR, <italic>cis</italic>-1,4-polyisoprene) necessary for national defense, modern transportation, and medicine<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. One challenge in guayule crop management is to maximize rubber yield while maintaining efficient irrigation water use. Techno-economic models for guayule cultivation point to water use as a major cost to growers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. However, high yields of rubber can be achieved with subsurface drip irrigation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. In that study, as in others<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>, guayule biomass and rubber yield responded positively to total water applied; however plant rubber content (wt%) consistently increased as irrigation water levels decreased. The possibility that drought stress may positively impact rubber biosynthesis is compelling, especially since water availability is an economic and environmental constraint in the Southwestern US.</p><p id="Par3">In addition to NR, guayule produces other secondary metabolites in appreciable amounts such as resin (5&#x02013;12% dry weight<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>). Guayule resin constitutes a mixture of terpenoids, sterols, fatty acids, aromatic compounds, and low-molecular weight rubber, but the precise composition is much more complex<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. Among the most abundant resin extractable compounds are argentatins (20&#x02013;30%) which may have anti-cancer properties<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup> and the guayulins (10&#x02013;15%) known to have fungistatic and miticide activities<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. The biological roles of individual resin compounds have likely evolved in response to biotic and abiotic stresses, and/or have ecological functions as is the case of many plant secondary metabolites<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. Interestingly, the cellular locations of resin and NR production in guayule are in close proximity. The terpene components of resin are produced in resin canals in the bark parenchyma tissue and in the pith of stems, and NR is predominantly found in a single layer of epithelial cells surrounding the resin canal<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. This intimate spatial distribution of the two metabolites makes it difficult to extract resin-free rubber (residual resin in the rubber extract compromises its stability<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>), and vice-versa. Proposed commercial uses of guayule resin include in wood preservatives, paints and adhesives<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>, asphalt<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>, and pharmaceutical compounds<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">Another abundant metabolite produced by guayule is the carbohydrate fructan (up to&#x02009;~&#x02009;10% dry weight<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>), a biobased chemical feedstock. Fructans are fructose-based polymers with the predominant role of serving as carbon reserves when metabolic demand exceeds carbon availability<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>, but are also considered to be protective agents against abiotic stresses<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. In guayule, fructans accumulate mainly in the root and stems and to lesser extent in leaves<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. Fructan levels fluctuate seasonally<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>, and are highest at the onset of and during winter conditions parallel to rubber biosynthesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">The precise mechanism of in vivo NR synthesis remains to be elucidated, but in general the biosynthetic pathway comprises two main phases. First, the monomeric unit isopentenyl pyrophosphate (IPP), the rubber polymer-monomer, and the allylic initiator (typically farnesyl pyrophosphate, FPP) required for rubber biosynthesis, are produced by the cytosolic mevalonate pathway (MVA). Importantly, the IPP and FPP pools are substrates for biosynthesis of all downstream isoprenoids (terpenes, dolichols, sterols, etc.) many of which make up guayule resin. The second phase involves the actual NR synthesis by an enzymatic complex (rubber transferase, RuT) of unknown identity. The RuT is presumed to be localized on the surface of a vesicle derived from the endoplasmic reticulum and known as a rubber particle (RP). Current models propose FPP first binds to the RuT-binding site, and subsequently thousands of IPP undergo condensation reactions to produce the rubber molecule. As NR is synthesized it accumulates inside the RP while various distinctive proteins associate to stabilize it and/or modulate rubber biosynthesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par6">It is well established that cold stress elicits rubber biosynthesis in guayule stem bark tissues<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>, but water stress has also been reported to have a positive effect in guayule rubber content<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. With the goal of identifying molecular players of drought-stressed guayule impacting rubber biosynthesis, we analyzed the transcriptome of field-grown plants under two irrigation water treatments: drought-like and fully irrigated control. A comprehensive transcriptome database was built using genome-guided<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup> and de novo RNA-seq assembly. Our comparative analyses of the global transcription expression revealed that transcripts related to rubber biosynthesis were mostly down-regulated. Further, transcripts related to fructan biosynthesis (but not fructan catabolism) were also down-regulated. Expression regulation of genes encoding enzymes responsible for terpene resin biosynthesis was mixed.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Transcriptome sequencing and read assembly</title><p id="Par7">To elucidate the molecular responses impacting secondary metabolite production in guayule during drought stress, six libraries from drought-treated and control stem tissue RNA were sequenced using Illumina HiSeq 2000 platform. In total, 196,861,972 raw pair-end reads with a read length of 2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;150&#x000a0;bp were generated (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). After quality trimming, 97.11% of cleaned reads were recovered and used for sequence assembly. A comprehensive transcriptome database was built using both genome-guided and Trinity de novo RNA-Seq assembly methods incorporated in the PASA pipeline<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. A total of 229,190 unique contigs were obtained with non-redundant cut off at 95%, following a further filtration process to retain transcripts longer than 300&#x000a0;bp only. The most highly expressed transcripts that represent 84% of the total normalized expression data achieved an N50 of 1851 bps. The total accumulated size of the assembled transcripts was approximately 249&#x000a0;Mb, with length ranging from 300 to 17,875&#x000a0;bp. Additionally, 90.75% of all clean reads perfectly mapped back to the reference transcriptome, suggesting a strong representation of the read input and the quality of the assembly was sufficient for downstream analysis.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Transcriptome assembly summary statistics. Annotation carried out with BlastX and cut-off at 1E-5.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="3"><bold>Assembly statistics</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Number of unigenes</td><td align="left" colspan="2">229,190</td></tr><tr><td align="left">GC content</td><td align="left" colspan="2">40.41%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">N50 (bp)</td><td align="left" colspan="2">1,640</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Media contig (bp)</td><td align="left" colspan="2">869</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Average contig (bp)</td><td align="left" colspan="2">1,172</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Database</th><th align="left">Contig counts</th><th align="left">% annotated</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="3"><bold>Functional annotation</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Nr</td><td char="." align="char">143,286</td><td char="." align="char">62.52</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Swiss-prot</td><td char="." align="char">111,873</td><td char="." align="char">48.81</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Trembl</td><td char="." align="char">142,449</td><td char="." align="char">62.15</td></tr><tr><td align="left">PlantTFDB</td><td char="." align="char">2,759</td><td char="." align="char">1.20</td></tr><tr><td align="left">KEGG</td><td char="." align="char">65,879</td><td char="." align="char">28.74</td></tr><tr><td align="left">GO</td><td char="." align="char">34,502</td><td char="." align="char">15.37</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Total Transcripts</td><td char="." align="char">229,190</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Differential gene expression and functional enrichment</title><p id="Par8">To quantify abundances of each unigene, Kallisto<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup> was used to generate TPM (transcripts per million), reflecting the relative molar concentration of transcripts in each sample. edgeR<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup> was deployed to identify the differentially expressed transcripts with FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and log2 fold change&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;2. As a result, 1677 were found to be significantly differentially expressed, with 881 up-regulated and 796 down-regulated transcripts in drought-stressed tissue compared to the control (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Volcano plot representation of differential expression. Red and blue points mark the transcripts with significantly increased or decreased expression in drought stressed plants versus control plants,&#x000a0;respectively (FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). The x-axis shows log2 fold-changes in expression and the y-axis log10 false discovery rate of a transcript being differentially expressed.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_1026_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par9">To predict and analyze the function of the differentially expressed unigenes, we assessed the assembled transcripts using BLASTX search against databases listed in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Among the 229,190 transcripts, 143,286 (62.52%) could be annotated in Nr (NCBI non-redundant protein sequences), 51,596 (47.94%) in Pfam (protein family database), 104,111 (45.43%) in Swiss-Prot (a manually annotated and reviewed protein sequences database), 34,502 (15.37%) in GO (Gene Ontology), and 40,917 (17.85%) in KEGG (Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes). Overall, 70.15% transcripts were significantly matched to known genes in the public databases mentioned above (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), while those with no significant protein matches may represent novel proteins and long non-coding RNAs in guayule.</p><p id="Par10">Transcription factors (TFs) regulate the transcription of genes and play key regulatory roles in plant growth, development, and response to environmental stress. Our analysis revealed that 2759 transcripts (1.20%) encode putative TFs that can be classified into 56 families (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). Most abundantly represented were the basic helix-loop-helix (bHLH) family (292, 10.58%), followed by cysteine2-histidine2 zinc finger (C2H2) family (179, 6.49%), basic leucine zipper (bZIP) family (166, 6.02%), no apical meristem/ATAF1&#x02013;2/cup-shaped cotyledon (NAC) family (160, 5.80%), myeloblastosis (MYB) and related (296, 10.73%) and the cysteine3histidine (C3H) family (139, 5.04%). It is worth noting that MYB-related, bHLH and WRKY families are known to regulate secondary metabolism pathways in plants. In the rubber producing tree <italic>Hevea brasiliensis</italic> (Hevea), HbMYC2 was found to be highly expressed in bark and possibly positively regulating the RP associated gene <italic>HbSRPP</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup> and to activate NR biosynthesis genes <italic>HbFPS1</italic> and <italic>HbSRPP1</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par11">The three most enriched differentially expressed TF families were constans-like (2 transcripts up- and 7 down-regulated), MYB-related (9 transcripts up), golden2-like (1 transcript up- and 5 down-regulated) and bHLH (3 up- and 1 down-regulated). More than 60% of CO-like TF family transcripts (9 of 15) were significantly enriched under drought condition, among which more than 77% were down-regulated. The identification of this large set of TFs, along with their expression profiling under drought stress, provides a rich resource for future characterization of specific roles of TFs in rubber biosynthesis pathway under drought stress condition. Interestingly, we performed a comparative analysis of the transcriptome profile from greenhouse grown guayule subjected to cold<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>, and our drought stressed guayule transcriptome found a total of 58 significantly differentially expressed contigs under both stresses; sixteen of these encode transcription factors (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>).</p><p id="Par12">Gene Ontology assignments were used to determine the potential functions of the transcripts and classify them based on various biological processes. In total, 34,502 contigs were assigned to three major functional categories: biological process, molecular function, and cellular component (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The GO sub-categories with the largest transcripts were &#x02018;cellular process&#x02019;, &#x02018;metabolic process&#x02019;, &#x02018;catalytic activity&#x02019;, &#x02018;binding&#x02019;, and &#x02018;cellular anatomical entity&#x02019;.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Gene Ontology (GO) analysis of RNA-seq. GO term classification of the entire transcriptome. <italic>BP</italic> biological process; <italic>CC</italic> cellular component; <italic>MF</italic> molecular function.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_1026_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par13">For GO enrichment analysis, we took consideration of correlations within a gene set with modest variability in expression but which may exhibit a general trend. The entire contig list, ranked based on the level of fold change without eliminating the ones considered non-significant, was supplied into Kolmogorov&#x02013;Smirnov test. Overall, a total of 33 ontology terms (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>) were enriched with FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01. Interestingly, only one set involving terpene synthase activity (GO:0010333) was recognized as down-regulated in the drought stressed plants. Seven out of the remaining 32 up-regulated gene sets were, not surprisingly, related to redox activity grouped across both biological process and molecular function. We also found 5 enrichment sets of transcripts associated with proton transport coupled with ATP production and decomposition via oxidative phosphorylation and the tricarboxylic acid cycle as well as transcription and translation machinery, indicating that drought stressed plants were in a highly active energetic state through cellular respiration. Notably, glycolytic process (GO:0006096) producing pyruvate as end-product, which after oxidative decarboxylation fuels the carbon source for rubber biosynthesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>, is also significantly enriched in drought-stressed plants.</p><p id="Par14">KEGG pathway analysis was performed to identify the active biological pathways in the annotated guayule sequences. Upon mapping the annotated sequences, 40,917 transcripts (17.85%) were identified and assigned to 353 metabolic pathways, including &#x02018;cellular processes&#x02019;, &#x02018;environmental information processing&#x02019;, &#x02018;genetic information processing&#x02019;, &#x02018;metabolism&#x02019; and &#x02018;organismal systems&#x02019; (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Among these pathways, signal transduction (18,565 transcripts), carbohydrate metabolism (8768), and transport and catabolism (6294) were the three most represented. Fisher&#x02019;s exact test on the identified 1677 differentially expressed genes (DEG) was performed to explore the changes in metabolic pathways under drought treatment (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Environmental adaptation, not surprisingly, was the category with the most differentially expressed transcripts. Interestingly, 1314 contigs mapped pathways involved in metabolism of terpenoids and polyketides, including monoterpenoid, sesquiterpenoid and triterpenoid, and terpenoid backbone biosynthesis. The expression of transcripts in this category were the second most differentially expressed by irrigation treatment. Terpenoids are highly abundant components of guayule resin. Isoflavonoid biosynthesis and circadian rhythm were among the topmost enriched pathways. Plant hormone signal transduction also showed a high enrichment score. Finally, the most enriched gene count among all pathways in our assembly encode a family of protein transporters. Aquaporins are water channels important for maintaining salt and water homeostasis, especially under biotic stress<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>. In agreement with Nelson et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>, PIP1-3 (PaTc_178810) is one of the most induced contigs (FC&#x02009;=&#x02009;12.18) in drought stressed guayule.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>KEGG classification of unique sequences in both entire transcriptome (dashed line) and differentially expressed contigs (solid line). (A)&#x000a0;Cellular processes;&#x000a0;(B)&#x000a0;Environmental information processing;&#x000a0;(C)&#x000a0;Genetic information processing;&#x000a0;(D)&#x000a0;Metabolism; and&#x000a0;(E)&#x000a0;Organismal systems. A total of 65,879 unique sequences were classified in the KEGG database.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_1026_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig><fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Scatter plot-enriched Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) pathways of differentially expressed genes (DEGs) in drought stressed plants compared to control plants in the field. The x-axis represents the gene ratio, which refers to the ratio of the DEG numbers annotated in the pathway term to all gene numbers annotated in the pathway term. The circle size indicates the number of DEGs that are associated with each significant pathway. The circle color indicates the significant level with the adjusted p-value using Benjamin Hochberg method.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_1026_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Rubber and resin content in guayule are impacted differently by water irrigation levels</title><p id="Par15">The guayule field irrigation study conducted in 2012&#x02013;2015 in Maricopa, Arizona found consistently higher rubber content in plants treated with low (25% replacement of evapotranspiration (EVA), simulating drought conditions) irrigation water levels compared to the control (100% EVA) irrigation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup> (Sup Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>A). Stem subsamples from plants harvested in March 2015 were collected for the transcriptome analysis reported here. At that point drought-stressed plants had 8.6% rubber content, significantly higher than the 6.0% rubber in control plants (Sup Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>B). Higher rubber content for guayule subjected to drought stress has been reported in greenhouse<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup> and field<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup> studies. The mechanism is unknown, but water stress could create less cell expansion due to the reduced turgor pressure, and smaller cell volume concentrating solutes in the cell, including substrate for rubber biosynthesis, providing a possible explanation to the observed higher rubber content in drought-stressed plants. Remarkably, Reddy and Das<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup> observed that low leaf water potential increased rubber transferase activity (and concomitant rubber content) in guayule.</p><p id="Par16">In contrast, resin content was not correlated to irrigation level (Sup Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>A) and was not significantly different between the two treatments (Sup Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>B). Resin content in guayule is relatively insensitive to growing conditions such as seasonal temperature and water inputs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>. It appears that, as a whole, unlike rubber, resin biosynthesis in guayule is less affected by the environment. However, guayule resin is a complex mixture<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup> and it is possible that biosynthesis of individual resin components such as terpenes may be impacted by water inputs or other environmental factors. Our transcriptome analysis found that many resin biosynthesis related transcripts were differentially expressed by drought (see section below), and therefore may provide breeding and genetic engineering targets for guayule improvement.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>The mevalonate pathway is mostly down-regulated in drought stressed guayule</title><p id="Par17">All isoprenoids, including NR, are derived from the precursor IPP. In plants, IPP is synthesized by two independent pathways: the mevalonate pathway (MVA) located mainly in the cytoplasm and the methylerythritol phosphate pathway (MEP) in plastids. Previous studies have shown that MVA pathway is likely the main source of IPP for rubber production in plants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>. All genes encoding the MVA pathway enzymes were represented in our transcriptome (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) however most of them (70%) were down-regulated by drought (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). The enzyme 3-hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl-coenzyme A reductase (HMRG) is considered the key regulatory step in cytosolic IPP synthesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>. Our analysis identified five putative <italic>HMGR</italic> transcripts. Two <italic>HMGR</italic>-like transcripts were statistically significantly down-regulated (PaTc_112447 and PaTc_099724 with adjusted p-value at 0.0004 and 0.000, respectively). Interestingly, isoform PaTc_112447 (HMGR1 in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>), corresponds to a previously identified isoform from a guayule cold acclimated EST library<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>. No correlation between <italic>HMGR</italic> expression and rubber transferase activity was found in that study. As for the other three putative isoforms, one was moderately down-regulated (PaTc_071662), one slightly up-regulated (PaTc_042319) and another showed no change in expression level associated with plant water status (PaTc_036263). Activity of one of these five HMGR isoforms tracked with rubber transferase activity corresponding to an increase in rubber formation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>. Identification of this rubber biosynthesis associated HMGR isoform will be critical not only for a better understanding of rubber biosynthetic pathway, but also to target this isoform, alongside other genes, in metabolic engineering and breeding efforts to increase rubber content in guayule.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Identification and expression analysis of rubber biosynthesis associated genes.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Gene name</th><th align="left">Contig</th><th align="left">logFC</th><th align="left">FDR</th><th align="left">Ctrl_TMM</th><th align="left">Drought_TMM</th><th align="left">Accession no</th><th align="left">Annotation</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="8"><bold>Mevalonate (MVA) pathway</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">ACAT1</td><td align="left">PaTc_041029</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;2.52</td><td align="left">0.06</td><td char="." align="char">409.38</td><td char="." align="char">72.76</td><td align="left">XP_024979490.1</td><td align="left">Acetoacetyl-CoA thiolase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ACAT1</td><td align="left">PaTc_041027</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;2.67</td><td align="left">0.14</td><td char="." align="char">2.66</td><td char="." align="char">0.42</td><td align="left">XP_024979490.1</td><td align="left">Acetoacetyl-CoA thiolase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ACAT1</td><td align="left">PaTc_041030</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;2.58</td><td align="left">0.82</td><td char="." align="char">0.95</td><td char="." align="char">0.18</td><td align="left">XP_024979490.1</td><td align="left">Acetoacetyl-CoA thiolase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ACAT2</td><td align="left">PaTc_085048</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;0.20</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td char="." align="char">49.05</td><td char="." align="char">41.85</td><td align="left">XP_022011037.1</td><td align="left">Acetoacetyl-CoA thiolase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ACAT3</td><td align="left">PaTc_107572</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;3.32</td><td align="left">0.11</td><td char="." align="char">47.83</td><td char="." align="char">4.83</td><td align="left">OTG07344.1</td><td align="left">Acetoacetyl-CoA thiolase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HMGS1</td><td align="left">PaTc_097206</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;1.17</td><td align="left">0.74</td><td char="." align="char">336.44</td><td char="." align="char">145.22</td><td align="left">XP_021969097.1</td><td align="left">3-Hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl-coenzyme A synthase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HMGS1</td><td align="left">PaTc_097204</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;1.51</td><td align="left">0.73</td><td char="." align="char">4.87</td><td char="." align="char">1.69</td><td align="left">XP_021969097.1</td><td align="left">3-Hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl-coenzyme A synthase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HMGS2</td><td align="left">PaTc_111123</td><td align="left">0.55</td><td align="left">0.95</td><td char="." align="char">1.74</td><td char="." align="char">2.56</td><td align="left">XP_022022159.1</td><td align="left">3-Hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl-coenzyme A synthase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HMGR1</td><td align="left">PaTc_112447</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;4.34</td><td align="left">0.00</td><td char="." align="char">849.24</td><td char="." align="char">42.90</td><td align="left">XP_022016011.1</td><td align="left">3-Hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl-coenzyme A reductase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HMGR2</td><td align="left">PaTc_099724</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;2.92</td><td align="left">0.00</td><td char="." align="char">104.71</td><td char="." align="char">13.74</td><td align="left">ASJ80969.1</td><td align="left">3-Hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl-coenzyme A reductase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HMGR3</td><td align="left">PaTc_042319</td><td align="left">0.91</td><td align="left">0.87</td><td char="." align="char">8.50</td><td char="." align="char">16.58</td><td align="left">XP_021981154.1</td><td align="left">3-Hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl-coenzyme A reductase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HMGR4</td><td align="left">PaTc_036263</td><td align="left">0.25</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td char="." align="char">0.86</td><td char="." align="char">1.04</td><td align="left">XP_024990111.1</td><td align="left">3-Hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl-coenzyme A reductase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HMGR5</td><td align="left">PaTc_071662</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;3.39</td><td align="left">0.06</td><td char="." align="char">55.53</td><td char="." align="char">5.59</td><td align="left">XP_024974039.1</td><td align="left">3-Hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl-coenzyme A reductase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MK</td><td align="left">PaTc_011919</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;1.45</td><td align="left">0.07</td><td char="." align="char">38.06</td><td char="." align="char">13.60</td><td align="left">XP_021982774.1</td><td align="left">mevalonate-5-kinase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">PMK</td><td align="left">PaTc_091190</td><td align="left">0.00</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td char="." align="char">6.32</td><td char="." align="char">6.37</td><td align="left">XP_022029028.1</td><td align="left">phosphomevalonate kinase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">PMK</td><td align="left">PaTc_087171</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;0.24</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td char="." align="char">8.45</td><td char="." align="char">7.15</td><td align="left">XP_021970137.1</td><td align="left">phosphomevalonate kinase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">PMK</td><td align="left">PaTc_140495</td><td align="left">0.11</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td char="." align="char">3.43</td><td char="." align="char">3.70</td><td align="left">XP_022029028.1</td><td align="left">phosphomevalonate kinase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">PMK</td><td align="left">PaTc_140494</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;0.88</td><td align="left">0.81</td><td char="." align="char">3.74</td><td char="." align="char">2.01</td><td align="left">XP_022029028.1</td><td align="left">phosphomevalonate kinase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MDD</td><td align="left">PaTc_032360</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;0.67</td><td align="left">0.95</td><td char="." align="char">249.84</td><td char="." align="char">155.84</td><td align="left">XP_021993996.1</td><td align="left">Diphosphomevalonate decarboxylase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MDD</td><td align="left">PaTc_032353</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;0.30</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td char="." align="char">3.12</td><td char="." align="char">2.54</td><td align="left">XP_021993996.1</td><td align="left">Diphosphomevalonate decarboxylase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IDI</td><td align="left">PaTc_051129</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;1.78</td><td align="left">0.02</td><td char="." align="char">29.22</td><td char="." align="char">8.46</td><td align="left">XP_022033582.1</td><td align="left">isopentenyl diphosphate isomerase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IDI</td><td align="left">PaTc_083602</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;2.48</td><td align="left">0.02</td><td char="." align="char">40.89</td><td char="." align="char">7.24</td><td align="left">XP_021982603.1</td><td align="left">isopentenyl diphosphate isomerase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IDI</td><td align="left">PaTc_208250</td><td align="left">0.06</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td char="." align="char">8.02</td><td char="." align="char">7.96</td><td align="left">XP_024990050.1</td><td align="left">isopentenyl diphosphate isomerase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IDI</td><td align="left">PaTc_208249</td><td align="left">0.95</td><td align="left">0.85</td><td char="." align="char">2.20</td><td char="." align="char">4.25</td><td align="left">XP_024990050.1</td><td align="left">isopentenyl diphosphate isomerase</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8"><bold>Rubber particle (RP) associated</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AOS1</td><td align="left">PaTc_229190</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;1.29</td><td align="left">0.71</td><td char="." align="char">1138.35</td><td char="." align="char">445.44</td><td align="left">XP_021983640.1</td><td align="left">Allene oxide synthase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AOSL2</td><td align="left">PaTc_122848</td><td align="left">0.87</td><td align="left">0.81</td><td char="." align="char">25.92</td><td char="." align="char">47.27</td><td align="left">XP_021983640.1</td><td align="left">Allene oxide synthase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AOSL3</td><td align="left">PaTc_122845</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;0.42</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td char="." align="char">34.35</td><td char="." align="char">25.58</td><td align="left">XP_022034250.1</td><td align="left">Allene oxide synthase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CBP</td><td align="left">PaTc_149493</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;1.25</td><td align="left">0.71</td><td char="." align="char">246.74</td><td char="." align="char">100.84</td><td align="left">ATD87120.1</td><td align="left">CPT-binding protein</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CPT1</td><td align="left">PaTc_044561</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;0.41</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td char="." align="char">2.73</td><td char="." align="char">1.99</td><td align="left">ATD87115.1</td><td align="left">cis-prenyltransferases</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CPT2</td><td align="left">PaTc_069159</td><td align="left">1.63</td><td align="left">0.89</td><td char="." align="char">1.76</td><td char="." align="char">5.09</td><td align="left">ATD87118.1</td><td align="left">cis-prenyltransferases</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CPT3</td><td align="left">PaTc_140080</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;0.28</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td char="." align="char">0.32</td><td char="." align="char">0.27</td><td align="left">ATD87116.1</td><td align="left">cis-prenyltransferases</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CPT3</td><td align="left">PaTc_140079</td><td align="left">n.a</td><td align="left">n.a</td><td char="." align="char">0.18</td><td char="." align="char">0.09</td><td align="left">n.a</td><td align="left">cis-prenyltransferases</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CPT3</td><td align="left">PaTc_140078</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;3.26</td><td align="left">0.01</td><td char="." align="char">869.51</td><td char="." align="char">90.99</td><td align="left">ATD87116.1</td><td align="left">cis-prenyltransferases</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SRPP1</td><td align="left">PaTc_109994</td><td align="left">1.16</td><td align="left">0.19</td><td char="." align="char">192.50</td><td char="." align="char">421.14</td><td align="left">AAQ11374.1</td><td align="left">small rubber particle protein</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SRPP2</td><td align="left">PaTc_109993</td><td align="left">1.51</td><td align="left">0.94</td><td char="." align="char">0.70</td><td char="." align="char">2.15</td><td align="left">AAQ11374.1</td><td align="left">small rubber particle protein</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SRPP3</td><td align="left">PaTc_141609</td><td align="left">0.92</td><td align="left">0.53</td><td char="." align="char">159.87</td><td char="." align="char">298.83</td><td align="left">AAQ11374.1</td><td align="left">small rubber particle protein</td></tr><tr><td align="left">FPPS1</td><td align="left">PaTc_059300</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;0.80</td><td align="left">0.94</td><td char="." align="char">20.41</td><td char="." align="char">11.89</td><td align="left">O24241.1</td><td align="left">farnesyl pyrophosphate synthase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">FPPS2</td><td align="left">PaTc_024209</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;0.07</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td char="." align="char">26.16</td><td char="." align="char">24.70</td><td align="left">O24242.1</td><td align="left">farnesyl pyrophosphate synthase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">FPPS</td><td align="left">PaTc_059294</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;1.80</td><td align="left">0.41</td><td char="." align="char">1.14</td><td char="." align="char">0.33</td><td align="left">O24241.1</td><td align="left">farnesyl pyrophosphate synthase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">FPPS</td><td align="left">PaTc_024210</td><td align="left">0.00</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td char="." align="char">2.20</td><td char="." align="char">2.18</td><td align="left">O24242.1</td><td align="left">farnesyl pyrophosphate synthase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">FPPS</td><td align="left">PaTc_024207</td><td align="left">n.a</td><td align="left">n.a</td><td char="." align="char">0.03</td><td char="." align="char">0.24</td><td align="left">O24242.1</td><td align="left">farnesyl pyrophosphate synthase</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8"><bold>Selected terpenoids pathway</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">GPPS</td><td align="left">PaTc_108154</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;0.98</td><td align="left">0.90</td><td char="." align="char">1.96</td><td char="." align="char">0.94</td><td align="left">XP_022027531.1</td><td align="left">geranyl pyrophosphate synthase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">GPPS</td><td align="left">PaTc_108145</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;2.39</td><td align="left">0.55</td><td char="." align="char">1.44</td><td char="." align="char">0.26</td><td align="left">XP_022027531.1</td><td align="left">geranyl pyrophosphate synthase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">GPPS</td><td align="left">PaTc_108152</td><td align="left">1.50</td><td align="left">0.86</td><td char="." align="char">0.55</td><td char="." align="char">1.57</td><td align="left">XP_022027531.1</td><td align="left">geranyl pyrophosphate synthase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">GPPS</td><td align="left">PaTc_222834</td><td align="left">1.38</td><td align="left">0.90</td><td char="." align="char">0.68</td><td char="." align="char">1.74</td><td align="left">XP_022027531.1</td><td align="left">geranyl pyrophosphate synthase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">GPPS</td><td align="left">PaTc_222833</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;0.45</td><td align="left">0.97</td><td char="." align="char">6.90</td><td char="." align="char">4.98</td><td align="left">XP_022027531.1</td><td align="left">geranyl pyrophosphate synthase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SQS</td><td align="left">PaTc_219827</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;2.84</td><td align="left">0.12</td><td char="." align="char">54.14</td><td char="." align="char">7.67</td><td align="left">XP_022013547.1</td><td align="left">squalene synthase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">GGPPS</td><td align="left">PaTc_023109</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;2.86</td><td align="left">0.83</td><td char="." align="char">0.63</td><td char="." align="char">0.92</td><td align="left">XP_022026732.1</td><td align="left">geranylgeranyl pyrophosphate synthase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">GGPPS</td><td align="left">PaTc_023108</td><td align="left">n.a</td><td align="left">n.a</td><td char="." align="char">0.30</td><td char="." align="char">0.34</td><td align="left">XP_022026732.1</td><td align="left">geranylgeranyl pyrophosphate synthase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">GGPPS</td><td align="left">PaTc_003194</td><td align="left">n.a</td><td align="left">n.a</td><td char="." align="char">0.45</td><td char="." align="char">0.10</td><td align="left">XP_022026732.1</td><td align="left">geranylgeranyl pyrophosphate synthase</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Expression of transcripts involved in mevalonate pathway (MVA), methylerythritol phosphate pathways (MEP) and rubber particle associated genes. Lower right, schematic model of the rubber biosynthetic machinery. Relative differential expression showed by a color gradient from low (blue) to high (red). Asterisks indicate significant differential expression (FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and log2 fold-change&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;2). Black dot sizes proportional to the expression level.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_1026_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p><p id="Par18">Interestingly, almost all MVA enzyme coding transcripts had at least one isoform unaffected by water treatment and/or another isoform slightly up-regulated. This diversity of transcriptional control suggests different MVA enzymes&#x02019; isoforms respond to different stimuli to exert specific metabolic control. The highest up-regulated transcript (PaTc_108152) encodes a geranyl pyrophosphate synthase (GPPS) isoform and the most down-regulated transcript encodes HMGR1 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Overall our results indicate most of the MVA pathway in guayule is transcriptionally down-regulated by drought. It should be noted that isoprenoid pathway genes such as <italic>HMGR</italic>, 3-hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl-coenzyme A synthase (<italic>HMGS</italic>), phosphomevalonate kinase (<italic>PMK</italic>), isopentenyl diphosphate isomerase (<italic>IDI</italic>), and genaryl genaryl pyrophosphate synthase (<italic>GGPPS</italic>), have been reported to be down-regulated by drought in other plant species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par19">Contigs coding all eight consecutive enzymes of the plastidic MEP pathway (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>) were identified (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>). Of 129 contigs, 29 showed a higher expression trend under drought stress, however none was significant, while 55 showed a lower expression trend. Among the down-regulated contigs, 1-deoxy-D-xylulose 5-phosphate synthase (DXS), the rate limiting enzyme of MEP pathway was significantly down-regulated (Foldchange&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;5.49). Down-regulation of 4&#x02010;hydroxy&#x02010;3&#x02010;methylbut&#x02010;2&#x02010;enyl diphosphate reductase (HDR) was also significant. MEP pathway analysis under drought stress in grape showed down-regulation of genes regulating the early pathway steps<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par20">It appears that at the transcription level, both MVA and MEP pathways are depressed by prolonged drought in guayule. In conifers, metabolic flux analysis found the MEP pathway was reduced by drought but much less than photosynthesis and transpiration, suggesting alternative carbon sources feed this metabolic pathway under drought stress<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup>. A similar situation could apply to drought-stressed guayule; that is, an alternative source of carbon may be activated to provide the necessary synthesis of IPP and subsequently rubber.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Is rubber biosynthesis under transcriptional control?</title><p id="Par21">The RP is the site of NR production in plants and some fungi<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref></sup>; the polymer is synthesized by the membrane-associated RuT enzymatic complex. Two potentially essential members of the guayule RuT complex are a <italic>cis</italic>-prenyltransferase (CPT3) and a CPT-binding protein (CBP) which are hypothesized to form an active heteromer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref></sup>. In addition to these proteins, the RuT complex may include two other RP-associated proteins: the small rubber particle protein (SRPP), and allene oxide synthase (AOS), both of indeterminate function but with a recognized indirect role in rubber biosynthesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref></sup>. Transcripts of all the above RP associated proteins were identified in our transcriptome (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) and found to be mostly down-regulated by drought, with the exception of <italic>SRPP</italic>. Interestingly, the transcript encoding CPT3 (PaTc_140078), the specific isoform involved in rubber biosynthesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref></sup> (<italic>PaCPT3</italic>) was found to be highly abundant in stem tissue as expected, but statistically significantly down-regulated by drought, in spite of the fact that drought-stressed guayule plants had higher rubber content (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). The two other guayule <italic>CPT</italic> transcripts not involved in rubber biosynthesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref></sup> (<italic>PaCPT1</italic> and <italic>PaCPT2</italic>) were of low abundance (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>), and were either slightly up-regulated (<italic>PaCPT2</italic>, PaTc_069159) or unaffected by plant water status (<italic>PaCPT1</italic>, PaTc_044561). These two CPTs are most likely involved in biosynthesis of dolichols<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref></sup> and/or plastidial polyprenols essential for photosynthesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref></sup>. Transcripts encoding CBP (PaTc_149493) were also down-regulated by drought, although not to the extent of <italic>CPT3</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). The <italic>AOS</italic> transcript PaTc_229190, encoding the most abundant protein associated with guayule RP<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref></sup>, not surprisingly had the highest expression levels among all other rubber biosynthesis related genes under both conditions (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Interestingly, this transcript was down-regulated 39% by drought despite the high rubber content. This negative correlation of AOS levels and rubber content was observed in <italic>AOS</italic>-silenced transgenic guayule lines, resulting in increased rubber content and higher RuT activity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref></sup>. In that study, a structural role of AOS in guayule RP was proposed. Two other AOS isoforms (AOS-like, AOSL) of unknown function and localization have different expression profiles of slightly up-regulated (<italic>AOSL2</italic>, PaTc_122848) or no differential expression compared to control (<italic>AOSL3</italic>, PaTc_122845). The function of these AOSs could be the well-known role in jasmonic acid synthesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par22">The only RP-associated transcript found to be up-regulated was <italic>SRPP</italic> (PaTc_109994). SRPP is a stress response protein<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref></sup> so it is not surprising drought would result in its up-regulation. Only one guayule <italic>SRPP</italic> gene has been cloned<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref></sup> (<underline>g</underline>uayule <underline>h</underline>omolog of <underline>S</underline>RPP, GHS); our assembly identified two additional putative SRPP isoforms of unknown function but also up-regulated by drought (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Kajiura et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup> antibodies used for RP proteins detection by western blot recognize an epitope present in GHS, and partially (92%) in the deduced protein sequences of the newly identified transcripts. The possibility of antibodies cross-reaction cannot be ruled out and therefore localization of the new SRPP isoforms remains to be determined. Although the role of SRPP in rubber biosynthesis remains to be elucidated, down-regulation of <italic>SRPP</italic> affected accumulation and quality of rubber in dandelion<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref></sup>. Dai et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup> propose SRPP (and a related protein, rubber elongation factor (REF)) are likely negatively charged in the electrically neutral environment of Hevea latex, thus allowing the RP to maintain a stable colloidal form. Additionally, they propose SRPP and REF associates to the growing RP, allowing it to enlarge for the accumulation of new rubber molecules. SRPP may be needed to stabilize growing rubber particles in drought-stressed, high rubber-producing guayule.</p><p id="Par23">Farnesyl pyrophosphate, required for initiation of rubber biosynthesis, is synthesized by farnesyl pyrophosphate synthase (FPPS) through condensation of genaryl pyrophosphate (GPP) and IPP. Two guayule <italic>FPPS</italic> genes have been cloned, characterized and their corresponding proteins confirmed to localize on the RP surface (Pan et al. 1996). Expression of <italic>FPPS1</italic> transcript (PaTc_059300) was slightly down-regulated by drought whereas that of <italic>FPPS2</italic> (PaTc_024209) appears to be unaffected (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Both transcripts are moderately abundant in stem tissue compared to three other putative isoforms identified in our assembly (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><p id="Par24">The fidelity of the in silico DEG predictions for rubber biosynthesis related genes was validated by quantitative reverse transcription PCR (qPCR). We analyzed the expression of <italic>CPT3</italic>, <italic>CBP</italic>, <italic>AOS</italic>, and <italic>SRPP</italic> as well as three MVA pathway genes (<italic>HMGS</italic>, <italic>HMGR</italic>, and <italic>FPPS</italic>, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). In agreement with the DEG analysis, only SRPP was up-regulated under drought; all others were down-regulated compared to the control.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>RT-PCR validation of expression levels. Selected guayule rubber biosynthesis related genes from stem tissues of plants grown under drought stress condition (black bars) relative to full irrigation control (grey bars). Values are the average of three biological replicates, error bars correspond to standard deviation error.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_1026_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p><p id="Par25">In summary, the low expression levels observed in rubber biosynthesis related transcripts (and the MVA pathway) contradict the high rubber content commonly found in drought-stressed guayule plants. These seemingly contradictory facts could be explained by the prospect that the rubber biosynthesis regulation is at the post-transcriptional, translational and/or post-translational levels. An earlier guayule field study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup> failed to find a direct correlation between gene expression and RuT activity, also implying the control point of rubber biosynthesis in guayule may not be at the transcriptional level. Interestingly, drought-responsive long non-coding RNAs have been identified in guayule<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>, including one (GFTW01168370.1) featuring a conserved binding site for miR166, a drought-responsive microRNA.</p><p id="Par26">Previously, under a laboratory environment, cold stress elicited expression of RP encoding genes in guayule including <italic>AOS</italic>, <italic>CPT</italic>, <italic>FPPS</italic> and <italic>SRPP</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. Although both stresses (drought and cold) in guayule promote rubber synthesis, it appears that different genes in the biosynthetic pathway are expressed differently under each type of stress. Additionally, evidence suggests the coarse control of the MVA pathway is at the transcriptional level while the fine-tuning control at the post-transcriptional and/or post-translational levels<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>. In Hevea, proteomic analysis of latex found phosphorylation of some REF and SRPP isoforms<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref></sup> following stimulation of rubber biosynthesis by ethylene treatment. Therefore, it is likely that both posttranscriptional and posttranslational mechanisms regulate rubber biosynthesis, as has been demonstrated for other plant secondary metabolites<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Drought has a mixed effect on expression levels of resin biosynthesis genes</title><p id="Par27">The largest class of compounds that make up guayule resin are terpenoids<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup> synthesized by terpene synthases (TPS). Using the highly conserved amino- and carboxyl- terminal domains, PF01397 and PF03936 respectively, we searched our assembly and identified a total of 70 contigs (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>). Phylogenetic analysis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>) clustered these contigs into 5 subfamilies with TPS-a and TPS-b the most expanded groups (26 and 27 contigs, respectively), comprising about 75% of the total TPSs. This is in accordance with other plant TPS profiles<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref></sup>. Previous studies have shown that <italic>TPS</italic> genes exhibit distinct tempo-spatial expression patterns with and without stress<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref></sup>. Among the 70 identified <italic>TPS</italic> in guayule, 15 of them showed no detectable transcript level in both control and drought-stressed plants for meaningful differential expression comparison. These <italic>TPS</italic> contigs are either nonfunctional pseudogenes or they are preferentially expressed in other organs. Among the other 55 contigs, which showed a differential expression pattern under drought stress, 21 contigs were up-regulated in the range of 0.23&#x02013;5.53-fold, with an average fold change of 1.59; only two (PaTc_112885, PaTc_180037; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>) were significant, both involved in sesquiterpene synthesis. These two putative &#x003b2;-caryophyllene synthases likely synthesize a volatile terpene known to be induced when plants are subjected to different stresses, including wounding and herbivore attack<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref></sup>.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Molecular phylogenetic analysis of terpene synthases <italic>TPSs</italic> in stem tissue of field-grown guayule. The tree was constructed with MEGA X with maximum Likelihood method. Subfamilies highlighted by color: green (TPS-a), purple (TPS-b), red (TPS-c), blue (TPS-e/f) and orange (TPS-g) respectively. Significantly differentially expressed contigs in bold.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_1026_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p><p id="Par28">Thirty-four <italic>TPS</italic> contigs were suppressed under drought stress, in the range from 0.17 to 9.14-fold. Four of them (PaTc_070258, PaTc_079214, PaTc_179699, PaTc_072148; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>) were significantly down-regulated, all putative monoterpene synthases. These four contigs encode R-linalool synthase QH1 which synthesizes (3R)-linalool from GPP. Linalool is one of the most common monoterpenoids produced by plants and has been extensively investigated for its role in plant&#x02013;insect interactions, including pollinator attraction<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref></sup> and defense<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref></sup>. Notably, studies in <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> and <italic>Camellia sinensis</italic> both showed significant decrease of linalool under drought<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par29">The most dramatically suppressed gene expression among the TPSs occurred to PaTc_079214 encoding a previously reported putative terpene synthase 3<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. Interestingly, this transcript is one of the most significantly down regulated among the DEG set identified in this study.</p><p id="Par30">The commercial viability of guayule as a crop depends on the successful utilization of resin as a high-value co-product. Our transcriptome offers a searchable database that can be mined to identify biosynthetic enzymes of the most abundant and high-value compounds including the guayulins and argentatins.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Down-regulation of fructan synthesis by drought is accompanied by up-regulation of fructan depolymerization and other osmolytes biosynthesis genes</title><p id="Par31">Fructan, a water-soluble polysaccharide, is the main reserve of carbohydrates in guayule<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. Evidence shows fructans are actively involved in cold and drought stress response in plants by their capacity of maintaining cell membrane integrity through insertion in the lipid headgroup region of the membrane<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. Two enzymes, sucrose:sucrose 1-fructosyl transferase (1-SST) and fructan:fructan 1-fructosyl transferase (1-FFT) are responsible for fructan synthesis, while the enzyme fructan 1-exohydrolase (1-FEH) catabolizes fructans<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. In our assembly, contigs encoding <italic>1Sst</italic> (PaTc_199271, PaTc_199269) and <italic>1Fft</italic> (PaTc_016980) were both down-regulated significantly under drought stress, with an average fold change of 4.3 and 5.6 respectively, while <italic>1-Feh</italic> (PaTc_110775) was significantly induced (FC&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.5). This suggests that drought-stressed guayule likely activated fructan depolymerization (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref>). In cereals, drought stress likewise led to fructan degradation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref></sup>. Notably, these three genes showed the same expression pattern in cold-induced guayule stem tissue<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup> (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref>). Cold stress triggers rubber biosynthesis in guayule and the commonality of fructan metabolism transcriptional control in both drought and cold stress justifies a deeper analysis of fructans&#x02019; role in rubber biosynthesis as previously suggested by Benzioni and Mills<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par32">Interestingly, a similar gene expression pattern was observed in other carbohydrates metabolism (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref>). For example, fructose-bisphosphate aldolase (PaTc_033225), &#x003b2;-fructofuranosidase (PaTc_004249), GDP-L-galactose phosphorylase (PaTc_066454) and &#x003b2;-glucosidase (PaTc_068062), all of which are involved in hydrolyzing polysaccharides into simpler saccharides, were significantly induced under drought condition. On the other hand, glucose-1-phosphate adenylyltransferase (PaTc_166809) and raffinose synthase (PaTc_066497), both involved in polysaccharide synthesis, were down-regulated in stressed plants. Moreover, extensive studies have shown that polyamine (PA) is an important stress modulator in plants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref></sup>. In our analyses, PA-synthesizing enzymes arginine decarboxylase (PaTc_082215) and S-adenosylmethionine decarboxylase (PaTc_065600, PaTc_003065, PaTc_118154) were heavily induced, while polyamine oxidase (PaTc_033142, PaTc_033141, PaTc_033146, PaTc_033145) were significantly down-regulated with average fold change of 3.5, suggesting a possible drought response strategy by maintaining a higher level of PA.</p><p id="Par33">Taken together, it appears that osmotic stress in guayule triggers the accumulation of soluble sugars and PAs to help the plant cope with low water status. Additionally, drought generally suppresses photosynthesis and therefore there is less sugar available to support metabolic reactions such as rubber synthesis. Other sources of carbon such as carbohydrates&#x02019; catabolism could be providing the needed carbon for rubber synthesis.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par34">Our transcriptome analyses introduce a new perspective to expression of gene families related to key metabolic pathways in guayule stem tissue under drought stress. Results revealed that transcriptional status of genes involved in biosynthesis of the three major compounds, natural rubber, terpene resin, and fructan, are affected differently. Under drought conditions, the cytosolic isoprenoid biosynthetic pathway genes (MVA) and transcripts of RP associated proteins (including putative components of the RT complex) are mostly down-regulated in stem tissue, the main site of rubber synthesis in guayule, despite higher overall rubber content. This suggests the rubber biosynthesis control point is at the post-transcriptional level and beyond. Future engineering strategies for guayule, and possibly other rubber-producing crops, should carefully consider the growing body of transcriptomic information beyond metabolic pathway genes, as evidence of more complex regulation schemes emerge. Guayule resin biosynthesis transcripts, on the other hand, appear to be variably affected by water status and transcriptional control of individual resin compounds&#x02019; synthesis is likely unique. Finally, carbohydrate metabolism (in response to drought) is shown to be under transcriptional control in guayule, as is the case under cold stress, and under both conditions leading to enhanced rubber content in guayule.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec12"><title>Plant material and treatments</title><p id="Par35">The plant material used was <italic>Parthenium argentatum</italic>, guayule, line AZ-3<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref></sup>, provided by the United States Department of Agriculture as publicly-curated germplasm (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.grin-global.org/),accession">https://www.grin-global.org/),accession</ext-link> number PI 599676. Seeds were greenhouse planted, grown into seedlings, then transplanted into a field site at the University of Arizona, Maricopa Agricultural Center (MAC) and grown as described in Hunsaker et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Following surface irrigation to establish the plants, subsurface drip irrigation was applied at 100% (control) and 25% (drought stress) of the soil water depletion, determined by field-calibrated, neutron moisture meters (Model 503, Campbell Pacific Nuclear, CPN, Martinez, CA). Plants were harvested in March 2015; rubber, resin, and biomass were quantified as per Hunsaker et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Three biological replicates of bark tissue from stem were collected during the harvest. Tissues were immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;80&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C until RNA extraction. All germplasm sourcing, field operations, and laboratory procedures complied with relevant institutional, national, and international permissions, guidelines, and legislation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Library preparation and RNA-sequencing</title><p id="Par36">Stem bark tissue (~&#x02009;2&#x000a0;g) from 29-month old guayule plants was the source of RNA for sequencing and qPCR analysis. Total RNA was extracted following Laudencia et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref></sup> protocol with the use of acid phenol:chloroform MB grade (Ambion, USA) instead of phenol:chloroform:isoamyl alcohol. The precipitated RNA was further cleaned with Qiagen RNeasy Plant Mini Kit (Qiagen, USA) and treated with DNA-<italic>free</italic>&#x02122; kit (Ambion, USA). PolyA-RNA was prepared employing Qiagen RNeasy/QIAshredder protocols (Qiagen, USA). RNA concentration was quantified with Quant-iT&#x02122; RiboGreen&#x02122; RNA Assay Kit (Thermofisher Scientific, USA). RNA quality was analyzed using 2100 Bioanalyzer (Agilent Technologies, USA). RNAseq library construction was carried out with KAPA Stranded RNA-Seq Library Preparation Kit Illumina&#x000ae; platforms (Kapa Biosystems, USA) per the manufacturer's instructions. RNAseq libraries with insert sizes of 200&#x02013;500&#x000a0;bp, and sequenced using Illumina HiSeq 2000 platform with paired-end (PE) reads of 150&#x000a0;bp.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>De novo assembly and sequence processing</title><p id="Par37">The raw reads were first cleaned by filtering out adaptor sequences and low-quality reads using Trimmomatic (v0.32). Trimmed reads, quality confirmed by running FastQC, were combined across six reads of both conditions. Both Trinity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref></sup> (v2.9.0) de novo and Trinity genome-guided (diploid guayule genome<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>) assemblies were supplied into the PASA pipeline<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup> to generate the comprehensive transcriptome database. To remove the redundant sequences, CD-HIT package was used for further clustering with a 300-bp sequence length and 95% similarity cut-off values. High-quality reads were mapped back to the assembled transcriptome sequences for validation. Reads were aligned using Bowtie-2 with default parameters.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Gene function annotation</title><p id="Par38">Gene functions were annotated against the Nr (NCBI non-redundant protein sequences), PFAM (protein family), Swiss-Prot (a manually annotated and reviewed protein sequence database), and TrEMBL (a computer-annotated protein sequence database) using local BLASTX program with an E-value threshold of 1e<sup>&#x02212;10</sup>. GO analysis was performed using Blast2GO with the same E-value cutoff. Metabolic pathway mapping of the transcripts was performed using the KEGG Automatic Annotation Server (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.genome.jp/tools/kaas/">https://www.genome.jp/tools/kaas/</ext-link>). Plant transcription factors (TFs), transcriptional regulators (TRs) and protein kinases (PKs) were identified and classified into different gene families using standalone iTAK<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref></sup> (v 18.12).</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Identification of differentially expressed genes (DEGs)</title><p id="Par39">Differentially expressed transcripts under the two irrigation treatments were identified with edgeR<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>, using transcripts per million counts for each sample generated by Kallisto<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>. A two-fold change (FC&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;2) and FDR value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 were used to define the significant DEGs between treatment and control. GO and KEGG enrichment were performed on the transcripts identified as DEGs as well. For comparative analysis with cold stress guayule transcriptome, the raw data was acquired from NCBI BioProject PRJNA387289 with accession SRR5597223, SRR5597220, SRR5597221, SRR5597216, SRR5597215, SRR5597214, SRR5597224, SRR5597213, SRR5597212, SRR5597228, SRR5597231 AND SRR5597230 mapped back to TSA GFTW000000000.1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. Expression and differential expression analyses were completed in the same way as stated for the current drought study.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Quantitative RT-PCR (qRT-PCR)</title><p id="Par40">Total RNA from ground (~&#x02009;100&#x000a0;mg) stem bark tissue was extracted with TRIzol&#x000ae; reagent (Life Technologies, USA), cleaned with RNeasy Mini Kit (Qiagen, USA), and traces of DNA removed with DNA-free&#x02122; Kit (Life Technologies, USA). Two micrograms of total RNA were the template for oligo (dT)<sub>20</sub>-generated cDNA with SuperScriptIII First-Strand Synthesis System for qPCR (Life Technologies, USA) following manufacturer instructions. The qPCR reactions were carried out using Applied Biosystems 7500 Fast Real Time PCR System and SYBR Green chemistry (Life Technologies, USA) in 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l volume reactions containing 400&#x000a0;ng of template cDNA, 900&#x000a0;nM of each forward and reverse primer, 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of Fast SYBR&#x000ae; Green Master Mix, and water as needed. The primers used are listed in Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S7</xref>. Thermocycler temperature regime was: 95&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 20&#x000a0;s, followed by 40 cycles of 95&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 3&#x000a0;s and 60&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x000a0;s. Data were analyzed using the 7500 Fast System Detection Software (Life Technologies, USA) with manually set threshold. Expression of each target gene was calculated with the Livak and Schmittgen<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">101</xref></sup> method, normalized to expression of the endogenous reference gene <italic>eIF4a</italic> or <italic>18S</italic>, and then to its expression in a calibrator (fully irrigated control plant). Three technical replicates reactions were run for each target gene, and the whole experiment was performed three times using the same RNA but freshly synthesized cDNA.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><sec id="Sec18"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2021_1026_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary Information.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p>These authors contributed equally: Chen Dong and Grisel Ponciano.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41598-021-01026-7.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors thank Yulex Corporation for providing the guayule seedlings for the study; Ms. Valerie Teetor, University of Arizona, for performing rubber and resin extraction analyses; Drs. Doug Hunsaker and Diaa Elshikha for field trial design and execution; the Maricopa Agricultural Center for providing field service operations. This project was supported by USDA-NIFA Biomass Research and Development Initiative Competitive Grant no. 2012-10006-19391 OH.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>C.M. devised the experimental design, collected plant tissue samples in the field, and wrote sections of the manuscript. C.D. performed all bioinformatics, data analysis, and wrote the manuscript. G.P. performed the RNA extractions, qPCR, data analysis, and wrote the manuscript. Y.Q.G and H.N. contributed to sequence acquisition. D.I. devised analysis and interpretation strategies. All authors reviewed and approved the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The raw Illumina data generated in this study were deposited in the NCBI Sequence Read Archive (SRA) under the BioProject accession number PRJNA400611. The transcriptome assembly generated from the current study has been made available on the ARS Guayule genome website: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://probes.pw.usda.gov/Guayule/">https://probes.pw.usda.gov/Guayule/</ext-link><underline>.</underline></p></notes><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par41">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">McGinnies, W. G. &#x00026; Haase, E. F. <italic>Guayule: A Rubber-producing Shrub for Arid and Semiarid Regions</italic> (ed. McGinnies, W. G.) 274 (University of Arizona, 1975).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sulas</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Adaptation, biometric traits and performances of guayule lines grown in two Mediterranean environments</article-title><source>Agri</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>651</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/agriculture10120651</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Beilen</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Poirier</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Establishment of new crops for the production of natural rubber</article-title><source>Trends Biotech.</source><year>2007</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>523</fpage><lpage>529</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tibtech.2007.08.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cornish</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alternative natural rubber crops: why should we care?</article-title><source>Tech. Innov.</source><year>2017</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21300/18.4.2017.245</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sproul</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Integrated techno-economic and environmental analysis of guayule rubber production</article-title><source>J. Cleaner Prod.</source><year>2020</year><volume>273</volume><fpage>122811</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2020.122811</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hunsaker</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Elshikha</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bronson</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High guayule rubber production with subsurface irrigation in the US desert Southwest</article-title><source>Agric. Water Manage.</source><year>2019</year><volume>220</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.agwat.2019.04.016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miyamoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bucks</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Water quantity and quality requirements of guayule: current assessment</article-title><source>Agric. Water Manage.</source><year>1985</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>205</fpage><lpage>219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0378-3774(85)90012-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bucks</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakayama</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name><surname>French</surname><given-names>OF</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasnick</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Irrigated guayule-Plant growth and production</article-title><source>Agric. Water Manage.</source><year>1985</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0378-3774(85)90036-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bucks</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakayama</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name><surname>French</surname><given-names>OF</given-names></name><name><surname>Legard</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Irrigated guayule-production and water use relationships</article-title><source>Agric. Water Manage.</source><year>1985</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0378-3774(85)90037-X</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benzioni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Forti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of irrigation regimes on the water status, vegetative growth and rubber production of guayule plants</article-title><source>Expl. Agric.</source><year>1989</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0014479700016690</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hunsaker</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Elshikha</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Surface irrigation management for guayule rubber production in the US desert Southwest</article-title><source>Agric. Water Manage.</source><year>2017</year><volume>185</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.agwat.2017.01.015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterization and evaluation of guayule processing residues as potential feedstock for biofuel and chemical production</article-title><source>Ind. Crops Prod.</source><year>2020</year><volume>150</volume><fpage>112311</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2020.112311</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dehghanizadeh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarvis</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Holguin</surname><given-names>FO</given-names></name><name><surname>Brewer</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of resin extracted from guayule (<italic>Parthenium argentatum</italic>): a dataset including GC&#x02013;MS and FT-ICR MS</article-title><source>Data Brief</source><year>2020</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>105989</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.dib.2020.105989</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32715039?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32715039</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tavarez-Santamar&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A higher frequency administration of the nontoxic cycloartane-type triterpene argentatin A improved its anti-tumor activity</article-title><source>Molecules</source><year>2020</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1780</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules25081780</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jara</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cornish</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Carmona</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potential applications of guayulins to improve geasibility of guayule cultivation</article-title><source>Agronomy</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>804</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/agronomy9120804</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Croteau R., Kutchan T. &#x00026; Lewis, N. <italic>Biochemistry and Molecular Biology of Plants</italic>. (eds. Buchanan, B., Gruissem, W., Jones, R.) 1250&#x02013;1268 (American Society of Plant Biologists, 2000).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kajiura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mouri</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakazawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Elucidation of rubber biosynthesis and accumulation in the rubber producing shrub, guayule (<italic>Parthenium argentatum</italic> Gray)</article-title><source>Planta</source><year>2018</year><volume>247</volume><fpage>513</fpage><lpage>526</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00425-017-2804-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29116401?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29116401</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Winkler</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Degradative effects of guayule resin on natural rubber</article-title><source>Rubber Chem. Tech.</source><year>1981</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5254/1.3535786</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakayama</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Guayule future development</article-title><source>Ind. Crops Prod.</source><year>2005</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2004.05.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lusher</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Guayule plant extracts as recycling agents in hot mix asphalt with high reclaimed binder content</article-title><source>J. Mater. Civ. Eng.</source><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1061/(ASCE)MT.1943-5533.0001238</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pascual-Villalobos</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New application of guayule resin in controlled release formulations</article-title><source>Ind. Crops Prod.</source><year>2013</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>44</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2012.07.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fructan reduction by downregulation of <italic>1-SST</italic> in guayule</article-title><source>Ind. Crops Prod.</source><year>2017</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>609</fpage><lpage>617</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2017.04.034</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ritsema</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Smeekens</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fructans: beneficial for plants and humans</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Plant Biol.</source><year>2003</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1369-5266(03)00034-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12753971?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12753971</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van den Ende</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>De Coninck</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Laere</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant fructan exohydrolases: a role in signaling and defense?</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci.</source><year>2004</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>523</fpage><lpage>528</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2004.09.008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15501176?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15501176</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valluru</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Van den Ende</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant fructans in stress environments: emerging concepts and future prospects</article-title><source>J. Exp. Bot.</source><year>2008</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>2905</fpage><lpage>2916</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ern164</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18603617?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18603617</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Livingston</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hincha</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Heyer</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fructan and its relationship to abiotic stress tolerance</article-title><source>Cell. Mol. Life Sci.</source><year>2009</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>2007</fpage><lpage>2023</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00018-009-0002-x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19290476?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19290476</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Staden</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A preliminary study of the carbohydrate metabolism in Parthenium argentatum</article-title><source>Bioresour. Technol.</source><year>1991</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0960-8524(91)90019-G</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salvucci</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Barta</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Byers</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Canarini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Photosynthesis and assimilate partitioning between carbohydrates and isoprenoid products in vegetatively active and dormant guayule: physiological and environmental constraints on rubber accumulation in a semiarid shrub</article-title><source>Physiol Plant.</source><year>2010</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>368</fpage><lpage>379</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1399-3054.2010.01409.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20727105?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20727105</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A Lettuce (<italic>Lactuca sativa</italic>) homolog of human Nogo-B receptor interacts with <italic>cis</italic>-prenyltransferase and is necessary for natural rubber biosynthesis</article-title><source>J. Bio. Chem.</source><year>2015</year><volume>290</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1898</fpage><lpage>1914</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M114.616920</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25477521</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamashita</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification and reconstitution of the rubber biosynthetic machinery on rubber particles from <italic>Hevea brasiliensis</italic></article-title><source>Elife</source><year>2016</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>19022</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.19022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Subcellular localization and interactions among rubber particle proteins from <italic>Hevea brasiliensis</italic></article-title><source>J. Exp. Bot.</source><year>2017</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>5045</fpage><lpage>5055</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erx331</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29036360?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29036360</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and subcellular localization analysis of two rubber elongation factor isoforms on <italic>Hevea brasiliensis</italic> rubber particles</article-title><source>Plant Physiol. Biochem.</source><year>2017</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plaphy.2016.11.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27915177?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27915177</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of temperature on rubber accumulation in guayule plant</article-title><source>Bot. Gaz.</source><year>1943</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>243</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/335212</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cornish</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Backhaus</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction of rubber transferase activity in guayule (<italic>Parthenium argentatum</italic> Gray) by low temperatures</article-title><source>Ind. Crops Prod.</source><year>2003</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0926-6690(02)00079-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benedict</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Greer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The physiology and biochemical responses of guayule to the low temperature of the Chihuahuan desert in the biosynthesis of rubber</article-title><source>Ind. Crops Prod.</source><year>2008</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>235</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2007.09.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakayama</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name><surname>Dierig</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasnick</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant water relations, photosynthesis, and rubber content of young guayule plants during water stress</article-title><source>Agron. J.</source><year>1987</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>1030</fpage><lpage>1035</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2134/agronj1987.00021962007900060016x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valdes Franco</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Modular assembly of transposable element arrays by microsatellite targeting in the guayule and rice genomes</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2018</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>271</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-018-4653-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29673330?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29673330</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Improving the Arabidopsis genome annotation using maximal transcript alignment assemblies</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>5654</fpage><lpage>5666</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkg770</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14500829?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14500829</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pimentel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Melsted</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pachter</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Near-optimal probabilistic RNA-seq quantification</article-title><source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>525</fpage><lpage>527</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.3519</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27043002?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27043002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>edgeR: a Bioconductor package for differential expression analysis of digital gene expression data</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2010</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp616</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19910308</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>SQ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A myelocytomatosis transcription factor from <italic>Hevea brasiliensis</italic> positively regulates the expression of the small rubber particle protein gene</article-title><source>Ind. Crops Prod.</source><year>2019</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>90</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2019.01.052</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Jasmonate signalling in the regulation of rubber biosynthesis in laticifer cells of rubber tree, <italic>Hevea brasiliensis</italic></article-title><source>J. Exp. Bot.</source><year>2018</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>3559</fpage><lpage>3571</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ery169</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29726901?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29726901</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stonebloom</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheller</surname><given-names>HV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptome analysis of rubber biosynthesis in guayule (<italic>Parthenium argentatum gray</italic>)</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol.</source><year>2019</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>71</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-019-1669-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30755179?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30755179</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alessandro</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Luiz Edson</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anatomical characteristics and enzymes of the sucrose metabolism and their relationship with latex yield in the rubber tree (<italic>Hevea brasiliensis</italic> Muell. Arg.)</article-title><source>Braz. J. Plant Physiol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1677-04202006000200002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kapilan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaziri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zwiazek</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of aquaporins in plants under stress</article-title><source>Biol. Res.</source><year>2018</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>4</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40659-018-0152-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29338771?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29338771</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>ADL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptomic and evolutionary analysis of the mechanisms by which <italic>P. argentatum</italic>, a rubber producing perennial, responds to drought</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol.</source><year>2019</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>494</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-019-2106-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31722667?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31722667</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Veatch-Blohm</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>McCloskey</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Water stress-induced changes in resin and rubber concentration and distribution in greenhouse-grown guayule</article-title><source>Agron. J.</source><year>2006</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>766</fpage><lpage>773</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2134/agronj2005.0203</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>VSR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhanced rubber accumulation and rubber transferase activity in guayule under water stress</article-title><source>J. Plant Physiol.</source><year>1988</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>152</fpage><lpage>155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0176-1617(88)80130-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benzioni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of water status and season on the incorporation of <sup>14</sup>CO<sub>2</sub> and [<sup>14</sup>C]-acetate into resin and rubber fractions in guayule</article-title><source>Physiol. Plant.</source><year>1991</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1399-3054.1991.tb01710.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schloman</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hively</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Krishen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Guayule byproduct evaluation: extract characterization</article-title><source>J. Agric. Food Chem.</source><year>1983</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>873</fpage><lpage>876</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf00118a050</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hepper</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Audley</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The biosynthesis of rubber from &#x003b2;-hydroxy-&#x003b2; methylglutaryl-Coenzyme A in <italic>Hevea brasiliensis</italic> latex</article-title><source>Biochem. J.</source><year>1969</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>379</fpage><lpage>386</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/bj1140379</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 4390212?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4390212</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sando</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cloning and characterization of the 2-C-methyl-D-erythritol 4-phosphate (MEP) pathway genes of a natura-rubber producing plant, <italic>Hevea brasiliensis</italic></article-title><source>Biosci. Biotech. Bioch.</source><year>2008</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>2903</fpage><lpage>2917</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1271/bbb.80387</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The rubber tree genome reveals new insights into rubber production and species adaptation</article-title><source>Nat. Plants</source><year>2016</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>16073</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/NPLANTS.2016.73</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27255837?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27255837</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bach</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hydroxymethylglutaryl-CoA reductase, a key enzyme in phytosterol synthesis?</article-title><source>Lipids</source><year>1986</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>82</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02534307</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 3959769?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3959769</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vranova</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Coman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruissem</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure and dynamics of the isoprenoid pathway network</article-title><source>Mol. Plant</source><year>2012</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>318</fpage><lpage>333</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/mp/sss015</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22442388?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22442388</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodr&#x00131;guez-Concepcion</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Boronat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Breaking new ground in the regulation of the early steps of plant isoprenoid biosynthesis</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Plant Biol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2015.04.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25909859?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25909859</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ponciano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptome and gene expression analysis in cold-acclimated guayule (<italic>Parthenium argentatum</italic>) rubber-producing tissue</article-title><source>Phytochemistry</source><year>2012</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2012.04.007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22608127?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22608127</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Benedict</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seasonal variations in rubber biosynthesis, 3-hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl-coenzyme a reductase, and rubber transferase activities in <italic>Parthenium argentatum</italic> in the Chihuahuan Desert</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>1993</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>535</fpage><lpage>542</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.103.2.535</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12231959?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12231959</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Modulations in primary and secondary metabolic pathways and adjustment in physiological behaviour of <italic>Withania somnifera</italic> under drought stress</article-title><source>Plant Sci.</source><year>2018</year><volume>272</volume><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plantsci.2018.03.029</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29807605?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29807605</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haider</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Insights into grapevine defense response against drought as revealed by biochemical, physiological and RNA-Seq analysis</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>13134</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-13464-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29030640?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29030640</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shivhare</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Asif</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lata</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative transcriptome analysis reveals the genes and pathways involved in terminal drought tolerance in pearl millet</article-title><source>Plant Mol. Biol.</source><year>2020</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>639</fpage><lpage>652</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-020-01015-w</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32430635?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32430635</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Savoi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptome and metabolite profiling reveals that prolonged drought modulates the phenylpropanoid and terpenoid pathway in white grapes (<italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> L.)</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>67</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-016-0760-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27001212?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27001212</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perreca</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of drought on the methylerythritol 4-phosphate (MEP) pathway in the isoprene emitting conifer Picea glauca</article-title><source>Front. Plant Sci.</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>546295</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2020.546295</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 33163010?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33163010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wachtel</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Shipman</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanko</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis of rubber by fungi</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1955</year><volume>122</volume><fpage>1271</fpage><lpage>1272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.122.3183.1271</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17778373?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17778373</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakazawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Production of eucommia-rubber from eucommia ulmoides oliv. (Hardy Rubber Tree)</article-title><source>Plant Biotechnol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5511/plantbiotechnology.26.71</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cherian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Cornish</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural rubber biosynthesis in plants, the rubber transferase complex, and metabolic engineering progress and prospects</article-title><source>Plant Biotechnol. J.</source><year>2019</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>2041</fpage><lpage>2061</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pbi.13181</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31150158?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31150158</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lakusta</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular studies of the protein complexes involving <italic>cis</italic>-prenyltransferase in Guayule (<italic>Parthenium argentatum</italic>), an alternative rubber-producing plant</article-title><source>Front. Plant Sci.</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>165</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2019.00165</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30858856?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30858856</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Epping</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A rubber transferase activator is necessary for natural rubber biosynthesis in dandelion</article-title><source>Nat. Plants</source><year>2015</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>15048</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nplants.2015.48</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwak</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A novel cDNA from <italic>Parthenium argentatum</italic> Gray enhances the rubber biosynthesis activity <italic>in vitro</italic></article-title><source>J. Exp. Bot.</source><year>2004</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>377</fpage><lpage>385</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erh039</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14718497?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14718497</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Collins-Silva</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Altered levels of the <italic>Taraxacum kok-saghyz</italic> (Russian dandelion) small rubber particle protein, TkSRPP3, result in qualitative and quantitative changes in rubber metabolism</article-title><source>Phytochemistry</source><year>2012</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>46</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2012.04.015</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22609069?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22609069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hillebrand</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Down-regulation of small rubber particle protein expression affects integrity of rubber particles and rubber content in <italic>Taraxacum brevicorniculatum</italic></article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e41874</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0041874</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22911861?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22911861</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Placido</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Downregulation of a CYP74 rubber particle protein increases natural rubber production in <italic>Parthenium argentatum</italic></article-title><source>Front Plant Sci.</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>760</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2019.00760</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31297121?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31297121</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brasher</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A two-component enzyme complex is required for dolichol biosynthesis in tomato</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2015</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>903</fpage><lpage>914</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.12859</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25899081?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25899081</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akhtar</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Polyprenols are synthesized by a plastidial cis-prenyltransferase and influence photosynthetic performance</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2017</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>1709</fpage><lpage>1725</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.16.00796</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28655749?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28655749</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Backhaus</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cornish</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bess</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Purification and characterization of an abundant rubber particle protein from guayule</article-title><source>Phytochemistry</source><year>1991</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>2493</fpage><lpage>2497</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0031-9422(91)85088-H</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The major protein of guayule rubber particles is a cytochrome P450. Characterization based on cDNA cloning and spectroscopic analysis of the solubilized enzyme and its reaction products</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>1995</year><volume>270</volume><fpage>8487</fpage><lpage>8494</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.270.15.8487</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7721745?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7721745</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harms</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Expression of a flax allene oxide synthase cDNA leads to increased endogenous jasmonic acid (JA) levels in transgenic potato plants but not to a corresponding activation of JA-responding genes</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>1995</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1645</fpage><lpage>1654</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.7.10.1645</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12242357?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12242357</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR78"><label>78.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Avdiushko</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hildebrand</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overexpression of a cytoplasm- localized allene oxide synthase promotes the wound-induced accumulation of jasmonic acid in transgenic tobacco</article-title><source>Plant Mol. Biol.</source><year>1999</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>783</fpage><lpage>793</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/a:1006253927431</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10487213?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10487213</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR79"><label>79.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wasternack</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Jasmonates, biosynthesis, metabolism, and signaling by proteins activating and repressing transcription</article-title><source>J. Exp. Bot.</source><year>2017</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>1303</fpage><lpage>1321</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erw443</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27940470?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27940470</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR80"><label>80.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Constitutive expression of <italic>CaSRP1</italic>, a hot pepper small rubber particle protein homolg, resulted in fast growth and improved drought tolerance om transgenic Arabidopsis plants</article-title><source>Planta</source><year>2010</year><volume>232</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00425-010-1149-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20361337?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20361337</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR81"><label>81.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Arabidopsis small rubber particle protein homolog SRPs play dual roles as positive factors for tissue growth and development and in drought stress responses</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>170</volume><fpage>2494</fpage><lpage>2510</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.16.00165</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26903535?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26903535</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR82"><label>82.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laibach</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Small rubber particle proteins from <italic>Taraxacum brevicorniculatum</italic> promote stress tolerance and influence the size and distribution of lipid droplets and artificial poly(<italic>cis</italic>-1,4-isoprene) bodies</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2018</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>1045</fpage><lpage>1061</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.13829</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29377321?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29377321</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR83"><label>83.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive proteomics analysis of laticifer latex reveals new insights into ethylene stimulation of natural rubber production</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>13778</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep13778</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26348427?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26348427</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR84"><label>84.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hemmerlin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Post-translational events and modifications regulating plant enzymes involved in isoprenoid precursor biosynthesis</article-title><source>Plant Sci.</source><year>2013</year><volume>203&#x02013;204</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plantsci.2012.12.008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23415327?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23415327</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR85"><label>85.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patra</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Schluttenhofer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Pattanaik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional regulation of secondary metabolite biosynthesis in plants</article-title><source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta.</source><year>2013</year><volume>1829</volume><fpage>1236</fpage><lpage>1247</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbagrm.2013.09.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24113224?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24113224</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR86"><label>86.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Tholl</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohlmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pichersky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The family of terpene synthases in plants: a mid-size family of genes for specialized metabolism that is highly diversified throughout the kingdom</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2011</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>212</fpage><lpage>229</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313x.2011.04520.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21443633?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21443633</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR87"><label>87.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zerbe</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohlmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant diterpene synthases: exploring modularity and metabolic diversity for bioengineering</article-title><source>Trends Biotechnol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>428</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tibtech.2015.04.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26003209?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26003209</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR88"><label>88.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Analysis of terpene synthase family genes in camellia sinensis with an emphasis on abiotic stress conditions</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>933</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-57805-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31969641?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31969641</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR89"><label>89.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muchlinski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Biosynthesis and emission of stress-induced volatile terpenes in roots and leaves of switchgrass (<italic>Panicum virgatum</italic> L.)</article-title><source>Front. Plant Sci.</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1144</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2019.01144</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31608090?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31608090</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR90"><label>90.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reisenman</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Riffell</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernays</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hildebrand</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antagonistic effects of floral scent in an insect-plant interaction</article-title><source>Proc. R. Soc. B.</source><year>2010</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>2371</fpage><lpage>2379</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2010.0163</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20335210?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20335210</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR91"><label>91.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Specific herbivore-induced volatiles defend plants and determine insect community composition in the field</article-title><source>Ecol Lett.</source><year>2012</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1130</fpage><lpage>1139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1461-0248.2012.01835.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22804824?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22804824</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR92"><label>92.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asensio</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rapparini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Pe&#x000f1;uelas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AM fungi root colonization increases the production of essential isoprenoids vs. nonessential isoprenoids especially under drought stress conditions or after jasmonic acid application</article-title><source>Phytochemistry</source><year>2012</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2011.12.012</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22296838?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22296838</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR93"><label>93.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><name><surname>Zuther</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Outred</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>McManus</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Heye</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tissue-specific changes in remobilisation of fructan in the xerophytic tussock species Festuca novae-zelandiae in response to a water deficit</article-title><source>Funct Plant Biol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>377</fpage><lpage>389</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/fp03230</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32688908?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32688908</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR94"><label>94.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activities of fructan- and sucrose-metabolizing enzymes in wheat stems subjected to water stress during grain filling</article-title><source>Planta</source><year>2004</year><volume>220</volume><fpage>331</fpage><lpage>343</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00425-004-1338-y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15290295?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15290295</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR95"><label>95.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group><source>A Guide to the Polyamines</source><year>1998</year><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR96"><label>96.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bouchereau</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Larher</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin-Tanguy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polyamines and environmental challenges: recent development</article-title><source>Plant Sci.</source><year>1999</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>125</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0168-9452(98)00218-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR97"><label>97.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Dierig</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Coffelt</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Registration of six guayule germplasms with high yielding ability</article-title><source>Crop Sci.</source><year>1999</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>300</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci1999.0011183X003900010073x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR98"><label>98.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laudencia-Chingcuanco</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional profiling of wheat caryopsis development using cDNA microarrays</article-title><source>Plant Mol. Biol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>651</fpage><lpage>668</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-006-9114-y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17211515?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17211515</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR99"><label>99.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grabherr</surname><given-names>MGA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Full-length transcriptome assembly from RNA-seq data without a reference genome</article-title><source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>644</fpage><lpage>652</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.1883</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21572440?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21572440</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR100"><label>100.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>iTAK: a program for genome-wide prediction and classification of plant transcription factors, transcriptional regulators, and protein kinases</article-title><source>Mol. Plant</source><year>2016</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1667</fpage><lpage>1670</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molp.2016.09.014</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27717919?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27717919</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR101"><label>101.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2(-Delta Delta C(T)) method</article-title><source>Methods</source><year>2001</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>402</fpage><lpage>408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/meth.2001.1262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846609</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>